<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Elucidating the genomic signature of mate competition in a pipefish using a population genomics approach</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18915</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George W. Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This study aims to understand how adult behavior can determine which genes are passed from parents to offspring and how these processes vary among populations within a species. These goals will be addressed by comparing the natural genetic variation in adults and their offspring within a single population of pipefish. This study will also quantify genetic variation in multiple populations across a broad geographic range, which will provide data regarding how reproductive patterns vary among populations. The focal organism is the straight-nosed pipefish, Nerophis ophidion, which is found in Sweden, and the project takes advantage of recent advances in DNA sequencing technology to analyze the genetic variation at the scale of the entire genome. This species is of interest because females compete intensely for access to mates and the males provide all care for the developing offspring. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses a major subject in biology and genetics, namely how behaviors at different stages during the life cycle affect how genes are passed on from one generation to the next. Additionally, the analytical approach of comparing genetic variation between adults and offspring using new sequencing technologies is a novel combination of a mathematical model from the 1970's and new statistical methods. This approach could have broad applications in many fields and for many species, including as a diagnostic tool for understanding what pressures are affecting threatened and endangered species and for understanding multi-generational effects of human diseases.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1401688</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>agjones@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Flanagan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sflanagan@bio.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M University Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
