<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Sense-and-Act Systems for Substance Release Modeling Drug Delivery Triggered by Immune-Sensing Based on Nanostructured Electrodes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>344000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal: 1403208/1403228&lt;br/&gt;PI: Katz, Evgeny/Martinez-Lemus, Luis&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Clarkson University/University of Missouri, Columbia&lt;br/&gt;Title: Collaborative Research: Sense-and-Act Systems for Substance Release Modeling Drug Delivery Triggered by Immune-Sensing Based on Nanostructured Electrodes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research program combines a nanostructured biosensing system with a drug-release system. The transformative nature of this work is in the novel concept of integrating the electrochemical sensing and electrochemical release processes, promising revolutionary changes in personalized drug administration, particularly in emergency situations and in point-of-care and end-user applications. Specifically, the program aims at designing new systems for detecting critical conditions associated with diabetes, with the detection followed by automated drug release to compensate for the medical problem. The research is initially carried out with model systems, but will culminate in animal study. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description of the project&lt;br/&gt;This research program addresses key challenges to developing bioelectronic systems for sensing non-electrochemically active biomolecules, e.g., proteins, as well as redox non-active low-molecular-weight substances. The sensing process is integrated with the actuation resulting in the signal-triggered release of biomolecular substances mimicking drug-release, for example, Insulin release triggered by ketone bodies that are biomarkers of ketoacidosis. The developed bioelectronic systems integrate parts characteristic of biosensing/immunesensing systems, biofuel cells and signal-triggered substance-releasing systems, thus representing a unique combination of components for autonomous self-powered operation. Specifically, model systems of increasing complexity are developed that can yield negative potential at a nanostructured electrode by utilizing attached enzymes and immunesensing assemblies, in response to antigens. The resulting potential suffices for activation, on another part of the connected electrode system, of the process of dissolution of an alginate layer in which the molecules mimicking drug are entrapped, triggering drug release. Such self-powered and self-activated drug-release systems operating in response to biomarker sensing represent novel approach to the "Sense-and-Act" systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1403208</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Privman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>privman@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Evgeny</FirstName>
      <LastName>Katz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ekatz@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clarkson University</Name>
      <CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
      <ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3152686475</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8 Clarkson Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7623</Code>
      <Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>142E</Code>
      <Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
