<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Neutrino Particle Astrophysics at the University of Maryland</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1568300</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James J. Whitmore</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Particle astrophysics explores some of the most tantalizing questions at the intersection of contemporary astrophysics and particle physics. These include the nature, source and acceleration mechanism of cosmic rays, neutrino properties, the search for dark matter and monopoles, and an understanding of extraordinarily energetic phenomena such as gamma ray bursts (GRBs) and active galactic nuclei. The recent first-ever observational evidence, by the IceCube Observatory, of high-energy neutrinos from distant astrophysical sources ushers in the long awaited era of neutrino astrophysics and promises to open a new window on the universe to provide information on the acceleration mechanisms at work in these sources and insight into the nature and source of cosmic radiation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IceCube Observatory was constructed at the U.S. Antarctic Amundsen-Scott South Pole Station and the detector deployment was completed in Dec 2010 with initial operation of the full detector commencing in Spring 2011. IceCube is comprised of 5160 photomultiplier tubes instrumenting a full cubic kilometer of ice and is the largest neutrino detector in existence. This award provides funds to support this group's contributions to the operation of this unique instrument. In addition to providing leadership within the IceCube Collaboration, the group will continue their analysis of IceCube data focusing on continuing searches for neutrino emission from GRBs, real-time neutrino searches and neutrino oscillations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The group has an established track record in both public outreach and providing strong scientific and educational opportunities for undergraduates, graduate students, and post-doctoral fellows. They will continue their work by bringing particle astrophysics to high schools and the public through their QuarkNet chapter, as well as through science fair judging and public lectures.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1403586</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sullivan@umdgrb.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hoffman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kara@icecube.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blaufuss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>blaufuss@icecube.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5115</Code>
      <Text>Antarctic Astrophys&amp;Geosp Sci</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1643</Code>
      <Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>011Y</Code>
      <Text>IceCube Research Support</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
