<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Communications coordination for the Geospace Environment Modeling Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carrie E. Black</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Geospace Environment Modeling (GEM) Program is a broad-based, community-initiated research program on the physics of the Earth's magnetosphere and the coupling of the magnetosphere to the atmosphere and to the solar wind. The work of GEM is accomplished in a series of campaigns and focus groups that solve specific problems leading to the construction of a global Geospace General Circulation Model (GGCM) with predictive capability. This project ensures the efficient communications and comprehensive archiving that GEM needs to continue its vital role in the geospace science community for the next 5 years. The project provides archives of GEM activities that are accessible by the scientists and students today and in the future and maintains an online forum for information exchange and coordination of activities in the program. Finally, the project provides access for researchers, students, and the general public to tutorials and other educational resources present the most updated knowledge about the near-Earth space environment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;GEM has a communications coordinator to ensure healthy information flows within the community and to maintain an archive of the program's activities. This project performs the tasks for the next GEM Communications Coordinator starting from 2009, following the guidelines described in the GEM bylaws. The tasks fall into the following four categories: (a) the electronic newsletter GEM Messenger, (b) the annual GEMstone reports (including special reports), (c) the GEM website GemWiki, and (d) the GEM Data Catalog.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1405565</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pchi@igpp.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/02/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5750</Code>
      <Text>MAGNETOSPHERIC PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1323</Code>
      <Text>SOLAR INFLUENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
