<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: THE RESPONSE OF MYXOMYCETE COMMUNITIES TO 14 YEARS OF N, P, AND K ADDITION IN A LOWLAND TROPICAL RAIN FOREST</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18980</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Myxomycetes, or plasmodial slime molds, are among the most abundant protozoans in many soils, where they feed on bacteria and other microorganisms. The ecological role of myxomycetes may be considerable but has been studied very little. In collaboration with the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama, this project takes advantage of a long-term, nutrient fertilization experiment in lowland, tropical forest to investigate the effects of additions of nitrogen, phosphorus and other nutrients on communities of myxomycetes in the soil using environmental DNA sequencing. Results are expected to provide the first data on how tropical soil protozoans respond to nutrients and to lead to increased understanding of how these tiny predators may influence the functioning of tropical forests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the project include enhancement of the genetic database for studies of myxomycetes, international collaboration, training of graduate and undergraduate students, and public outreach. DNA sequencing data will be made available to the public. The project will provide research experience for Panamanian students attending the University of Arkansas through an international scholarship program and for the co-PI, a Ph.D. student. The co-PI has already presented her research through several public media outlets and plans further presentations to the public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1406667</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lmw009@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stephenson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slsteph@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
      <CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
