<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EXTREEMS-QED: Undergraduate Research in Computational and Data-Enabled Mathematics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599885</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Computational and data-enabled mathematics plays an ever-increasing role in the advancement of modern science and engineering. The main objective of this project is to promote and enhance undergraduate research experience at George Mason University (GMU) with the goal of preparing broadly trained computational mathematicians by immersing them in significant applied research projects. This research experience, while the students are still in formative stages of their education, will increase the likelihood of success in graduate studies in applied and computational mathematics and statistics. Recruitment from GMU's diverse student population and collaboration with a majority Hispanic university in Puerto Rico will promote participation of under-represented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A student cohort consisting of eight GMU students will be admitted to the two-year long intensive interdisciplinary training program each year. In the summer, the students will be immersed in data-enabled research projects, covering a wide range of topics and application areas, from uncertainty quantification and bifurcation phenomena in large datasets, to modeling complex physical or financial systems and constrained optimization problems. It is expected that the students will conduct research for the whole duration of the program. As part of the education program, the students will attend a year long Undergraduate Seminar which will enhance their communication and dissemination skills, as well as other preparatory work for possible graduate studies in STEM fields. In fall semester, students will take a recently designed Applied and Computational Partial Differential Equations course followed by a new Advanced Topics in Computational Mathematics course in the spring. The project will include several unique faculty development and outreach opportunities, involving both GMU and non-GMU faculty. In addition, GMU will host industrial workshops and faculty boot camps that will involve selected students and faculty from a variety of institutions in hands-on data-driven projects. The project is a team effort that builds upon a strong record of successful undergraduate research and collaboration experience, including a recently established connection with InterAmerican University of Puerto Rico that will help to broaden the impact of the proposed training program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1407087</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harbir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Antil</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hantil@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Evelyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esander@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Emelianenko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>memelian@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wanner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>twanner@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Padmanabhan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seshaiyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pseshaiy@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/12/2015</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Anderson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>danders1@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Mason University</Name>
      <CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7335</Code>
      <Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7361</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND WORKFORCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8606</Code>
      <Text>EXTREEMS-QED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
