<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Using the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect to Measure AGN Feedback</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>498199</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan Wrobel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This program will use the Sunyaev-Zeldovich (SZ) effect (scattering of certain kinds of light by electrons) to assess, through data analysis and simulations, the impact of quasars on heating the gas between galaxies and influencing galaxy evolution. Broader impacts of the work include training of undergraduate and graduate students. The project will also include a significant component targeted at communicating the work to the general public. At the national level, Dr. Scannapieco will continue to contribute to popular science journals such as Scientific American, and present lectures at REU programs. At the local level, he will give regular public lectures, which will be coordinated through the Mars Education Project (http://marsed.asu.edu).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SZ effect occurs when inverse Compton scattering increases the energy of cosmic microwave background (CMB) photons passing through hot, dense gas. In this way the SZ effect acts as a calorimeter, indicating exactly how much energy was added to the intergalactic medium and when. Dr. Scannapieco will employ stacking of public archival data from the South Pole Telescope (SPT), analyzing a suite of simulations using three codes, and making targeted observations to determine the way that energy deposits from active nuclei affect galaxy evolution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1407835</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Evan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scannapieco</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>evan.scannapieco@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1217</Code>
      <Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1206</Code>
      <Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
