<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Precisely Functionalized Molecular Nanoparticles are Fundamental and Unique Elements for Macromolecular Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>700000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Polymer program in the Division of Materials Research to University of Akron is to study in precisely controlling self-assembled supramolecular structures across different length scales, and these supramolecular structures are the key to the 'bottom-up' nanofabrication technology. New class of self-assembling materials, termed as 'giant molecules', which refer to precisely-defined macromolecules composed of selected and specifically functionalized molecular nanoparticles as the elemental building blocks ('nano-atoms'), are designed to achieve this goal. These 'nano-atoms' possess persistent volume, symmetry, and surface functionalities for further processing in chemical assembly. Typical 'nano-atoms' are exemplified by the derivatives of fullerenes, polyhedral oligomeric silsesquioxanes, polyoxometalates, and folded globular proteins. Highly efficient 'click-type' reactions are used to construct prototype giant molecules in a modular and precise manner. Novel and rich self-assembly behaviors have been demonstrated by the newly-designed giant molecules in the bulk, thin-film, and solution states, revealing a promising way to advance the understanding of self-assembly and to obtain unconventional hierarchical structures and dynamics. Students and postdoctoral researchers will be trained in this new interdisciplinary field, and they will acquire a combination of synthetic skills, characterization techniques, and physical principles, and provide them a platform to develop new discoveries at the interface of chemistry, physics and life science and careers in these areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposed research has the following broader impacts. The education aspects of this proposal are intended to benefit students at all educational levels in the community with the cutting-edge research activities and scientific demonstrations. The PI will continue to actively participate in recruiting and training undergraduate and graduate students, and will provide them with hands-on experiences in the laboratory. In addition, the PI is planning to develop a new course specifically focusing on the progress related to the proposed research. The traditional collaboration among the PI's research group, department and the Akron Global Polymer Academy has provided STEM teaching and training opportunities for K-12 students from local schools, and these activities will be continued with this award. The proposed research is not only scientifically innovative and interesting, but also technologically relevant, and the PI is actively involved in tech transfer of his research findings. This is especially reflected by the recent efforts to develop sub-22 nm nanopatterning technology with industry. The PI is also active in developing a more diverse, interdisciplinary workforce through the advanced training of students, specifically from various minority and underrepresented groups, for the next-generation evolution in soft materials-based sciences, engineering and technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1408872</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen Z.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scheng@uakron.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Akron</Name>
      <CityName>Akron</CityName>
      <ZipCode>443250001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3309727666</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>302 Buchtel Common</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1711</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
