<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Defect-Managed, High-Mobility Oxide Thin Films and Heterostructures for Fundamental Study</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>366000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: This project focuses on the development of an advanced state-of-the-art thin film deposition technique for the synthesis of a new class of complex oxides that are highly perfect. These materials possess multi-functional properties that are of great interest for next generation devices of power electronics and energy conversion. The exploration of these materials with unprecedented structure quality and low defects provides valuable input for experimental testing of theoretical models, in addition to facilitating the fundamental study of materials physics at reduced size and dimensionality. The research activities contribute to the professional development experience for students from local high schools, minority organizations and community colleges through training and "science awareness" workshops. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS: Through the establishment of molecular beam epitaxy growth approaches, this project is studying the fundamental physics of highly stoichiometric, precisely doped, defect-managed complex oxides with outstanding potential for room temperature electronics. The project is seeking to exploit these structures by conducting detailed structural and electronic transport studies in order to understand, and eventually control, specific defects, local structure, and electronic mobility. In particular, the work is seeking a fundamental understanding of factors, which control room temperature electron mobility in perovskite oxides using a "model" material system (BaSnO3) that presents opportunities to enhance electron mobility at room temperature via defect-management and remote doping approaches. The project is providing opportunities for graduate, undergraduate and high school students to obtain training in the interdisciplinary areas of materials science and engineering, electrical engineering, materials chemistry, and materials physics. Students are gaining experience with cutting-edge thin film deposition approaches, advanced characterization techniques, and theoretical calculations. The project also contributes to the education outreach by training students enrolled in a vacuum and thin film technology program at local community colleges in Minneapolis. These students are often find employment as technicians after completing this program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1410888</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bharat</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jalan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bjalan@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1774</Code>
      <Text>CERAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
