<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ongoing Accretion onto a Galactic Disk and Primordial Galaxies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>275722</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph E. Pesce</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This program will develop a better understanding of the way in which fuel for star formation settles into the galactic disk of the Milky Way from the intergalactic medium. This goal will be accomplished through the use of survey data from the Arecibo Observatory that helps trace the location of gas in and near our Milky Way galaxy. Broader impacts of the work include training of undergraduate and graduate students. The project will have a direct impact on society through a program that brings astronomers into diverse middle schools throughout New York City. The goal is to inspire students at a juncture where they often choose to turn towards or away from science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Putman and her students will construct a multiphase map of the interface between the disk and halo of the Milky Way through the combination of a catalog of clouds from the GALFA-HI Survey, examination of their dust content, and comparisons to models and multi-wavelength observational data. The process of cooling at the disk-halo interface will be explored, as well as the interplay between accretion and feedback in controlling the star formation rate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1410800</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Putman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mputman@astro.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1217</Code>
      <Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
