<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Redshift Measurements of the Swift Serendipitous Cluster Survey</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98049</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard E. Barvainis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>One of the primary objectives of extragalactic astronomy is to understand the formation and evolution of structures over cosmic time. Clusters of galaxies are the largest gravitationally bound structures in the universe, and so a better understanding of their formation and evolution leads to deeper knowledge of the physics of the cosmos. In order to fully probe the physics and evolution of clusters, however, a co-ordinated multi-wavelength campaign is needed: while observations with X-ray telescopes are excellent at finding clusters, follow-up observations with optical telescopes are critical to measuring their distances from us. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaborative project will use the Michigan-Dartmouth-MIT (MDM) 2.4m, Magellan, and Large Binocular Telescope (LBT) optical observatories to measure the redshifts and distances to clusters identified in the X-ray Swift Serendipitous Cluster Survey (SSCS). The program will produce one of the largest X-ray selected cluster catalogs to date, and make it available to the entire astronomical community. The increased numbers of high-redshift clusters as a result of this work will lead to a better understanding of the evolution of cluster properties over cosmic time. The team will also study the relationships between the optical and X-ray properties of clusters as a function of redshift. Finally, they will use the sample to constrain cosmological parameters, such as the energy densities of dark matter and dark energy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The two Principal Investigators of this collaboration will also launch an innovative series of outreach events that are designed to further develop the STEM workforce. At the University of Oklahoma-Norman, Dr. Xinyu Dai will use a portable planetarium to deliver presentations to high schools in the Greater Oklahoma City area. At the same time, Dr. Joel Bregman will develop new shows for the on-campus planetarium at the University of Michigan Ann-Arbor. The results of their scientific efforts will also be distributed to the general public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1412730</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bregman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jnbregman@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1217</Code>
      <Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
