<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT: A Novel Reactive Separation Process for the Clean-up of Landfill Gas and Other Gaseous Renewable Fuels</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250176</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating novel catalytic oxidation technology based on the "pore-flow reactor" (PoFR) concept together with an ultra-violet (UV)-photodecomposition-based (PhoR) technology for the removal of siloxanes, a particularly problematic class of impurities found in biogas and landfill gas (LFG). This technology addresses the need for the development of a novel clean-up method to remove toxic contaminants from these important renewable fuels. The project will result in the completion and the validation of the proof-of-concept both at the lab-scale and the field-scale of this landfill gas and biogas clean-up technology. This LFG and biogas clean-up system has the following unique features: (i) it completely destroys the toxic contaminates rather than transfer them into a different medium; (ii) it does not require the use of adsorption media and their regeneration or the flaring of desorbed contaminants; (iii) it is a continuous process. These features provide process performance, reliability, safety, environmental and cost savings advantages when compared to the leading competing adsorption/absorption technologies in this market space. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The preliminary results, so far, with the LFG/biogas clean-up technology are promising. This project addresses technology gaps as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application, specifically: (i) gaining a better insight about the characteristics of each individual technology subsystem (PoFR and PhoR), but also how they potentially function together as an integrated technology; (ii) acquiring a better understanding of the reaction/transport processes that occur during contaminant destruction; (iii) developing an effective process model to be able to optimize performance without the need of extensive and costly experimentation; (iv) field-testing of the technology to validate its ability to function with real LFG and biogas; (v) process modeling to demonstrate process feasibility &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project engages three principal partners, the University of Southern California (USC) and two small US companies, Media and Process Technology, Inc. of Pittsburgh, PA (M&amp;PT), and GC Environmental, Inc. of Anaheim, CA (GCE) working as a team to develop this novel cost-effective clean-up method to remove toxic contaminants from LFG and biogas. The project will engage three additional broader-context partners, namely the EISGTTP Program at San Diego State University (guiding commercialization aspects), and a small business (BENA) and Southern California Gas Company (SoCalGas), both providing test environments, all working together towards a common goal of the translation of this technology from research discovery toward commercial reality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This novel clean-up technology is important because it will allow LFG and biogas to gain their full potential as renewable fuels; it also shows promise for widespread application, beyond the LFG/biogas market, for volatile organic compounds (VOC) destruction in contaminated gas streams, encountered in many energy and industrial applications. This technology will contribute to the U.S. competitiveness in the renewable energy and environmental fields by providing superior treatment capability allowing engines, combustion and process equipment to experience longer life with less maintenance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414179</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hossein</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pourmand</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hossein@stevens.usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prosser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rprosser@gc-environmental.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tsotsis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tsotsis@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fokion</FirstName>
      <LastName>Egolfopoulos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>egolfopo@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
