<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Effects of UV disinfection on intracellular and extracellular distribution of antibiotic resistance genes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5301</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Antibiotic resistant pathogens are a global human health threat, and there is growing attention on the potential role of the aquatic environment as a significant route by which antibiotic resistance may spread. Disinfection at wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs) is designed to limit the pathogens that enter rivers and streams. However this may not significantly reduce genes which give bacteria the mechanisms by which they can defend against antibiotics, known as antibiotic resistant genes (ARGs). This project will study the effect of UV disinfection on the fate of ARGs in the effluent of the Xiamen, China WWTP, focusing on the location of ARGs with respect to whether ARGs are inside or outside of the cell. The location of ARGs impacts how the genes are acquired by pathogens, and how they persist in the environment. In collaboration with Professor Chang-Ping Yu at the Institute of Urban Environment the Chinese Academy of Sciences, this research seeks to advance technologies for minimizing the spread of antibiotic resistance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Samples will be taken before and after disinfection at the WWTP and then examined using a combination of methods to determine the shift in location of ARGs. The methods used will quantify two representative ARGs (tetM and sulI) by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR). Propidium monoazide (PMA) qPCR will be conducted to determine the intracellular portion of ARGs, and qPCR will determine total ARGs. This will give information on the role UV disinfection on whether these ARGs will be inside or outside the cell. This research will lead to a better understanding of antibiotic resistance and therefor may lead to better combatants to the spread of ARGs and increased public health. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414774</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
      <LastName>Metch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Metch Jacob</Name>
      <CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
