<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Transparent Antenna Technology for Next Generation Wireless Consumer Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>173325</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is that it offers low cost, and compact&lt;br/&gt;tablet/mobile devices with better wireless connectivity and increased battery life. Lower cost of these&lt;br/&gt;devices will enable their widespread use in the society and enable use of broadband services with higher&lt;br/&gt;efficiency and better connectivity. The transparent antenna technology offers a platform on which&lt;br/&gt;several other applications can be built. For instance, compact health monitoring sensors can be&lt;br/&gt;integrated with wireless capability by integrating antennas on their displays. This technology also will&lt;br/&gt;also improve wireless capability of wearables as they have very limited real estate for antennas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to develop transparent antenna&lt;br/&gt;technology for wireless consumer devices. This SBIR project will advance our understanding of&lt;br/&gt;interactions between touch sensor and transparent antennas and enable development of multifunctional&lt;br/&gt;touch sensors that not only operates as a touch sensor but also a transparent antenna as&lt;br/&gt;well. A very comprehensive research approach will be undertaken in Phase I. Namely, in addition to&lt;br/&gt;evaluating performance of the antenna technology in the presence of touch sensor, performance of&lt;br/&gt;touch sensor in the presence of transparent antennas will also be characterized to ensure that the&lt;br/&gt;proposed multi?]functional touch sensors meet the requirements of wireless consumer devices such as&lt;br/&gt;tablets and mobile phones.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1416355</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yakup</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bayram</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yakup.bayram@paneratech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>PaneraTech Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Chantilly</CityName>
      <ZipCode>201511272</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6145998493</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4125 Lafayette Center Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
