<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ideas Lab: Interdisciplinary Pathways towards a Secure Internet</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>111816</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Today the Internet constitutes a critical infrastructure: an attack or disruption has the potential to cause serious damage to institutions supporting key resources, such as water, power, transportation, finance, emergency response, business operations and manufacturing supply chains. Consequently, there is interest in a myriad of interdisciplinary approaches to achieve increased security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to conduct a 2.5-day workshop for 20-30 invited participants in order to gain a deeper understanding of the challenges and potential solutions for a secure Internet. The workshop brings together experts in network design, cybersecurity, and policy, spanning industry, academia, and the government. The goal of the Ideas Lab is to explore pathways and find solutions for a secure Internet based on interdisciplinary approaches that take into account technology, social sciences, policy and education. The Ideas Lab will be coordinated by a five-member Steering Committee composed of leading experts and the PI. In addition, expert facilitators will be used to create a highly productive workshop that will be tailored to achieve the specific objective of finding solutions for a secure Internet.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1418289</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Damon</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCoy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dm181@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Mason University</Name>
      <CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
