<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Development Of Hierarchy In Emergent Complex Societies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24940</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The central goal of this research is to understand how, in traditional societies, social structure is affected by warfare. When a society is under such stress are class and economic boundaries emphasized and societal structural differences increased or is there a leveling of difference? Archaeology provides a means to gain insight by following the process across an extended period of time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under the supervision of Dr. Wendy Ashmore, Kirby Farah will perform archaeological excavations and analyses at an elite residence in Xaltocan, Estado de Mexico, Mexico. Xaltocan is located in the northern Basin of Mexico on a human-made island in what was formerly a shallow, brackish lake (Lake Xaltocan). The ethnohistorical record indicates that Xaltocan was founded in the 11th century by Otomí speakers and served as the capital of the Otomí city-state until the end of the 14th century when it was conquered by an alliance between Cuauhtitlan and the Tepanecs of Azcatpotzalco. Ms. Farah's research will focus on identity formation and domestic spatial practices of the elite at Xaltocan in the centuries leading up to Xaltocan's conquest (ca. AD 1100-1400). During this period Xaltocan was at the height of its power and constantly entangled in regional conflict. Using methods and theory developed for doing household archaeology, this research will determine how class impacted everyday life practices at Xaltocan. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The historical record contains numerous references to the powerful rulers that controlled Xaltocan for centuries, however to date there has been no intensive archaeological research performed at elite spaces. This research will provide much needed insight into the domestic practices of Xaltocan's elite and will help determine how these practices changed over time in response to escalating regional warfare. Methodologies for isolating activity areas including soil chemical and microartifact analyses, in addition to more conventional macroartifact analyses will enable a nuanced understanding of spatial practices. In addition, radiocarbon and relative dating techniques (using the extremely refined ceramic chronology from Xaltocan) contribute to our knowledge of how elite practices changed over time. Data gleaned from this research will be comparable to extant data on commoner households at Xaltocan and to other Postclassic elite residences in the Basin of Mexico. Through these comparisons, this project pursues new ways to examine how elites managed their dual roles as local leaders and regional elites. This research is significant because it will provide a comparative model for studying class relations and identity formation that is pertinent for archaeological projects worldwide.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this project will have broader impacts beyond the topics outlined above. This research is an integral component of Ms. Farah's graduate student training and will also incorporate Mexican students from the Escuela Nacional de Antropología e Historia. The project will provide these students with in-field training (a degree requirement in Mexico) and fosters international cooperation. Results of this project will be disseminated in peer-reviewed publications within the US and will be accessible to Mexican scholars in the form of annual and final project reports to INAH. This project will also actively involve the local community by providing site tours and lectures, curating museum exhibits, posting weekly project updates at the local museum, and by distributing research results in Spanish. Such efforts will empower residents of Xaltocan to learn about their local heritage by making current archaeological findings more accessible. This model, wherein the interest of local communities is a central priority, is broadly applicable for archaeological projects worldwide, and for any research endeavors that have implications for local communities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1419202</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ashmore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wendy.ashmore@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kirby</FirstName>
      <LastName>Farah</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kirby.farah@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
