<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Student Participation in the 2014 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cozzens</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Conference on Acoustics Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP) is an annual event, and is the most widely-attended gathering of experts from the signal processing community. In 2014, it will take place in Florence, Italy. Historically, about 25% of the ICASSP participants have been students. This is a very healthy statistic because the future of this all-pervasive discipline is largely determined by the number of young people adopting signal processing as their field of endeavor. Many of the students are coauthors of accepted papers and presenters at the conference. For them, ICASSP is a unique opportunity to meet many of the leaders in the field and to broaden their horizons by being exposed to areas of research different from their own. The conference is also an excellent opportunity for them to start networking with people who will likely be their future collaborators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Unfortunately is expected that the number of US-based students attending the conference in Florence will be smaller than usual. This is largely due to the high travel costs to get to Florence from North America. This proposal aims at providing travel support for some of these students, hence, insuring better representation of US students at ICASSP 2014.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1419742</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Petar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Djuric</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>petar.djuric@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/24/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7797</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7936</Code>
      <Text>SIGNAL PROCESSING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
