<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Graduate Student Travel Support from US Institutions to the 14th International Conference on Nanotechnology (IEEE Nano 2014). To be held in Toronto, Canada August 18-21, 2014.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7700</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nadia El-Masry</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract Title: Graduate Student Travel Support from US Institutions to the 14th International Conference on Nanotechnology (IEEE Nano 2014)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract: &lt;br/&gt;The aim of this grant is to support graduate students from US institutions to travel to the 14th International Conference on Nanotechnology (IEEE Nano 2014 in Toronto, Canada from August 18-21, 2014. Funds will be given as an NSF fellowship to attend the conference, where students will present their research as oral or poster presentations. Students will have the opportunity to gain valuable knowledge and insight into leading edge research from international researchers in nanotechnology. Students will also have the opportunity to attend workshops lead by experts in their fields to gain skills in new areas of nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The outcome of this grant is student training in nanotechnology, nanoscience, and nanoengineering, which are critical research and development areas for the US. By enabling the participation of graduate students from US institutions in this conference, they will gain valuable knowledge through their active participation in giving technical presentations on their research, attending oral talks, and poster presentations. They will also have the ability to network and learn about global research in the nanotechnology community through formal and informal events.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1420380</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carmen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lilley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clilley@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>097E</Code>
      <Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>108E</Code>
      <Text>Bioelectronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8028</Code>
      <Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
