<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Cross Layer Control of Dynamic Optical Networks - from Theory to Experimentation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Current optical networks are mostly statically provisioned at the lowest optical layer. Moving the communications infrastructure to a dynamically provisioned optical infrastructure will allow on-demand provisioning of high-bandwidth circuits in support of science, commerce, media, and national security. Dynamic optical networks will contribute to bridging the digital divide and supporting bandwidth intensive transformative applications such as 3-D video for telepresence in education and telemedicine. The physical layer components of such a network are emerging from research on dynamic optical devices and technologies and offer unique opportunities. However, controlling dynamic optical networks while considering the physical layer Quality of Transmission and the higher layer requirements poses major challenges due to both the interactions of multiple light paths sharing the same fiber and the challenges of adapting to multiple fiber types and physical infrastructures with varying impairments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project contributes to the deployment of dynamic optical networks by developing cross-layered network control algorithms for wide-area and data center optical networks. The algorithms rely on the capabilities of real-time optical performance monitors (OPMs) and allow efficient use of the optical resources through dynamic network configuration, regeneration, and power, bandwidth, and modulation control. Since the effects of dynamic operation in wide-area networks are analytically intractable, the project develops an optimization framework that, rather than employing theoretical models and analytical solutions, uses direct input from OPM measurements. For data center networks, the project is designing network configuration schemes that allow physical support of various *-cast (unicast, anycast, multicast, etc.) higher layer requirements. This project includes engaging diverse student populations in the cross-layered research and outreach activities to the Harlem community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1423105</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zussman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gil@ee.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Keren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bergman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bergman@ee.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
