<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on Infinitary Ramsey Theory, May 24-28, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Conference on Infinitary Ramsey Theory will be held at the University of Denver May 24 - 28, 2014. In the past thirty years, Ramsey theory has risen to a prominent place in mathematics, providing the key to solutions of long-standing problems, in particular, Gowers' solution to the distortion problem. Recently, the paper of Kechris, Pestov, and Todorcevic connecting Ramsey theory with topological dynamics led to the recent boom in research regarding applications of Ramsey theory applied to finding minimal flows; and the recent book of Todorcevic on Ramsey Spaces has prepared a path for a surge in progress on Ramsey theory. This conference will focus on Ramsey theory of an infinite flavor and its applications in the fields of Banach spaces, homogeneous structures, set theory, and topological dynamics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference will promote cross-pollination of ideas and results among Ramsey theorists from different four or more continents, many of whom have never met each other. It will serve as a unifying point for the subject of infinitary Ramsey theory and increase future collaborations. It will also provide entry to the field for young researchers with diverse backgrounds. As such, the field of infinitary Ramsey theory will be strengthened, very likely speeding up the rate of progress in this area and areas in which it is applied. The conference website is at https://portfolio.du.edu/ramsey</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1424270</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Natasha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dobrinen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>natasha.dobrinen@du.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/21/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Denver</Name>
      <CityName>Denver</CityName>
      <ZipCode>802104711</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3038712000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2199 S. University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
