<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Pressure Rheometer with Structural Analysis Accessories for Oil Well Cement and Other Materials Characterization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140438</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Rheological properties - the flow and deformation of materials under shearing - is critical to the functioning of many large-scale systems, ranging from water pipelines, to landfills, oil wells and pipelines and biofuels plants. This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award will fund the acquisition of a pressure rheometer with structural analysis accessories to support ongoing research, teaching, and training programs at the University of Louisville (UofL), Kentucky. The instrument will be shared by UofL faculty to conduct potentially transformative fundamental research in civil engineering and materials science. It will allow researchers to obtain the rheological properties of a wide range of engineering materials, including oil well cement slurry, pipe seals, organoclay suspensions, and biomass and biofuels. This knowledge will enable the design of advanced materials and more efficient and resilient systems, enhancing the safety of the nation's oil production facilities and landfills, the quality of the water supply, and promoting sustainable energy development. The instrumentation will also enhance interdisciplinary research collaborations and provide educational opportunities for graduate and undergraduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The significant feature of this instrument is its ability to apply extreme high temperature (400 °C) and high pressure (100 MPa) when measuring a sample's rheological properties. A high resolution microscope and a small angle light scattering system can be attached to the rheometer to characterize the microstructure of the material when subjected to shear. The multi-functional instrument will simulate the critical downhole conditions in a deep oilwell to systematically study the rheological properties of oilwell cement slurry under both dynamic and static status. These measured rheological properties are believed to be the true indications of the pumpability and gelation of the cement slurry, which are crucial to the safety of oilwell construction. The attached microscope and the small-angle light scattering system will allow in-situ observations of cement particle dispersion, agglomeration, and flocculation during gelation of cement. These findings will close the knowledge gap of cement slurry microstructure and its influences on rheological properties during and after oilwell construction. The instrument will also facilitate fundamental research on 1) the mechanical and thermal behavior of geo/soil materials under temperature change and dynamic loads to investigate the their potential application as slurry wall filling materials, 2) the chloramine degradation progression of the elastomer in pipe seals and 3) characterizing and developing new geological materials, smart materials, mechanical fluids, and bio and bio-inspired materials to advance the development of renewable energy and sustainable materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1427660</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhihui</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>z.sun@louisville.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Louisville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>402021959</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5028523788</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>The Nucleus</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>025E</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>040E</Code>
      <Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
