<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an Accurate-Mass Quadrupole Time-of-Flight (Q-TOF) LC/MS for Multidisciplinary Research, Research Training, and Education at Tuskegee University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>420800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) and support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Program (CRIF), Professor Marilyn Tourne and collaborators from Tuskegee University will acquire a quadrupole, time-of-flight liquid chromatograph mass spectrometer (Q-TOF- LC/MS). In general, mass spectrometry (MS) is one of the key analytical methods used to identify and characterize small quantities of chemical species embedded in complex matrices. In a typical experiment, the components flow into a mass spectrometer where they are ionized into the parent ion and its fragment ions and their masses are measured. This highly sensitive technique allows detection and determination of the structure of molecules in a complex mixture. An instrument with a liquid chromatograph provides additional structural identification power by separating mixtures of compounds before they reach the mass spectrometer. As a primarily undergraduate institution, the faculty at this historically black university (HBCU) embraces undergraduate research experiences as one of the most important outcomes of their research activities. The proposed instrument will directly impact the research experiences of a large number of undergraduate students within the three-year project period, and many more in years to come. The instrument will also be used in a variety of science courses, including organic, analytical, instrumental analysis, and biochemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels, especially in areas such as (a) investigating aberrant protein-protein associations; (b) developing new methodology utilizing transition metal nanoparticles (Pt, Co, and Ru) for production of ethanolic biofuels; (c) identifying designed small molecules with enhanced binding to selected targets; and (d) developing simpler identification methods for commercially available emulsion explosives and their residues.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1427720</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marilyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tourne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mtourne@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tuskegee University</Name>
      <CityName>Tuskegee Institute</CityName>
      <ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3347278233</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 W Montgomery Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
