<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Microscope-based, Spectrofluorometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>141378</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Benedictine University faculty and student researchers will use the spectrofluorometer/microscope system to initiate projects that involve the detection of rapid changes in the fluorescence state of molecules in response to their chemical environments. This work allows researchers to investigate contemporary issues in the fields of physiology, molecular biology, and biochemistry by using high-tech instrumentation to acquire real-time measures of cell physiology and signaling without damaging the cells. Undergraduates, including those from underrepresented backgrounds, have the opportunity to participate in research and gain a solid foundation for careers or graduate school. This work also supports an internship program involving both pre-service and K-8 in-service teachers, enabling them to learn first-hand the excitement of investigation and achievement in science that they then bring to the next generation of students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Researchers in the biology and chemistry departments at Benedictine University will use the spectrofluorescence system to advance their scientific research programs in four biochemistry projects: (1) Regulation of paracellular permeability and ion transport in epithelial cells; (2) Anti-estrogenic effects of metals in osteoclasts; (3) Structure/function properties of G-protein signaling; (4) Fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET)-monitored phage display system for the targeting of signal proteins. By promoting interdisciplinary work at Benedictine, these projects together improve the competencies of students by providing access to classical and state-of-the-art techniques in cellular biology and chemistry, such as in the capstone biochemistry and molecular biology cell laboratory. Students gain first-hand experiences and opportunities to conduct original science, with extensive planning, data analysis and reporting, that can potentially lead to new discoveries. The projects contribute to the integration of science processes and quantitative reasoning with Benedictine's curriculum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1427937</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smeyer@ben.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jayashree</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sarathy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jsarathy@ben.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rylaarsdam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rrylaarsdam@ben.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>awilson@ben.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Benedictine University</Name>
      <CityName>Lisle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>605320900</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6308296004</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5700 College Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
