<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Major Research Instrumentation: Development of Epitaxial Growth System for Few Layer Semiconductors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>750036</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-technical: Semiconductor technology today is used for many applications including computation, communication, energy conversion, and sensing. Most semiconductor devices used today are built from near-perfect rigid 3-dimensional crystalline solids. However, recent work on a new generation of layered 2-dimensional (2D) materials has generated great scientific and technological interest. These materials consist of single atomic or molecular 2D layers that can be placed on arbitrary substrates such as flexible plastics, or transparent glass while offering performance that is comparable to more expensive electronic materials. 2D semiconductors could have significant impact on technology by enabling low cost flexible and transparent electronics and optoelectronics. They could also enable lower power computation and biological and chemical sensors. This project will enable the development of unique equipment and techniques for synthesis of these 2D semiconductor materials. The material synthesis techniques developed would help the electronics industry as well as equipment manufacturers. The project will help to educate several graduate students and researchers on the details of developing a new growth system, new tools for in situ characterization, and the broad applications and science of 2D materials. The research team will organize annual workshops on 2D layered material epitaxy where researchers from other universities will be invited to share their experiences on development of growth systems for 2D semiconductors, and also share information about the new tools developed under this MRI award.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: One of the main challenges in the area of 2D semiconductor research today is the synthesis of electronic grade material. This activity directly addresses the most important challenge by attempting to develop a dedicated molecular beam epitaxial growth system for the synthesis of 2D layered materials. Since the growth and characterization methods needed for 2D materials are quite different from those of 3D crystals, this system will be unique in having a suite of synthesis and characterization capabilities. The MBE system will be specifically developed to help understand and control the complex chemistry and physics of the 2D metal-dichalcogenide epitaxy process. The research team will build upon early work and focus on the synthesis of 2D (monolayer) materials and complex heterostructures by MBE. In collaboration with an instrument manufacturer, a variety of source materials and source types to develop a broad set of technology solutions for growth of 2D layered semiconductors will be developed. The project will investigate in situ real time monitoring and feedback during growth, to enable automatic growth of arbitrary single layers and heterostructures. The ultimate aim is to develop a robust, reproducible MBE-based growth methodology appropriate for further research (electronic/optical properties and device development), as well as future commercialization.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1429143</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brillson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brillson.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ringel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ringel@ece.osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roland</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kawakami</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kawakami.15@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Siddharth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rajan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rajan@ece.osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roberto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Myers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>myers.1079@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
