<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Serendipitous Search System Using Lateral Analogy to Match Potential Solutions to Unmet Needs:Feasibility Study Based on Screening Approved Drugs for Repurposing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>810748</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to accelerate the pace&lt;br/&gt;of research and development to enable more rapid deployment of technologies&lt;br/&gt;into commercial / industrial contexts. In many fields, information is expanding at&lt;br/&gt;such an exponential rate that finding relevant results to technical knowledge&lt;br/&gt;searches is increasingly difficult. Further, content is expanding so fast that most&lt;br/&gt;fields are rapidly forming sub-disciplines, leading to the ?silo-ing? of different&lt;br/&gt;knowledge sub-domains, a clear challenge to both academia and industry. We&lt;br/&gt;need ever better ways to organize and present information to users. There are&lt;br/&gt;disadvantages of the current search engines, mostly relating to excessive&lt;br/&gt;similarity in search results. Further, while these engines present information&lt;br/&gt;relating to a known search target, they are less effective at presenting&lt;br/&gt;unexpected results for information that a user has never heard of but that would&lt;br/&gt;be useful. What is therefore needed is an exploration system giving searchers a&lt;br/&gt;strong serendipitous element with a maximum likelihood of results from diverse,&lt;br/&gt;unexpected, and potentially provocative sources. This will break down silos by&lt;br/&gt;providing a rapid, relevant means for knowledge-transfer between different&lt;br/&gt;disciplines, fostering interdisciplinary innovation. This system has been designed&lt;br/&gt;to provide a means for systematic, automated discovery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 2 project is focused on&lt;br/&gt;optimizing and scaling a serendipitous document search system for repurposing&lt;br/&gt;technologies by analogy into lateral fields. Both by sub-parsing discrete content&lt;br/&gt;into ontologically separable entities, such as capability, characteristic, and&lt;br/&gt;composition, and by comparatively assessing certain of these attributes between&lt;br/&gt;such entities, the attribute relatedness of these entities can be used to drive their&lt;br/&gt;self-assembly into related attribute networks. This approach provides a&lt;br/&gt;significant value proposition for drug repurposing, which is the current focus of&lt;br/&gt;this project. To scale the pair-wise comparison and network assembly of millions&lt;br/&gt;of documents, a map-reduce based text-processing framework will be developed&lt;br/&gt;so that massively parallel computations can be carried out in a time- and costefficient&lt;br/&gt;manner. A distributed search engine technology will be deployed to&lt;br/&gt;enable rapid querying of the emerging document relationship network. A series of&lt;br/&gt;machine learning algorithms will then be used to determine potentially hidden&lt;br/&gt;structural architectural features within the document relationship network.&lt;br/&gt;Machine learning will elucidate the nature of the relationships in drug networks&lt;br/&gt;through analyses of inter-node relationships and sub-graph motifs (termed&lt;br/&gt;?innovation motifs?). Documents including U.S. patents and scientific papers will&lt;br/&gt;be processed in the system.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1430780</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sager</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brian_m_sager@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Leonardo Innovations Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940251848</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6502244508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>423 8th Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4080</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED COMP RESEARCH PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8032</Code>
      <Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8034</Code>
      <Text>Hardware Components</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8035</Code>
      <Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9139</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>169E</Code>
      <Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
