<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Evaluating barriers and opportunities addressed by diversity internship programs: A social cognitive analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14495</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Under the supervision of Susan K Jacobson, at University of Florida, Ph.D. student Nia Haynes will analyze the influence of two national internship programs on racial and ethnic minority youth perceptions about natural resource careers, using a framework based on social cognitive career theory. She will also conduct a quantitative survey of current students in natural resource fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will help promote diversity in the natural resource career fields and will result in the co-PI completing theoretically driven research using social research designs, methods and analysis. The researchers will build partnerships with natural resource institutions and agencies that will encourage future collaborations. Research results will be disseminated through presentations at stakeholder meetings, an international conference, through manuscripts submitted to peer-reviewed journals, and a report to natural resource agencies, non-government organizations and academic programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1431398</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jacobson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jacobson@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haynes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>n.haynes@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
