<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2014 Industrial Ecology GRC: Transforming the Industrial Metabolism Renaissance Tuscany II Ciocco Resort, Lucca (Barga), Italy, June 1-6, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1431898 &lt;br/&gt;Weisz &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a grant for participant support of leading scholars and excellent young scientists from the USA to attend the Gordon Research Conference on Industrial Ecology (GRC-IE). The conference will be held in Lucca (Barga), Italy, June 1-6, 2014. The conference will focus on the science informing the transformation of the industrial metabolism towards sustainability. The concept of industrial metabolism refers to the flows of energy and materials that constitute the physical basis of modern societies: the use of raw materials, their conversion into manufactured capital, goods and services, and their subsequent release to the environment as wastes and emissions. This is a topic of increasing policy importance, as multiple challenges including climate mitigation &amp; adaptation, motivate a stronger focus towards transforming the industrial metabolism. Special emphasis will be given to new modeling techniques and scenario-based analysis. Invited speakers will present the research frontiers in spearheading this topic.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1431898</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Helga</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weisz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chavez@pik-potsdam.de</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
