<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Teaching to Learn: Improving Undergraduate Science Education Through Engagement in K-7 Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>810876</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The majority of research on undergraduate science education focuses on the impact of various instructional techniques on students' learning of science. Less understood are the roles of undergraduates' understanding of and attitude toward science in shaping science course-taking and persistence in science majors. This project aims to address this gap in research by investigating the impact of science teaching experiences on undergraduate students. The project will accomplish this by engaging science, education, and liberal arts students in a year-long experience to develop and teach science lessons in K-7 classrooms in a high-needs school district (North Adams Public Schools). This experience is expected to (1) deepen undergraduates' understanding of the nature of science, (2) increase their ability to explain science concepts to non-specialists, (3) increase their confidence in their own ability in science, (4) create a "community of science learners" that can sustain pursuit of further science coursework, and ultimately (5) lead to more science course taking and higher retention in science majors. Undergraduates from the Massachusetts College of Liberal Arts (a small public liberal arts college) and Williams College (a small private liberal arts college) will work with K-7 teachers and college science professors to develop science units based on the Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS). Pairs of undergraduate students will co-teach these units with K-7 classroom teachers and the support of college science education professors over the course of the school year. The undergraduates and K-7 teachers will also participate in joint professional development to deepen their understanding of both the nature of scientific inquiry and science teaching, and to reinforce their connection as a community of learners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project bridges two areas of research to investigate the impact of teaching science in elementary settings on the science learning and education outcomes for science, education, and liberal arts undergraduates. NSF's Graduate Teaching Fellows in K-12 Education (GK-12) program, which engaged STEM graduate students in K-12 teaching, found several positive impacts of teaching experiences on graduate students, including increased teaching skills, improved skills at communicating scientific concepts to non-specialist audiences, increased skill in collaboration, improved research skills, and an enhanced understanding of the relevance of their research to society. Studies of informal STEM education opportunities (including undergraduate research, internships, and mentoring) have found impacts on students' understanding of the nature of science, science self-efficacy, communication skills, and retention in science majors. However, there has been little research to date on the impact of informal science teaching experiences on the science education and attitudes of undergraduates. This project is designed both to influence the likelihood that undergraduates will enter into and complete science majors and to improve science literacy in the general populace by improving key aspects of science literacy among liberal arts undergraduates and pre-service and in-service elementary school teachers. Project outcomes will be assessed through a variety of surveys completed by participating undergraduates and a matched comparison group, participant questionnaires to gather qualitative data on the "Teaching to Learn" experience, observations of teaching practice, and longitudinal transcript reviews of participants and comparison group students. In addition, the collaboration between multiple colleges and a school district will enable the assessment of the model's feasibility and impact across institutional types and diverse undergraduate populations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1432591</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stroud</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>N.Stroud@mcla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Himes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c.himes@mcla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bacon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbacon@napsk12.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swoap</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jswoap@williams.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts College of Liberal Arts</Name>
      <CityName>North Adams</CityName>
      <ZipCode>012474124</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4136625106</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>375 Church Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1998</Code>
      <Text>IUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8209</Code>
      <Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
