<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Study Group on Diversity, Equity and Excellence in Achievement and Assessment in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>359001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julia Clark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project seeks to find ways to make the measurement sciences more useful to the production of intellective competence in diverse students of the STEM disciplines. A Study Group on Diversity, Equity and Excellence in Achievement and Assessment in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics Education will be established to address a set of issues posed as critical to the future of assessment for education. Building on the work of the Gordon Commission on the Future of Assessment in Education, the Study Group will undertake a series of activities culminating in the production of a report to the field including conceptual analyses, knowledge syntheses findings, and recommended specifications for a program of research and development to advance STEM education through assessment for education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Study Group will consist of fifteen research scientists and scholars of pedagogical practice who are being organized to inquire into the potential of the measurement sciences to more effectively inform the teaching and learning of STEM subject matter for students whose development is challenged by the demands of diversity, equity and excellence in intellective competence. Group members are especially interested in balancing the capabilities of the measurement sciences in the assessment of developed abilities, with equal strength in the analysis, documentation and understanding of the learning and teaching processes by which intellective competence is developed. The Group will conduct a conceptual inquiry into the interrelatedness of diversity, equity, and achievement in STEM. Special attention will be given to variance in attributions, contexts and perspectives associated with differences in life conditions, cultural experience and cultural identity. The Study Group will utilize in-person and virtual deliberations; consultative conversations; and commissioned position and review papers to generate recommendations and suggested specifications for programs of research, development and praxis designed to better inform the teaching and, especially, the learning of STEM disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1433181</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edmund</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gordon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eg379@tc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Teachers College, Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276625</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2126783000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>525 West 120th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7645</Code>
      <Text>DISCOVERY RESEARCH K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
