<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Passive shock wave attenuation using shock-free surface interaction in combination with shock focusing techniques</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>269911</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Eliasson, Veronica&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1437412&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposed experimental study is to investigate the interaction of shock waves with liquids and to discover ways to mitigate shock wave effects. This proposal is aimed at the investigation of how shock wave attenuation can be obtained by adding liquid sheets in specific geometric shapes in the path of a propagating shock wave. The fundamental work proposed here can have applications on designing cheap and reliable methods to protect buildings, vehicles, and humans from threats of shock and blast wave impact. For example, it can have an impact in the construction and mining industries where blast technology, explosives and detonation are important. Accidents in both surface and underground mines can lead to shock wave propagation with devastating effects, therefore, shock wave attenuation should be promoted to reduce damage and injury.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary research objectives are (a) to understand the dynamics between the incident shock wave and the free surface, and (b) to explore and quantify how the degree of attenuation depends on the role of Newtonian and non-Newtonian fluids and their mass, as well as thermal and inertial properties. Direct measurements of shock wave amplitude, peak pressure, total impulse in addition to quantitative and qualitative high-speed shock wave imaging will be obtained for all cases. Gaining such fundamental understanding can lead to methodologies to reduce shock impact using available and environmentally friendly liquids. Experiments will be performed in a shock tube, and numerical simulations will be performed using a finite volume approach. In terms of outreach and education, the proposal includes a well-articulated plan to involve graduate and undergraduate students in research. The Pi will work with the WiSE Program (Women in Science and Engineering) at the U of South California, whose purpose is to support and promote the participation of women and minorities, both students and faculty, in the academic life at USC. The PI will also involve high school students from the Los Angeles area in her research throughout this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1437412</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bermejo-Moreno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bermejom@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Veronica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eliasson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jeliasson@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/13/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>058E</Code>
      <Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
