<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Partial Support of the Committee on Atomic, Molecular and Optical Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports the Committee on Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Science (CAMOS) of the Board on Physics and Astronomy of the National Academies. CAMOS is a standing committee with membership drawn from universities, industry, and government laboratories. Its members have expertise that is intended to cover the full breadth of the atomic, molecular, and optical (AMO) sciences. The activities of CAMOS engage a group of leading scientists from across the subfields of AMO science in joint deliberations and provide a learning environment for that body regarding the public-policy process for science and the position of AMO in the broader context of the physical sciences. In addition, CAMOS activities lead to an improved understanding of AMO science by the broader scientific and policy-making communities. By holding multi-disciplinary workshops, preparing short, nontechnical documents, and initiating studies, CAMOS will continue to educate researchers, policy makers, and the general public about advances in AMO science that have impact in other fields of science and technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CAMOS has the following objectives: to provide active stewardship of the agenda laid out by the most recent decadal study prepared for AMO sciences, "Controlling the Quantum World"; to provide a means by which federal agencies can request technical information and assistance from the NRC about AMO science and related fields, and by which other units in the NRC can obtain expertise on AMO science; to initiate ad hoc studies and workshops on important timely topics in AMO science and/or its multidisciplinary connections with other fields of science and technology; to develop brief informational summaries of emerging topics and/or questions of current interest; to provide an interface for communication among the subfields of the AMO community as well as with the staff of federal agencies that support research in the field; and to begin preparations for the next decadal survey of AMO science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1438848</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlancaster@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1241</Code>
      <Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
