<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2014 Solid State Chemistry Gordon Research Conference: Solid State Compounds and Materials for Emerging Technologies and Sustainable Energy Generation, July 27 - August 1, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON TECHNICAL &lt;br/&gt;The 2014 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Solid State Chemistry: Solid State Compounds and Materials for Emerging Technologies and Sustainable Energy Generation funded by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry Program will be held at Colby-Sawyer College July 27-August 1, 2014. This meeting will directly impact all of the attendees by providing an open atmosphere for exchange of ideas on the cutting edge of Solid State Chemistry and it will provide a unique forum to bring together experts, young scientists, and students to disclose unpublished data, to challenge and discuss novel ideas, and to push the frontiers of science and innovation forward. New collaborations can be formed and new ideas generated that would not otherwise occur if not for these important conferences. Speakers are expected to convey cutting edge information to their colleagues with the objective that this disclosure will stimulate expansive discussion among all attendees and progressively advance the field. The inclusive, collegial atmosphere of the meeting, and the emphasis on sharing previously unpublished information, enables the cultivation of innovative approaches to address the most important challenges facing our world. This strategy is a hallmark of GRC and has served the scientific community and facilitated the advancement of science for over eight decades. There is special funding for underrepresented groups. The intent of this meeting is to promote the exchange of ideas and the building of partnerships between researchers from the academic world, industry and government laboratories. Many younger scientists are included in the program along with more senior and distinguished scientists, promising to make the presentations and discussions representative of new directions in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL &lt;br/&gt;The focus of this conference is the design and properties of materials for energy and environment applications, and the conference highlights the challenges that we face in producing enough energy while maintaining our environment. To conquer this important problem, the design of new compounds, the optimization of existing materials and the understanding of the relationship of structure and physical properties require a multidisciplinary approach in which Solid State Chemistry is the bedrock, and this conference brings together a diverse array of scientists to discuss the latest advances and challenges in Solid State Chemistry. Speakers and poster presenters are explicitly encouraged to emphasize advances, unpublished results, new and risky ideas on a variety of current topics. The organizers strongly encourage active contribution to discussions and participation in poster sessions, which offer an excellent opportunity for presenting new and exciting research. Solid State Chemistry is a multidisciplinary field whose importance continues to increase not only with the discovery of new classes of materials, but also through a deeper understanding of the diverse properties of solids made possible by modern techniques. The importance and scope of the field has grown in response to the continuing challenge to understand, control, and predict the structures and properties of solids and the need to synthesize new materials with enhanced physical properties.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1439359</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kauzlarich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smkauzlarich@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
