<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Socioeconomic And Political Development In Imperial Context</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25006</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Researchers wish to understand the nature of empires and the varying impacts of imperialism. Archaeology can contribute unique insights at both local and broad regional scales, and over considerable ranges of time. The strategies empires use to impose their power over new peoples and regions depend upon how those societies and economies are organized. Therefore to study empires one must study not just the empire, but also the people that fell under its control, and in what ways each influenced the other. This project will investigate interactions between people living in the Nasca region of Peru and representatives of the one of the earliest New World empires, the Wari, during the period AD 750-1000. It will provide specific information about the collapse of the Nasca Civilization as it was conquered by the Wari Empire, and the ways in which the Wari imposed its control over the Nasca people. It will contribute to general studies of empires and imperialism, adding to knowledge of the varied strategies available to expanding states. The knowledge thus derived will have application in a present day context as many extant "states" are the result of such processes and face similar issues in maintaining political control and unity. In addition, this project will provide international experience for American students, and educational opportunities for them and Peruvian students. Field experience gained on the project will fulfill students? degree requirements; and data recovered during this project will be used as the basis for the Co-PI?s doctoral dissertation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The following questions guide this research: 1) What was the relationship between the Wari Empire and Nasca peoples? 2) What effect did Wari imperial policies and agendas have on the Nasca community of Zorropata? 3) Did the Wari Empire exert direct political or economic control over Nasca communities in the valley around that community? Archaeological excavations will examine the remains of houses and public buildings in order to understand Nasca economic and cultural practices that may have been impacted by the Wari Empire. Researchers will investigate differences in social status, the use of space at the site, the local economy, the production and use of pottery and textiles, cooking practices, agricultural production, and other traditional practices. Archaeologists will map and excavate the site of Zorropata, and analyze artifacts and other samples collected during excavation. In addition, samples will be prepared for special analyses to be performed in American labs including chemical analyses of pottery and stone tools, and samples for radiocarbon dating.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1441840</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dost Kerchusky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sarah06@umail.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katharina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schreiber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kschreiber@anth.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
