<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2014 Gordon Research Conf.on Nanostructure Fabrication:Nanostructures in Information Tech. Energy Conversion,&amp; Nanoelectromechanical Systems Biddeford,Maine,July 13-18,2014.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9650</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will support participation of graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in the Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Nanostructure Fabrication, which will be held in Biddeford, Maine, on July 13-18, 2014 on the campus of the University of New England. The conference will bring together leading scientists and engineers from around the world for discussions on the role of nanofabrication in a wide and increasing number of scientific and technological disciplines. The conference will promote international collaboration across a broad, interdisciplinary scientific community, actively seeking speakers and participants from underrepresented groups and from geographic regions around the entire world. This format provides an ideal environment for younger scientists to establish and grow their professional network, develop their presentation skills by presenting their work to engage audiences at the poster sessions, receive mentoring from their more established peers, and gain a broader perspective on their discipline. Fostering graduate student participation and encouraging future scientific leadership are vital for the future of the field of nanofabrication. This award provides funds specifically to facilitate graduate student/postdoc attendance and participation at this GRC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nanofabrication has been integral to advances in all areas of Nanoscale Science and Technology. This GRC program will be comprised of invited oral presentations by international young and established researchers employing innovative and world-class nanofabrication in pursuit of their scientific programs. The weeklong GRC will give participants an excellent overview of the diversity with which nanofabrication drives scientific discovery and technology development. The meeting will include eight topical sessions, four poster sessions, and one session composed of short presentations of selected contributed posters. The meeting will be focused on advanced lithography options, including their role in design of new materials; chemical and bio-inspired methods for assembly of complex nanostructured materials; nanomagnetics; polymer self-assembly and its application in semiconductor electronics; high density magnetic storage; nanoelectromechanical systems; roles for nanostructures in optoelectronic devices and materials; advanced semiconductor electronic devices; and advances in devices for solid-state quantum computation. Four poster sessions will run in the afternoons and evenings during the entire weeklong meeting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1441515</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shalom</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wind</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sw2128@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Black</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ctblack@bnl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
