<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Cincinnati Symposium on Probability Theory and Applications 2014, September 19-21, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Cincinnati Symposium on Probability Theory and Applications 2014 will take place September 19 to 21, 2014 at the University of Cincinnati with a focus on current research in limit theorems for dependent structures. Dependent structures are ubiquitous in physical applications, yet present many mathematical challenges. Several important breakthroughs have been made in recent years by combining ideas from two or more of the Symposium focus areas. The Symposium will provide a platform to showcase recent developments and stimulate new cross-disciplinary investigations and collaborations. In order to stimulate new ideas and assist with the professional development of young probabilists, the Symposium will emphasize the participation of graduate students and recent PhD recipients. Besides invited talks by senior researchers, there will be ample opportunities for young investigators to present their research in shorter talks and at a poster forum. By providing travel support, especially to junior probabilists, this award will facilitate interactions and potential collaborations between junior and more established researchers, and encourage the infusion of new ideas across probability and related fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recently, significant progress has been made in understanding how classical limit theorems persist or break down when the assumption of weak dependence is not valid. At the same time, models with complex dependence structures, notably arising from random matrix theory and mathematical physics, present new challenges to probabilists. The Symposium will bring together experts and junior researchers working on &lt;br/&gt;1) almost sure limit theorems via martingale approximations, &lt;br/&gt;2) long-range dependence phenomena and infinite ergodic theory, and &lt;br/&gt;3) spectra of large-dimensional random matrices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Symposium website: http://math.uc.edu/probability</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1441641</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Magda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peligrad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peligrm@ucmail.uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buckingham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>buckinrt@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ju-Yi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ju-yi.yen@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yizao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Yizao.wang@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
      <ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1263</Code>
      <Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
