<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CyberSEES: Type 1: Collaborative Research: Infrastructure and Technology Supporting Citizen Science Data Usage and Distribution for Education and Sustainability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will develop and study a proof-of-concept cyberinfrastructure to support effective distribution and use of data from citizen science, a form of collaboration engaging both volunteers and professionals in authentic scientific research, with integrated ecological and social science research to improve the system and demonstrate the utility of the data. Biodiversity data that document the degree of variation of life through species diversity, phenology, and geographic occurrence will be generated by science classrooms and delivered to scientists who need this data for sustainability research, enriching ongoing studies of invasive species, biodiversity, and climate science. Interviews and surveys will help identify and address scientific, social, and technological challenges associated with citizen science data sharing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will result in: 1) new hands-on STEM learning opportunities in classrooms across the nation; 2) ecological research on sustainability in both professional research settings and in participating classrooms; and 3) insights into opportunities, challenges, and strategies for improving the distribution and use of citizen science data.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1442668</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wiggins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>akwiggins@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Preece</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>preece@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8211</Code>
      <Text>CyberSEES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
