<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Supporting young scientists to attend the Gordon Research Conference Centromere Biology:The Genomics and Epigenomics of Centromere Function and Dysfunction; Waltham, MA-7/27-8/1/14</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13980</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William B. Eggleston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The centromere is the chromosomal locus that drives chromosome movement during cell division. The proper functioning of centromeres requires a complex cascade of events involving assembly of hundreds of different proteins, however, the precise mechanism by which this cascade proceeds is still largely unknown. Failure to assemble the proteins at centromeres during each cell cycle ultimately leads to chromosome mis-segregation and cell division defects in subsequent cell cycles, leading to cell division defects. Remarkable discoveries in the past decade have led to the identification of a few key players in the protein assembly involved in centromere maintenance. The 2014 meeting ?Gordon Research Conference: Centromere Biology? is the first to bring together scientists who share a common interest in elucidating the organization, assembly and dynamics of the centromere, the cellular structure that is critical to the basic cellular processes and evolution of a species. The topic of centromere biology is typically under-represented at other chromosome and centromere meetings, or alternatively, is widely dispersed and diluted across many different conferences. By highlighting diverse approaches and new discoveries, this conference aims to spur progress in the field of centromere biology across a myriad of topics, from understanding protein assembly and biochemical pathways to defining patterns of inheritance. This conference will promote discussion between scientists with common professional interests and the exchange of ideas from advanced aspects of their field, enabling scientific collaborations to evolve in new directions. This conference represents a unique opportunity to encourage collaboration and discussion of new discoveries, since unpublished data is the main focus of presented material.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The venue and the program are organized to promote a welcoming, inclusive atmosphere for junior scientists and students to present their work and exchange ideas through poster sessions and informal discussions. The relatively small number of attendees (~100-150) will provide networking opportunities, mentoring, and perspectives on new research for younger participants at a critical stage in their scientific careers. Each session will include one to two talks, depending on the session length, chosen from the submitted abstracts. These selected talks will be targeted towards late breaking discoveries as well as early career scientists. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this request is to support exceptional early career scientists in the research community as well as trainees such as postdocs and graduate students working in this field with diverse backgrounds to attend the Centromere Biology Gordon Research Conference 2014. The funding from NSF will provide support for registration fee and/or travel support for participants, with preference given to post docs and graduate students to attend the meeting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1443318</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Neill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rachel.oneill@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>BETH</FirstName>
      <LastName>SULLIVAN</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>beth.sullivan@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
