<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on Frontiers in Applied and Computational Mathematics 2014, May 22 - 23, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports the participation of undergraduate and graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, junior faculty, and other researchers in a conference on "Frontiers in Applied and Computational Mathematics" (FACM) at the New Jersey Institute of Technology (NJIT). This successful conference series has been organized over the past ten years by the Department of Mathematical Sciences and Center for Applied Mathematics and Statistics at NJIT. The annual meeting has established itself as a leading forum for the dissemination of research in applied and computational mathematics and statistics. FACM conferences are more intimate and student centered than large society meetings and a goal of the organizers is to introduce future leaders of applied mathematics to established investigators and emerging research areas. Participation among graduate students and postdocs is greatly enhanced through a competitive application process by which they can give presentations in minisymposia alongside leading scientists. Past FACM conferences have an excellent record of participation of women and underrepresented minorities, and special efforts will be made to continue this trend.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;FACM 2014 is focussed on mathematical biology and biostatistics. The meeting features invited plenary talks, minisymposia, and poster sessions on areas of great current interest, such as analysis of large data sets, computational biology, circadian rhythms, and models of brain disorders. This conference series brings together mathematicians, statisticians, scientists and engineers in an environment where significant interaction and cross-fertilization take place. For students and postdocs, this will be a major learning and networking experience that will help them with their research and career paths.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1444295</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Siegel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>misieg@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amitabha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bose</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bose@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cyrill</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muratov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>muratov@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>323 DOCTOR MARTIN LUTHER</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
