<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NUE: Sustainable Nanotechnology Education for Undergraduate Engineering Students</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this NUE program, Sustainable Nanotechnology Education for Undergraduate Engineering Students, under the direction of Dr. Navid Saleh, is to develop two technical electives, a theory-based course and a laboratory course, with integrated social and ethical aspects utilizing metacognitive pedagogical strategies. In addition, a workshop involving experts experienced with real-life decision-making in nanotechnology development will support the courses three goals: introduce nanoscale concepts and sustainability principles to engineering students; integrate social and ethical aspects in the context of nanomaterial sustainability; and enhance core knowledge by infusing critical thinking with the hands-on PBL-based modules in laboratory sessions. The proposed courses and workshop will be novel in four aspects: their metacognitive teaching style; the integration of ethical and societal aspects with the technical content; the integration of sustainability with nanotechnology; and emphasis on safe and sustainable nanomaterial design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The National Nanotechnology Initiative (NNI) calls for nano-education in the context of real-life implications. There is a critical need to introduce nanoscale principles to undergraduate students so that these future engineers will consider sustainability and safety of this emerging technology at the outset. Often, nanomaterial design is disconnected from its safety and sustainability concerns. Students suffer from this and extend it to real-world practice. However, educating students in nanotechnology with integrated societal components challenges traditional pedagogical structure. Problem-based learning (PBL) is one approach that can confront such challenges, where the fundamental nanoscale concepts can be taught in an inquiry-based setting. This program addresses these challenges by integrating societal and ethical aspects with technical nanoscale phenomena, utilizing an interactive PBL approach under a theme of sustainable nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program will be a true collaboration among researchers and educators of engineering, sustainability, ethics, and communication, and the merging of these disciplines into the proposed courses will provide a novel experience for undergraduates. It is projected that 60-100 students will be impacted by the courses during the two year project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1445960</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blackhurst</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mfb30@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/14/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Navid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Saleh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>navidsaleh@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Korgel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>korgel@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hillary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hart@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary Jo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kirisits</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kirisits@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7219</Code>
      <Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY UNDERGRAD EDUCA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>113E</Code>
      <Text>ENG CURRICULUMN DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7219</Code>
      <Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY UNDERGRAD EDUCA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
