<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Conference on Nanoscience and Technology (ICN+T 2014); Vail, Colorado; July 20-25, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is for the partial support of the International Conference on Nanoscience and Technology (ICN+T 2014), to be held in Vail, Colorado, July 20-25, 2014. This major international meeting will provide a single forum for discussion of the latest developments in nano-scale science and technology and recent advances in scanning probe and related instrumentation techniques. Regular meetings of the key researchers in this field are necessary for the exchange of ideas, information, and state-of-the-art technologies, in order to enable and accelerate advances and breakthroughs the fields of nanoscience and nanotechnology. This international conference is a key mechanism for linking basic science with engineering towards the development of nano-enabled products, which are of significant importance to the US and world economies. This conference is held biannually and offers a forum for the open exchange of new and previously unpublished scientific ideas. It will cover a variety of topics ranging from nanoelectronics to nanomedicine to nanomanufacturing. The conference includes presentations and extended discussions and interactions among international participants. This forum has been instrumental in the generation and incubation of breakthrough and transformative ideas in many areas of nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will partially support the participation of junior participants, including graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and early career faculty members. A total of 400 attendees are expected at the conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1445378</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murday</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>murday@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
