<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Common Vision for the Undergraduate Mathematics Program in 2025</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>144802</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project, led by the Mathematical Association of America (MAA), is to bring together leading national stakeholders in the mathematics education enterprise to reconsider long-standing traditions, both curricular and pedagogical, of the process of undergraduate mathematics education. The outcome from this workshop will lead to a roadmap for modernizing the undergraduate mathematics curriculum. The primary goal of this initiative is to develop a shared vision in the mathematical sciences community of the need to update the undergraduate mathematics program, especially the first two years. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MAA is partnering with other professional societies to evaluate how a modernization of programs in the mathematical sciences would better prepare students for the demands of the 21st century workplace. The project aims to catalyze widespread adoption of curricula and pedagogies that are (1) geared toward developing a broad base of intellectual skills and competencies to better prepare students for the workforce and (2) simultaneously endorsed by a broad cross-section of the mathematical sciences community. Another major objective of the project is to highlight alternative pathways through the general education mathematics requirement, including alternatives to traditional remedial mathematics courses, for entering students not adequately prepared for college mathematics. These alternatives could more effectively prepares students for their future careers and studies in STEM disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1446000</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Saxe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>saxe@macalester.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ensley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>densley@maa.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Braddy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lbraddy@maa.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mathematical Association of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200361358</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023875200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1529 18th St NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1998</Code>
      <Text>IUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
