<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pan-American Conference on Differential Equations and Non-linear Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the conference "Pan-American Conference on Differential Equations and Nonlinear Analysis" that will take place at University of Buenos Aires, Argentina, February 9-20, 2015. The conference is the tenth installment in a series of triennial conferences started in 1994. Locations alternate between North and South Americas. The project will support participation of junior American researchers who will be exposed to their international peers and to the stimulating atmosphere of the conference. Educational program of the Conference is integrated with research activities. It includes a series of mini-courses, half of which will be taught by the US women mathematicians. The Conference will further foster international collaboration between mathematicians of the Americas. The conference and related mini-courses cover a wide array of subjects from some of the most important applications of differential equations as well as some of the latest mathematical analysis techniques for their study. The type of questions to be discussed is instrumental for many applications, ranging from mathematical and statistical physics, fluid dynamics to engineering macro and micromechanics, mathematical finance, collective dynamics in social sciences, as well as biological and climate sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, the intellectual focus of the conference is to bring together a group of experts in different aspects of continuum and statistical models for gas dynamics and associated free boundary problems, as well as well as the associated dynamics, and stochastic noise effects, among others. Some of the leading world experts in applied partial differential equations, dynamical systems, financial mathematics, analysis and geometric analysis will serve as plenary speakers or mini-course lecturers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conference web site http://mate.dm.uba.ar/~xamericas/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1446125</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Irene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gamba</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gamba@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
