<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Data-Driven Organic Chemistry: Enabling and Innovating the Study of Chemical Reactions, Sept. 11-12, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99815</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Participants at this workshop will explore opportunities for capturing and exploiting the wealth of information that is increasingly becoming available from highly instrumentation-focused, data-driven investigations of chemical reactions. They will outline future possibilities for incorporating new tools in academic and industrial research, as well as highlighting both existing and potential funding models to drive pre-competitive collaboration. Ultimately this approach may lead the way to new scientific insights, new ways of addressing scientific questions and new tools with which to address them. The workshop includes discussion of novel educational approaches for the training of future generations of students and practitioners in the study and application of organic reactions through multidisciplinary teams and approaches.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposed workshop will lay the foundation for new, multi-disciplinary, systems-based research infrastructure that combines recent advances in reaction monitoring and data analysis. Developing research tools to provide a deeper understanding of reaction processes will ultimately provide a platform for future innovations in organic synthesis, synthetic methodology, and catalysis, and in how these are in turn applied in future industrial processes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1447743</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blackmond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>blackmon@scripps.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The Scripps Research Institute</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920371000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8587848653</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10550 N TORREY PINES RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1978</Code>
      <Text>PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8084</Code>
      <Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
