<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: US IGNITE: A gigabit network and Cyber-Physical framework for Advanced Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>237210</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Manufacturing, and especially advanced manufacturing, is a key element of long-term U.S. prosperity and national security. Advanced manufacturing is at the threshold of the next major revolution catalyzed by advances in networking and Internet technologies. A new generation of agile and 'information based manufacturing' will involve collaborative use of cyber physical resources, simulation and other design/manufacturing tools. In this project, the manufacturing domain of interest is an emerging field called Micro Devices Assembly (MDA). MDA is an emerging advanced manufacturing field involving the manipulation and assembly of micron sized devices. Products in sensors, medical devices (such as heart monitors), surveillance devices and semiconductor manufacturing can be produced using such technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project an ultra-fast network links distributed cyber physical resources which are used to accomplish the assembly of micron sized devices. The project has two major categories of tools involving the life cycle of micro devices assembly: cyber and physical. Cyber tools will be used to accomplish of assembly planning alternatives, analysis of candidate assembly plans, and Virtual Reality (VR) based simulation of assembly alternatives for target micro designs. Physical tools (or resources) will include manufacturing equipment (to assemble target micro designs), cameras and other related sensors (to guide in the complex assembly as well as to provide feedback during assembly). Such a cyber physical approach demonstrates the feasibility of using ultrafast networks and advanced networking technologies such as Software Defined Networking to support next generation collaborative frameworks for advanced manufacturing. In this system the high-definition multimedia streaming interfaces associated with the VR environment will enable partners to collaboratively propose, compare and refine assembly planning alternatives. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will use the advanced manufacturing test bed outlined in this project to support teaching of cyber physical concepts and manufacturing frameworks to engineering students at Oklahoma State University; some of the cyber tools developed will also be used subsequently as part of K-12 STEM learning activities involving students in Stillwater, Oklahoma City and the Muscogee (Creek) Nation schools in Oklahoma.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1447237</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cecil</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>j.cecil@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
      <CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
      <ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
