<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps Sites: Michigan Tech Innovation Corps (I-Corps) Site Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>293026</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anita J. LaSalle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project creates an NSF I-Corps Site at Michigan Technological University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF Innovation Corps (I-Corps) Sites are NSF-funded entities established at universities whose purpose is to nurture and support multiple, local teams to transition their technology concepts into the marketplace. Sites provide infrastructure, advice, resources, networking opportunities, training and modest funding to enable groups to transition their work into the marketplace or into becoming I-Corps Team applicants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A typical I-Corps Site is funded for approximately $100,000 per year for up to three years. The Site funding is used to by academic institutions to catalyze teams (with amounts ranging from $1,000 to $3,000) whose technology concepts are likely candidates for commercialization. The make-up of teams at the Sites is modeled after the composition of I-Corps Teams, and education at the Sites shares the principles of the I-Corps Curriculum. With the support and mentorship of the Sites, the teams will learn first-hand about entrepreneurship and explore the transition of their ideas, devices, processes or other intellectual activities into the marketplace.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I-Corps Sites also strengthen innovation locally and regionally and contribute to the National Innovation Network of mentors, researchers, entrepreneurs and investors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Michigan Tech's innovation success looks to the Sites Program to achieve higher levels of translating innovations to market through a structured I-Corps Site approach, particularly at the undergraduate and graduate levels. Also, this project adapts and applies the recently developed Lean Start-up methodology as a means to strengthen their innovation ecosystem. By introducing Lean Start-up methodology to I-Corps Site teams, as in the National Program, it is anticipated that there will be increased start-up business development and other commercialization initiatives, increased rate of success of those initiatives, and improved knowledge and skill development that will be used, shared, and perpetuated by all faculty, staff and student participants in current and future initiatives. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;By strengthening their infrastructure and support systems with an I-Corps Site, Michigan Tech will be better positioned to contribute to the economic challenges of the country and their geographical region. Participation in NSF's I-Corps Site program will allow Michigan Tech to increase the reach of the program and contribute to the expansion of start-ups that are critical to the economic and employment growth required to survive and thrive in the 21st century.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1450364</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jrbaker@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Diebel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jfdiebel@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Raber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mraber@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berkey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjberkey@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
      <CityName>Houghton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8046</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps - Sites</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
