<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Experimental tests aimed at understanding debris flow initiation from runoff</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Marisa C. Palucis has been granted an NSF Earth Sciences Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a research and education plan at the California Institute of Technology. The initiation mechanisms and hazards associated with debris flows generated through runoff are poorly understood, but are common in areas recently burned by fire, and in semi-arid to arid regions with sparse vegetation and an abundance of exposed bedrock. Dr. Palucis' investigation will focus on examining two possible mechanisms that may initiate debris flows generated by runoff, progressive transport of the sediment and elevated pore pressures. The results will be used to inform about location (i.e. slopes) and environmental conditions (i.e. grain size and discharge) leading to debris flow initiation, which is needed for hazard mapping and assessment, especially in fire prone regions of the world. The education plan will consist of developing and implementing interactive desktop laboratories will be presented on a monthly basis to K-8 students within the Pasadena Unified School District (PUSD). Also, two undergraduate students will be mentored through Caltech's Summer Undergraduate Research Fellows (SURF) program, where the students will design and perform flume experiments over the course of 10-weeks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will conduct multiple flume experiments to investigate these two mechanisms, where the flow discharge (and hence shear stresses on the bed), grain size distribution (which may control pore pressure generation in granular flows), and slope are tested independently. These experiments will provide a valuable and robust dataset linking sediment supply characteristics and flow hydraulics on steep slopes. The experimental data collected here will provide one of the most detailed datasets to date on sediment transport modes and will bridge the gap between data being collected in the field and experimental data. Debris flows are a major geomorphic process in mountainous landscapes, though most models currently do not account for debris flows as sediment transport agents. Therefore, better definition of the parameter space describing debris flow occurrence is a key ingredient for predicting landscape evolution over longer timescales.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1452337</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marisa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Palucis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Palucis Marisa C</Name>
      <CityName>Oakland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>946091103</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
