<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Full-duplex wireless networks by means of reflected power: Theory and applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>182594</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>phillip regalia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>One key limit to spectrum utilization efficiency involves the current practice of half-duplex communication, in which a node cannot transmit and receive on the same frequency at the same time. Some recent studies have provided experimental evidence and methodologies for full-duplex communication. To date, however, all full-duplex demonstrations have been predicated on the principle that the transmitter and the receiver must generate their own radio-carrier waves independently, which in practice results in a high level of self-interference at both nodes. The objective of this CAREER project is to create reliable full-duplex wireless networks by means of reflected power.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will pursue backscatter modulation, where electromagnetic waves are modulated and reflected by the same antenna that receives them. Within this framework, the end-user receives a signal free of self-interference. This research offers a new paradigm for two-way wireless networks: rather than avoiding self-interference as in half-duplex -- or combating self-interference as in full-duplex -- nodes will re-use the received interfering radio-carrier waves to transfer information. The results of this analysis will advance the knowledge of antenna scattering for a wide range of applications. The proposed implementation in hardware will incite an exchange between algorithm innovation and hardware implementation, pushing the limit of spectrum-efficiency communication.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal investigator will also embed the proposed research into pedagogy by creating a center of wireless communications at Purdue University Calumet. The center will provide a range of opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students to gain direct experience in testing, evaluating, and improving backscatter modulation for full-duplex communications. Given the current pervasiveness of two-way wireless communication, the results of this research can be used to significantly increase the spectral efficiency of future wireless networks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1453426</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Besma</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smida</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smida@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7797</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
