<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Molecular Catalysis for Waste Valorization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Yuriy Roman&lt;br/&gt;Proposal #: 1454299&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is aimed at advancing the use of abundant domestic energy sources for liquid transportation fuels and chemicals to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by improving the utilization of renewable carbon. The PI proposes to valorize biomass-derived waste streams, a long-standing challenge in the chemical/biological conversion of lignocellulosic biomass. The approach uses a coupled synthetic and reaction engineering approach to develop catalytic materials capable of selectively upgrading waste biomass fractions and links advanced synthesis and characterization techniques with rigorous reactivity measurements. Catalyst design efforts are focused on reducible and tunable metal oxides that feature the appropriate properties required to upgrade complex macromolecules at scale. Prior results from the PI's group have shown that such catalysts are capable of breaking targeted C-O bonds of oxygenates with high specificity without saturating C-C double bonds. The PI aims to bridge the existing gap between model compounds and real streams by studying macromolecules of increasing complexity. The proposed work is based on the analysis of numerous scenarios for the integration of waste products into various fuel and chemical streams in a biorefinery with maximum economic benefit. Ultimately, the goal is to devise a catalytic toolbox that can be used to maximize carbon efficiency, product yields, and catalyst longevity during waste conversion, thereby improving current state-of-the-art valorization methods. When taken together, these solutions represent a tipping point in the prospects for specific biomass waste as a viable, commercially relevant sustainable feedstock.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the growing interest in the use of renewable carbon sources for the production of chemicals, polymers, and fuels, lignin conversion into value-added chemicals has been of high interest in biorefining. Lignin is the most abundant source of aromatic carbon in nature and the most abundant natural macromolecule after cellulose and hemicellulose. The U.S. Energy Security and Independence Act of 2007 mandates the development of 79 billion liters of second-generation biofuels annually by 2022. Assuming a yield of 355 liters per dry ton of biomass, 223 million tons of biomass will be used annually, producing about 62 million tons of lignin. The amount of lignin from an industrial cellulosic ethanol plant will potentially increase to ca. 100,000 to 200,000 tons per year. The scale disparity existing between lignin output and the low-market volume of chemical additives currently derived from lignin will shape the outlook on lignin valorization towards an accelerated development effort for new conversion strategies. Cleavage of lignin's primary ether linkages leads to several monomeric and oligomeric aromatic compounds that are highly functionalized with alcohol, aldehyde, ether, or acid substituents. These monomeric compounds are susceptible to an extensive array of reductive or oxidative transformations to generate paraffinic, olefinic, aromatic hydrocarbons, or aromatics with increased or targeted functionality. A monomer yield as small as 7 wt.% could provide revenues ranging from $0.14 to $0.21 per kg of lignin based on the value of the "green chemicals" produced during depolymerization. Leftover oligomer-rich fractions comprised of oxygenated dimeric and trimeric compounds may serve as fuel additives after hydroprocessing to produce commodity products, including jet fuel. Despite its perceived potential, lignin is usually burned as a low-grade fuel. In select cases, unprocessed lignin is used commercially as a dispersant, emulsifier, adsorbent or chelating agent. Therefore, the mandated production of 79 billion liters of second-generation biofuels annually by 2022 will inevitably generate massive amounts of carbonaceous waste streams (e.g., lignin). One route to the effective processing of such streams into value-added products hinges on the development of an efficient catalytic system capable of selectively depolymerizing and activating targeted C-O and C-C bonds. To address this challenge, the PI proposes an integrated research plan that focuses on reducible metal oxides as a platform to create a catalytic toolbox that can be tailored to perform targeted depolymerization and deoxygenation sequences. Ultimately, he aims to provide guidance for the development of disruptive catalytic technologies to valorize waste streams while also establishing a comprehensive fundamental framework for molecular catalyst design and mechanistic understanding of C-O/C-C bond activation. The implementation of earth-abundant, redox active catalysts that operate under mild conditions in bio-refining processes is consistent with a vision of an integrated biorefinery that combines biological and thermochemical technologies to produce a range of value-added fuels and chemicals from non-food agricultural feedstock. This research could contribute to the long-term national scientific progress, economic growth, and improved international competitiveness in the development of sustainable technologies. The research and educational activities conceive an integrated strategy to train students, including undergraduates from underrepresented communities, in subjects related to sustainable energy, materials science, catalysis, and reaction engineering, while also disseminating the results and approaches to the broader community through outreach programs and curriculum development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1454299</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuriy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yroman@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>044E</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
