<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Development of a robust multiplex protein test for cardiovascular disease research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>750000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is in the $1 billion life science research market that is served mainly by multiplex protein tests. The research proposed here has tremendous potential as a tool for highly accurate and robust detection of proteins that have been linked to cardiovascular disease. Additionally, the development of this core technology can be used for research of numerous other diseases. The product developed during this project has potential applications in the pharmaceutical and contract research organization markets for drug discovery, monitoring therapeutic efficacy, and assisting with clinical studies. While this Phase II proposal includes the development and commercialization of a DVT panel, the commercial product offering will cover a wider variety of disease-related proteins for research applications (e.g. protein combinations in which academic researchers, contract research organizations, or pharmaceutical companies have interest).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will result in a better, more robust tool for detection of disease-related proteins in patient blood. The product will be able to measure the amounts of multiple proteins at one time without a problem known as ?antibody crosstalk?, which hinders the quality of results when using other technologies. Work on this project will involve developing a kit that includes equipment and reagents for an end-user to work with and analyze blood samples for proteins of interest, in this case those involved with cardiovascular disease. A working prototype device was developed as part of Phase I funding, and Phase II will improve upon the device (increased analysis time and multiplexing) until useful for the analysis of clinical samples. Patient samples, already collected, banked, and de-identified under IRB approval, will be analyzed in a collaborative effort with researchers at the University of Michigan. Results from Phase II support will include a useful multiplexed protein biomarker immunoassay platform that has been validated using patient blood samples.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1456281</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dishinger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.dishinger@phasiqinc.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>PhasiQ, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Plymouth</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481700000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7342333151</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>46701 N. Commerce Center Dr.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8038</Code>
      <Text>Biotechnology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8042</Code>
      <Text>Health and Safety</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
