<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WiFiUS: Ubiquitous Video over Dynamic Spectrum</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Mobile phones and tablets are the most widely-used wireless communication devices nowadays. Video already represents the majority of mobile traffic and is expected to grow significantly in the coming years. Network operators are already facing shortage of bandwidth to support such a huge amount of traffic, despite the availability of newer cellular communication technologies. A solution to increase the availability and the efficiency of wireless communication technologies is given by cognitive radio networks (CRNs). Enabled by adaptive communication protocols, CRNs have the capability to sense a wide range of the spectrum and the agility to make use of the available resources dynamically. Accordingly, they can reclaim unused spectrum (i.e., whitespace) for wireless communications while avoiding interferences with between licensed and unlicensed users. However, video delivery over CRNs presents several challenges related to the highly-varying nature of the channel, the presence of misbehaving users, and the dynamic availability of heterogeneous resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses such challenges and makes CRNs suitable as a platform to provide ubiquitous wireless video. The research takes a flexible approach that is applicable to diverse regulations across national boundaries and specifically targets mobile devices. It helps create a cognitive phone, i.e., a smartphone with cognitive radio capabilities, to bridge the gap between the technologies behind CRNs and real applications. The project builds on two major research thrusts. First, it adopts spectrum crowd-sensing as a means to model the availability of whitespace at multiple scales and support long-lived communications. Such an approach enables novel solutions to accurately characterize the channel and enforce the policies established by the communication authorities. Second, it leverages adaptive mechanisms as foundations to efficiently deliver video streams to end users. These mechanisms are implemented through streaming protocols and components in the network infrastructure that provide video content with a target quality of experience. The project also integrates synergistic activities between the United States and Finland in education, industry collaboration, and entrepreneurship.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1456847</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chiang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chiangm@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8229</Code>
      <Text>WiFiUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
