<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Mathematics Mentoring and Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>612206</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stephanie August</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Mathematics Mentoring and Scholarship (MMS) program at the University of the Incarnate Word (UIW) in San Antonio Texas will increase the number of academically talented but financially needy students qualified to enter the STEM workforce or graduate school upon completing a bachelor's degree in mathematics. The program will provide annual scholarships to 15 mathematics majors along with funds for travel for professional development and to conduct academic presentations. Students will participate in weekly mentoring sessions to address any issues concerning their courses, degree, and college experience. Recruitment will target local high schools and five local community colleges in the Alamo Colleges network. This project will increase the number of academically talented but financially needy students qualified to enter graduate school in mathematics or to enter the workforce in a technical area of national need that requires professionals with advanced mathematics knowledge.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of the program are to increase student retention and graduation and to ensure participation in mentoring and professional development activities. The program also encourages student participation in research programs and/or internships to facilitate placement of in a technical field or graduate program. Scholars in the program will be paired with a peer to guide them through issues or concerns they have regarding university life, the mathematics degree, and other program related issues. Field trips to local employers will expose students to real-world STEM experiences and provide them with potential employment opportunities. The MMS program has the potential to increase the number of woman and underrepresented groups available to purse STEM related graduate degrees or employment and to develop effective academic interventions to support these groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1458026</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sulyeman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tek@uiwtx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joleen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beltrami</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>beltrami@uiwtx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Theresa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martines</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>martines@uiwtx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of The Incarnate Word</Name>
      <CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782096318</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2108296000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4301 Broadway St.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
