<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Paradox of Salt Marshes as a Source of Alkalinity and Low pH, High Carbon Dioxide Water to the Ocean: A First In-depth Study of A Diminishing Source</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>336731</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henrietta N. Edmonds</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Carbon production in vegetated coastal systems such as marshes is among the highest in the biosphere. Resolving carbon production from marshes and assessing their impacts on coastal carbon cycling are critical to determining the long-term impacts of global change such as ocean acidification and eutrophication. In this project, researchers will use new methods to improve the assessment of carbon production from salt marshes. The overarching goals are to understand the role of coastal wetlands in altering carbonate chemistry, alkalinity, and carbon budgets of the coastal ocean, as well as their capacity to buffer against anthropogenically driven chemical changes, such as ocean acidification. This project will involve training for undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral researchers, and will provide educational opportunities for students from a local Native American tribe. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tidal water, after exchange with intertidal salt marshes, contains higher total alkalinity (TA), higher carbon dioxide, but lower pH. These highly productive, vegetated wetlands are deemed to export both alkalinity and dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) to the ocean. This creates an apppartent paradox in that salt marshes are both an acidifying and alkalizing source to the ocean. Limited studies suggest that marsh DIC and alkalinity export fluxes may be a significant player in regional and global carbon budgets, but the current estimates are still far too uncertain to be conclusive. Unfortunately, tidal marsh ecosystems have dramatically diminished in the recent past, and are likely to diminish further due to sea level rise, land development, eutrophication, and other anthropogenic pressures. To assess the potential impacts of this future change, it is imperative to understand its current status and accurately evaluate its significatce to other parts of the carbon cycle. Similarly, little is know about the distinct sources of DIC and alkalinity being exported from marshes via tidal exchange, although aerobic and various anaerobic respiration processes have been indicated. In this study, researchers will undertake an in-depth study using new methods to vastly improve export fluxes from intertidal salt marshes through tidal exchange over minutes to annual scales, characterize and evaluate the compostiion (carbonate versus non-carbonate alkalinity) of marsh exported TA, the role and significance of the DOC pool in altering carbonate chemistry and export fluxes, identify sources of DIC being exported in tidal water, and investigate how marsh export of TA and DIC impacts carbonate chemistry and the carbon and alkalinity budgets in coastal waters.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1459521</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhaohui 'Aleck'</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zawang@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/27/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1670</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1382</Code>
      <Text>OCEAN ACIDIFICATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
