<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Social Networks, Transactive Memory and Team Performance: An Experimental Investigation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jonathan W. Leland</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Teams are increasingly used in a variety of organizational contexts, including education, health care, government and for-profit firms. Information about how to increase their effectiveness promises to improve the performance and competitiveness of organizations in the U.S. and the well being of their members. Our proposed research has implications not only for teams in traditional work settings but also in new emerging settings such as distributed work teams and online communities. We identify the patterns of communication that lead to the strongest transactive memory and the highest team performance. Thus, the research will result in information that team members and leaders can use to improve their team's performance. In addition, the development of a behavioral measure of TMS would enable researchers to analyze TMS in large teams and geographically distributed contexts, which are becoming increasingly prevalent in organizations and online communities around the world. All together, the results have the potential to advance our understanding of team collaboration, team formation, communication networks and team performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research examines the effects of communication networks on transactive memory system development and team performance. A transactive memory system (TMS) is a collective system for encoding, storing and retrieving information. Teams with well-developed TMSs have been found to perform better across a variety of tasks compared to teams lacking TMSs. Known as systems of "who knows what," a TMS emerges through communications and interactions among team members as they learn and rely on each other's skills and knowledge. Although a TMS hinges on communication and interaction, very little research has been conducted on how communication networks affect a group's TMS. Communication networks constrain or enable communication within a team and thus potentially alter the development of TMS. Our research investigates the characteristics of communication networks that enhance the development of TMS in a series of studies incorporating complementary laboratory and archival methods. First, we manipulate the communication networks that exist within teams in an experiment to examine the effects of network characteristics on the team's TMS and performance. We investigate two dimensions of team performance: the number of errors and creativity. Second, because in many contexts individuals choose their own networks and/or their positions within the network, we compare the effects of networks and position assignments that are imposed by the experimenter to those that are chosen by participants. This enables us to determine if effects observed are due to the communication network itself or due to participants' enactment of the network. By manipulating the networks and using random assignment to networks and to positions within the networks, we are able to make causal statements about the effects of network characteristics on TMS development and team performance. Third, using data from our experiments, we will develop and refine a new unobtrusive, behavioral measure of TMS. This measure will be applied to data from real teams who use online networks for large-scale technology-mediated projects. Following the validation of this new TMS measure, we will examine how it relates to performance for large online teams.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1459963</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brandy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aven</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aven@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Argote</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>argote@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1321</Code>
      <Text>DECISION RISK &amp; MANAGEMENT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8031</Code>
      <Text>Science of Organizations</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
