<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU site: Advancing polymer materials by integrating chemistry and chemical engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>369058</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This renewal Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at Colorado School of Mines (CSM) offers unique interdisciplinary research experiences especially related to cutting edge technologies like fuel cells, solar materials, sustainability, and health care to highly qualified chemistry and chemical engineering students from diverse backgrounds. Polymer materials improve the daily lives of nearly every person in the United States. At the end of the 20th century, many mass-produced items, like car bumpers, started to be made with polymers due to combining good mechanical properties with being lightweight and cost effective. Technological innovation in the 21st century will also leverage polymer materials in the areas of renewable energy, sustainability, and medicine. Introducing undergraduate research experiences such as this will train our future human resources and help drive the plastic and polymer industry toward more advanced technology, innovative products, and efficient processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The REU Site offers opportunities for undergraduate students to engage in a 10-week summer research experience on cutting-edge projects integrating polymer science and engineering, using state-of-the-art methods, which reinforce and strengthen their classroom knowledge and encourage pursuit of graduate education. This will be achieved through integration of chemistry and chemical engineering. Unique aspects of this program include the exchanges between chemistry and chemical engineering students, as well as the range of application areas to be addressed - from renewable energy to sustainability to health care. Summer research activities are also supplemented with technical lectures as well as collaborations with the National Renewable Energy Laboratory (NREL) and the Children's Hospital Colorado. Another unique aspect of this program is the proposed workshop on the challenges inherent in commercializing new technologies, as innovations move from lab to market. This approach complements the strong professional development program that will prepare students to consider advanced studies in the field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1460712</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boyes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sboyes@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ning</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ningwu@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
      <CityName>Golden</CityName>
      <ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>115E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
