<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Research Experiences for Undergraduates in Next-generation Plant Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>662147</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This REU Site award to the Center for Plant Cell Biology (CEPCEB) of University of California at Riverside (UCR), CA, will support the training of 12 students for 10 weeks during the summers of 2015 to 2019. The CEPCEB-REU program provides authentic research experiences in "next-generation" technologies investigating the cell biology of plants and plant pathogens. Program participants get exposed to innovative experimental techniques and benefit from state-of-the-art genomics, bioinformatics, microscopy and proteomics facilities. CEPCEB supports interdisciplinary studies and encompasses 45 faculty from 12 UCR departments. The CEPCEB-REU targets a broad range of students from both two- and four-year colleges, including institutions that offer limited research opportunities or serve groups traditionally underrepresented in the sciences. A committee of three CEPCEB members selects program participants. While GPAs are considered, each student's entire record and enthusiasm for research are considered. Participating undergraduates live on campus and receive a stipend. Each student works on an independent research project mentored by an experienced researcher and/or the PI of a CEPCEB lab. Students also participate in several workshops and present their work at a symposium. Workshops include introductory sessions into concepts and methods of contemporary cell biology as well as coverage of additional topics, such as technical science writing, bio-ethics, responsible conduct of research, and preparation for graduate school. The program is evaluated on an annual basis using a common assessment tool for REU site programs, and the career outcomes of participants are tracked. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is anticipated that a total of 60 students, primarily from schools with limited research opportunities, will be trained in the program. Students will learn how research is conducted, and many will present the results of their work at scientific conferences. The CEPCEB REU will help to prepare the next generation of scientists to meet the challenges of producing food, fiber, and plant-derived fuels for mankind.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Students are required to be tracked after the program and must respond to an automatic email sent via the NSF reporting system. More information is available by visiting http://cepceb.ucr.edu/reu/ or by contacting the PI, Dr. Thomas Eulgem (thomas.eulgem@ucr.edu; 951-827-7740), or the co-PI Dr. Howard Judelson (howard.judelson@ucr.edu; 951-827-4199).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1461297</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Judelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>howard.judelson@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eulgem</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thomas.eulgem@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
