<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on Equivariant and Motivic Homotopy Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>28000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the conference "Equivariant and Motivic Homotopy Theory" held at Reed College, in Portland, Oregon on May 30-31, 2015. This meeting will bring together leading researchers, postdoctoral associates, and graduate students interested in equivariant and motivic homotopy theory to share recent progress and ideas for future research in these fields during a two-day research conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will focus on the interplay between equivariant and motivic homotopy theory. Each field has enjoyed recent success in resolving a number of longstanding problems, including the Kervaire invariant one problem and the Milnor and Bloch-Kato conjectures. They remain relevant to the study of such wide-ranging topics as topological Hochschild homology, algebraic cobordism, chromatic homotopy theory, and algebraic K-theory, and both topics are vibrant fields of research. The conference will catalyze research progress through a series of eight talks by disciplinary experts and multiple forums in which participants can communicate and collaborate on topics such as (generalized) infinite loop space machines, Picard groups of stable homotopy categories, and computations of stable motivic and equivariant homotopy groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More information can be found on the conference web page&lt;br/&gt;http://people.reed.edu/~ormsbyk/eqmotconf2015/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1462793</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Angelica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Osorno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aosorno@reed.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ormsby</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>epimorphism@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Reed College</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972028138</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037711112</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3203 S E Woodstock Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
