<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a Laser Ablation-HPLC-ICP-MS system</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1463936&lt;br/&gt;Kulp&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant supports the acquisition of a quadrupole detection inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometer (ICP-MS) equipped with high performance liquid chromatograph (HPLC) and laser ablation (LA) microprobe sample introductions systems for the Department of Geology at SUNY-Binghampton. The HPLC front-end will allow for the determination of the speciation of trace metals and metalloids in the environment for investigations of the geomicrobiological cycling of trace elements, in particular Arsenic and Antimony, that are toxic at certain valence states. The LA probe will allow for the introduction of evaporite and marine carbonate hosted fluid inclusions into the ICP-MS for determination of major (e.g., Na, Mg, Ca, K) and minor (Ba, Br, Sr) element concentrations and their ratios as proxies of the chemistry of the seawater from which they formed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Studies of fluid inclusion chemistry in Halite and marine carbonates can shed light on the variability of past ocean chemistry throughout the Phanerozoic with implications for understanding past climate and mid-ocean ridge hydrothermal processes. The instrument will also support studies of trace metal concentrations in mineral aerosols with relevance to environmental health research, studies of igneous petrogenesis with implications for understanding magma chamber processes, and studies of the composition of metallic and oxide nanoparticles used for advanced fuel cell and Li-ion battery engineering. The instrument will support graduate student research training in analytical geochemistry. This support is congruent with NSFs mission of promoting the progress of science and may advance the national prosperity and welfare through advancing knowledge of the fate and transport of potentially toxic trace metal species in the environment and related strategies to mitigate environmental health impacts and in promoting green energy technology engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1463936</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kulp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tkulp@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Graney</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgraney@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lowenstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lowenst@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>H. Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Naslund</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>naslund@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
      <CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
