<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Chemical Connectomics: Nonlinear Dynamics of Electrochemical Reaction Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>406002</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms (CSDM-A) Program of the Division of Chemistry is funding Professor Istvan Z. Kiss of Saint Louis University to investigate complex, far-from-equilibrium charge transfer chemical reactions that take place on networks imposed by dynamic environments of electrochemical devices (e.g., sensors and batteries). The identification of organizing principles and experimental characterization of far-from-equilibrium systems have broad applications in physical, chemical, and biological systems. The investigation is relevant to needs of industrial applications of galvanic and electrolytic cells. The oscillatory electrochemical media test theories on synchronization and network dynamics that have importance in circadian rhythms and hypersynchronous neural discharges in epileptic seizures. The project includes outreach activities aimed at middle school, high school and college students and the general public through the "Nonlinear Corner," and conveys novel scientific notions of nonlinear science and the emergence of complex, intelligent behavior of abiotic systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Professor Istvan Kiss and his research group address three specific aims that are based on fundamental scientific problems in analytical chemistry utilizing multi-electrodes, design specifics of batteries and electrolysis cells, and energy distribution networks: (1) Test the hypothesis that emergent electrochemical networks in multi-electrode microfluidic flow cells can describe the complex dynamical phenomena, (2) explore self-organized spatio-temporal behavior in cathode-anode multi-electrodes, and (3) explore the pattern formation of electrochemical reactions that take place on a designed network facilitated by a resistance interface. The construction of versatile emergent and engineered networks provides a new geometrical space for the chemical reactions to take place. The extraction of network topology contributes to the establishment of Chemical Connectomics, the science of connected reactions in dynamic environments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1465013</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Istvan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kiss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>izkiss@slu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Saint Louis University</Name>
      <CityName>St Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3149773925</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>221 N. Grand Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9101</Code>
      <Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8091</Code>
      <Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
