<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Graphene Nanomechanics: The Role of Van der Waals Forces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dennis Robert Carter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to understand the mechanical behavior of graphene nanostrucutures as influenced by van der Waals forces. As a single suspended layer of atoms, graphene sheets are among the thinnest objects imaginable. A suspended single layer of graphene is one of the stiffest and strongest known materials. While these attributes are attractive for many reasons, the mechanical behavior of graphene is dominated by the influence of van der Waals forces. This situates graphene, and many nanomechanical structures in general, in a regime that is not yet well understood or even studied. The research approach consists of a tightly-coupled experimental-theoretical research program. It involves a novel experimental platform that will facilitate the characterization of numerous aspects of the nanomechanical behavior of single and multilayer graphene, including elastic properties, adhesion, and the influence of van der Waals forces in the range of a few to 100s of nm on dynamical behavior. Deliverables include a new experimental platform, analytical and numerical modeling and simulation approaches, documentation of research results, engineering student education, and impact on K-12 students.&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research program will uncover aspects of the behavior of nanomechanical structures that live in a world where van der Waals forces are ever-present, and as structures become smaller the influence of van der Waals forces become stronger. It will broadly impact a wide range of applications where graphene is intensely being pursued for technological insertion, including nanomechanics, microelectronics, energy, and biomedical applications. The coupling of research discoveries with ongoing and new educational activities will expose students at all levels (K-12, undergraduate, and graduate, including students from typically underrepresented groups) to the excitement of nanotechnology in general and the fascinating world of the mechanics of nanostructures in particular.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0900832</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Martin.Dunn@Colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/18/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bunch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bunch@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7479</Code>
      <Text>Biomechanics &amp; Mechanobiology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>028E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
