<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Exploration of Graphene-Nanocrystal Metamaterials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>228672</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research objective of this award is to advance the manufacture, the fundamental understanding, and the device application of graphene-nanocrystal metamaterials or hybrid graphene-nanocrystal structures, i.e., graphene sheets with discrete nanocrystals decorations on their surfaces. Specific tasks to be performed include experimental and theoretical characterization of the metamaterials, particularly electronic and physical interactions between nanocrystals and graphene sheets with various external stimuli; investigation of methods for low-cost and large-scale manufacturing of such materials; and exploration of their use for gas sensors. The availability of affordable hybrid nanostructures and their fundamental properties will open up new opportunities for nanoscience and nanotechnology and accelerate discoveries and inventions. The synergistic response from the nanocrystal and the graphene can be harnessed for various innovative device applications, including gas sensors, biosensors, and photovoltaic cells. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the project results will enable a wide range of innovative applications of graphene-nanocrystal metamaterials with optimal properties that can be tailored for specific conditions. The new sensor to be demonstrated will be attractive for environmental monitoring and directly benefit society. The project will train both graduate and undergraduate students in areas of graphene engineering and applications, and will reach the broader student population through a course module on hybrid nanostructures, integration of small nanotechnology projects into existing curricula at both UWM and UT, and training of science teachers. Additional efforts through "Science Saturdays" will be used to attract more underrepresented students to STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>228672</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0900569</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rodney</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruoff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>r.ruoff@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
