<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CyberWatch: Creating the Next Generation of Cybersecurity Professionals</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3531900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In 2005, CyberWATCH was established as an ATE regional center for cybersecurity education serving the Washington, DC, metropolitan area (Award DUE-0501828). Following four successful years of operation, the current grant renews the center for a second phase.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CyberWATCH consortium has grown from 10 original core institutions in Maryland, Virginia, and the District of Columbia to 26 members, including affiliates in Delaware, North Carolina, Louisiana, New York, Massachusetts, and Washington State. CyberWATCH Phase II is expanding academic resources to meet constantly changing industry needs; strengthening the K-12 pipeline and increasing enrollments in Information Security/Information Assurance (IS/IA) programs; expanding the consortium and providing resources and support to new members; providing real-life or simulated work experiences for students; addressing public awareness of cybersecurity; promoting the IS/IA profession; and developing a revenue stream that will sustain the consortium over the long term.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While continuing the successful efforts in curriculum, faculty, and student development that were launched during Phase I, CyberWATCH Phase II is adding several innovative programs. New initiatives include:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;* online model A.A.S. and A.S. curricula, paired with appropriate faculty training, dissemination of materials, a curriculum maintenance and update process, and mapping updates;&lt;br/&gt;* specialized curriculum tracks in digital forensics, network security, database management security, and secure programming;&lt;br/&gt;* curricula and case studies that utilize the center's digital forensics lab;&lt;br/&gt;* faculty self-assessment instruments, which allow faculty to assess their skills in IS/IA in the context of the CyberWATCH curriculum and identify training to fill gaps;&lt;br/&gt;* a clearinghouse of guest speakers;&lt;br/&gt;* a mentoring program that pairs industry professionals with students;&lt;br/&gt;* a high school-to-college articulation program focusing on IS/IA;&lt;br/&gt;* additional curriculum modules and case studies that fill in gaps in the existing 85 modules and their alignment with CyberWATCH courses;&lt;br/&gt;* an enhanced K-12 cybersecurity education program, including summer camps for high school students, 1-2 day programs for middle school girls, after-school enrichment programs for elementary students, and a 1-2 week program for STEM teachers;&lt;br/&gt;* specialized security training for the personnel who are responsible for maintaining IT infrastructure in K-12 schools;&lt;br/&gt;* a CyberWATCH presence in Second Life, which will allow students and faculty to participate in virtual classes, workshops, conferences, and training scenarios;&lt;br/&gt;* an annual online job fair and a program to prepare students for interviews; and&lt;br/&gt;* additional activities promoting cybersecurity awareness, education, and careers to the public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0902747</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Davina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pruitt-Mentle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dpruitt@edtechpolicy.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fred</FirstName>
      <LastName>Klappenberger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>faklappenberger@aacc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Casey</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Brien</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>obriencx@pgcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leary</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mleary@nvcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spear</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rspear@pgcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Prince George's Community College</Name>
      <CityName>LARGO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207742199</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3015460722</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>301 LARGO RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>I466</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>K627</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
