<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Modeling the Dynamics and the Gravitational-Wave Emission of Co-Alescing Compact Binary Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>980000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research spans several topics in gravitational-wave theory, data-analysis and astrophysics of coalescing compact binaries. It aims at (i) Extending perturbative calculations at higher post-Newtonian order; (ii) Building effective-one-body templates of precessing, spinning black-hole binaries which faithfully reproduce accurate numerical relativity simulations; (iii) Implementing these effective-one-body templates in Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory (LIGO) software and carrying out searches for gravitational waves with LIGO and Enhanced LIGO; (iv) Extending the effective-one-body approach to neutron-star/neutron-star and neutron-star/black-hole binaries and to eccentric binaries; and (v) Grasping the physics of recoil from merging black holes, providing a simple, manageable analytical formula for the recoil velocity that can be easily incorporated by astrophysicists in numerical hierarchical-merger codes. This research will have an impact on detecting gravitational waves with LIGO, improve the ability to extract from observed waves unique information that the waves carry, and test fundamental equations of general relativity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>980000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0903631</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alessandra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buonanno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>buonanno@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
