<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Photonic Quantum Networking of Trapped Ion Qubits</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ann Orel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will push experimental limits in the local and nonlocal networking of quantum information. It is generally accepted that future quantum networks will require both stable quantum memories and appropriate quantum channels that can traverse macroscopic distances. We concentrate on the use of hyperfine ground states of trapped ions as quantum memories, and individual photons as the quantum communication channel. Building on previous work from our group in the Yb+ system, we will investigate (a) larger numbers of ions at each network node, (b) enhanced probabilities of heralded gate operations with nearby optical elements, (c) larger distances between trapped ion nodes by exploiting infrared transitions in the Yb+ system. These directions represent promising routes toward a variety of quantum information and quantum communication protocols, including distributed quantum computing and long-distance quantum repeaters circuits. This research may also lead to an attractive method for observing a "loophole-free" Bell inequality test, where the entangled ions are space-like separated with respect to the qubit measurement time. Finally, the ion/photon interfaces discussed here are not necessarily specific to trapped ions memories, and may be applied to other systems such as quantum dots in a semiconductor or doped glass host.&lt;br/&gt;This work is at the heart of laboratory quantum information science, and it is expected to attract great interest from students at all levels and backgrounds from a variety of disciplines in physics, computer science, and engineering. The results of this research will be widely disseminated at meetings and workshops, and also through lectures at primarily undergraduate institutions. As part of an internal initiative at U. Maryland to attract the best high school science students in the area to College Park, this work will be aggressively presented at local high schools. &lt;br/&gt;Where possible, the presentation of this research to young students and other newcomers to the field will be rooted in a particular approach to the foundations of quantum mechanics that relies more on information theoretic viewpoints such as entropy and measurement and less on wave mechanics, differential equations, and complex mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0903945</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Monroe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>monroe@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7281</Code>
      <Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7203</Code>
      <Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
