<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Taming the scale explosion in nuclear structure calculations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>586719</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Solving for the structure and reactions of the atomic nucleus&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The discovery of nuclear fission revealed the tremendous amount of energy that can be released when the strong bonds between the neutrons and protons forming atomic nuclei are broken. Ever since that history-making discovery, theoretical nuclear physicists have sought a detailed explanation of the properties of the atomic nucleus based on knowledge of the strong force between these constituents. When this goal is achieved, we will be able to predict reactions that take place in extreme environments ? from the interiors of stars to the core of nuclear reactors. Improving our knowledge of nuclear structure and reactions will help us economically and safely harness nuclear phenomena in support of a broad spectrum of humanitarian needs. Future nuclear science and technology advances promise a growing line of medical, industrial and energy applications. Nuclear medicine and nuclear magnetic resonance imaging provide just two prominent medical applications that rely on elementary properties of atomic nuclei.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to expand dramatically the reach as well as the impact of nuclear theory by harnessing the vast computational power of NSF's leadership class computer facilities under construction. The goal is to develop and implement a symmetry-based extension of the ab initio no-core shell model. By effectively ferreting out important interactions at the fundamental quantum level, we can achieve accurate predictions of nuclear properties based upon a deep understanding of the underlying forces. All participating particles are treated on the same footing within a matrix (?shell model?) picture of the quantum many-particle system, the nucleus. We aim to predict the structure and reactions of light-nuclei important for stellar processes and, possibly, for fusion reactors within five years. As part of this PetaApps grant, future leaders ? primarily graduate students and postdocs, will be supported to conduct this research under the guidance of senior investigators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0904782</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vary</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jvary@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Masha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sosonkina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>msosonki@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7691</Code>
      <Text>PetaApps</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
