<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometry, topology and group theory of surfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>289270</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0905748&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Christopher J. Leininger&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to study the geometry of various structures on&lt;br/&gt;surfaces, actions of the mapping class group on these spaces, and&lt;br/&gt;topological/dynamical aspects of surface homeomorphisms. This&lt;br/&gt;includes (1) an ongoing project with R.P. Kent on convex&lt;br/&gt;cocompactness in the mapping class group, with a focus on free&lt;br/&gt;groups and surface groups; (2) a topological investigations of&lt;br/&gt;algebraic relations in the mapping class group and the closely&lt;br/&gt;related braid groups with D. Margalit; (3) a study, via geodesic&lt;br/&gt;length functions, of certain singular euclidean geometric&lt;br/&gt;structures on surfaces and their degenerations in a joint project&lt;br/&gt;with M. Duchin and K. Rafi; (4) a continuing project with&lt;br/&gt;B. Farb and D. Margalit to provide a topological model for&lt;br/&gt;"minimal complexity" surface homeomorphisms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Surfaces---like the surface of a ball or a doughnut---have been&lt;br/&gt;studied for hundreds of years, and are fundamental and beautiful&lt;br/&gt;objects in mathematics. The study of surfaces is intrinsically&lt;br/&gt;interesting, but is also responsible for the creation of entire&lt;br/&gt;fields of mathematics, as well as the development of techniques&lt;br/&gt;in many others. As such, the theory of surfaces and their&lt;br/&gt;geometries lies at the juncture of several fields of mathematics&lt;br/&gt;including complex analysis, differential geometry,&lt;br/&gt;low-dimensional topology, geometric group theory and dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;Many geometric objects can be described using surfaces as the&lt;br/&gt;basic building blocks. To study these objects one naturally&lt;br/&gt;encounters the notion of a "homeomorphism" of a surface: this is&lt;br/&gt;a kind of "symmetry" which preserves only the most basic&lt;br/&gt;properties of the surface. The set of all homeomorphisms is&lt;br/&gt;somewhat unwieldy, but the most important features can be&lt;br/&gt;distilled into a more manageable structure called the "mapping&lt;br/&gt;class group." This project proposes the study of several related&lt;br/&gt;problems about surfaces, their homeomorphisms and mapping class&lt;br/&gt;groups, and the implications of these studies to related&lt;br/&gt;geometric objects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/30/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0905748</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leininger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clein@math.uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
