<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TC: Medium: Collaborative Research: Techniques to Retrofit Legacy Code with Security</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Though perhaps unfortunate, as a practical matter software is often&lt;br/&gt;built with functionality as a primary goal, and security features are&lt;br/&gt;only added later, often after vulnerabilities have been identified.&lt;br/&gt;To reduce the cost and increase assurance in the process of security&lt;br/&gt;retrofitting, the aim to develop a methodology involving automated and&lt;br/&gt;semi-automated tools and techniques to add authorization policy&lt;br/&gt;enforcement functionality to legacy software systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main insight is that major portions of the tasks involved in&lt;br/&gt;retrofitting code can be or already have been automated, so the design&lt;br/&gt;process focuses on enabling further automation and aggregating these&lt;br/&gt;tasks into a single, coherent approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, techniques and tools are being developed to: (1)&lt;br/&gt;identify and label security-relevant objects and I/O channels by&lt;br/&gt;analyzing and instrumenting annotated application source code; (2)&lt;br/&gt;insert code to mediate access to labeled entities; (3) abstract the&lt;br/&gt;inserted checks into policy-relevant, security-sensitive operations&lt;br/&gt;that are authorized (or denied) by the application's security policy;&lt;br/&gt;(4) integrate the retrofitted legacy code with the site's specific&lt;br/&gt;policy at deployment time to ensure, through advanced policy analysis,&lt;br/&gt;that the application enforces that site's policy correctly, and (5)&lt;br/&gt;verify correct enforcement of OS policy delegation by the retrofitted&lt;br/&gt;application.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The techniques and tools being developed are useful not only&lt;br/&gt;for retrofitting, but also for augmenting and verifying existing code&lt;br/&gt;already outfitted with security functionality; hence improving the&lt;br/&gt;state-of-the-art in creating more secure software.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>300000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0905343</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Trent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jaeger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tjaeger@cse.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
