<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Exploiting the Low Dimensional Physics of Incompressible Particles to Tailor the Stability and Morphology of Finite Phases Through Designed Surface Energies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>598664</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070012</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Polymer program in the Division of Materials Research to University of Akron is to study the structure-functional relationships of hybride materials prepared from incompressible nanoparticles and homopolymers - both crystallizable and homopolymers. Study of 2-D phase transitions on flat and curved surfaces, and use of the 2-D phase transitions associated with these novel homopolymer-nanoparticle hybrides to control the stability, morphology and transitional pathways of micelles are parts of this project. Using lamellar crystals of specifically designed and synthesized particles-crystallizable homo- and copolymers grown in dilute solution, the proposed research will create a flat substrate with particles closely tethered to the surface using these ?sandwiched? single crystals. With near monodispersed molecular weight, the tethered particle will possess a uniform and controllable volume fraction on the surface. Monitoring the lamellar crystal thickness changes at different crystallization temperatures will enable a quantitative investigation of theoretically and technologically important 2-D phase transitions. Lamellar single crystals of hybride linear diblock copolymers, where the two immiscible, non-crystallizable ends will be located at opposite basal surfaces of the single crystal, will be grown. The newly developed method to create the tethered particle substrates using particle-crystallizable polymers would provide precisely controlled systems that will give significant insight into low dimensional phase transitions which will be an important contribution to the previously developed theories. In addition, combining knowledge from both particle and polymer physics would enable the development of materials with accurately controlled particle interfacial volume fractions, block molecular weights, block chemistries, and molecular architectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is expected to enhance the knowledge base in developing additional understanding of soft materials physics in general and their behavior in crystals, on surfaces and on micelles. The proposed research would be exposing graduate and undergraduate student to topics in advanced soft materials while promoting an interdisciplinary approach to research. Recruiting and training of gifted and underrepresented high school students through "Upward Bound Math/Science" and "Summer Honors Institute for Gifted High School Students" programs are also planned as part of this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0906898</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen Z.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scheng@uakron.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Akron</Name>
      <CityName>Akron</CityName>
      <ZipCode>443250001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3309727666</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>302 Buchtel Common</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
