<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Growth and Physical Properties Measurements of Novel Condensed Matter Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>345000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Sokol</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates low-dimensional solids, which are known to exhibit unusual forms of electrical conduction, magnetism, superconductivity, and highly correlated electron behavior. The thermal expansion will be measured to investigate their phase transitions and to expand the state of knowledge regarding dimensionality in such systems. The thermal expansion technique, which was developed at Montana State University, offers relative resolution of 1 part in 108. This is at least 1000 times better than x-ray or neutron diffraction. This resolution, coupled with measurement of other physical properties, will enable evaluation of the role of structure in determining the physical properties, a subject of great importance in condensed matter physics. The results will also be used to develop and test fundamental thermodynamic relationships regarding phase transitions in solids. Sample preparation, single crystal growth, specimen characterization, and the development of new measurement technologies add breadth to the project. The research involves collaboration with other experimentalists, a theoretician, and it is the core of an active mentoring and training program involving undergraduates, graduate students and international visitors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates novel compounds, which are known to exhibit unusual forms of electrical conduction and magnetism. Study of these compounds helps to evaluate new candidates for applications in cutting-edge technologies, while at the same time answering questions of fundamental scientific interest. Sample preparation, single crystal growth, and specimen characterization are important components of the work; they provide valuable training to students and young scientists that can readily be applied in the private sector. A significant component of the project is the measurement of thermal expansion with extremely high relative resolution, a technique that was developed at Montana State University. Further improvements in the technique will result from the planned work. Young scientists will participate in these improvements while simultaneously applying this tool, in conjunction with other measurement methods, to current research problems. The project involves collaboration with researchers at national laboratories and universities, and it is the core of an active mentoring and training program involving undergraduates, graduate students and international visitors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0907036</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neumeier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>neumeier@physics.montana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Montana State University</Name>
      <CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
