<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Nonlinear Effects in Strongly Driven Magnetic Structures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Guebre X. Tessema</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The magnetics group at the University of Colorado at Colorado Springs, a predominantly undergarduate instition, has recently developed a method which creates large magnetic fields which oscillate about 10 billion times per second. This allows the study of many magnetic materials in the so-called "nonlinear limit" where unique and useful behavior can be found. For example, this can be used to amplify weak electromagnetic waves in a material, or to pick out a real signal hidden in noise. The work will have a number of broader impacts. It has important implications in practical problems because of the special signal processing devices that can be made using nonlinear motion. Furthermore, nonlinear effects are important for ultrafast switching of small magnetic elements in magnetic memory systems. In addition, the project will provide education and training for all levels of students - high school students, undergraduates, graduate students and post-doctoral researchers. Finally, the magnetics group in Colorado Springs has an excellent record of involving underrepresented groups in research, starting at the high school level, and this effort will be continued. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The magnetics group at the University of Colorado at Colorado Springs, a predominantly undergarduate instition, has recently developed a method which creates large oscillating magnetic fields, up to 500 Oe in comparison to the typical 0.1 Oe found in standard ferromagnetic resonance. This allows the study of nonlinear magnetic motion with large precession angles. Three fundamental research topics will be studied: 1) Nonlinear effects in metallic ribbons of Fe and Py, 2) Nonlinear effects in ultra-small elements of Fe and Py, and 3) Spectral analysis of the spin waves involved in nonlinear processes. The experimental effort will be supported by theoretical calculations. This work will have a number of broader impacts. It has important implications in practical problems because, for example, unique signal processing devices such as a signal to noise enhancer can be made using the nonlinear behavior studied here. Furthermore, nonlinear effects are significant for ultrafast switching of small magnetic elements in magnetic memory systems. In addition, this project will provide education and training for all levels of students - high school students, undergraduates, graduate students and post-doctoral researchers. Finally, the magnetics group in Colorado Springs has an excellent record of involving underrepresented groups in research, starting at the high school level, and this effort will be continued.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0907053</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Camley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rcamley@uccs.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zbigniew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Celinski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zcelinsk@mail.uccs.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Colorado Springs</Name>
      <CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>809183733</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7192553153</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1420, Austin Bluffs Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
