<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transition Metal-Mediated Construction of Novel Molecules</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>795859</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project aims to use transition metals, in particular cobalt complexes, for the development of methodology for the rapid construction of novel complex molecules by multiple bond formation. These include the phenylenes, a new class of novel cyclohexatrienoid hydrocarbons endowed with strain and antiaromatic activation. These molecules are not only adding fundamental knowledge to the understanding of aromatic delocalization, but also have great promise in applications such as thin film transistors, organic semiconductor materials, electroluminescent devices, energy storage systems, and others. A long term goal is to facilitate the invention of integrated nanotechnologies for the microsystems of the future. In another thrust, the synthetic methodology to be developed under this program should facilitate the construction of hitherto inaccessible novel compound classes of synthetic and medicinal interest. Through the understanding of mechanisms, and aided by computational methods, catalytic selectivity will be sought. This effort should greatly simplify routes to natural and unnatural products, with impact on total synthesis and the development of compound libraries endowed with new potentially pharmacophoric motifs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor K. Peter C Vollhardt of the Department of Chemistry at the University of California at Berkeley. Professor Vollhardt's research efforts focus on the development of transition metal mediated transformations that lead to novel molecules. His efforts could positively impact materials, energy, and medical research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0907800</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>K. Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vollhardt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kpcv@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
