<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Moduli spaces in enumerative and combinatorial geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>78991</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tie Luo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigator will study several enumerative and combinatorial problems&lt;br/&gt;in algebraic geometry. In particular, she will study Gromov-Witten theory&lt;br/&gt;of Deligne-Mumford stacks with applications to classical enumerative&lt;br/&gt;geometry, higher-dimensional analogues of the moduli space of curves, and&lt;br/&gt;(equivariant) cohomology and (equivariant) Schubert calculus of Hessenberg&lt;br/&gt;varieties and affine Grassmannians. These are distinct projects, but are&lt;br/&gt;similar in that each of the spaces involved has a rich combinatorial&lt;br/&gt;structure. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is a fundamental problem in algebraic geometry to understand objects&lt;br/&gt;satisfying certain geometric criteria, often naturally parametrized by an &lt;br/&gt;algebraic scheme or stack. Such moduli and parameter spaces are at the &lt;br/&gt;forefront of mathematical and scientific research. Enumerative and &lt;br/&gt;combinatorial problems which arise are of particular excitement as part of&lt;br/&gt;a collision of the fields of algebraic geometry, algebraic combinatorics, &lt;br/&gt;symplectic geometry, and representation theory, as well as topology and &lt;br/&gt;theoretical physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/25/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0908091</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lchen@swarthmore.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/25/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Swarthmore College</Name>
      <CityName>Swarthmore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>190811390</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6103288000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 COLLEGE AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
