<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High-Precision Optical Interferometry with Coherent Integration: Stellar Pulsations, Limb-darkening and Faint Binary Companions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>329158</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Womack</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Anders Jorgensen of the New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology will undertake a detailed study of the diameters and other fundamental parameters of nearby stars. The research will employ a new technique, called Coherent Integration, developed by the author. This technique has been tested on the Navy Prototype Optical Interferometer but can be used on other instruments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Accurate measurements of stellar diameters and other parameters provide fundamental tests of the theory of stellar evolution. Until recently, the only good calibrating star was the Sun, but now the Dr. Jorgensen and other groups are assembling data on stars of different masses, ages, and compositions. These data will allow improved understanding of the interiors and evolution of stars of many types, and will uncover differences between the evolution of single and binary stars. Early tests show that the method yields diameter measurements to an accuracy of 0.2%, a significant improvement over previous work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will make unique measurements of several aspects of stellar properties, and is naturally divided into self-contained projects for student and classroom involvement. Students involved with learn valuable lessons in experimental planning, data analysis, programming, critical thinking, mathematical modeling, and high-performance parallel computing. The PI will also continue his previous outreach efforts in public education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>329158</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0909184</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anders</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jorgensen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anders@nmt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Socorro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>878014681</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5758355915</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 Leroy Place</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1215</Code>
      <Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
