<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis, Reactivity and Mechanisms of Group 4 Metallocene Catalysts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>616000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry Program supports the research of Professor Richard F. Jordan of the University of Chicago to design general methods for the syntheses of enantiopure group 4 metallocenes and libraries of the new catalysts for applications in asymmetric catalysis. The new chiral metallocenes enable the development of new catalytic, stereoselective C-H functionalization reactions that can be applied in organic syntheses and in the syntheses of novel polymers that contain heterocycles in the main chain. The studies of the d0-metal alkene and alkyne complexes provide new insights to the structures, thermodynamics, kinetics, dynamic properties, and insertion mechanisms of these species. The synthesis of chiral compounds is of critical importance in the pharmaceutical and polymer chemical industries. This project provides valuable research training for undergraduates at the University of Chicago, Lake Forest College, and other Chicago-area undergraduate schools. The project also offers exciting science experiences for high school students from the Chicago Public School system through the University of Chicago Collegiate Scholars Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0911180</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jordan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rfjordan@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
