<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Structure and Dynamics of Radical Intermediates in Biological Electron Transfer Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this award, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Prof. Judy E. Kim of the University of California, San Diego, and her graduate and undergraduate student colleagues will study amino acid radicals that play important roles in long-range electron transfer and catalytic reactions. Special focus will be placed on the aromatic residue tryptophan. A unique aspect of this research is the assembly of a suite of powerful spectroscopic techniques, including picosecond time-resolved and UV resonance Raman, transient absorption, and electron paramagnetic resonance, to probe the structures and kinetics of radical intermediates. Several topics will be explored, such as the role of the protein microenvironment and pH on radical stability as well as kinetics associated with radical formation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results from these studies will not only enhance our understanding of biological radicals, but may impact the design of protein mimics and other synthetic systems for critical catalytic reactions. In addition to providing students with the opportunity to participate in interdisciplinary research, the current proposal strongly promotes teaching, training and learning. Undergraduate and graduate education will be bolstered through the integration of a diverse set of students in these projects. Involvement with the community and K-12 students will foster the development of a close relationship between the UCSD Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry and the local community. In general, the current research and education activities are poised to benefit society through (1) critical discoveries in electron transfer reactions that impact fields in chemistry, biology, and physics, and (2) educational enhancements for undergraduate and graduate students as well as community members.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0911766</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Judy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>judyk@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1960</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURE AND REACTIVITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
