<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: An enhanced UHD RFID system for warehouse management</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I research project is aimed at developing an innovative Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) based warehouse management system utilizing a new patent-pending component that will help to address fundamental shortcomings of present day Ultra-High Frequency (UHF) RFID systems. When integrated with conventional UHF RFID systems for warehouse management, this technology will bring value by enabling precise localization of tagged pallets, localization of forklifts, prevention of cross dock pallet reads, tracking of direction of pallet motion and improving the read rate or read accuracy of pallet tags. The project objectives are directed towards hardware prototyping, protocol implementation, software development and initial pilot deployment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;RFID is a rapidly emerging technology with applications in diverse fields such as supply chain management, indoor asset tracking, healthcare and manufacturing. This technology can enhance the handling of material and supply chain operations and the operational efficiency of various businesses processes including greater control over inventory, more accurate production forecasting, and more timely order fulfillment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>100000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0912774</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Petar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Djuric</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmdjuric@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Scandent LLC</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100042434</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6315138316</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>85 Broad St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
