<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Customizable Meniscus Implant Prepared by dielectrophoretic Biofabrication</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Josephine Yuen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to develop a prototype meniscal implant using bacterial cellulose and a novel biofabrication process, dielectrophoretic microweaving. Nanocellulose networks produced by the bacteria Acetobacter xylinum are biomaterials with unique hydrogel-like properties and biocompatibility that is ideal for cartilage tissue replacement. For applications such as meniscus there is however need to direct the nanofibril orientation. A new biofabrication process has been invented at Virginia Tech in which the precise control of bacterial motion in an electric field is used to control morphology of the nanocellulose network. In this project a microweaver, a device to manufacture customizable meniscus implants based on images from patients will be developed. This will be a major breakthrough in biomaterials for orthopedics applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this project is technology for inexpensive but high performance, biocompatible materials for health care. Over 15 million people worldwide suffer from knee-joint failure each year. More than 225,000 people annually undergo arthroscopic meniscal repair at an average cost of $25,000 each. There are no satisfactory products on the market today and there is an urgent need for a new biomaterial that mimics properties of natural meniscus. By developing a meniscal implant that can substitute for the injured native meniscus, it may be possible to diminish the prevalence of osteoarthritis and its related economic costs. BC Genesis LLC is a biomedical start-up company working with technology for developing implants and tissue scaffolds by using bacteria to grow cellulose biomaterial.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>100000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0912617</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gatenholm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pgatenholm@bcgenesis.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>BC Genesis</Name>
      <CityName>Riner</CityName>
      <ZipCode>241492578</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5408087552</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3335 Torrey Pines Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
