<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Algebraic hierarchical matrix preconditioners for two- and three-dimensional saddle point problems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>137149</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project deals with the development, analysis and implementation&lt;br/&gt;of novel techniques for the solution of large, sparse linear systems&lt;br/&gt;of equations of saddle point type. Despite much recent progress,&lt;br/&gt;the solution of large systems of equations remains one of the main&lt;br/&gt;bottlenecks in many numerical simulations. Applications include&lt;br/&gt;fluid dynamics, magnetohydrodynamics, image processing, and many more.&lt;br/&gt;This project deals with the further development of the &lt;br/&gt;technique of hierarchical (H-)matrices. H-matrices &lt;br/&gt;provide an efficient technique for computations&lt;br/&gt;involving approximations to fully populated matrices.&lt;br/&gt;The standard construction of an H-matrix is based&lt;br/&gt;on the underlying geometry of the application. Similar to the generalization&lt;br/&gt;of geometric to algebraic multigrid methods, the PI proposes to &lt;br/&gt;develop an algorithm for the algebraic construction of H-matrix &lt;br/&gt;preconditioners for saddle point problems. Sequences of three-dimensional &lt;br/&gt;Oseen problems that result in the numerical solution of the Navier-Stokes &lt;br/&gt;equations will serve as the major application of the novel techniques.&lt;br/&gt;An additional topic to be considered in this project is&lt;br/&gt;the application of H-techniques in only recently developed&lt;br/&gt;Kronecker product preconditioners. The techniques of this proposal &lt;br/&gt;have a high potential to lead to robust and scalable blackbox solvers &lt;br/&gt;for large, linear systems arising in the simulation of scientific and &lt;br/&gt;technical problems of increasing size and complexity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;H-matrices have first been introduced in 1998 and &lt;br/&gt;since then entered into a wide range of applications.&lt;br/&gt;The approach of H-matrices is of significant importance &lt;br/&gt;within its own field of numerical analysis and also with respect to&lt;br/&gt;practical large-scale computing challenges that scientists are &lt;br/&gt;currently facing. Examples for applications include models for &lt;br/&gt;magnetic fusion, accelerator design, electrochemical processes &lt;br/&gt;or the growth of ceramic nanostructures.&lt;br/&gt;Progress in the areas targeted in this proposal will have a &lt;br/&gt;positive impact on science and engineering by allowing for faster&lt;br/&gt;and more accurate computer simulations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>137149</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0913017</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sabine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Le Borne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sleborne@tntech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/29/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mills</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amills@tntech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tennessee Technological University</Name>
      <CityName>Cookeville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>385050001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9313723374</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Dixie Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
