<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Energy Manufacturing; Arlington, Virginia; March 24-25, 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>76683</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhijian Pei</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support to conduct a workshop on energy manufacturing. The objective of which is to gather a multi-disciplinary group of experts to explore and define the research challenges in manufacturing required to translate new sources of energy into petroleum substitutes. The focus of this workshop is to assess the feasibility and near-term viability of various energy manufacturing approaches, and to set forth an agenda for research on manufacturing technologies that will accelerate the emergence of the more promising approaches. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The benefits of this workshop will include defining new connections between manufacturing research problems that will arise as a result of considering them in the context of scaling up energy manufacturing. It is expected that the challenges will stimulate new ideas about how manufacturing could be organized, and how liquid fuels could be delivered. The United States manufacturing industry will benefit from this workshop, and this industry is a vital component of the United States economy. Delivering new energy infrastructure is a significant opportunity for the manufacturing industry to develop a new market for its capabilities. Therefore it is important to identify the gaps in manufacturing technologies that could be bridged by fundamental research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0913075</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Danyluk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>steven.danyluk@marc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Realff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>matthew.realff@chbe.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
