<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Starter Grant - Causes and Consequences of Biocomplexity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George W. Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Pacific salmon are renowned for the great diversity of life histories and morphologies among populations. This diversity is the product of the combination of natal homing, which leads to reproductively isolated populations, and spatially varying selection pressures. Divergent natural selection acting on heritable phenotypic traits then drives adaptation to local conditions and, ultimately, population differentiation. Diversity among salmon stocks is important for the long-term sustainability of salmon fisheries because the relative contribution to total production of a fishery shifts depending on the prevailing environmental conditions. The overall goal of the PI?s research program is to illuminate the causes and consequences of diversity among salmon stocks. This research three components. First is in depth exploration of the ecological and evolutionary causes of diversity among current populations of coho salmon. The second component is a study of the consequences of population homogenization (i.e., diversity loss) by focusing on California's recently collapsed Chinook salmon. Finally, a theoretical component will focus on advancing methods for analyzing selection. The research starter award will help to launch this research program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research will have direct implications for the management and conservation of Pacific salmon. In the United States, 28 Evolutionary Significant Units of Pacific salmonids are currently listed as threatened or endangered. Ten of these units are found, either wholly or in part, in California. Explicit consideration of the evolutionary challenges facing these organisms should result in more effective management and conservation efforts. The PI is making a strong effort to engage members of underrepresented groups in her research program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0915173</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carlson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smcarlson@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
