<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III: Small: Automatic Incremental Design for Next-Generation Database Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frank Olken</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Data management systems are undergoing a sea change. Specialized&lt;br/&gt;engines with specialized physical storage structures are emerging to&lt;br/&gt;address the extreme data volume and performance requirements of modern&lt;br/&gt;applications. At the same time, the complexity of these systems, the&lt;br/&gt;applications in which they are used and the platforms on which they&lt;br/&gt;are built is increasing. Thus, there is a growing need for automatic&lt;br/&gt;database design for these emerging database systems. Unfortunately,&lt;br/&gt;previous work in automatic design cannot be used directly. While the&lt;br/&gt;conceptual framework of previous research is useful, the specifics&lt;br/&gt;must be reworked in order to adequately take advantage of the&lt;br/&gt;opportunities and address the challenges that these new structures&lt;br/&gt;present. Furthermore, most design tools only create complete designs.&lt;br/&gt;There is also a need for automatic designers that can produce a new&lt;br/&gt;design that is sensitive to the cost of migrating an old design to a&lt;br/&gt;new one. Such an incremental designer would often generate a&lt;br/&gt;sub-optimal design if that design will produce 80% of the benefit with&lt;br/&gt;20% of the work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs propose to investigate this incremental automatic design&lt;br/&gt;paradigm for newly emerging database systems. Specifically, the&lt;br/&gt;project addresses three data management platforms: column stores for&lt;br/&gt;OLAP, main memory, cluster-based systems for OLTP, and an extension to&lt;br/&gt;row stores for exploiting correlations in data attributes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs expect to extend the work on current design tools by&lt;br/&gt;demonstrating workable incremental designers as described above. There&lt;br/&gt;is a strong need for such tools, and if this research is successful,&lt;br/&gt;it should enable successful deployment of many new-style data&lt;br/&gt;managers. Moreover, incremental design ideas based on sound&lt;br/&gt;cost-benefit analysis are applicable to other data-intensive computing&lt;br/&gt;environments and constitute an important direction towards truly&lt;br/&gt;autonomic computing. Further information on the project can be found&lt;br/&gt;on the project web page: http://database.cs.brown.edu/projects/auto/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0916691</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ugur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cetintemel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ugur@cs.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stanley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zdonik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbz@cs.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
