<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI: Small: Efficient Reinforcement Learning for Generic Large-Scale Tasks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>501000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Hector Munoz-Avila</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Recent advances in autonomous agents research are pushing our society closer to the brink of the widespread adoption of autonomous agents in everyday life. Applications that incorporate agents already exist or are quickly emerging, such as domestic robots, autonomous vehicles, and financial management agents. Reinforcement learning (RL) of sequential decision making is an important paradigm for enabling the widespread deployment of autonomous agents. However, a few notable successes notwithstanding, state-of-the-art reinforcement learning algorithms are not yet fully capable of addressing generic large-scale applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is advancing in four directions to scale-up application of RL systems. Specifically, the project is (1) developing algorithms to automatically structure the input, output, and policy representations for learning; (2) introducing parallelizable reinforcement learning algorithms so as to exploit modern parallel architectures; (3) unifying abstraction and hierarchical reasoning with model-based learning for the purpose of enabling intelligent exploration of large-scale environments; and (4) enabling reinforcement learning algorithms to benefit from low-bandwidth interactions with human users. Finally, we intend to unify the four research thrusts above into a single algorithm and conduct empirical evaluation on real-world/large-scale applications, to include biped robot balancing and walking, robot soccer in simulation and with real robots, and a full-size autonomous vehicle capable of planning paths in an urban environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to research advances and implications for improving national infrastructure, the project will contribute to undergraduate and graduate curriculum development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0917122</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pstone@cs.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
