<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Digital Resource for Developing Mathematics Teachers' TPCK."</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2687955</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen King</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project A Digital Resource for Developing Mathematics Teachers' TPCK is developing and conducting initial tests of a highly innovative interactive digital textbook to enhance middle grades mathematics teachers' understanding of core concepts in proportionality and their understanding of ways that technology can be used to enhance instruction. The project is led by professionals from SRI International with substantial contributions by mathematics educators at San Diego State University, San Francisco State University, the Singapore National Institute of Education, and the Center for Applied Special Technology (CAST).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The digital textbook combines elements from SimCalc, Geometer's Sketchpad, and data analysis software to teach core ideas of proportionality from algebraic, geometric, and statistical perspectives. It also includes elements designed to help teachers see the connections among those uses of proportional reasoning and the ways that such tools can be used in classroom instruction with middle school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The basic hypothesis of the project is that the proposed DynaBook will be a highly effective tool for mathematics teacher preparation and professional development and, ultimately, for classroom instruction of middle school students. Pilot tests in laboratory, teacher preparation, and professional development settings are providing initial empirical evidence about two core research questions:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;* In what ways does the DynaBook effectively support teacher learning of &lt;br/&gt; pedagogical and technological content knowledge?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;* Does the DynaBook foster teachers' understanding of the coherence and &lt;br/&gt; connectedness of middle school mathematics?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project explores very promising new forms of instructional materials with potential to transform the ways that we think about educational texts and teaching strategies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0918339</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Courey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scourey@sfsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bowers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbowers@math.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roschelle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jeremy.roschelle@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blackorby</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jose.blackorby@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Patton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>charles.patton@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SRI International</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508592651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7645</Code>
      <Text>DISCOVERY RESEARCH K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
