<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CBMS2010: A Study of Undergraduate Programs in the Mathematical and Statistical Sciences in the United States and the Publication of the Results</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>589907</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myles G. Boylan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project, CBMS2010, is a comprehensive stratified random sample survey of the nation's undergraduate mathematical and statistical sciences programs at two-year and four-year institutions in the fall of 2010. A comprehensive report describing this survey will be available in the spring of 2012 online. This project continues a cross-sectional survey of undergraduate mathematics programs that has been done every five years since 1965. This project is coordinated by the Conference Board for the Mathematical Sciences (CBMS) and is being managed by the American Mathematical Society (AMS). CBMS surveys track changes in the curriculum, pedagogy, enrollment levels, graduates, and faculty in US undergraduate mathematical sciences programs. In addition, CBMS2010 is also focusing on: requirements for mathematics and statistics majors, assessment of mathematics and statistics programs, mathematical preparation of teachers, dual enrollment, and instructional strategies in College Algebra, Calculus I, and Elementary Statistics. CBMS2010 will provide the national benchmark data that the nation's mathematical sciences department chairs called for in the AMS publication "Towards Excellence: Leading a Mathematics Department in the 21st Century."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The statistical design and associated computations are being conducted by statisticians at Westat in consultation with a steering committee appointed by CBMS, and the final report will be written by the project's senior personnel and published by the American Mathematical Society. The survey's evolving structure contributes to educational survey research methodology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0918881</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maxwell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwm@ams.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kirkman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kirkman@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blair</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>richelle.blair@sbcglobal.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Mathematical Society</Name>
      <CityName>PROVIDENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029042294</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4014554150</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7492</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7625</Code>
      <Text>REAL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
