<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RIG: Genetic and Molecular Basis of Bacteriophage Life History Variation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174155</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>To construct an organism, DNA is translated into proteins which are assembled into or direct the assembly of a physical structure. This process is almost unimaginably complex for most organisms, but what about the simplest of them, the bacterial viruses (i.e. phages)? For example, the coliphage lambda consists of a strand of DNA enclosed by a protein shell. How is the assembly of lambda phage controlled? How does stochasticity in the control mechanisms affect the ultimate product? How does evolution shape the control mechanisms? The ultimate goal of this research is to determine how phage assembly is controlled, to assess the role of variation in the assembly network, and to understand how evolution shapes this biological system. This project is an initial step towards that goal as it uses mutagenesis to systematically alter the expression of phage structural proteins. Organismal responses will be assessed by quantifying mean and variation of phage reproductive output. Evolution experiments will further determine how phages respond to changes in phage reproductive output. Successful completion will provide a clearer picture of how a complex process responds to system-wide perturbation, and how evolution is able to return the process to an optimal state. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposed research include encouraging persons of disability to participate in scientific research, increasing the participation of underrepresented minorities in science and enhancing research in evolutionary biology with next-generation scientific instrumentation and recently developed molecular techniques. The project will not only improve opportunities for the PI, a hearing impaired individual, but will increase the visibility of disabled scientists and encourage other disabled individuals to explore science as a career. As an underrepresented minority, the PI is keenly aware of the importance of fostering inclusiveness in the scientific community. The PI is active in efforts to increase scientific literacy including keeping a blog, giving science talks to the general public and participating in a web encyclopedia project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0918199</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dennehy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.dennehy@qc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Queens College</Name>
      <CityName>Flushing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>113671575</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7189975400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>65 30 Kissena Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
