<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Investigation of the mechanisms that regulate interactions between the transcription elongation factor Spt16 and chromatin.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>473089</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Martha Peterson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The genetic information carried by all living cells is contained within long molecules of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA). In eukaryotic cells, most of the DNA is localized within a cellular compartment referred to as the cell nucleus. In order to fit within the small confines of the nucleus, DNA associates with a number of proteins to form a highly compacted structure known as chromatin. Whereas this compaction is essential for life, it also represents a physical barrier to those factors that bind DNA and that are required for the initial steps in the conversion of genetic information into specific biological events, a process more generally known as gene transcription. In recent years it has become clear that cells utilize a number of chromatin-altering proteins that can interact with and change the structure of chromatin to make the DNA more or less accessible to factors needed for transcription. In this project a combination of genetic and biochemical strategies will be used to elucidate the mechanisms that regulate how one of these chromatin-altering proteins, known as Spt16, interacts with chromatin during the process of gene transcription. Because accurate regulation of transcription is crucial for the proper function of all cells and organisms, these studies promise to provide new insights into a basic biological process of general importance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts. This project will provide an excellent opportunity for undergraduate students to be actively involved in cutting-edge genetic and biochemical research. During this project, undergraduate students will be trained on important aspects of scientific research, including the proper design and execution of experiments, accurate analysis and interpretation of experimental data, and the development of scientific writing and oral communication skills. In addition, undergraduate students involved in this project will have the opportunity to present the results of their research at regional, national and international scientific meetings. These combined experiences will not only introduce undergraduate students to the exciting world of scientific research, but will also better prepare them for making informed decisions regarding their career paths following graduation from college.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0919241</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
      <LastName>Duina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>duina@hendrix.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/04/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hendrix College</Name>
      <CityName>Conway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>720323080</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5014504501</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Washington Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1154</Code>
      <Text>GENE EXPRESSION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
