<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NOAA Sea Grant Knauss Fellowhip</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>142000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Interagency Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Polly A. Penhale</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Fellow would participate in the development of marine and terrestrial protected area management plans and in the development of policy positions on environmental protection in Antarctica, including marine areas. Projects would also include reviewing and preparing environmental impact assessments for U.S. science and operational activities in Antarctica. Some work would involve environmental assessments of science activities in the Arctic. The skills gained would include an understanding of interagency and international governance within the context of the Antarctic Treaty system, understanding the relationship between marine and terrestrial components of complex ecosystems, proficiency in environmental impact assessment process and in the development and preparation of management plans. Ultimately the Fellow would gain an understanding of a broad range of environmental protection activities and their interrelationship with scientific research and operational activities in Antarctica. The deliverables will include final draft management plans of protected areas for international review and position papers for senior management on a range of environmental, ecosystem management, and protection issues within the Antarctic Treaty system. Work would include in activities related to the Antarctic Treaty and the Protocol on Environmental Protection and the Convention for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/11/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0921165</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cammen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leon.cammen@noaa.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NOAA</Name>
      <CityName>Silver Spring</CityName>
      <ZipCode>209103282</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3017133388</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1315 East West Highway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5187</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9199</Code>
      <Text>UNDISTRIBUTED PANEL/IPA FUNDS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
