<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4165570</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bauke H. Houtman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System (UNOLS) is a consortium of sixty-one U.S. academic institutions with research and educational programs in the ocean sciences and dedication to the major shared-use facilities that support these programs. These institutions support a broad array of facilities, which include research vessels, submersibles, remotely operated vehicles, autonomous underwater vehicles, aircraft, icebreakers, major instrumentation, and national facilities. The institution or the supporting federal agencies own these shared-use assets and it is through the UNOLS system that the community is able to access them. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's request funding to host the UNOLS Office beginning in May 2009. As one of the founding institutions of UNOLS, GSO has a long tradition and deep experience with this organization and with the federal agencies that fund it. Since its inception in 1971, UNOLS has played an increasingly important role in coordinating and improving the operations of the nation's academic research fleet. Because the organization functions largely through the voluntary efforts of scientists and professionals from across the country, it is essential that the UNOLS Office be staffed by people who thoroughly understand UNOLS and are committed to its success.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0921084</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alberts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jalberts@mail.uri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Annette</FirstName>
      <LastName>DeSilva</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>desilva@gso.uri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Rhode Island</Name>
      <CityName>KINGSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028811967</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018742635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>RESEARCH OFFICE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
