<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Role of Vegetation, Aerosols and Surface Fluxes for Land-Atmosphere Feedbacks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>533447</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric T. DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Three different interactions within the climate system will be investigated in this project, involving at one end clouds and precipitation, and at the other end: 1) vegetation; 2) terrestrial aerosols (dust and biogenic volatile organic compounds); 3) land surface energy and water fluxes. The study of vegetation impact on the atmospheric branch of the hydrologic cycle follows two paths; observational analysis (relying heavily on remote sensing data) and climate modeling sensitivity studies. The aerosol-based component of the research contains direct analysis of each of the two types of aerosols followed by modeling studies, this time using a regional atmospheric model with much higer spatial resolution than the global climate model. These studies are targeted to improve the representation of these interactions in climate models. The investigators link assessments for vegetation and the aerosols they produce. The surface energy and water balance research is aimed primarily at model improvements for the land component of the climate model, using data from a network of in situ flux measurement sites to develop better parameterizations of surface processes. Three graduate students will be supported. The PI has maintained strong working and training relationships with the Chinese scientific community, and that effort continues in this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0921898</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dickinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robted@jsg.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
