<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Neurotensin regulation of maternal aggression</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Aggression is found in a wide range of species. Reactive aggression is triggered by a perceived threat to oneself or one's resources and accounts for high levels of aggression across species. Maternal aggression (also called maternal defense) is a powerful form of reactive aggression that is produced in the defense of offspring. It is found in species ranging from humans to mice and is notable because females can be peaceful and nurturing one moment and then fiercely aggressive the next. An understanding of how fierce aggressive outbursts can occur in an otherwise peaceful individual is still missing and maternal aggression therefore provides an excellent model for understanding the biological basis of this form of aggression. This project will examine the neurobiological basis of maternal aggression and will focus on the neurotransmitter neurotensin. This work is expected to provide novel insights into the regulation of aggression because, until recently, no studies had linked neurotensin to aggression. It is expected that the results from these studies will determine where and how neurotensin acts in the brain to regulate maternal aggression. Behavioral, pharmacological, and biochemical approaches will be used in a mouse model system. Because this research examines aggression during reproduction, another possible benefit is that the research will provide insights into emotional changes that occur during the postpartum period. These studies will provide training opportunities in neuroscience for undergraduate, graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows. Underrepresented minority high school and undergraduate students will participate in these projects as part of programs that promote the involvement of underrepresented minorities in science. The studies will also strengthen links within and outside the scientific community and results from studies will be disseminated to a broad audience via press releases and other media outlets.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0921706</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gammie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scgammie@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
