<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a High Performance Computer Cluster for The New York Botanical Garden</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>291703</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award funds the acquisition of a high performance computer cluster at The New York Botanical Garden (NYBG). The cluster will be used to study a wide variety of topics in plant biology including evolution, gene function, three-dimensional image reconstruction, ecosystem function, and DNA based specimen identification. The analyses conducted with the computer cluster will be published in peer-reviewed scientific journals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A computer cluster at NYBG will broadly impact the research of a wide variety of constituencies: (1) An internship program formed between NYBG and the Bronx High School of Science, a school of highly gifted students from predominantly minority background, will give at students the opportunity to perform independent research in a laboratory. (2) The quality of the graduate program will improve as students will have a more powerful data analysis option and will be more broadly trained in current techniques. (3) Undergraduate and graduate students will be offered a class on Computational Methods in Biology at Lehman College (CUNY), a predominantly minority institution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>291703</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0922799</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Litt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amy.litt@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/19/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Damon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Little</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dlittle@nybg.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmiller@nybg.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York Botanical Garden</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104585126</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7188178840</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2900 Southern Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
