<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Conservation Geographic Information Systems (GIS) Instrumentation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>305389</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chicago Botanic Garden has obtained Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) funding to equip a state-of-the-art Conservation Geographic Information System (GIS) laboratory in support of research and conservation, as well as secondary, post-secondary and graduate education and citizen science programs. GIS has been the greatest technological advance in the handling of geographic and spatial data since the invention of the map. These technologies will greatly enhance fundamental and applied research and training programs at the Chicago Botanic Garden. With climate change and invasive species at the forefront of conservation concerns, GIS technology provides the tools necessary to elucidate the spatial ecology of plant populations, how they are predicted to move in response to a changing climate, and whether fragmented landscapes are connected enough to allow this to happen. Understanding the spatial ecology of native and invasive organisms in the context of human-impacted landscapes is crucial to conserving native landscapes and the valuable ecosystem services they provide. This equipment will streamline research efforts, helping Garden scientists (including citizen scientists and students) advance plant conservation science and our understanding of topics as diverse as the global and regional distribution of plants and associated soil organisms, the spatial genetics of fragmented populations, predictions of species range shifts under climate change, dispersal of invasive species, and the climatic and habitat requirements for reintroduced species.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Garden's Center for Teaching and Learning has partnerships with many local K-12 schools and envisions adding a geographic element to existing science education offerings. Spatial thinking and research skills will help future scientists and decision makers succeed in an increasingly technology-driven world. Research results will be widely and effectively disseminated to the public through active participation in scientific and conservation groups. Additionally, the Garden hosts over 750,000 visitors per year, and the general public will have an opportunity to view the laboratory facilities and learn about research activities through exhibits outside of the laboratory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0922995</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pati</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vitt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pvitt@chicagobotanic.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kayri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Havens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>khavens@chicagobotanic.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Krissa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Skogen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kskogen@chicagobotanic.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fant</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jfant@chicagobotanic.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Larkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>djlarkin@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Chicago Botanic Garden</Name>
      <CityName>Glencoe</CityName>
      <ZipCode>600221168</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8478355440</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Lake Cook Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9184</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY - INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
