<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a Quadrupole Laser Ablation ICP-MS for Materials Science, Biology, Earth and Environmental Science and Anthropology at Washington College</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>333579</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant will be used to acquire a quadrupole inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometer (ICPMS) with a laser ablation (LA) system to support research in geosciences, chemistry, biology and anthropology at Washington College. The quadrupole LA-ICPMS is a highly flexible instrument capable of sensitive and precise measurements of a wide range of elements in liquid or solid samples. The LA-ICPMS will be used in the exploration of benign synthetic pathways for the production of modern electroceramics, in the analysis of solar wind elemental ratios by stepped etching of lunar soil grains, in a study of the impacts of prescribed burning on the chemistry of a weathered soil on the mid-Atlantic Coastal Plain, in a study of the interactions of toxic metals with DNA repair, in trace element sourcing of metal artifacts and lithic materials from archaeological sites, and in an investigation of heavy metal contamination in bottom sediments in marinas on the Chester River in Maryland in collaboration with the Chester River Association and teachers and students from the Kent County STEM (science technology engineering mathematics) academy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research performed using the LA-ICPMS will create new opportunities for faculty-student collaborative research and experiential learning at Washington College, which will improve recruitment of science majors, and enhance research training for students going on to graduate school and industry. In particular, the investigation of metal contamination in Chester River sediments will facilitate scientific outreach to local organizations and public schools, thereby promoting scientific research among high school students and citizens in our community. The presence of the instrument will also enhance our efforts to attract underrepresented groups and women to scientific fields by creating research opportunities for undergraduates and high school students from diverse backgrounds. The involvement of researchers from multiple disciplines will generate excitement about science on our campus and in our community by promoting the continuing growth of the scientific research culture at Washington College.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0922733</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marteel-Parrish</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amarteel2@washcoll.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leslie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sherman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lsherman2@washcoll.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kehm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kkehm2@washcoll.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington College</Name>
      <CityName>CHESTERTOWN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>216201197</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4107782800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
