<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Collaboration in Chemistry: Nanoscale Single-Crystal Ensemble Electrocatalysis for Fuel Cell Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program at NSF Division of Chemistry will support the international collaborative research project of Prof. YuYe Tong of Georgetown University. A Collaborator in the project is Prof. Shi-Gang Sun of Xiamen University, China. Profs. Tong and Sun and their students will synthesize and characterize surface-confined two and three dimensional self-assembled molecular architectures using advanced scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) to provide insights into and facilitate the "bottom up" nano-fabrication of novel molecular-based devices. Molecular-based devices, e.g. molecules that possess the ability to act as sensors, switches, motors, machines and memory components, when properly designed and controlled, constitute the backbone of the nascent nanotechnology that has the potential to revolutionize manufacturing and consumer goods in the 21st century. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This international collaborative research project is supported jointly by NSF and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC). The study is also supported by the Office of International Science and Engineering (OISE) at NSF.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>450000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0923910</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>YuYe</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yyt@georgetown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgetown University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200571789</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026250100</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>37th &amp; O St N W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
