<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of a phase and polarization modulated ultrafast laser source for nonlinear optical imaging and molecular identification</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>749369</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation and Facilities: Instrument Development (CRIF:ID) program, Marcos Dantus and his research group from Michigan State University will develop a phase and polarization modulated ultrafast laser source for a broad range of scientific applications. The proposed laser will be capable of generating multiple individually addressable pulses from a single ultrashort pulse. The proposed laser source will be used in a number of projects: 1) a multimodal non-linear imaging microscope; 2) biological and biomedical imaging applications; 3) detection of explosives or pathogens and 4) in-situ chemical analysis of the combustion products in jet turbines. The project will be carried out by a diverse group of scientists, ranging in experience from undergraduate students to professors and research scientists. The work involves collaboration with a number of American industrial partners, as well as with the Air Force Research Laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;New kinds of spectroscopy techniques open up brand new avenues of research. The instrument developed with this award will allow scientists to study the composition and properties of a broad range of materials -- from biological samples to hot combustion gases. Knowledge developed with this kind of tool can lead to: improved medical diagnostics, improved food safety, and better materials for advanced technologies. In addition, the researchers working with Prof. Dantus will receive invaluable training in high technology development, an important skill in today's workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>749369</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0923957</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marcos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dantus</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dantus@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
