<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Closed-Loop Hydraulic Test System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>234075</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Y. Grace Hsuan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is for the acquisition the following equipment: an MTS structural test system and ARAMIS three dimensional non-contact deformation and strain measurement system. The acquisition of these structural testing components will enable the Structures and Computational Mechanics laboratory at Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology (RHIT) to undertake fundamental and applied research in the area of structures and mechanics of new and promising materials. This will be done in collaboration with industry and/or government institutions. Most importantly, the research activities will propel some of the best undergraduate students into the advanced degree pipeline so that the United States can stay competitive with the rest of the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Successful acquisition of this equipment will benefit RHIT, the Civil and Mechanical Engineering departments, and the students and faculty members involved. The following are the anticipated impacts of our proposal: recruitment of RHIT students to graduate school, enhanced quality/marketability of RHIT students for the job market, improved curricula, faculty development, and improved laboratory capabilities at RHIT. Additionally, RHIT can undertake outreach programs with the goal of attracting under-represented students into the fields of science, math and engineering. The proposed research use of this equipment will contribute directly to improving the performance of the built infrastructure and also lead to a better understanding of the anisotropic material properties of fiber reinforced polymer composites. Finally, planned research use of this equipment will also further the development of a nationally accepted fracture toughness testing standard for concrete.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0923135</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aidoo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aidoo@rose-hulman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hanson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james.hanson@rose-hulman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Onyancha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>onyancha@rose-hulman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Terre Haute</CityName>
      <ZipCode>478033920</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128778519</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5500 Wabash Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>025E</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1037</Code>
      <Text>DETERIORATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1444</Code>
      <Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
