<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>In-Line Label-Free Fluid Diagnostics using Photonic Resonators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>351740</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In-Line Label-Free Fluid Diagnostics using Photonic Resonators&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Prof. Brian T. Cunningham&lt;br/&gt;University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign&lt;br/&gt;Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective is to integrate two novel photonics-based label-free detection modalities into the internal surface of plastic tubing. The first detection method is a plastic-based distributed feedback laser biosensor that is capable of high sensitivity affinity-based detection of analytes such as disease biomarkers and bacterial pathogens. The second detection method utilizes the resonant electric fields of a photonic crystal surface to enhance the detection sensitivity of surface enhanced Raman spectroscopy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The approach is to develop an active photonic resonator that generates its own narrowband light output that has no stringent alignment requirements for coupling to its excitation source, and thus elegantly solves an important problem that currently inhibits high Q-factor passive resonator biosensors from implementation upon curved surfaces such as medical tubing. The photonic crystal surface-enhaced Raman approach will increase detection sensitivity by an additional factor of 30-50x, enabling detection of analytes at lower concentrations, shorter integration times, and lower laser power than is currently possible. Demonstration for applications relevant for infused intravenous drug delivery, urinary catheter metabolite monitoring, and early bacterial pathogen detection in intravenous lines will be performed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Development of the capabilities described in this project will have far-reaching implications for patient care in hospitals for a broad range of clinical treatments that utilize sterile plastic tubing for drug delivery and urinary catheterization. The proposal describes an education plan with impact upon graduate student research, undergraduate research, undergraduate classroom/laboratory learning, and teaching biosensing/photonics concepts to a University-based all-girls middle school.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0924062</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bcunning@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>099E</Code>
      <Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
