<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Collaboration in Chemistry: Spatially Resolved Measurements of Cellular Releasates</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Dan Chiu at the University of Washington is supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry with co-funding from the Office of International Science and Engineering for an International Collaboration in Chemistry (ICC) seeking to develop new methodology for monitoring the spatiotemporal dynamics of cellular releasates. Through the International Collaboration in Chemistry Program, the work includes collaboration with Professor David McGloin at the University of Dundee (UK); Dr. McGloin's work is supported by the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC) of the UK.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The approach is based on holographic optical trapping, sensitive microfluidic manipulation, and single-molecule assays. It targets orders of magnitude improvements in spatial resolution and sensitivity over current techniques, enabling progress toward answering biological questions that are currently inaccessible with existing methods. The technology pushes the current limits in holographic optical trapping and imaging, develops new techniques in microfluidic manipulation, and expands current capabilities in single-molecule assays. Applications address the spatial and temporal dynamics of cell secretion and cell-cell communication, seeking a new level of understanding on the functioning of immune cells.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the technical impacts, the project provides broader impact through a unique multidisciplinary international training experience for graduate students via bidirectional visits.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0924320</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chiu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chiu@chem.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1974</Code>
      <Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1974</Code>
      <Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
