<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Uncooled, High-Efficiency Mid-Infrared Lasers by Using Intersubband Quantum-Box Structures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399886</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>john zavada</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of the proposed work is to demonstrate devices that utilize intersubband transitions in arrays of quantum boxes (QBs), to achieve room-temperature, continuous-wave (CW) oscillation in the mid-infrared (IR) wavelength range, with low heat-dissipation powers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;The novel approaches proposed are: 1) the use of block-copolymer lithography for the realization of arrays of 20-25 nm-diameter QBs; 2) the use of deep quantum wells for the QB active material for strong carrier confinement; 3) the use of selective regrowth of high-bandgap barriers to confine carriers in the plane of the QBs..&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The realization of uncooled, CW mid-IR sources will make possible hand-held, real-time sensors for a wide range of noninvasive medical diagnostics and enable exciting developments such as practical sensing of chemical agents and explosives. A central goal and natural outcome of this project is the research-based education of both undergraduate and graduate students. The students will be involved in all aspects of the research within an established collaborative team-based environment. The proposed program provides opportunities for outreach to underrepresented groups through our ongoing partnering with the existing college and NSF Center-based programs at the University of Wisconsin. &lt;br/&gt;The realization of the proposed QB lasers will have a transformational impact on both the science and technology of mid-IR lasers because reducing the heat dissipation by two orders of magnitude will lead to uncooled devices, which in turn will revolutionize the mid-IR sensors industry since hand-held sensors would become available for a vast array of applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0925104</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuech</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Kuech@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Botez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>botez@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>101E</Code>
      <Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>103E</Code>
      <Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
