<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Optoelectronic Chaotic Communications Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to demonstrate chaotic communications systems that are secure and enable high data-rate communications at 10 gigabits per second. The approach is to use semiconductor lasers with optoelectronic time delays to provide chaotic emitters and receivers that when coupled exhibit synchronized chaotic dynamics. By concealing a message in the output of the emitter, it can be transmitted securely and decrypted at the receiver. The work seeks to multiplex several messages for high data rates. Internal and operation parameters are explored to conceal the encryption key to ensure high security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is to find ways to optimally utilize the optical bandwidth acknowledging that the chaotic carrier's bandwidth exceeds that of any individual message. By multiplexing several messages within a single chaotic carrier, one can achieve bandwidths compatible with deployed optical communications systems. Preliminary work shows that choosing judicious parameters, chaotic time-delay systems can mask the encryption key, offering high security. One aim is to see if this holds for more complex systems for practical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this work include increasing security in optical communications in a manner that is compatible with existing communications infrastructure and new systems. Chaos encryption is a form of physical layer security; the only layer rarely used. Chaos encryption can, thus, be combined with software encryption. The research provides a mechanism for multidisciplinary training. The work involves an international collaboration between Georgia Tech in Atlanta and in Metz and Supélec in Metz, France.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0925713</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Citrin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.citrin@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
