<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: Illinois Summer Neuroscience Institue, University of Illionois at Urbana-Champaign, IL; May 2010, 2011 and 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Ann Asson-Batres</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will support the Illinois Summer Neuroscience Institute (ISNI) for three years. The Institute provides students with an introduction to neuroscience research, to graduate school, to careers in neuroscience, and to the neuroscience community. The ISNI is a one-week intensive introduction to neuroscience, targeting mainly students from underrepresented groups in science, in their first two years of undergraduate study. The ISNI is held at the campus of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC) and is organized and led by the UIUC Neuroscience Program. Students learn about state of the art questions and techniques from UIUC faculty who are experts in a broad range of areas within neuroscience. After hearing about research from the faculty, the students conduct a laboratory exercise that allows them to experience the challenge, excitement, and the inevitable frustrations of research. The exercises will take advantage of the expertise in insect neuroethology and Drosophila genetics at UIUC. The purpose of the Institute is to attract students to neuroscience who might not otherwise have the opportunity or exposure to the discipline and to the neuroscience community. The ultimate goal is to expand the pool of applicants, especially from underrepresented groups, to UIUC and to other neuroscience programs in the US.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0925332</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Robinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>generobi@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7712</Code>
      <Text>ORGANIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1096</Code>
      <Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
