<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ion Beam Engineering of Single-Crystal Sapphire Fibers for Fabrication of Buried Optical Claddings in Harsh Environment Sensing Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>233846</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Clark V. Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The implementation of advanced sensing technology based on single-crystal sapphire fiber optics in harsh environment sensing applications is hindered by the lack of an appropriate cladding structure for sapphire fibers that is able to function without degradation or failure under harsh conditions. This NSF project aims to address the challenge by exploring a solution relying on ion implantation and thermal annealing for achieving buried optical claddings within single-crystal sapphire fibers. Basic knowledge about the effects of ion implantation and thermal annealing on the optical and structural properties of single-crystal sapphire fibers, will be acquired. On the basis of such knowledge, design and fabrication of embedded claddings in sapphire fibers will be performed. The performance of prototyped sapphire fiber claddings will be evaluated under harsh conditions encountered in combustion processes of industrial applications (e.g., power plants and engines). Possible correlation between the performance characteristics of such claddings and the material properties of sapphire fibers, will be identified to optimize materials processing in fabrication of high-quality buried claddings in single-crystal sapphire fibers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The success of the research would be very useful for industrial applications requiring harsh environment sensing. The project will facilitate a close collaboration/partnership between university and industry, promising a rapid transfer of enabling harsh-condition sensing technology from an academic setting to the industry if the technology proves viable. The research will enable a coherent integration of research with education, by establishing connections between basic scientific concepts and industrial applications in teaching of graduate student courses, and by providing the involved graduate student and underrepresented undergraduate students with various research experiences on materials processing and characterization, as well as fabrication and testing of fiber-based optical devices. These will prepare the students for their future research careers, and in turn will help the industry recruit talents for its R&amp;D programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0926141</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>MengBing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mhuang@sunypoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
      <CityName>Albany</CityName>
      <ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5184374550</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
