<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER:Unveiling Trends in Global Nanotechnology Research and Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250348</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce M. Kramer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nanotechnology is a fundamental research area that holds the promise of revolutionizing a wide range of significant applications for everyday life. In the 30-year history of nanotechnology, its research and development has experienced rapid but uneven progress in different countries and institutions as well as research directions. The recent dynamics of the nanotechnology research landscape and the factors that have caused these changes are of the interest to nanotechnology researchers and policy makers. This research proposes to apply bibliographic analysis, citation analysis, and content analysis methods on the paper and patent publications of emerging countries and institutions in nanotechnology to unveil changes in research focus and outputs. In addition, in-depth analysis will also be conducted to quantify the effects of public funding and knowledge diffusion in these countries/institutions? development of nanotechnology. &lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will draw attention to the exceptional regions and areas that may have a long term impact on the nanotechnology field and extend our understanding of the important factors leading to success. Lessons learned will help policy makers, such as governments, funding agencies, and other interested parties to devise strategies for excellence in nanotechnology research and development. The proposed framework can be applied to other rapidly changing research fields for similar studies. The analytical methods and visualization techniques developed in this process could also be used in the education of students majoring in nanotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0926270</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hsinchun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hchen@eller.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7702</Code>
      <Text>SOCIETAL IMPLICATIONS OF NANO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
