<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Support for the 2009 Nonlinear Optics Topical Meeting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wendell Talbot Hill</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The NSF is providing student support for the 2009 Nonlinear Optics Topical Meeting, held July 12-17, 2009 in Honolulu, Hawaii. The funds support students of US nationality. The first priority is to cover the registration fee of the qualified students, where funds are distributed equally. Other funds are used to cover hotel room fees, spread equally. The meeting covers nonlinear optical phenomena which are being studied and applied over a wide range of energies and powers, from single-photons to petawatts, and over broad spectral regimes, from THz to X-ray frequencies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The meeting provides an international forum for discussion of all aspects of nonlinear optics, including new phenomena, novel devices, advanced materials and applications. Summaries of papers are collected and published. Publications are provided to participants and are also available to others interested in the meeting subject. These topical meetings provide stimulus in research areas such as: integrated optics, optical fiber communication, optical storage of digital data, atmospheric transmission, reconstruction from projections, image processing, and picosecond phenomena.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0927887</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gauthier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dan.gauthier@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Optical Society of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200361012</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2024166102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2010 Massachusetts Avenue NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
