<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Process Analysis and Variation Control in Micro-stamping</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research objective of this Grant Opportunity for Academic Liaison with Industry (GOALI) award is to explore the scientific bases and technologies for fabricating precision metal micro-features through the micro-stamping process. This research is motivated by increasing demand for low-cost, high-precision metallic components to satisfy the requirements of efficiency, strength, temperature and/or corrosion resistance in the areas of electronics, medical devices, energy generation and heat exchangers, etc.. To accomplish this goal, four research tasks are planned: (1) Mechanical characterization of thin metal sheets to accurately model the nonlinear kinematic hardening behavior; (2) Experimental and numerical analysis of springback in thin sheets; (3) Friction characterization in micro-stamping; and (4) Exploratory study of process control in micro-stamping to minimize variations in micro-stamping. Thin metal sheets less than 300 µm in thickness with feature sizes less than 500 µm are of interest to this work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will enhance the fabrication capability of thin precision metallic parts; thus, establishing new opportunities for less energy consumption due to part miniaturization and efficient energy generation. For example, a 70% reduction in hard disk size leads to a 75% reduction in energy consumption; micro-channel heat exchangers (with a characteristic length of 100 µm) have demonstrated heat fluxes 3 to 5 times higher than conventional heat exchangers; sub-millimeter needles increase patient comfort during insertion, etc.. The research is a collaboration between Northwestern University, Intri-Plex, Inc., and an international partner from the Nagoya Institute of Technology in Japan. This team provides a nurturing environment for the training of the next generation of post-doctoral fellows, graduate, undergraduate students and junior high students through advising, short courses, early exposure to industry, and opportunities for international collaborations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>300000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0928001</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Damon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brink</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>damon@intri-plex.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jcao@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
