<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Collaborative Research:A Mode-based Simulation Enabling Model and Methodologies for Geometric Variation and Tolerance Control</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>christiaan paredis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this GOALI award is to establish methods for modeling geometric dimensioning &amp; tolerancing (GD&amp;T) to enable effective GD&amp;T design simulation, and to develop methods for probabilistic GD&amp;T tolerance analysis and synthesis. The research will result in a tolerance modeling methodology that is capable of simulating random variations and incorporating them into product function models for probabilistic design in the face of manufacturing uncertainties. The research approach progresses from the development of tolerance modeling for a single complex part, to the creation of models capable of analyzing tolerances for multiple part assembly. Deliverables include a unified framework for geometric tolerance modeling, geometric tolerance representation and models on the various one-dimensional and two dimensional geometric features, statistical model parameter estimation, and tolerance analysis and synthesis methodologies for assembly, new curriculum model creation, and laboratory development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will fill the vacancies in the state of the art of computer aided tolerancing (CAT) techniques, provide practical solutions for GD&amp;T tolerance design and quality assurance, and shift the traditional dimensional tolerancing and heuristic GD&amp;T design into a new tolerance design paradigm with a rigorous model and methodological basis. The results of this research are generally applicable to many industries for high quality product design, e.g. aerospace, Micro-Electro-Mechanical Systems (MEMS), alternative energy (e.g., fuel cells), optical, automotive, and shipbuilding, among others. The results will strengthen students' research skills, and build faculty and students' experience, and publications. Results will be incorporated into new educational curricula and lab practicum, thus providing hands-on training for students in mechanical and industrial engineering. The results will be disseminated widely via professional academic and industrial collaborative networks, an industrial case study, seminars, publications, and professional conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0928609</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wenzhen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whuang@umassd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yingqing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yzhou@3dcs.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth</Name>
      <CityName>North Dartmouth</CityName>
      <ZipCode>027472300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5089998953</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>285 Old Westport Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1464</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING DESIGN AND INNOVAT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>067E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>068E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1464</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING DESIGN AND INNOVAT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9148</Code>
      <Text>TOOLS &amp; TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
