<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Implementation Grant of Enhancement, Enrichment, and Excellence in Mathematics and Science (E3MaS)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1824903</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT HRD 0929092&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Southern University at New Orleans (SUNO) is strengthening undergraduate recruitment and retention activities in the STEM disciplines. Their goals are being achieved through several interrelated activities such as: (1) improving the quality of incoming high school students through Summer Enrichment Program (SEP), Early Career Awareness, Science Fair and Algebra tutorials, (2) developing high school mathematics and science teachers through content enhancement workshops, Summer Enrichment Program and software and technology training, (3) improving the quality of undergraduates through scholarships, learning center support, research mentoring, placement in summer internships, and GRE preparation, (4) implementing an aggressive faculty development through peer mentoring, seed grant award for research development, and sponsorship to HBCU research consortium workshops, and (5) enhancing curriculum through infusion of algebra to science learning, instituting Computer Aided Learning (CAI) software in mathematics and science courses, and developing an environmental awareness elective for all majors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The expected project outcomes include: (1) increased STEM graduation; (2) increased faculty participation in research, publications, and grants writing; (3) enhanced quality of undergraduate research experiences; (4) strengthened partnerships with academic institutions and research labs; (5) increased use of technology in teaching and research in all STEM disciplines; and (6) increased numbers of STEM students completing the path from high school through college to graduate school. This proposal builds on the successes of the previous HBCU-UP grant, which resulted in significantly increasing student research and summer internships, enrollment in graduate schools, and graduation rate in STEM disciplines. The project team anticipates that this project will enable SUNO to regain some of the ground lost in STEM disciplines due to the impact of hurricane Katrina.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project leadership includes Dr. Joe Omojola, Professor of Mathematics and Physics, who was honored with the distinguished 2006 Presidential Award for Excellence in Science, Mathematics, and Engineering Mentoring (PAESMEM), given in an award ceremony at the White House.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0928797</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cjohnson@suno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joe</FirstName>
      <LastName>Omojola</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jomojola@suno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Murty</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kambhampati</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkambham@suno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern University New Orleans</Name>
      <CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
      <ZipCode>701260002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5042865314</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6400 Press Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6859</Code>
      <Text>HBCU-UP IMP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
