<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a gas source isotope ratio mass spectrometer and high temperature elemental analyzer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>290600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). With this award we will purchase a modern gas source isotope ratio mass spectrometer with a high temperature elemental analyzer. The mass spectrometer will replace the aging Delta S that is currently operating and aging in the Stable Isotope Lab in the GeoAnalytical Laboratory at Washington State University. The manufacturer has recently informed us that our 16 year-old Delta S will no longer be supported. The laboratory has seen extensive use by graduate students and has collaborated with researchers from WSU, the University of Idaho, and other institutions and government laboratories across the country. The lab has made significant contributions to scientific investigations of igneous petrogenesis, hydrothermal systems, groundwater, and paleoclimate, and other scientific areas. It will continue to contribute to these and other research programs. The laboratory has been supported by grants and contracts from the National Science Foundation, The National Geographic Society, and federal research laboratories, among other sources. We anticipate continued support from these and other sources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The laboratory has contributed to important broader impacts. It has fostered scientific collaboration across disciplinary boundaries and among scientists from different institutions. The lab has contributed to helping establish the careers of young academic scientists. Many graduate and undergraduate students have received important training in the lab. We consider this to be a critical function for providing capable and competent future scientists. The lab encourages women, minority, and international students to make use of the facilities, and has been and will continue to be successful in doing so. One of the labs current major projects is investigating the older hydrothermal alteration in the Grand Canyon of the Yellowstone River, Yellowstone Park, Wyoming. Some of our scientific results have already been transmitted to the Park Rangers who use to enhance the experience of Park visitors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>290600</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0929819</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Larson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>plarson@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington State University</Name>
      <CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
