<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Symposia on Cyberinfrastructure:A Series of 2 Workshops on the Challenges of the Complexities of Cyberinfrastructure for the 21st Century</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>35000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>OCI 0929541&lt;br/&gt;Purdue University&lt;br/&gt;Barbara Fossum&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal requests funding for a two day International Workshop to be held April 14-15, 2009 at Tsinghua University in Beijing, China. The Co-Chairs for this workshop are Jun Li, Dean of the Research Institute of Information Technology and Vice Dean of the School of Information Science and Technology, Tsinghua University, and Alex Pothen, Director of the Computer Research Institute, Director of the Combinatorial Scientific Computing and Petascale Simulations Institute at Purdue University. The program committee consists of Junwei Cao, and Xiaoge Wang from Tsinghua University and Barbara Fossum and Carol Song from Purdue University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this workshop is to address some of the major challenges presented&lt;br/&gt;by evolving cyberinfrastructure and to identify one or two areas of common interest where&lt;br/&gt;joint collaboration will bring together an international team to solve these challenges. The&lt;br/&gt;broader impacts of this workshop are to engage with international colleagues to create a venue&lt;br/&gt;for leveraging existing cyberinfrastructure investments beyond the United States. This workshop offers the opportunity for the community to create a global cyberinfrastructure enabling science and engineering between the U.S. and China.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the major challenges facing cyberinfrastructure is how to meet the needs of a rapidly changing and growing global society whose dependence on computing and information technology is growing exponentially. As we move closer to the end of the first decade of the 21st century it is essential that cyberinfrastructure evolve to be ready to meet the needs of all communities in all areas of research on a global level. To address the issues of building cyberinfrastructure for the next decade with a view to enabling global science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0929541</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaohui Carol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Song</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>carolxsong@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fossum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bfossum@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
