<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IDR - Digital luminescent particle image barometry thermometry and velocimetry - DLPIBTV</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>850038</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Song-Charng Kong</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0929864&lt;br/&gt;Dabiri &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Turbulent fluid flow is ubiquitous and important in a wide array of technological, environmental and biological situations. Our understanding of and, in turn, our ability to analyze and predict such flow is limited. This research seeks to develop new experimental techniques that will allow simultaneous measurement of local and instantaneous fluid velocities, pressures, and temperatures in turbulent convective flows; key elements in advancing our ability to understand and manipulate this complex phenomena.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The proposed technique involves fabrication of particles that are loaded with pressure- and temperature-sensitive dyes. The particles are sufficiently small as to follow the instantaneous velocities of the fluid into which they are introduced, and are simultaneously illuminated with appropriate optical sources to excite the various dyes. The fluorescent responses of the dyes will be monitored, and related to the instantaneous temperatures and pressures of the particles. Simultaneously, instantaneous fluid velocities will be determined using a laser particle image velocimetry technique. The data collected are expected to be particularly relevant to the future development of predictive models for turbulent, single phase, nonisothermal fluid flow. A multidisciplinary team of investigators with backgrounds in Chemistry, Materials Engineering, and Fluid Dynamics will be involved in the design of the pertinent dyes, the particle synthesis, and the construction of the associated laser-based measurement methodologies.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This research addresses longstanding challenges in fluid dynamics and, as such, will address related issues in environmental, energy, transportation, biomedical, and biological applications. The research will be integrated into the core curricula at the PIs institutions. A new graduate level experimental methods class will be developed at the University of Washington, based in large part upon the proposed research. Recruitment of graduate students from underrepresented groups will be included, leveraging existing programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0929864</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Younan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>younan.xia@bme.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dabiri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dabiri@aa.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7951</Code>
      <Text>ENG INTERDISC RES (IDR)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>055E</Code>
      <Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>057E</Code>
      <Text>Thermodynamics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>064E</Code>
      <Text>Convection heat and mass transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>066E</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
