<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TIE: UF-FIU inter-I/UCRC collaboration to explore autonomic computing for the TerraFly server system</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>IIP - 0931517&lt;br/&gt;Florida International University&lt;br/&gt;Rishe&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IIP - 0932023&lt;br/&gt;University of Florida &lt;br/&gt;Fortes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is to request supplemental funding to support a collaborative project between the I/UCRC Center for Advancement Knowledge Enablement (CAKE) at Florida International University (FIU), and the I/UCRC Center for Autonomic Computing (CAC) at the University of Florida (UF). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This TIE proposal brings together the two centers in a synergistic project that investigates, on one hand, the benefits of applying autonomic computing principles to the management of Web-based geospatial infrastructures, and on the other hand, provides autonomic computing researchers with access to data and expertise in the context of a rich IT environment representative of an important class of Web applications, thereby helping conduct quantitative, experimental systems research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed collaborative study will provide direct benefit to the I/UCRC stakeholders (industry partners) and help recruit additional members. Member organizations that provide servers, server software, and data center services would benefit from a direct technology transfer; and their customers in turn would thereby benefit indirectly, from the improved application performance that would result from acquisition of software and services. The successful completion of this work will, therefore, aid companies and universities by allowing them to be able to tap into this powerful tool and not have to invent and deploy the same solution for their own organizations to utilize.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0931517</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Naphtali</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rishe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rishen@cs.fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida International University</Name>
      <CityName>Miami</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
