<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CPS: Medium: Collaborative Research: The Foundations of Implicit and Explicit Communication in Cyberphysical Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>750000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to develop the theoretical&lt;br/&gt;foundations for understanding implicit and explicit&lt;br/&gt;communication within cyber-physical systems. The approach is&lt;br/&gt;two-fold: (a) developing new information-theoretic tools to&lt;br/&gt;reveal the essential nature of implicit communication in a&lt;br/&gt;manner analogous to (and compatible with) classical network&lt;br/&gt;information theory; (b) viewing the wireless ecosystem itself&lt;br/&gt;as a cyber-physical system in which spectrum is the physical&lt;br/&gt;substrate that is manipulated by heterogeneous interacting&lt;br/&gt;cyber-systems that must be certified to meet safety and&lt;br/&gt;performance objectives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project comes from the&lt;br/&gt;transformative technical approaches being developed. The key to&lt;br/&gt;understanding implicit communication is a conceptual&lt;br/&gt;breakthrough in attacking the unsolved 40-year-old Witsenhausen&lt;br/&gt;counterexample by using an approximate-optimality paradigm&lt;br/&gt;combined with new ideas from sphere-packing and cognitive radio&lt;br/&gt;channels. These techniques open up radically new mathematical&lt;br/&gt;avenues to attack distributed-control problems that have long&lt;br/&gt;been considered fundamentally intractable. They guide the&lt;br/&gt;development of nonlinear control strategies that are provably&lt;br/&gt;orders-of-magnitude better than the best linear strategies. The&lt;br/&gt;keys to understanding explicit communication in cyber-physical&lt;br/&gt;systems are new approaches to active learning, detection, and&lt;br/&gt;estimation in distributed environments that combine worst-case&lt;br/&gt;and probabilistic elements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Beyond the many diverse applications (the Internet, the smart&lt;br/&gt;grid, intelligent transportation, etc.) of heterogeneous&lt;br/&gt;cyber-physical systems themselves, this research reaches out to&lt;br/&gt;wireless policy: allowing the principled formulation of&lt;br/&gt;government regulations for next-generation networks. Graduate&lt;br/&gt;students (including female ones) and postdoctoral scholars will&lt;br/&gt;be trained and research results incorporated into both the&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate and graduate curricula.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0932410</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anant</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sahai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sahai@eecs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
