<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Targeted Design of Biomaterials for Water Treatment: Arsenic Removal and Recovery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>324460</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0932060&lt;br/&gt;Zimmerman&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this study is to design and develop bio-based hydrogels aligned with the goals of green engineering for arsenic removal from aqueous solutions. A sub-objective is to evaluate the potential for regeneration of these materials and any subsequent impact on performance to estimate functional lifetime. Additionally, end of life strategies will be evaluated, including biodegradation. To close the loop, a feasibility analysis will be conducted to evaluate the recovery of arsenic from the waste stream for use as a feedstock to industrial processes. By considering the entire life cycle of the system including the material itself and the waste streams from the process, the design of an arsenic removal system for water purification has an increased likelihood of optimizing performance of the entire system while aligning environmental and economic objectives. The study involves the functionalization of chitosan, a biopolymer, and its use in arsenic removal. This research presents potential benefits for improved health and quality of life for those whose groundwater source contains toxic arsenic levels. The team will work with the Yale Peabody Museum staff to develop an exhibit communicating global water issues, particularly as they relate to water quality and scarcity in developing communities. Also, the team will work with high school students in the Evolutions Program at Peabody to develop exhibits about global water issues, and additionally high school students will work in the team?s laboratories over summers. Undergraduate and graduate students will be actively engaged in the research throughout the year.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0932060</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zimmerman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>julie.zimmerman@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
