<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Probing and optimizing quantum dot confined states for next generation intermediate band solar cells</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>381559</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ram Gupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0933348&lt;br/&gt;Johnson&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Merit: Intermediate-band (IB) solar cells have the potential to convert sunlight to electricity with record efficiency. Perhaps the most promising approach to IB semiconductors is quantum dot (QD) arrays. In principle, these QD arrays would replace the intrinsic region in state-of-the-art p-i-n solar cells. Although this concept was originally proposed in the 1990s, the anticipated efficiency records have yet to be achieved. The performance to date has been limited by a lack of fundamental design rules for energy conversion processes in the context of QD confined states and minibands. In particular, an understanding of the influence of QD shapes, sizes, strain states, and QD/matrix interface uniformity on the formation of and interaction between QD confined states and minibands is needed. Furthermore, novel miniband architectures which enable optimum sunlight to electricity conversion efficiencies must be developed. The proposed approach involves a unique combination of state-of-the-art nanofabrication methods, measurements with unprecedented spatial resolution, and multi-scale simulations. The long-term objective of the work is to provide a set of design rules to optimize sunlight-to-electricity conversion in a wide variety of nanostructured materials. Several fundamental questions critical to the development of optimum sunlight-to-electricity conversion design rules will be addressed, including: what is the critical length scale at which the electronic states associated with a collection of point defects appear similar to those of a small QD? How do QD shapes and sizes influence the QD electronic states? How do interfacial disorder and strain influence the coupling of QD electronic states, as well as the formation of electronic mini-bands in two-dimensional and three-dimensional QD arrays? Which miniband architectures are needed to optimize the sunlight to electricity conversion efficiency? Using the unique combined expertise of the co-PIs in state-of-the-art nanofabrication, measurements with unprecedented spatial resolution, and multi-scale simulations, a set of design rules to optimize sunlight-to-electricity conversion in nanostructured intermediate band solar cells will be developed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This research is expected to have a substantial impact on energy and sustainability. The PIs will also develop an outreach program in energy and sustainability. The outreach program will build partnerships in the local public high schools. This approach will lay the groundwork for a more ambitious outreach program developed by the co-PI in Ann Arbor, which has brought more than 30 local high school students to the UM campus for summer research internships. The PIs will develop a module, 'Materials for Solar Cells", to be incorporated into existing high school physics and chemistry courses. They will present this interactive and hands-on module to students from various backgrounds within several school systems. The module will draw on the excitement surrounding major new initiatives at UIUC and UM in sustainable energy research, and will serve to generate interest in engineering research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0933348</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goldman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rsgold@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>htj@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0306000</Code>
      <Name>Energy Research &amp; Resources</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>045E</Code>
      <Text>Adv Mats for Separation Process</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>046E</Code>
      <Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>051E</Code>
      <Text>Interfacial trans &amp; thermodynamic</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>090E</Code>
      <Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7974</Code>
      <Text>GRAD RESEARCH SUPPLEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
