<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Starter Grant: Characterization of Genetic and Biochemical Mechanisms of Iron Acquisition by Pseudomonas mendocina strain ymp</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Iron is the most abundant element on earth and thus it is not surprising that most forms of life have evolved an obligate dependence on iron. However, under aerobic conditions the majority of iron exists as insoluble ferric mineral forms. In response to such environmental pressures, prokaryotes have evolved strategies such as the use of siderophores for sequestering iron from a limited soluble supply. Siderophores and siderophore-producing microbes have indeed been shown to have significant effects on rates of mineral dissolution. Pseudomonas mendocina strain ymp has been studied for siderophore production and mineral dissolution, but very little is known about the genetic content of any strain of P. mendocina. The goals of this research project are to characterize genes involved in iron uptake by both siderophore-mediated pathways, and by unanticipated iron uptake pathways. The characterization of such pathways in P. mendocina will lead to a greater understanding of how microorganisms play an important role in biogeochemical processes as well as potentially providing unique solutions to enhance bioremediation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts &lt;br/&gt;This project will facilitate student training in the field of environmental molecular microbiology by integrating classroom education and laboratory training for minority undergraduates and graduate students of Hawaii. The University of Hawaii at Hilo is dedicated to undergraduate education and is a minority-serving institution. Approximately 68% of students are residents of Hawaii and 21% of those students are Native Hawaiian. The project will have the following educational components: 1) providing hands-on training of undergraduate and graduate students in a multidisciplinary laboratory using molecular, biochemical, and microbiological techniques; 2) mentoring and bringing in minority undergraduates to the laboratory to work on environmental molecular microbiology projects as summer research interns; 3) developing a laboratory-based course in environmental microbiology, which integrates classroom discussions/lectures and hands-on experience for senior undergraduates.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0933350</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Awaya</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>awayaj@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii at Hilo</Name>
      <CityName>Hilo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>967204091</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 West Kawili Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1144</Code>
      <Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1168</Code>
      <Text>METABOLIC BIOCHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7184</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY POSTDOC RSRCH STARTER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
