<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Planning Grant: I/UCRC for Surveillance Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Planning Grant for an I/UCRC for Surveillance Theory&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;0934250 Ohio State University; Randolph Moses &lt;br/&gt;0934293 Wright State University; Brian Rigling&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center for Surveillance Theory (CST) will develop a mature theory and advanced body-of-knowledge for modern surveillance systems. Ohio State University (OSU) and Wright State University (WSU) are collaborating to establish the proposed center, with OSU as the lead institution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Surveillance and situational awareness are critical technologies needed to address societal needs of safety and security. Surveillance is used to provide our nation with both international and homeland security, and situational awareness for disaster mitigation and management (e.g. Hurricane Katrina). The main motivation behind the proposed center is to address the theory behind the complex surveillance systems mostly based on sensors and sensor systems. The proposed Center is expected to generate research that significantly advances current surveillance theory and technology and to become a focal point within the surveillance community. The inherent multidisciplinary nature of surveillance systems means that the Center will include researchers across a broad spectrum of disciplines, including signal processing, computer science, sensor technology and human factors. OSU and WSU plan to use the NSF planning grant fund to hold a meeting with prospective industrial partners to establish the proposed Center's organizational framework, and to establish research projects of greatest relevance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research advances in surveillance technology developed by CST will be transitioned to applications of significant societal and national interest. The Center plans to develop and promote a collaborative, focused scientific community in surveillance theory, including short courses, cross departmental and cross-university graduate course offerings, and internships with member organizations. CST will recruit underrepresented groups, and plans to leverage existing programs such as the Ohio STEM Ability Alliance, the ADVANCE program at OSU, and through collaborations with the Air Force Research Laboratory Sensors Directorate's Minority Leaders Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0934293</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fdgarber@valhalla.wright.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rigling</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brian.rigling@wright.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/27/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wright State University</Name>
      <CityName>Dayton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>454350001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9377752425</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3640 Colonel Glenn Highway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0400000</Code>
      <Name>Industry University - Co-op</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1049</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>122E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
