<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Cultivating Participation of Underrepresented Institutions and Students in NEON Science and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>207283</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth R. Blood</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The National Ecological Observatory Network is a research platform to enable research and education in understanding the consequences of climate, landuse, and invasive species changes on the biosphere at regional to continental scale. This cyber-enabled platform will provide an exciting opportunity to address many ecological challenges that society faces. Addressing the complex ecological challenges of tomorrow require a diversity of approaches and a diversity of human backgrounds. NEON?s education and outreach mission is to enable society and the scientific community to use ecological information and forecasts to understand and effectively address critical ecological questions and issues. NEON?s vision is for a broad spectrum of society to be engaged in NEON science with the ability to use data, information and forecasts to address the critical environmental challenges of our time. This award is a collaboration of two organizations (Science and Engineering Alliance - SEA, and the NEON, Inc.) and a professional society (Ecological Society of America -ESA) with extensive experience in working with under-represented groups and institutions. Three activities will be conducted: a workshop for college students to explore the use of integrated social media applications for NEON, four educational webinars, and a series of College Speaking Tours to 17 Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) and Minority-Serving Institutions (MSIs). These activities are intended to build the foundations for participation of under-represented minority institutions and students in the science and education necessary to address the ecological challenges, issues, and research of the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0934200</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gram</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wgram@neoninc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Don</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bowie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbowie@sea2.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mourad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>teresa@esa.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ecological Society of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200363415</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2028338773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1990 M Street NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7350</Code>
      <Text>NAT ECOLOGICAL OBSERVATORY NET</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7350</Code>
      <Text>NAT ECOLOGICAL OBSERVATORY NET</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
