<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop- Mechanics of Research Grant Proposal Development Workshops for Minority-Serving Institutions (MSIs) Atlanta, GA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>244120</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth R. Blood</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The full and effective engagement of junior faculty at minority-serving institutions in NSF funded research remains a challenge. As NSF moves forward with development and deployment of environmental observing system infrastructure, the need and opportunity for such faculty participation is increased. This award will provide a multifaceted approach to effective and ongoing education and mentoring of junior faculty (five years or less at these institutions), to assist them in remaining competitive and productive researchers and assure they are fully aware of NSF funding opportunities, proposal and review processes, and education and training opportunities. Building on its previous successful workshops for engaging junior faculty at historically black colleges and universities (HBCUs), Hispanic Serving Institutions (HSIs) and Tribal Colleges and Universities (TCUs), the Science and Engineering Alliance, Inc., (SEA) will conduct a series of grant proposal development workshops for junior faculty at minority-serving institutions (MSIs) to enhance their knowledge of NSF's proposal, review, and award processes. A unique aspect of the award is the establishment of campus communities of scholars, each of which is to be composed of established researchers, experienced administrators, institutional points of contact (POCs) and workshop participants to provide a support network within and among institutions to nurture and mentor the young faculty. Additional communication, mentoring support and follow up with attendees will be provided through project email and a project website.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0935384</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shepard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shepard@sea2.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Don</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bowie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbowie@sea2.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Science and Engineering Alliance Incorporated</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200080000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2028420388</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4301 Connecticut Avenue, NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
