<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: An Interactive Exhibition in Nanotechnology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>251791</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Chiu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A 1,200 square foot exhibition that focuses on nanotechnology will be designed, fabricated and evaluated. This exhibit will become part of the permanent exhibition assets at Epcot, Walt Disney World Resorts, Lake Buena Vista, Florida. The opportunity is significant as in excess of one million guests visit the Innoventions exhibition hall each year. The exhibition will be developed as a collaboration between Cornell University and Tamarack Design, a team that has successfully developed two other exhibitions that are currently on national tour. The exhibition will also be a platform for ?broadcasting? videos on scientific discoveries in a variety of areas. This 1,200 square foot exhibition builds on advances made by the PI in the development of Too Small to See and also the web site and magazine, Nanooze. Learning goals that are based upon core concepts in nanoscale science and engineering will be the subject of on-site assessment by an external evaluator. &lt;br/&gt;The exhibition will promote awareness of nanotechnology in one of the largest venues available, targeting youth in the upper elementary and middle school years, with a specific emphasis on women and minorities that are underrepresented in science, technology, engineering and math. The demographics of the Walt Disney World Resort visitors are more representative than other science museums. The exhibition will promote awareness of career opportunities in STEM for all audiences, and it will specifically target women and those from minority groups using diverse role models, video and other media, non-competitive exhibit and program activities, and family group interaction.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0937179</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Batt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cab10@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell Univ - State: AWDS MADE PRIOR MAY 2010</Name>
      <CityName>Ithica</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502488</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
