<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Structural control of hydrothermal flow: A comparison between the RIDGE2000 sites and the Iceland spreading centers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>159411</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara L. Ransom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research carries out an integrative, comparative synthesis and compilation of known data among hydrothermal sites along the mid-ocean ridge at the RIDGE2000 focus sites on the East Pacific Rise, the Juan de Fuca Ridge, and the Lau Basin and extensively studied geothermal areas in Iceland. Analysis of the resulting co-registered bathymetric/ topographic, morphological, geological, and hydrothermal vent fluid chemistry and vent location data allow generation of a detailed picture of the distribution of vents and vent sites with respect to mapped and imaged structures, volcanic features, and hydrothermal deposits. Data from repeat surveys and/or long-term monitoring provide detail on changes in vent distribution and behavior over time to provide a clear picture of the short-term evolution of hydrothermal activity at each location. Results shed light on the interplay between heat sources, fluids and permeable pathways in the ocean shallow crust which has direct implications for the transport of heat, alteration of the crust, and distribution of hydrothermal products/ore deposits (both active and fossil). Broader impacts of the work include postdoctoral training and international collaboration with Icelandic scientists. Public outreach to K-12 classrooms will also be carried out.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0937393</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Karson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jakarson@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
