<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EFRI-BSBA: Biology Inspired Intelligent Micro Optical Imaging Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT for EFRI BSBA: Biology Inspired Intelligent Micro Optical Imaging Systems&lt;br/&gt;PI: Hongrui Jiang, UWI, Madison;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This interdisciplinary research seeks to realize bio-inspired intelligent micro optical imaging systems. Six types of natural eyes are selected to provide inspirations to meet those challenges: camera-type eyes (e.g., human eyes), apposition compound eyes (e.g., flies), eye arrays (spiders), non-circular shaped pupils (e.g., rays), reflecting superposition compound eyes (e.g., shrimps), and bi-fovea retinas (e.g., hawks). This research incorporates the useful elements of natural visual systems into integrated, intelligent, micro imaging systems without anatomic and physiological constraints. This research has the following main tasks: 1) Development of spherical multi-micro-camera arrays (MMCA) integrating light field photography. This integration enables miniaturized systems to acquire panoramic videos with large depth of field. 2) Development of artificial reflecting superposition compound eyes (ARSCE) by coupling a spherical micro-mirror-box array and a spherical photodetector array. This integration enables high-transmittance and low-chromatic-aberration imaging over a wide spectrum. 3) Development of bio-inspired multi-fovea coordination software as a general framework for efficient processing of visual information and a simulation platform for verification of hypotheses in bio-vision research. 4) Validation of developed hardware and software prototypes through computer simulation and physical experimentation. The PIs also propose a coherent and comprehensive education and outreach plan that includes curriculum improvement and development, mentoring graduate, undergraduate and underrepresented students (especially those with learning disabilities), creation of and participation in interdisciplinary educational programs, and dissemination and outreach to the local community and general public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is transformative and novel and has the potential to broadly impact many scientific disciplines, including electrical engineering, mechanical engineering, computer science and engineering, materials science and engineering, biomedical engineering, ophthalmology, visual sciences, and optics. This study will enhance the understanding in comparative vision, ophthalmology, visual neuroscience and neurophysiology, and might contribute to the grand task of realizing artificial vision. This research can also make significant contribution to research in micro optics in optical imaging and microanalytics, which have wide applications in medical diagnostics, biophotonics and lab-on-a-chip technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This interdisciplinary research will generate significant educational &lt;br/&gt;opportunities for students at both college and K-12 levels. Accomplishments will lead to development of new courses and greatly benefit existing ones in multiple areas, such as microelectromechanical systems, microsensors, microdevice and integrated circuit fabrication, integrated circuit design, computer vision, comparative vision, physiological optics, neurophysiology, ophthalmology and veterinary ophthalmology, electronic materials, polymer physics, and mechanics of polymers. This project will provide opportunities for undergraduate and underrepresented students to conduct transformative and novel research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0937847</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rogers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.rogers1@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Li</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lizhang@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>VerHoeve</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>verhoeve@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hongrui</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jiang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hongrui@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murphy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>MURPHYC@SVM.VETMED.WISC.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7633</Code>
      <Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
