<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Climate Literacy &amp; Energy Awareness Network (CLEAN) Pathway</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1308426</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myles G. Boylan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Climate Literacy and Energy Awareness Network (CLEAN) pathway for NSDL is being developed. The primary audience is a broad one ranging from middle school students to college graduates. The goal of the CLEAN collaborative project is the assembly of a collection of approximately 500 authoritative, scientifically sound resources so that teachers, their students and the general citizenry may improve their knowledge of climate and its impact on society and enable them to make better informed decisions about energy use and stewardship of planet earth. The CLEAN pathway utilizes science literacy maps (strand maps) to aid users in finding needed resources and illustrate connections between concepts and how concepts build on one another. The resources are aligned with the AAAS Project 2061 Benchmarks for Scientific Literacy, the National Science Education Standards and, the NAAEE Excellence in Environmental education Guidelines for Learning. Teleconference-online workshops are helping teachers and citizens learn to use the resources. An online community using Web 2.0 social networking tools to promote collaboration, interactivity and knowledge sharing among educators, experts and enthusiasts is being facilitated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is receiving co-funding under the Dear Colleague Letter: Climate Change Education to support the development of NSDL efforts directly related to climate science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0938051</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Niepold</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fniepold@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/28/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tamara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ledley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tamara_ledley@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>TERC Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021401339</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6178739600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2067 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
