<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Physics of Solar Radio Emission Process</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174075</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ilia I. Roussev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The principal investigator (PI) plans to investigate the detailed physics of the radio emission from solar Type II and Type III radio bursts. He hopes to advance the basic understanding of nonlinear plasma behavior by solving the complete set of electromagnetic weak turbulence kinetic equations for electrons, ions, Langmuir turbulence, ion-acoustic turbulence, and electromagnetic transverse radiation. Since such a complete solution has never before been obtained, the PI asserts that such a result will lead to fundamental breakthroughs in nonlinear plasma physics. The PI plans to study the time scale of the plasma emission, the intensities for fundamental and harmonic emissions, and the radiation beaming patterns for fundamental and harmonic emissions. He will focus on determining which of the two competing processes for fundamental emission (decay or scattering) is dominant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since Type II bursts can provide a view of coronal mass ejections (CMEs) that complements the traditional coronagraph, and Type III bursts are often associated with the CME lift-off, these two classes of solar radio emission are important for the space weather research. Both emission signatures can serve as early warnings for CMEs and also as diagnostic tools for space weather forecasts. The PI also states that the results of this project will aid space weather modelers and observers. This activity will provide for the education and training of a graduate student and promote international scientific collaboration with researcher collaborators in Brazil.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0940985</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yoon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>YoonP@UMD.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/04/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0205000</Code>
      <Name>Space</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
