<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Control of Animal and Plant ABA receptor interaction with Associated G-Protein</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark R. Brodl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Name: Fedora Sutton&lt;br/&gt;Proposal #: IOS 0940858&lt;br/&gt;Title: EAGER: Control of Animal and Plant ABA receptor interaction with&lt;br/&gt;Associated G-Protein&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abscisic acid (ABA) is a hormone naturally produced in plants to regulate stress responses, including stomatal closure in times of drought. Identification of the ABA receptor has been pursued for more than 20 years. To date, no ABA receptors have been identified in animals; however, pancreatic cells have been shown to produce ABA and respond to ABA suggesting the presence of a pancreatic ABA receptor. The investigators propose that the pancreatic ABA receptor interacts with other proteins in order to function. As a result the investigators propose using the interacting proteins to isolate the ABA receptor by use of the yeast two-hybrid molecular technique. If the hypothesis is correct, the researchers will identify an animal ABA receptor and corresponding regulators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The following aspects of the project are broader impacts of the work. The project activity includes the education of two undergraduates and two women scientists. Recent findings suggest that ABA may play an important regulatory role in animal cells, including activation of human granulocytes and stimulation of insulin release through an ABA signaling pathway in human and rat pancreatic cells. Therefore, not only could the increased understanding of these signaling pathways lead to additional drought-tolerance strategies in plants, treatments for Type II diabetes and obesity in humans could also follow. Thus, the project has broader impacts in the area of potentially impacting agricultural plant productivity under environmental stress, and also in the area of human health.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0940858</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fedora</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sutton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>svi.research@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ropp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>samatak@itctel.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>South Dakota State University</Name>
      <CityName>Brookings</CityName>
      <ZipCode>570070001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6056886696</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1015 Campanile Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
