<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Novel MEMS Biosensor for Real Time Study of the Attachment of Cancer Cells</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Novel MEMS Biosensor for Real Time Study of the Attachment of Cancer Cells&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this proposal is to design and fabricate a novel biosensor with capabilities of detecting in real time the adhesion and stiffness of normal and cancer cells. This biosensor will merge two biosensing techniques namely resonant frequency measurements and impedance spectroscopy technique on a single device. The approach is to situate the detecting microelectrodes for impedance spectroscopy technique on the acoustic path of a piezoelectric resonator. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed biosensor will be able to simultaneously perform, in real time, two different types of electric measurements on the same cell and will represent an analysis platform for in vitro diagnosis of cancer cells. This biosensor will have novel capabilities to test different subcellular regions of a cell, using an array of microelectrodes for impedance spectroscopy detection. During this research mathematical models that will predict the relationship between the electrical measurements and the mechanical properties of the cell will be also formulated. The proposed research is exploratory work in early stage and will offer novel cell analysis capabilities provided by integrating two separate measurement methods in a single device.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This biosensor could have other important applications as: detecting different cancer biomarkers, and facilitating steam cells differentiation. The principal investigator is interested in integration of this research with education and especially to increase the participation of underrepresented students in the engineering field and attract women to the doctoral program. The educational plan also includes mentoring high school students from minority population and involving underrepresented students in international research in Japan.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0940111</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ioana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Voiculescu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>voicules@me.ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY City College</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
