<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: InfoCalc, a Spreadsheet Interface to Web Archive Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vijayalakshmi Atluri</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>It has long been recognized that while the World Wide Web (WWW) has a wealth of information, there is a severe lack of tools to access and analyze its contents. The tool proposed here, if the effort is fully successful has the potential to radically extend use of WWW contentsThis project will construct a new set of tools that will make World Wide Web archives and present web data available to a wide group of researchers whose efforts depend upon examination of large amounts of data captured in different forms over extensive periods of time. This would include such researchers from the social sciences, health information management research, political science, an environmental sciences, to name a few. The project will comprise two components: a user interface to analysis tools that operate and an architecture for supporting the tools. The analysis tools will provide fundamental data management operations such as formula creation, and data summarization.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0941727</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hector</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garcia-Molina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hector@cs.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
