<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Flash Applets for WeBWorK Online Homework System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>193751</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Jacobson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Mathematical Sciences (21)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is developing a collection of applets and embedding those applets in mathematics problems used with the online homework system WeBWorK. Traditional WeBWorK problems require the user to type a response or to select a response from a provided list. In contrast, the applet-enhanced homework problems that are being created as part of this project are providing a richer array of response options by allowing users to click, drag and/or drop objects as all or part of their responses. For instance, problems are asking users to sketch a graph meeting some specified conditions, and allowing users to click and drag to produce the desired graph. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is developing a full collection of applets and WeBWorK homework problems for Calculus I and II, with additional applets and problems that are appropriate for selected topics from precalculus, multivariable calculus, and differential equations. Problems are being reviewed by experts in the area of web-based mathematics instruction, and are being used by a variety of high school and university mathematics instructors and their students. A collection of Flash ActionScript 3 classes is being designed to facilitate the work of others in developing applet-enhanced WeBWorK homework problems. Online tutorials are being developed to assist developers in using the class libraries, and a workshop on developing Flash enhanced WeBWorK problems is being offered. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Applet enhanced homework problems are being made available through the WeBWorK National Problem Library. Flash ActionScript 3 classes are being shared via WeBWorK sites and MathDL. Flash enhanced WeBWorK problems are providing a framework in which others may study the effectiveness of applet technology in student understanding of mathematical context. Embedding the applets in the WeBWorK environment, where student use can be easily tracked, is facilitating the ability of this team and others to study students' use of the tools and how the tools affect students' understanding of concepts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0941388</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Margolius</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>b.margolius@csuohio.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luiz</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>l.martins@csuohio.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>y.wu88@csuohio.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cleveland State University</Name>
      <CityName>Cleveland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441152214</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2166873630</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2121 Euclid Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
