<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integrated Approach for Mechatronics Education Using Industrial Motion Control Technology and Active Learning</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>141691</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Krupczak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Engineering - Mechanical (56)&lt;br/&gt;This CCLI Type 1 project is developing a sequence of ten lecture and eight laboratory modules to incorporate industrial motion control into a senior level mechanical engineering course in automation. Motion control is defined as a subfield of automation in which the position and/or velocity of multiple axes in a machine are controlled in a synchronized fashion. The motivation for this effort comes from the extensive use of motion control in the packaging, assembly, textile, paper, printing, food processing and semiconductor manufacturing industries that employ many mechanical engineering graduates. The ten modules are path generation, transmission elements, feedback devices and motors, motion controllers, basic and advanced feedback control, tuning, motion controller programming, programmable logic controllers, and applications of motion control, and the last eight modules have corresponding laboratory modules. The materials development plan is being informed and reviewed by an industrial advisory board. The lecture modules are being developed using advanced pedagogies including collaborative learning and just-in-time teaching. The modular format of the materials enables other institutions to adopt only materials appropriate for their curriculum. The project is also developing a "Where is Math?" outreach workshop for middle and high school students and teachers that is designed to illustrate the importance of mathematics in everyday life and to stimulate interest in STEM education. The project includes formative and summative evaluation plans for all aspects of the project coordinated by an independent evaluator.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0941035</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hakan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gurocak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hgurocak@vancouver.wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington State University</Name>
      <CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
