<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Guiding General Chemistry Laboratory Toward a Green Revolution: An Inquiry Approach</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>192595</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Chemistry (12)&lt;br/&gt;This grant provides two years of funding to allow the Department of Chemistry and Physics at Armstrong Atlantic State University to infuse guided inquiry green chemistry experiments to spur student interest in and commitment to chemistry. The involved faculty and staff are developing a series of guided inquiry modules, which are based on the 12 Principles of Green Chemistry and environmental sustainability, into the general chemistry laboratory. Traditionally, general chemistry laboratories have been modeled after "cookbook" type activities that enable high throughput of students but limit the amount of discovery and inquiry that are fundamental to science. The standard four week guided inquiry modules are being investigated in groups to promote collaborative student work and include projects with a green chemistry theme. These topics include ore refinement, soil analysis, water pollution, green synthesis of nanoparticles, biodiesel, acid rain, air pollution, and fuel cells, each of which illustrate one or more of the major theoretical aspects of general chemistry such as stoichiometry, gas laws, equilibrium, kinetics, thermodynamics, electrochemistry, and acid/base chemistry. The overarching goal of the transformative project is sharing the excitement of chemistry with students to favorably affect the recruiting and retaining of students in chemistry. The experience is equipping students with greater critical thinking skills to better prepare them for future coursework and lifelong learning. The general chemistry sequence impacts the greatest number of students across the disciplines of science and is creating a community of green scholars. The two semester inquiry experience culminates in an environmentally related green chemistry research experience for every student enrolled. The adaptation and results are being shared with educators for implementation in their classrooms through internet based resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0942047</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Werner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ewerner@ut.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/21/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Clifford</FirstName>
      <LastName>Padgett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clifford.padgett@armstrong.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lea</FirstName>
      <LastName>Padgett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lea.padgett@armstrong.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>MacGowan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Catherine.MacGowan@armstrong.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Will</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lynch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Will.Lynch@armstrong.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>josh.smith.ctr@wpafb.af.mil</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Armstrong Atlantic State University</Name>
      <CityName>Savannah</CityName>
      <ZipCode>314191997</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9123442875</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11935 ABERCORN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
