<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Statistics Teaching Using Resampling and Randomization (STURR)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ron Buckmire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In recent years many statisticians have become involved in the reform movement in statistical education aimed at improving the teaching and learning of introductory statistics. While instructors are incorporating technology into courses, it is primarily used to support outdated methods even though freely accessible technology for teaching modern statistical approaches is available. Many educators in the reform movement are embracing the power of technological advances to promote statistical thinking through the teaching of statistical computing, especially at the undergraduate level. In conjunction with the NSF-funded Change Agents for Teaching And Learning STatistics (CATALST) curriculum project, the Statistics Teaching Using Resampling and Randomization (STURR) project makes some of these statistical computing approaches accessible to non-statistics majors enrolled in general, non-calculus based introductory statistics courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Existing software packages (such as SPSS, Minitab, R, and Fathom) can be programmed to carry out modern methodologies, but the knowledge and skills required to do so are often daunting for most of the undergraduate students who enroll in an introductory statistics course. The primary goal of the STURR project is to develop freely accessible and easy to use tools that provide a Graphic User Interface (GUI) to the R statistical computing environment. The incorporation of these "R Tools" into the CATALST curriculum supports and builds students' conceptual understanding of modern statistical methods, such as resampling and randomization, but without requiring them to learn computer programming or develop other computational skills needed to use R. In this project the research team fully develops and tests the R Tools. They also make modifications and improvements to the tools, and integrate them into the CATALST curriculum, resulting in a more effective CATALST course. Videotaped think aloud interviews with individual students and small groups working together on activities that use the R Tools, along with videotaped class sessions, and results from assessments provides feedback for modifying the R Tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0942408</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>delMas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>delma001@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
