<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Visual Portfolio - based Approach to CS1 using Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Don L. Millard</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Computer Science (31)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computing, as a discipline, continues to struggle with recruiting sufficient numbers of students to meet employer demand. A variety of approaches in the introductory course have been proposed to increase recruitment. Investigators for this project are developing a course that uses a novel approach of having students create visual projects using the programming language Processing. The language is built on top of Java but provides a simplified syntax and enhanced features to support art and multimedia. Students post their project portfolios on a social networking site where they can view and comment on each other's work. Fundamental concepts from the traditional CS1 course are covered with the goal of preparing students for a traditional CS2 course. Expected results include a sketchbook-oriented text and ancillary materials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Emphasis on art, as well as computing, aims to increase recruitment and engagement of students not previously attracted to the discipline. In particular, experience suggests women respond well to this approach. Wide adoption is encouraged with faculty training workshops targeted to a variety of colleges and universities. Pilot versions of the course are being offered at a small liberal arts college as well as a comprehensive university.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/07/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0942628</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ira</FirstName>
      <LastName>Greenberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ira@iragreenberg.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Methodist University</Name>
      <CityName>Dallas</CityName>
      <ZipCode>752750302</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2147682030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6425 BOAZ</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
