<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Community Science Workshops: Beginning a National Movement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>342105</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia M. James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"Community Science Workshops: Beginning a National Movement" is an extension of a successful, NSF-funded project that created a network of community science centers in California. Green Mountain College has now taken this successful venture to a national level by working with partner organizations throughout the country to establish new Community Science Workshops (CSWs) in underserved communities. Once sites are selected, CSW directors participate in an intensive two-week training program. This is followed by visits by site mentors, annual meetings, and ongoing support through the Internet and other media, which contributes to the establishment and eventual sustainability of the centers. Each site partners with local, established museums, science centers and community-based nonprofit organizations to gain much needed assistance with exhibits and education programs. Community Science Workshops contain permanent exhibit space, a workshop area for student projects and classroom/storage space. They serve a variety of audiences through after school, family, school and summer science programs. National CSW locations include Miami, Houston, New Orleans, Boston, and Washington, D.C. A CSW program is also in development in Biloxi, MS. "</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0942613</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fonteyn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paul.fonteyn@umb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Green Mountain College</Name>
      <CityName>Poultney</CityName>
      <ZipCode>057641098</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8022878214</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Brennan Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Vermont</StateName>
      <StateCode>VT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
