<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Elastomer matrix nanocomposites reinforced with pseudoelastic metal nanowires</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ben Schrag</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project is to develop pseudoelastic metal nanowires to produce elastomer matrix nanocomposites which provide desired combinations of electrical conductivity, stiffness, strength, deformation capacity, and cost for various applications. The proposed Phase I research will: (i) synthesize pseudoelastic metal nanowires, and produce elastomer matrix nanocomposites; (ii) Evaluate the structure and key properties of elastomer matrix/nanowire nanocomposites; (iii) Assess the technical merits and competitive promise of the technology; and (iv) Devise and verify strategies for improving the structure and properties of nanocomposites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Pseudoelastic nanowire/elastomer matrix nanocomposites promise enhanced elastomeric constitutive behavior, high electrical conductivity (at various strains), and improved thermo-mechanical performance for use in morphing UAV skins, conductive adhesives/seals, electromagnetic shielding of mobile electronics, and electrostatic automotive painting. The nanocomposites could be designed to offer improved barrier and tribological attributes, and high levels of hydro-thermal, chemical and UV resistance for enhanced longevity in these applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0944152</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anagi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Balachandra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tchnv@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>TECHNOVA CORPORATION</Name>
      <CityName>OKEMOS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488643705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5174859583</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3927 Dobie Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
