<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Gordon Research Conference and Seminar on the Origin of Life, to be held January 10, 2010 through January 15, 2010, in Galveston, Texas</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen C. Cone</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The origin and early development of life, whether specifically on Earth or possibly elsewhere in the universe, remain great unsolved scientific problems. At the 2010 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) "The Origin of Life", investigators will present interdisciplinary, cutting-edge research designed to improve our understanding of origins while allowing increasingly realistic scenarios for major events in life's history. The conference will underscore the rich diversity of perspectives while addressing a variety of key questions. Does life uniquely reside on the Earth or is it found elsewhere? Speakers will present and examine the most recent results of studies on Mars. How might an RNA world have emerged and led to modern living systems? Speakers will discuss recent advances in understanding self-replicating systems and the prospects for developing model synthetic living systems. What was the earliest life on Earth like? Using insights gained from genes and genomes, speakers will examine the nature of the last common ancestor, the possibility of actually reconstructing ancient proteins, and the early development of the translation machinery. What can the deep carbon cycle tell us about origins? Speakers will examine abiotic synthesis and deep microbial life. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On the weekend immediately preceding the main conference, a Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) for young investigators will be held. Approximately 30-50 students, postdoctoral researchers, and new faculty members will gather with a small number of senior mentors. The participants will present their own research on origins and most will stay for the extended conference. The "Origin of Life" conference and associated GRS will foster an environment that attracts the brightest and most interactive members of the scientific community. Since its first incarnation in 1982, the "Origin of Life GRC" has been held 16 times and proven to be a unique open forum focused on identifying, refining, and solving new interdisciplinary problems in the origins field. The GRC and GRS are unique in bringing astronomers, geoscientists, physicists, chemists, and biologists of various types together to share their ideas and approaches to origins questions. With its focus on the subject matter, the GRC fosters the genesis of new constellations of collaborators and intense intellectual discourse. Networking opportunities are abundant as a result of the weeklong schedule with its emphasis on discussion time, and this networking fosters interactions between young investigators and more established researchers. As a result, the conference will provide unique training opportunities for scientists at different career stages. GRS participants will select one of their own to present his or her work at the GRC. Participants will include underrepresented groups and will come from around the world including countries in Asia, Europe, and the Americas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0945433</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fox</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fox@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
