<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Durable Anti-Reflective Nanostructured Coatings for Photovoltaic Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Grace Jinliu Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Program Phase I project is to develop a&lt;br/&gt;manufacturing process for precisely controlled application of layers with precisely controlled nanostructure leading to a scalable multi-layered, nanostructured anti-reflective coating for use on commercial photovoltaic modules. Sol-gel chemistry will be employed as the basis for these coatings owing to the low materials cost, friendly and scalable chemistry, ease of solution coating, and durability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this project is to produce a durable multi-functional coating that will increase power output of solar modules by 7% to 15% with an incremental cost of energy of &lt;$0.17/W (&lt;$0.001/kW-hr) for typical thin film installations. The fundamental knowledge gained about the chemical and mechanical mechanisms that determine the long-term mechanical and optical stability of anti-reflective coatings made with multi-layer nanoporous materials will be a further impact.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0945584</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Robinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>matthew@nanosolar.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Nanosolar, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951381017</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4083655960</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5521 Hellyer Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
