<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium: Hybrid Smart Micro and Nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0946615&lt;br/&gt;Minko&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this project is a support for the Symposium of the American Chemical Society Division of Polymeric Materials:Science and Engineering titled ?Hybrid Smart Micro- and Nanoparticles? which will be held in the frames of 238th ACS National Meeting in Washington DC, August 16-20, 2009. The planned symposium overviews the very recent developments in science and engineering of responsive nanoparticles and colloidal systems with special emphasis on new biomimetic systems and applications for biosensors.&lt;br/&gt;Responsive polymer materials can adapt to surrounding environments, regulate transport of ions and molecules, change wettability and adhesion of different species upon external stimuli, or convert chemical and biochemical signals into optical, electrical, thermal, and mechanical signals and vice versa. These materials have played an increasingly important role in a diverse range of applications, such as drug delivery, diagnostic, tissue engineering, and ?smart? optical systems, as well as biosensors, microelectro-mechanical systems (MEMS), coatings, and textiles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The present symposium will help to integrate various aspects of the responsive colloidal systems? study in the event open for a wide community of engineers, materials scientists and students and involve the brightest undergraduate and graduate students in modern areas of biosensors, colloidal and material science, and biotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0946615</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sergiy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Minko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sminko@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clarkson University</Name>
      <CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
      <ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3152686475</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8 Clarkson Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
