<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An extensible framework for the web based distribution of data derived from multiple geophysical data sets.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Erica L. Key</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>As part of the Arctic High Spectral Resolution Lidar (HSRL) program, the investigators have developed a web portal to disseminate HSRL data, and this portal is designed to reduce overhead tasks that most users encounter in accessing data. These web-based tools give a user considerable flexibility in manipulating data, retrieving the latest version of data or data product, combining the data with other data types including satellite imagery, and generating publication-quality graphics directly fro the archive. In this project, this set of tools will be extended and adapted to incorporate a wide variety of geophysical data types, considerably beyond HSRL, and this extended framework will be deployed at NCAR for access by the climate science community. The framework will be open source, and will be flexible with respect to common scientific programming languages and commonly used data formats. Broader impacts involve the ability to foster additional interdisciplinary scientific collaboration in the climate sciences through more transparent access to many complex data types from sophisticated instruments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0946359</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edwin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eloranta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eloranta@ssec.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
