<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Early Career: Acquisition of an Inductively Coupled Plasma - Mass Spectrometer (ICP-MS) for Research in Geochemical, Environmental, and Paleoenvironmental Geoscience</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>171469</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0948366&lt;br/&gt;Bain&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will fund a new inductively Coupled plasma-mass spectrometer (ICP-MS) which will significantly increase sensitivity over the existing ICP-OES and allow synergistic analyses with the institution's TIMS machine. The new instrument will support geochemical investigations by multiple faculty. Trace elemental concentration measurements will be made in precipitation, dry deposition, airborne particulate matter, trace materials in natural waters, sediment digests and in sequential extractions. The requested collision cell technology will assist in obtaining signals from elements with polyatomic interferences such as iron and chromium. An autosampler will improve throughput from multiple users. The acquisition will be used to define human activity geochemical tracers - expanding the list of potential tracers, particularly in surface hydrologic and atmospheric systems, and facilitate cross-comparison between gaseous stable isotope tracer techniques and trace metal/heavy stable isotope techniques. TIMS is currently used at the University of Pittsburgh in order to understand a variety of isotope systems of interest (B, Fe, Cr, Cd). The new ICP-MS will assist in measuring elements from environmental samples and be complementary. Overall research goals involve tectonic structuring and interpreting paleorecords, especially those indicating responses to human forcings. Metal and metalloid flux through Earth systems is of critical societal importance and touches on public health issues. This request supports several early career PIs. K-12 education will be enhanced through better understanding metal contaminants in Southwestern Pennsylvania. Environmental water sampling and reporting will be made available to stakeholders and policy makers and the general public. The ICP-MS instrumentation will be made available to the larger local scientific community. The instrument will also be incorporated into courses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0948366</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stewart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bstewart@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abbott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mabbott1@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rosenmeier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mrosenme@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/22/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bain</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbain@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elliott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eelliott@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1575</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
