<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of an X-Ray Fluorescence instrument for research and teaching at Wesleyan University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149720</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The analytical technique of X-ray fluorescence (XRF) is well proven, and provides quantitative information on a broad range of elements, with relatively simple sample preparation and ease of use. This award will fund the acquisition of a new XRF instrument that is ideal for use in teaching and research in a mid-sized, intensely focused earth science department such as the Wesleyan University E&amp;ES department. Wesleyan BA and MA students as well as those from neighboring universities will use the new instrument for their research. Wesleyan teachers will use the instrument to inspire students on the path of ?original discovery? and stimulate curiosity into scientific endeavors that may ultimately lead to innovations in industry, recognition of environmental hazards, or new energy resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Science education of college students is important given the role that technology and scientific discourse play in society and the need to compete in the global economy. The use of ?active learning projects? greatly facilitates the teaching of science. Students collect new data from their samples, and interpret these to test a hypothesis, show a spatial anomaly, or derive a new hypothesis on the origin of the samples. The chemical composition of rocks and minerals provides direct evidence on their origin and evolution. Therefore, petrology is a prime tool in deciphering earth history as well as helping to locate new energy resources or ore bodies. Sedimentary rocks may reveal evidence of the climate at the time when they were deposited, whereas volcanic rocks yield clues to the deeper, inaccessible parts of the earth, such as the mantle. The chemical composition of soils and sediment may give clues to anthropogenic or natural pollution with toxic elements, including Lead, Copper and Arsenic. Acquisition of a new X-ray fluorescence spectrometer at Wesleyan University enables us to reach these goals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0949376</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Johan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Varekamp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>JVAREKAMP@WESLEYAN.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/03/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wesleyan University</Name>
      <CityName>Middletown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>064593208</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8606853683</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>237 HIGH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
