<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III: Workshop support for meeting on algorithms for modern massive data sets, MMDS 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vasant G. Honavar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposal is a request for funds to support the biennial MMDS&lt;br/&gt;meetings on Algorithms for Modern Massive Data Sets. The goals&lt;br/&gt;of these meetings are: (1) to explore novel techniques for&lt;br/&gt;modeling and analyzing massive, high-dimensional, and&lt;br/&gt;nonlinearly-structured scientific and internet data sets; and&lt;br/&gt;(2) to bring together computer scientists, statisticians,&lt;br/&gt;mathematicians, and data analysis practitioners to promote&lt;br/&gt;cross-fertilization of ideas. The meetings will occur in the&lt;br/&gt;wake of two related meetings in 2006 and 2008 that addressed&lt;br/&gt;similar topics. Both MMDS 2006 and MMDS 2008 were an enormous&lt;br/&gt;interdisciplinary success, and they clearly highlighted the&lt;br/&gt;need for a regular meeting forum to bring together junior and&lt;br/&gt;senior researchers from a range of backgrounds to address the&lt;br/&gt;challenging foundational problems that will be faced in upcoming&lt;br/&gt;years as increasingly large and complex data sets are generated&lt;br/&gt;in a wide range of application domains. The proposed meetings&lt;br/&gt;will capitalize on these past successes and extend the MMDS&lt;br/&gt;series into a more regular series of meetings to address&lt;br/&gt;algorithmic, statistical, and computational aspects of modern&lt;br/&gt;massive data set analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The topics covered by MMDS address fundamental algorithmic&lt;br/&gt;questions underlying much of the recent work in large-scale data&lt;br/&gt;analysis. In addition, topics of interest at MMDS include data&lt;br/&gt;problems ranging from better search and ranking at internet&lt;br/&gt;sites to improved methods for extracting structure in genetics&lt;br/&gt;applications to analyzing biomedical images for improved disease&lt;br/&gt;detection. Progress on these fronts will be fueled by junior&lt;br/&gt;researchers as well as researchers from a wide range of&lt;br/&gt;application areas. Thus, every effort was be made to include&lt;br/&gt;junior researchers, including women and minorities, at past&lt;br/&gt;meetings and to disseminate the information presented at the&lt;br/&gt;meetings to people who were not able to attend. This will be&lt;br/&gt;continued at future meetings. For more information, please see&lt;br/&gt;the meeting webpage: http://mmds.stanford.edu/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0949412</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gunnar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carlsson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gunnar@math.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
