<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Landscapes in the Anthropocene: Exploring the Human Connections</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>54058</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Cutler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop, "Landscapes in the Anthropocene: Exploring the Human Connections," will be held 4-6 March, 2010 at the University of Oregon. The workshop will provide an important venue for intellectual cross-fertilization among scientists from disparate disciplines who otherwise would have little opportunity to interact. It will also provide a mechanism to bridge the real and perceived gaps that exist across the natural and social-scientific divide. Overcoming such barriers will build the community necessary to forge scientific advances, to anticipate and mitigate the human-induced changes to Earth's surface, as well as to factor the changes that have already occurred into human decision processes. The proposed workshop will develop knew knowledge of integrated human-landscape systems, and will build capacity to predict the future of Earths surface under human influence. Two days of activities, comprising short research presentations, discussion, and breakout sessions, are planned to meet several specific objectives: identify key research questions and integrative linkages for cross-disciplinary research, examine theoretical and methodological approaches among disciplines, assess data availability and needs, and explore models and tools toward predicting complex human-landscape systems. The outcomes will include a white paper to be submitted to NSF, and summaries of the workshop to be potentially published in disciplinary and interdisciplinary newsletters, as well as in outlets for the public. The workshop is also expected to produce a multi-authored manuscript, in addition to specific integrated research projects that will be ready for launch by collaborative teams. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It has become increasingly clear over the past several years that humans and the surface of the Earth are intertwined in a complex manner. Decisions that people make about building cities, damming rivers, and exploiting natural resources cause fundamental changes in the surrounding environment. In like manner, natural disasters, rising sea levels, and climate change have acute and chronic influences on the human economic and social fabric. This project will bring together researchers from the physical and social sciences to collaborate on methods for addressing these important issues, and prepare plans that will pave the way for future progess.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0952354</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harden</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>charden@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wohl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ellen.wohl@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>English</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>menglish@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria Carmen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lemos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lemos@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anne.chin@ucdenver.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7458</Code>
      <Text>GEOMORPHOLOGY &amp; LAND USE DYNAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9278</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
