<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Molecular Regulation of Cortical Synapse Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>744900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Evan Balaban</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proper brain development involves elaboration of a network containing billions of neurons. This complex process requires the precise initiation, and subsequent maturation, of trillions of synaptic connections between these cells. This research project aims to improve our understanding of the cellular and molecular mechanisms that regulate the developmental maturation of cortical synapse structure and function. These studies focus on the role of a unique neurotransmitter receptor, the n-methyl-d-aspartate (NMDA) receptor. NMDA receptors, which sense glutamate released from other neurons are known to regulate changes in synaptic strength that underlie learning and memory in the adult brain. However, the role of these receptors during synapse development is less well understood. Interestingly, the protein subunit composition of these receptors is tightly controlled during development. NMDA receptors are heteromultimeric structures formed by association of two NR1 and two NR2 subunits. Heightened synaptogenesis, during late embryogenesis and early postnatal life, corresponds with the exclusive expression and incorporation of NR2B subunits to this receptor complex. These studies apply current techniques in genetics, molecular biology and electrophysiology to probe the role of these unique NR2B-containing receptors during a postnatal cortical circuit patterning. Mentorship support is provided for both undergraduate and graduate students. In addition this project aims to promote career opportunities in neuroscience and/or biomedical research to students at minority-serving schools in Louisiana through the initiation of an annual training course in Neurobiology research. This course will be held each spring at the Louisiana Universities Marine Consortium (LUMCON) DeFelice Marine Station in Cocodrie Louisiana.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0952455</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hall</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>benhall@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tulane University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
