<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Magnetization Dynamics and Damping in Magnetic Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>527250</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>****NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;This Faculty Early CAREER award funds research to investigate magnetization dynamics as well as the damping of the magnetization in magnetic nanostructures. A better understanding of the magnetization dynamics and its damping in magnetic nanostructures is of fundamental importance for the research area of spintronics, which targets the use of a quantum mechanical property of the electron known as "spin" to develop electronic devices with new functionality. In this context the damping of the magnetization will be a key factor, for example, to minimize the overall power consumption of spintronic devices. This project will investigate established material systems as well as new materials, but will also investigate the feasibility of high frequency biosensing using magnetic nanoparticles, which would have a number of possible applications. This project will seamlessly integrate education activities at all levels of education through research experiences for local high-school and undergraduate students and training of graduate students. In addition online educational material pertaining to this CAREER project will be designed and developed and will be made accessible for the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the magnetization dynamics and damping in magnetic nanostructures is of fundamental importance for many aspects of spintronics, a research area that targets the use of the electron spin to implement new electronic devices. This Faculty Early CAREER award funds research to investigate the magnetization dynamics and damping in magnetic nanostructures. Broadband ferromagnetic resonance techniques will be used to investigate the magnetization dynamics and damping in: (a) ferromagnet/antiferromagnet structures including systems modified using ion irradiation, expected to provide new insights in the role of two-magnon scattering in these structures; (b) new spintronic materials including B2 ordered alloys, aimed at providing guidance for the future development of low damping materials; (c) magnetic nanoparticles, aimed at investigating the feasibility of high frequency biosensing. This project will seamlessly integrate education activities at all levels of education through research experiences for local high-school and undergraduate students and training of graduate students. In addition online educational material pertaining to this CAREER project will be designed and developed and will be made accessible for the general public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0952929</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mewes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tmewes@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1710</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9232</Code>
      <Text>RES OPPOR AWARDS(ROA) (SUPPLEM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
