<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Simultaneous Inversions of GPS Time Series for Kinematics and Transients in Cascadia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>136050</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory J. Anderson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In recent years continuously operating GPS sites have been established in many parts of the world, including Earthscope's Plate Boundary Observatory network in the western US. Prior to that, most GPS observations were made in survey-mode, where campaigns were used to occupy the marks on a yearly or multi-year basis. This project is to explore how to extract long-term plate kinematics and time-dependent deformation information from both continuous and survey-mode GPS data. The science target is to learn about the spatial and temporal relationship between slow slip and non-volcanic tremor throughout Cascadia. The continuous networks of PBO and PANGA are being used to test whether or not slow slip beneath Cascadia coincides spatially and temporally with non-volcanic tremor. Southern Cascadia has a very different pattern of slow-slip than northern Cascadia where slow-slip events are very regular and similar in size. Non-volcanic tremor suggests that there may be some, but different, patterns in southern Cascadia but tremor does not constrain the sizes of the slow slip events. Utilizing the time series directly in the analyses and applying new GPS processing techniques will enhance the signal-to-noise ratio of the vertical component which is critical in estimating the up-dip extent of slow slip on the Cascadia interface. One goal is to test whether or not non-volcanic tremor (NVT) coincides with slow slip. Since NVT is easier to observe than slow slip for small events, their coincidence will help delineate the portions of faults that slip slowly. The work will place important bounds on the up-dip limit of slow slip at Cascadia and hence whether or not slow slip extends into the locked portions of the megathrust. The research will further our understanding of slow-slip events and how they should be presented to the public. The simple question of whether they increase or decrease the earthquake hazard is not yet answered but is of obvious importance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0952047</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCaffrey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mccafr@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>017F</Code>
      <Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
