<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Bio-inspired MEMS imaging platform with ultrawide, dynamically tunable field-of-view for biomedical and assistive applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mona Zaghloul</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this CAREER project is to advance optical MEMS technology by developing an ultrawide field-of-view imaging system utilizing biological inspirations. Coherently integrated plans for promoting interests in science and technology at early stages of education, especially in female students, through education and outreach are also included.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project aims to develop a novel optical MEMS platform interfacing a highly curved array of light-collecting optics with a flat array of optical detectors to accomplish ultrawide field-of-view imaging. A bundle of flexible polymer waveguides, inspired by the unique eye structure of deep-sea amphipods, connect the two arrays optically. In contrast to previously reported wide field-of-view solutions, the proposed scheme allows separate fabrications of the two arrays and enables dynamic tuning of the viewing angle. Biology-scale miniaturization of the proposed structure, based on a new class of polymeric fabrication techniques, is also an objective. The developed technologies will find applications in biomedicine, assistive devices, and environmental imaging/sensing. The combined utilization of optics and MEMS in biomimetic framework will promote transformative developments in future science and technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The successful demonstration of imaging systems with dynamically tunable, ultrawide field-of-view will generate significant impact on optical MEMS and accelerate the pace of the nascent field of biomimetics greatly. With endoscopic imaging and assistive safety monitoring as their immediate applications, they will benefit human welfare significantly. The knowledge and techniques obtained in the course of the proposed research will create interdisciplinary influences and widen the boundaries of science and technology through the proposed curricula and extra-curricula activities. The easy and interesting theme of the project will appeal to children and female students, encouraging their interests in science and technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0954845</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jaeyoun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>plasmon@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
