<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Development and Characterization of Bio-Binder from Swine Manure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29971</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Y. Grace Hsuan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this EAGER proposal is to produce and characterize bio-binder from swine manure to be used as partial replacement for asphalt binder on highways and airport pavements. Bio-binder is produced from thermochemical conversion of swine manure to both eliminate the need for huge manure storage lagoons and improve asphalt binder characteristics. This proposal is focused on the preparation, modification and characterization of bio-binder from manure mainly for asphalt pavements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will strengthen the areas of bio-fuel, energy and sustainable infrastructure design. These areas are attractive to both students and researchers who are seeking an understanding of the relationships between biology, agriculture, chemistry, and engineering to produce environmentally friendly replacements for construction materials to protect and improve the health of individuals and our environment. Production of bio-binder from manure can address this need in addition to finding a solution for manure and waste management. This becomes even more significant taking into account the relatively low cost of bio-binder production. While asphalt binder costs $2/gallon, biobinder can be produced at $0.54/gallon. The broader impact of the proposed partnership will be demonstrated through the exposure of minority students at NC A&amp;T which is one of the top Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) to the recent advances in materials characterization, and to reach broader audiences ranging from university educators to industry technicians.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>29971</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0955001</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elham</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>efini@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University</Name>
      <CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1601 E. Market Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1635</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>025E</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1037</Code>
      <Text>DETERIORATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
