<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Towards Complete MAV Control Using Arrays of Synthetic Jets: Preliminary Study</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>71503</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitrios Papavassiliou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project investigates the development of flow/flight control system for a fixed-wing micro air vehicle (MAV) operating in a gusty urban environment, by using a carefully distributed array of zero-net-mass-flux (ZNMF) synthetic-jet actuators. A detailed analysis of a target scenario is provided as the primary motivation for the proposed efforts. Critical issues in the MAV flow, flight stability and propulsion MAV are identified. A high-fidelity numerical approach is proposed for addressing a number of fundamental issues related to (i) accurate modeling of synthetic jet micro-flows including scaling effects, (ii) elucidating effectiveness of synthetic jets for control of highly separated unsteady MAV flows at low Reynolds numbers, and (iii) examining the possibility of using reduced-order models of synthetic jets for future multi-disciplinary design optimization studies. Additionally, the project efforts include supervision of student teams in developing a Matlab Simulink environment for design of controlled MAV flight envelope using low-order representation of arrays of synthetic jets with tailored phase alignment and frequencies to produce adequate forces and moments. This work will lay foundation for follow-up collaborative efforts on MAV flow, flight stability and thrust control modeling, multi-disciplinary design optimization, micro-manufacturing, and eventual testing of the vehicle prototype. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advancing the state-of-the-art of the micro air vehicle flight control technology, addressing fundamental flow control issues at the level of interacting jet micro flows and highly unsteady, separated grazing macro flows, and ensuring strong participation of undergraduate and graduate students in challenging design tasks constitute the primary intellectual merits of the proposed plan. As an educational merit, the planned activities will significantly enhance the offered design curriculum by introducing new advanced topics with focus on analysis, design, and optimization of micro air vehicle systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In its broader impact, the integrated plan will contribute to creating a research team environment in the predominantly teaching university, will involve a significant number of undergraduate (including female and minority) students in advanced research projects, and will pave the way to the proposed multi-university collaboration effort involving simulations and design of a MAV prototype equipped with arrays of synthetic jets for complete control of the vehicle.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0955970</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Reda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mankbadi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reda.mankbadi@erau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Golubev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>golubd1b@erau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hany</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nakhla</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hany.nakhla@erau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University</Name>
      <CityName>Daytona Beach</CityName>
      <ZipCode>321143966</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3862267695</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Research Adm</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>057E</Code>
      <Text>Thermodynamics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>060E</Code>
      <Text>BIO-TRANSPORT &amp; FLUID MECH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
