<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CI Days:Laying the Foundation for Cyberinfrastructure Campus Bridging</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CI Days Program&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As science research has changed from the individual in the lab to research groups distributed across multiple institutions, Cyberinfrastructure (CI) has become an important component to enable these groups to work together. The CI Days program will help campuses create an event to bring the campus together to understand the campus CI needs, resources that are available, and to start planning for the further development of CI on campus. The campus event will include all players in the CI picture including faculty, IT personnel, librarians, and administrators. Campus participants will have the opportunity to create connections with others on campus as well as with those from other institutions and organizations. Through understanding of the complete CI system and the responsibilities of all involved, the campus can build cohesive CI resources that tie into the global CI environment. Post-event activities will foster planning and implementation of the total campus CI environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of CI Days will come from the documentation of activities and methodologies for campus CI coordination and planning that can be used by other campuses as they address CI issues. Intellectual Merits of CI Days include analysis and reporting on barriers and unmet needs in CI as discovered during the event which will help the R&amp;E community understand issues and areas of work needed to improve the overall CI environment and better serve researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956272</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Russ</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hobby</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdhobby@internet2.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>INTERNET2</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200363825</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7349134264</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1150 18th St NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7684</Code>
      <Text>STRATEGIC TECHNOLOGIES FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9217</Code>
      <Text>NATNL RESERCH &amp; EDUCAT NETWORK</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7684</Code>
      <Text>STRATEGIC TECHNOLOGIES FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
