<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>HESTEC:GreenNovation-Footprints to the Future</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>59412</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sherrie B. Green</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Hispanic Engineering, Science and Technology (HESTEC) program at The University of Texas-Pan American, serves as a catalyst to promote awareness and increase the full participation of Hispanics in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) fields by encouraging and motivating students to pursue higher education and STEM careers. HESTEC will convene a weeklong series of events on September 27- October 2, 2009 to engage high school and undergraduate students, and the community at large in STEM educational activities, and provide a forum where higher education, federal, and corporate sector stakeholders can discuss and address key issues on preparing Hispanics for the science and engineering workforce. The program supports the Foundation?s strategic outcome goals of learning and stewardship, and expands efforts to increase participation from all under-represented groups. The HESTEC activity will foster communication among stakeholders to help prepare a diverse cadre of future scientists and engineers ready to meet the challenges of advancing the frontiers of knowledge, and equipped to solve the imminent concerns confronting the nation domestically and globally.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956101</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lawrence-Fowler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wfowler@utpa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley</Name>
      <CityName>Edinburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>785392909</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9566652889</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1201 West University Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>119P</Code>
      <Text>H.S.I. LISTENING SESSIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
