<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Catalytic Hydrolysis of Phosphonothioate Toxins by Molybdocene Complexes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carol Bessel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Catalysis Program supports the efforts of Professor Louis Y. Kuo of Lewis and Clark College in the study of phosphonothioate hydrolysis using molybdocene complexes in the presence of either gold or silver nanoparticles or polymer resins. This project focuses on improving the turnover of phosphonothioate hydrolysis while developing an understanding of the stereochemical, electronic and steric factors associated with selective P-S scission and the rate acceleration provided by the molybdocene catalysts. The structures of the various molybdocenes are compared with their catalytic activities to determine the important relationships that impact reactivity and selectivity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The detoxification of phosphonothioates, compounds found in insecticides and chemical weapons, is of practical importance. The molybdocene compounds used in this study are among the first to destroy these potential environmental poisons, in water and under very mild conditions and temperatures. The experiments included in this program are well-integrated into the undergraduate curriculum. Several of the molybdenum complexes and nanoparticles are synthesized either in the general chemistry laboratory or by the upper level inorganic chemistry students. Professor Kuo participates in the award-winning "Saturday Academy", a program that enables high school students to conduct summer internships in his research group.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956740</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kuo@lclark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lewis and Clark College</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972197879</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037687680</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>0615 S W Palatine Hill Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
