<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Organocatalytic Polymerization: New Synthetic Methods for Polymer Chemistry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>510000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Catalysis Program supports Professor Robert M. Waymouth at Stanford University and Dr. James L Hedrick at IBM for a research project that will explore new patterns of reactivity of organic catalysts for controlled polymerization reactions. Specific objectives are to: (1) develop novel bifunctional strategies for organocatalytic polymerization reactions; (2) develop a detailed kinetic and mechanistic understanding of zwitterionic polymerizations for the synthesis of macrocyclic polymers; and (3) develop new organocatalytic methods for the synthesis of biodegradable and biocompatible polyphosphates. The zwitterionic polymerization mediated by N-heterocyclic carbenes is a new conceptual advance for the enchainment of monomers to high molecular weight cyclic polymers. Mechanistic and kinetic insights on the details of these reactions will provide a conceptual and quantitative picture of the scope, power and limitations of this new synthetic method. Organocatalytic polymerization strategies provide an environmentally friendly approach for the synthesis and recycling of major commodity polymers. Mechanistic insights on new mechanisms of enchainment will create new opportunities for the generation of novel polymer architectures, including new families of polyphosphates for biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Chemical Catalysis Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation, Drs. Waymouth and Hedrick will perform research that will provide new catalytic strategies for the design of biodegradable polymers derived from renewable resources. New synthetic methods developed as part of this program will enable new strategies for the synthesis of well-defined polymer architectures. These developments will enable studies of the role of polymer structure on properties and function, issues that are fundamental to our understanding of chemistry and to the application of macromolecules in modern technologies. Broader impacts include involving students in an exceptional training environment involving a highly interdisciplinary and collaborative effort between an academic institution and an industrial laboratory. The PIs have taken an active role in recruiting and mentoring underrepresented minorities and disabled students. In addition, IBM is committing significant resources to this effort, including laboratory and office space for a postdoctoral coworker and visiting Stanford students, materials and supplies, extensive access to IBM facilities and infrastructure as well as 25% of Dr. Hedrick's time.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0957386</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Waymouth</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>waymouth@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/22/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9163</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
