<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Designed Photoactive Metal Nitrosyls for Site-specific NO Delivery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>434325</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program of the Division of Chemistry supports the research efforts of Professor Pradip K. Mascharak of the University of California Santa Cruz in studying metal nitrosyl complexes as exogenous NO donors that are activated with light. Such photoactive nitrosyl complexes are employed to deliver NO to chemical, biological and cellular targets on demand. Density functional theory (DFT) and TD-DFT calculations are used in the smart design of metal (Fe, Mn, and Ru) nitrosyls. These computational techniques are used to fine tune the ligand design so that the complexes are sensitive to near infrared light (which is better for photodynamic therapy). The nitrosyl-dye conjugates are used as "trackable NO donors" in tracing NO delivery in cellular targets (malignant sites) and monitoring NO-induced apoptosis (programmed cell death). In order to make the various nitrosyls suitable for site-specific delivery of NO, the group incorporates the metal complexes into different polymer matrices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nitric oxide (NO) is recognized as a key mediator in a variety of physiological and pathological pathways such as blood pressure regulation, immune response, neurotransmission, and cellular apoptosis. Typical systemic NO drugs (such as glyceryl trinitrate) cannot be used for site-specific NO delivery because of the inexorability of NO release from NO donors. The drug goes everywhere in the body and NO is released via various enzymatic and non-enzymatic (such as pH and temperature) pathways. Light, on the other hand, can control NO release from proper NO donors in a cellular environment. This research project provides insight into the design and synthesis of metal complexes that release NO in response to specific stimuli (light). This goal-oriented project provides an excellent opportunity for graduate and undergraduate students to participate in research at the interface of chemistry and biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0957251</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pradip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mascharak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pradip@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
