<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Inducing molecular single file diffusion by co-adsorption in one-dimensional channels for gas separations and catalysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>371546</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project supported by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program of the Division of Chemistry, Professors Clifford R. Bowers and Sergey Vasenkov of the University of Florida will employ advanced nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) techniques to characterize the transport of gases in nanoporous materials. Pulsed field gradient NMR (PFG-NMR) and xenon-129 hyperpolarization techniques will be applied to materials with one-dimensional nanochannels composed of dipeptides, gallium molecular wheels, and aluminum-germanium and aluminum-silicon. The primary goals of the project are (1) to realize the conditions under which a transition between normal and single-file diffusion can be induced by one-component in a multi-component gas mixture inside one-dimensional nanochannels, and (2) to understand the relationship between diffusion and exchange of gases between the bulk and channel-adsorbed phases in such systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of the proposed research may have impacts on the development of new strategies for highly selective separations of mixtures of gases and catalysis. These are two of the most vital industrial processes of our day, with applications to renewable/clean energy. The educational plan integrated into this research project will emphasize the mentoring of undergraduate women and underrepresented minority students, and involvement of high school students in coordination with the University of Florida?s Center for Precollegiate Education and Training.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0957641</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Clifford</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bowers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bowers@chem.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sergey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vasenkov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>svasenkov@che.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
