<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Metal Phosphonate Interfaces for Phosphopeptide Enrichment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>392500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project supported by the Chemical Measurement and Imaging program (with co-funding from the Office of International Science and Engineering), Professor Daniel Talham and coworkers at the University of Florida are exploring metal phosphate and metal phosphonate solids and thin films as a new class of phosphopeptide separation and enrichment media. The expected improvements in performance are based on a new mechanism for phosphopeptide affinity involving the ability of some metal phosphate solids to selectively form covalent linkages to divalent phosphate groups while excluding other common anions. The project will explore new particle systems for affinity enrichment and new surface modification approaches to extend metal phosphonate-based enrichment strategies to on-target techniques. The new mechanisms and materials will be evaluated using surface analytical methods to quantify the activity of the new materials toward different phosphopeptide structures. Finally, newly developed systems will be tested to prove their applicability to phosphoprotein mass spectrometry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These experiments seek to devise new means of isolating a wide range of biomaterials that are important in high-technology applications ranging from sensing and diagnostics to enabling fundamental studies of proteins - a fundamental building block of life. In addition, training related to biomaterials, interfaces, chemical measurement, and protein chemistry will provide graduate and undergraduate students with the skills and knowledge needed to be competitive in biotechnology related high-technology professions. The project also fosters collaboration with international partners at the Université de Nantes in France. This cooperation includes an extensive international educational component through the exchange of graduate student researchers. These exchanges are designed to facilitate thesis work and to also provide students with important alternative perspectives on research and approaches to scientific exploration.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0957155</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Talham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>talham@chem.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
