<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RCN-UBE: Promoting Concept Driven Teaching Strategies in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology through Concept Assessments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>369650</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher Meyer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A network will be created to develop, test, and distribute assessment tools specific to the fields of biochemistry and molecular biology. These tools will be used to evaluate prior knowledge of students entering biochemistry and molecular biology classes from various backgrounds. A central web-based resource for biochemistry and molecular biology educators will be created featuring these assessment tools to help facilitate educational approaches focused on foundational concepts, discipline specific knowledge, and essential research skills, all of which are necessary to prepare students to take on the challenges of the 21st century. Support will be provided for pedagogical approaches based on validated assessments of outcomes. The network has four specific aims: 1) Identification of foundational concepts in terms of core knowledge and foundational principles, research and skills, 2) Creation of a taxonomy of foundational concepts and skills, linked to topics outlined in the undergraduate curriculum recommendations of ASBMB, 3) Development and evaluation of appropriate assessment tools, and 4) Creation of a toolkit that can be easily accessed by the academic community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the project will include bringing faculty from community colleges, primarily undergraduate institutions, research institutions that serve diverse populations of students and institutions serving under-represented minorities together to form teams that will address specific assessment issues. The first large working group, which will include a wide range of experts in content, concept development, pedagogy, and assessment, will meet to define the framework and needs of the concept assessment network. A smaller working group will meet each year to continue development assessment resources. Undergraduate Affiliated Network (UAN) groups from six regions in the country will meet to both contribute to the development of assessment resources and provide feedback to inform the smaller working group. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported jointly by the Biological Sciences Directorate and the Division of Undergraduate Education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0957205</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjohnson@biology.as.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harold</FirstName>
      <LastName>White</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>halwhite@UDel.Edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Duane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sears</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sears@lifesci.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cheryl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bailey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baileyc@mtmary.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbell2@richmond.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</Name>
      <CityName>Rockville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>208523310</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2402836600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11200 Rockville Pike</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7972</Code>
      <Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7492</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1664</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
