<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Structure, Bonding, Reactivity and Catalysis with Transition Metal-Main Group Compounds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>549000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award in the Chemical Synthesis (SYN) program supports work by Professor T. Don Tilley at the University of California, Berkeley, to carry out fundamental studies on the search for new chemical transformations that are mediated by transition metal-main group element multiple bonds. In general, reactivity centered on multiple metal-ligand bonds is very important, and the chemistry of metal-silicon double bonds in silylene complexes is expected to lead to new, useful transformations. Chemical conversions mediated by silylene complexes have recently been found to promote the addition of hydrogen-silicon bonds to alkenes, and a range of related transformations seem likely. The fundamental principles established from these studies should be applicable to a range of problems in chemistry, materials science and catalysis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The basic research of this proposal should point the way to replacement of rare and expensive metals such as platinum and rhodium with less abundant metals such as iron and cobalt, in industrial catalytic processes. In general, new, more efficient chemical transformations will enable the more efficient use of energy and resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0957106</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>T. Don</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tilley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tdtilley@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/04/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
