<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Acquisition of Shared Digital Video Data Analysis Infrastructure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>473434</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cherniavsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation award funds the acquisition of high quality video production and post-production equipment to support research at Syracuse University. Several research projects at Syracuse University currently collect and analyze large quantities of digital video (DV) data to investigate diverse questions that consider both the obvious and the subtle interactions people have with each other and with technology. Digital video data analysis, which requires high quality video production and post-production equipment and specialized analytical software, allows for repeated and detailed examination of acquired footage and increased analytic accuracy. Findings from DV data analysis can play an important role in fostering the integration of research and education in research-intensive learning environments and can play an important role in reconfiguring research practices that challenge the distinction between practitioners and researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Syracuse University currently lacks comprehensive infrastructure for supporting research endeavors that generate and analyze DV data. Because of the lack of robust DV infrastructure, researchers at the University have not been able to engage in research on questions that are best addressed by methodologies that generate DV data. The requested equipment and software will have a direct and immediate impact on faculty in three disciplines involved in research in Science Education, Teacher Education, Instructional Technology, and Linguistics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the research supported by this equipment is in the areas of science teaching and situated cognition that refine and enhance science pedagogy, which will be integrated into K-12 and higher educational practices and will include pre-service and in-service teachers. Undergraduate and graduate researchers will work on all of the projects enabled by this grant.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>473434</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0959822</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dotger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sdotger@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Foley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>afoley@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dotger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bdotger@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gordon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cygordon@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abrown08@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
