<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III:EAGER:Collaborative Research:A Collaborative Scientific Workflow Composition Tool Supporting Scientific Collaboration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>43335</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vijayalakshmi Atluri</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this research aims to produce a general-purpose but domain-customizable collaborative scientific workflow tool for accelerating scientific discovery, particularly facilitating large-scale and cross-disciplinary research projects that are collaborative in nature and require intensive user interaction from multiple distributed domain scientists. As a natural extension to the existing single user-oriented scientific workflow management tools by providing direct system support for scientific collaboration, this project seeks to pave a way toward a next-generation tool supporting scientific collaboration over the Internet. The expected tool can be easily expanded to support data-centric collaborative information management in any intelligence community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; To achieve this broader impact, this research seeks to establish a set of foundational models and techniques supporting collaborative scientific workflow composition and management; and based on them, construct an Internet-based collaborative scientific workflow tool framed with an open-source initiative. The initial focus of the Early Concept Grants Exploratory Research(EAGER) project is on rapidly creating a prototype tool as a proof of concept, equipped with basic dataflow-oriented scientific workflow models and collaboration patterns integrated in an agile service-oriented architecture. To avoid reinventing the wheel, the efforts will be concentrated on transforming and extending Taverna, a known open-source scientific workflow management tool, into a collaborative version. Evaluations and validations will be conducted through partnerships with multiple collaborative scientific communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For further information, see the project website at http://www.CollaborativeScientificWorkflows.org/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0959215</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jia.zhang@sv.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northern Illinois University</Name>
      <CityName>De Kalb</CityName>
      <ZipCode>601152860</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8157531581</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>301 Lowden Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
