<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Acquisition of Instrumentation for a Biomedical Materials Research Laboratory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>293450</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0959951&lt;br/&gt;Gettens&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will allow the Western New England College (WNEC) School of Engineering to acquire the equipment necessary to achieve a state-of-the art biomedical materials and mechanics research and training laboratory. The requested equipment will supplement existing equipment and serve a common goal of supporting current and pending biomedical materials and mechanics research and educational activities. The two major pieces of equipment requested are an electrodynamic test instrument (mechanical fatigue instrument) and a materials and mechanics. The equipment will also place the WNEC engineering faculty in a better position to pursue additional research opportunities and partnerships with local industry. The primary areas of research that will be directly supported by the equipment will be: (i) dynamic testing of tooth enamel/dentin for stress/fatigue corrosion susceptibility, (ii) screening of nano-scale topographies for applications in tissue engineering and implantable devices, (iii) pre-clinical&lt;br/&gt;evaluation of novel prosthetic socket designs, and (iv) continued collaboration with the Santore lab at the University of Massachusetts for the development of nano-scale engineered surfaces.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>293450</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0959951</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Judy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cezeaux</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>judy.cezeaux@wne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gettens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rg289622@wnec.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rust</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mrust@wne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Western New England University</Name>
      <CityName>Springfield</CityName>
      <ZipCode>011192684</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4137821373</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1215 Wilbraham Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
