<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Acquisition of a Highly Charged Ion Beamline for Interdisciplinary Materials Research and Education at Clemson University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1648901</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0960100&lt;br/&gt;Sosolik&lt;br/&gt;Clemson U.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We propose the acquisition of a highly charged ion (HCI) beamline dedicated to the exploration of HCI-materials interactions. The intrinsic high energy density present in an HCI-solid impact, where a reproducible quantum mechanical state of a highly ionized atom transfers energy into a solid at atomic length scales, gives irradiance values (~1014 W/cm2) that rival those achievable with petawatt lasers (~7x1011 W/cm2) and that can be obtained and maintained more easily than a laser. Understanding the physical mechanisms that control how an HCI can deliver this energy to a target is the primary and open question of materials research that will be addressed. With this instrumentation we will be able to create HCIs of a selected charge state and impact them onto well-defined targets where secondary electron, X-ray, and mass loss sensing will be used for real-time analysis and precisely timed clocking (via X-ray deexcitation) of impact events. In doing so, we will probe the complex interplay between fundamental atomic physics (X-ray emissions, Rydberg atom formation, etc.) and energy dissipation that is the defining characteristic of HCI-materials interactions. Results obtained with this beamline will be directly applied to the use of HCIs in electronic device processing as well as the evaluation of candidate materials for fusion reactor walls, the role of HCIs in astrophysically relevant ion-target impact conditions, and the accelerated spaceflight-readiness testing of electronics devices and materials. This instrumentation will be housed on the central campus of Clemson University, will be operated by a trained staff technician, and will be maintained through the committed and combined support of the College of Engineering and Science and the university. The core investigators and management team will utilize this acquisition to enhance our outreach programs to women and minorities through established programs on campus and through our existing connection with South Carolina State University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Summary: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We propose the acquisition of a highly charged ion (HCI) beamline for interdisciplinary materials research and education at Clemson University. Highly charged ions, which are atoms stripped of a large fraction of their electrons, are unique as they possess a high energy density that can lead to novel HCI-solid interactions not typically encountered in a materials laboratory environment. Our goals with this acquisition are to explore the physical mechanisms that control how a HCI can deliver energy to a target and apply that knowledge to the development of HCIs as a processing tool for electronic materials fabrication. In addition, the inherent presence of HCIs in fusion reactors, a candidate technology for clean energy production, as well as in the space environment makes this acquisition a prime tool for reproducing these conditions in a laboratory setting. Operating as a research laboratory and user facility for the study of HCI interactions with materials, this beamline will open new doors to a multitude of researchers and encourage their explorations into this unique form of matter. The incorporation of cryogen-free technologies for the production of HCIs into this proposed acquisition ensures that it will function as a low cost, single-operator beamline that has a low threshold for user and collaborator participation. This instrumentation will be housed on the central campus of Clemson University, will be operated by a trained staff technician, and will be maintained through the committed and combined support of the College of Engineering and Science and the university. The core investigators and management team will utilize this acquisition to enhance our outreach programs to women and minorities through established programs on campus and through our existing connection with South Carolina State University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>1648901</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0960100</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>McNulty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mpeter@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harrell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rod.harrell@ces.clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Luo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jluo@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brittain</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbritt@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sosolik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sosolik@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clemson University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
