<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Acquisition of a high performance central computing facility at UCSB</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>665000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)." &lt;br/&gt;Proposal #: 09-60316&lt;br/&gt;PI(s): Brown, Frank, L.; Fredrickson, Glenn, H.; Garcia-Cervera, Carlos; Gilbert, John, R.; Van de Walle, Christian, G.&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of California-Santa Barbara &lt;br/&gt;Title: MRI-R2: Acquisition of a High Performance Central Computing Facility at UCSB&lt;br/&gt;Project Proposed:&lt;br/&gt;This project, acquiring of a computational cluster to replace a six-year-old system, allows access to fast mid-sized parallel computation to dozens of researchers and serves as the institution's primary resource for parallel computation. The system is structured for a variety of uses. Standard MPI computation is carried out with a tightly coupled cluster of quad core processors, while 'fat nodes' with 256 GB of RAM as well as local high speed disk storage service jobs that require large shared memory. Researchers actively developing codes can take advantage of the unique performance characteristics of GPU (graphics processing) nodes. The system will have several NVidia Tesla nodes.&lt;br/&gt;The users of the system are drawn from all five departments of the College of Engineering (Chemical Engineering, Computer Science, Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, Materials, and Mechanical Engineering), seven departments of the Division of Mathematical, Life and Physical Sciences (Chemistry &amp; Biochemistry, Earth Science, Ecology Evolution &amp; Marine Biology, Mathematics, Molecular Cellular &amp; Developmental Biology, Physics, and Psychology), as well as the departments of Economics, Geography, and Media Arts &amp; Technology from the Division of Humanities and Social Sciences. In addition, the system supports research in eight campus centers: Allosphere Research Facility, the California NanoSystems Institute, the Center for Polymers and Organic Solids, the Institute for Crustal Studies, the Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics, the Materials Research Laboratory, the National Center for Ecological Analysis &amp; Synthesis, and the Neuroscience Research Institute.&lt;br/&gt;The new system will be housed in the same location as the previous one where the same successful administrative and maintenance procedures used for the past six years will be applied. The proposed cluster will be accessible via the UC Grid, a web portal interface that makes high performance computing resources easy to use from desktop machines (PCs or Macs). The acquired system will come with a three-year warranty. Prior experience has shown that only a small number of nodes are expected to malfunction during the useful lifetime (&gt; 3 years) of the cluster. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The research enabled by the campus-wide facility, interdisciplinary and collaborative in nature, is available to the broad research community. The large majority of users, roughly 75%, consists of postdocs, graduate students, and undergraduates (5%), allowing this award to accomplish NSF's longstanding goal of integrating research and education. Outreach to K-12 takes place via a new initiative, The School for Scientific Thought (SST), an extension to the Let's Explore Physical Sciences (LEAPS) Program. Under the SST Program UCSB science and engineering graduate students design and teach a course for an audience of high school students on Saturdays. In addition, many of the faculty associated with this proposal participate in the UC Leadership Excellence through the Advanced Degrees program that has increased the number of underrepresented students in science and engineering at UCSB.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>665000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0960316</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gilbert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gilbert@cs.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van de Walle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vandewalle@mrl.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>flbrown@chem.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Glenn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fredrickson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ghf@mrl.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garcia-Cervera</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cgarcia@math.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
