<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Development of Common Platform for Unifying Humanoids Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5999997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)." &lt;br/&gt;Proposal #: 09-60061&lt;br/&gt;PI(s): Kim, Youngmoo E., Gogotsi, Yury, Hong, Dennis H., Regli, William C., Schaal, Stefan&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Drexel University&lt;br/&gt;Title: Development of Common Platform for Unifying Humanoids Research&lt;br/&gt;Project Proposed: &lt;br/&gt;This project, developing and disseminating HUBO+, a new common humanoid research platform instrument, enables novel and previously infeasible capabilities for future research efforts while working with a common instrument. HUBO will be the first homogeneous, full-sized humanoid to be used as a common research and education platform. Eight universities (Drexel, CMU, MIT, Ohio State, Penn, Purdue, Southern California, and VaTech), representing a critical mass of humanoids research within US, participate in this development of the world's first homogeneous full-sized humanoid team. Building upon unique expertise, the work extends current capabilities, resulting in six identical units, facilitating the following potentially transformative advances in robotics:&lt;br/&gt;- A state-of-the-art, standardized humanoid platform instrument with embedded capabilities for sensing, manipulation, and rapid locomotion, ideal for a broad range of future humanoids research&lt;br/&gt;- The ability, for the first time, to directly compare and across validate algorithms and methodologies and consistently benchmark results across research teams&lt;br/&gt;- Novel energy storage technology for mobile robotics incorporating supercapacitors for operations requiring high power density, far exceeding the capabilities of traditional battery-only power sources&lt;br/&gt;- A widely distributed platform that motivates, recruits, and trains a broad range of students spanning multiple disciplines, including artificial intelligence, digital, signal processing, mechanics, and control&lt;br/&gt;Humanoids, robots engineered to mimic human form and motion, open broad avenues of cross disciplinary research spanning multiple fields, such as mechanical control, artificial intelligence, and power systems. Common humanoids are rarely autonomous and are not-ready for unconstrained interaction with humans. The most compelling demonstrations are meticulously pre-programmed and painstakingly choreographed. A few common platforms have already advanced some research. Hence, having a consistent platform should facilitate rapid progress in areas needed for autonomy and natural interaction, including mobility, manipulation, robot vision, speech communication, and cognition and learning. However, although currently Japan and Korea are considered world leaders in design and construction of humanoids, best practices have not been developed for constructing multiple, identical humanoids. These conditions call for the making of an urgently needed benchmark providing evaluations and cross-validation of results. With this development and the servicing of 6 humanoids, this project aims to create knowledge and best practices contributing to robotics research, possibly leading to the standardization needed for ubiquity.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The instrument enables US researchers to develop expertise in the design and construction of humanoids, while the distribution of the work activities ensures the broad dissemination of the knowledge. Humanoids research, inherently interdisciplinary and integrative, inspires young students. The graduate and undergraduates students participating are likely to receive a world-class training in robotics. Outreach partners, including several high-profile museums will introduce people of all ages to the exciting technologies of robotics, particularly useful in recruiting K-12 students into science, engineering, mathematics, etc. A partnership with the Science Leadership Academy (SLA), a magnet school with more than 63% underrepresented students, assures their involvement. With SLA, the project initiates an annual program modeled on a NASA-style experiment design competition, in which students use simulation tools to propose humanoids projects and activities. Selected winner(s) will have their proposed projects implemented on HUBO.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>5999997</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0960061</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schaal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sschaal@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yury</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gogotsi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gogotsi@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Youngmoo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ykim@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Regli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>regli@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dhong@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
