<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Emergence of Latino Street Gangs in Indianapolis: Migration or Emulation?</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30667</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christian A. Meissner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Like many medium to large Midwestern cities, Indianapolis, Indiana, has witnessed the growing presence of Latino street gangs over the past decade. This recent development is clearly linked to a substantial Latino population influx to the region that began in the early 1990's. Seizing on the opportunity to analyze the early stages of gang emergence, this study seeks to advance theoretical understanding of gang formation. The project is guided by two competing perspectives on how and why these gangs are emerging in the Midwest. Most research on gang emergence in new locations claims it is a "homegrown" problem, a function of increasing local poverty and human adaptation to deteriorating social conditions. An alternate view, common among law enforcement officials, suggests that gang members strategically migrate from other places in the U.S. or Latin America as a way to expand their criminal operations. The researchers will conduct extensive fieldwork to investigate the issue in a large Midwestern city and determine which of these processes best explains the Latino gang growth phenomenon.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team began interviewing gang officers, school personnel, and members of Latino street gangs in the summer of 2004 and have followed developments there ever since. The evidence gathered to date slightly favors the migration explanation over the homegrown thesis. Many gang members claim direct or indirect gang ties to California, Chicago, New York, and several Latin American countries. The gangs they claim affiliation with are well-known street organizations with branches or "sets" across the nation. This research continues to interview former and current gang members about their reasons for migrating to the Midwest and whether they brought their gang affiliations with them or joined locally-formed groups. Upon completion, this research effort will yield the most thorough understanding of domestic and international migration as a cause of Latino gang formation in U.S. cities historically devoid of such groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0961755</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mike</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tapia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mtapia@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
      <CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1372</Code>
      <Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
