<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Meiosis Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Porter Ridley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Chair: Abby Dernburg Vice-Chair: Nancy Hollingsworth&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Meiosis is a specialized cell division process that is essential for sexual reproduction. During meiosis, a "diploid" cell, which contains two copies of each chromosome - one inherited from each parent - splits to form "haploid" cells such as sperm, eggs, or pollen, which contain only a single copy of each chromosome. When two of these haploid cells fuse at fertilization to form a new zygote, this results in restoration of the diploid chromosome number. During meiosis, chromosomes undergo genetic exchange, also known as crossover recombination, resulting in new combinations of genes. This recombination process underlies both genetic diversity within individual species and the evolution of new species. Defects in meiosis can give rise to infertility or to offspring with any of a wide range of devastating defects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2010 Meiosis Gordon Conference will bring together researchers studying meiosis in a broad variety of organisms. The meeting will focus on cutting-edge, unpublished research presented by invited speakers who employ a diverse array of approaches and who represent a wide range of perspectives. Included among the speakers will be early-career investigators who will have a chance to present their work to an expert audience for feedback. A notable feature of this year's gathering is the addition of a Gordon-Keenan Research Seminar, a 1½-day meeting preceding the actual conference and organized by students and postdoctoral fellows. The seminar offers an opportunity for junior researchers to meet each other and be introduced to the topics to be covered in more depth during the 4½-day conference immediately following. The goal of both the seminar and the conference is to offer a highly interactive environment for the exchange of ideas and development of collaborations that will move the field forward. Advances in this field will enhance our understanding of the fundamental mechanisms that cells use to control and coordinate complex processes - processes such as DNA repair and chromosome division - that are so essential to life.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0963674</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abby</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dernburg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>AFDERNBURG@LBL.GOV</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
