<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: Medium: Collaborative Research: Shaping, Learning and Optimizing Dynamic Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project develops, from the ground up, a new theoretical framework for analyzing and designing algorithms for dynamic ad-hoc wireless networks. This proposal embraces network dynamics as an opportunity to be exploited, not an adversity to be overcome. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The approach is based on four inter-related thrusts:&lt;br/&gt;1. Incremental Topology Learning: Tracking changes in the network much more efficiently than re-learning entire topology, using sparse "error graph" representations.&lt;br/&gt;2. Topology and Traffic Shaping: Controlling the "effective" wireless network topology so that (i) at any instant of time it appears to be highly disconnected to scheduling algorithms, but retains global connectivity over time; and (ii) modifying traffic statistics to ensure statistical spatial correlation decay.&lt;br/&gt;3. Warm-starting Distributed Algorithms: Message-passing algorithms that can warm-start the optimization based on local knowledge of past solutions.&lt;br/&gt;4. Proteus - A Mobile Robot Testbed: This project validates its approach via implementation on a mobile robot testbed called Proteus, which is used to optimize algorithms in a practical setting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: Industry is involved in this research from the start, via the WNCG Affiliates program at UT. The research will be disseminated via publications in top-tier venues, industry interactions, and specially organized workshops. Both graduate students and undergraduate students, via a REU program at UT (with emphasis on recruiting women and minorities), get exposure to both real-world wireless networks (via the testbed), and cutting edge theory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0963989</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sekhar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tatikonda</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sekhar.tatikonda@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
