<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research in Science of Science and Innovation Policy: How Do Prizes Induce Innovation? Learning from the Google Lunar X-Prize</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10440</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04000000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julia I. Lane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project investigates technology prizes and the means by which they induce innovation. Specifically, the project examines three aerospace prize competitions: (1) the Ansari X-Prize (rewarding "the first non-government organization to launch a reusable manned spacecraft into space twice within two weeks") (2) the Northrop Grumman Lunar Lander Challenge (NGLLC) (for "building and flying a rocket-powered vehicle that simulates the flight of a vehicle on the Moon"), and (3) the ongoing $30 million Google Lunar X-Prize (GLXP), which requires participants to land a robot on the surface of the Moon. This project studies three main aspects of those competitions: (1) how prize entrants respond to incentives, (2) how they organize R&amp;D activities, and (3) how technology advancement takes place in this context.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The project combines a two-stage research design, multiple data sources, and different data gathering methods, including questionnaires, interviews and direct observation. The first stage tests a model of prizes that links incentives with entrant characteristics, R&amp;D organization, and technological outcomes. This model is tested and revised by studying the Ansari X-Prize and NGLLC competitions. The second stage applies the revised model to the ongoing GLXP and prize entrants, which has exceptional significance due to its real-time data access and possibility to explore real-time perceptions of prize entrants in a competitive context characterized by technological uncertainty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The project contributes to innovation theory. In addition, it draws significant implications for policies to advance technology, promote competitiveness, or achieve other societal goals by using prizes. Moreover, insights gained from this research can be also applied across fields like business, technology management, and engineering systems design. More broadly, this project contributes a better understanding on the potential of technology policies in times of economic crisis and the incentives that may promote engagement of different social groups, including underrepresented groups and students, for training within a competitive environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0965103</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luciano</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>luciano.kay@ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shapira</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ps25@prism.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
