<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI:Conducting, Semiconducting and Ferroelectric Polymer Nanofibers for Electronic Device Fabrication: Motivating Undergraduate Students to pursue Higher Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249009</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070012</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant will expand research on conducting and semiconducting polymers and to include ferroelectric polymers and ceramic metal oxides. A simple technique called electrospinning will be used to prepare nanofibers of conducting/semiconducting/ferroelectric polymers and metal oxides and to use them as the active material in the fabrication of devices and sensors. Due to their small dimensions, nanofibers have a large surface to volume ratio and hence they have the potential to be used in the fabrication of low power consumption devices and supersensitive and rapid response sensors. Individual nanofibers that possess both semiconducting and ferroelectric properties are inherently multifunctional and will be used in non-volatile memory field effect transistors. The intellectual merit of this proposal also includes finding new ways of combining these materials that possess very different electronic, mechanical and optical properties, then using them in the form of nanofibers that have a large aspect ratio and even larger surface to volume ratio to fabricate and test devices and sensors. A range of experiments has been proposed using electrospun polymer and metal oxide nanofibers, and thin films and to study charge transport in crossed polymer nanofibers. The approach presented to making polymer nanofibers via electrospinning is unique and differs from the research of others who typically use templates or other complex methods. The proposed research includes polymer science, ceramics, physics, nanoscience and electronics and is multidisciplinary, giving students a sound and direct research experience that will help them in graduate school and in job searches.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will expose undergraduate students to various branches of science and engineering. The proposed experiments are within the intellectual grasp of undergraduate students. All of the students will be trained in the scientific method and will be motivated to pursue graduate studies in science and engineering by providing them with real opportunities to participate in scientific research. Modified experiments based on the proposed research are planned to be included into the Intermediate Laboratory course that the PI has taught for the last eight years, thereby integrating research and education. The instruments requested in this proposal will strengthen the institutional infrastructure, increase faculty collaboration and also have a broader impact of improving the research facilities in the southeastern region of the Island. New results will be published in a timely manner and an up-to-date web page will be maintained, thereby broadening the dissemination of results from this proposal. The University of Puerto Rico at Humacao is a minority serving institution. This proposal will therefore increase the number of undergraduate students that participate in scientific research and who are underrepresented in the fields of science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0965023</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pinto</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nicholas.pinto@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/11/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Puerto Rico at Humacao</Name>
      <CityName>Humacao</CityName>
      <ZipCode>007920860</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7878509374</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Call Box 860</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
      <StateCode>PR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9141</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD. INST - EQUIP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
