<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TLS and DAT: Construct Utilization in the Behavioral Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>358622</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04000000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joshua Rosenbloom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>While it is natural for research disciplines to split into more specialized areas, the resulting divide complicates efforts to share the benefits of related research. Constructs are important underpinnings of a research method used in many behavioral and social sciences, and virtually identical constructs have been developed to support different theories, frequently under different names. As a result, useful connections are missed, constructs and theories are reinvented, and little knowledge exists about the construct origins and flow among disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project addresses the problem by investigating the following research question: is it possible to identify closely related constructs, including those in different disciplines and use this information to measure the extent to which existing constructs are utilized effectively? The question is examined in the domain of 'latent construct research using scales,' which is typified by the studies using questionnaire scales to assess latent constructs, thus spanning multiple disciplines in the behavioral and social sciences. For this domain, the notion of a Closely Related Construct (CRC), is formulated and operationalized using a method that integrates automated text analysis, citation analysis, and meta-analysis. Using CRC, a science metric termed Construct Utilization Ratio, is formulated that measures the extent to which closely related constructs are recognized between two units, where the unit may be chosen at different collective levels, such as between theories, journals, or research areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The project examines how this metric can be used to quantitatively and qualitatively assess the extent to which CRCs for a given construct are recognized and utilized within and across different research areas. It can also reveal where opportunities and redundancies reside.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0965338</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jintae</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jintae@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Larsen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kai.larsen@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eliot</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>erich2@albany.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
