<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Engineering 2020 Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Yvette Weatherton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is awarding scholarships to academically talented but financially-disadvantaged students in computer, electrical, and mechanical engineering. The scholarships are supporting three cohorts of nine students through completion of the final three years of an integrated five-year baccalaureate and master's degree program. Community college transfer students, as well as engineering students who have completed their first two years of study at the host institution, are eligible for scholarship support. The program is recruiting students who would otherwise complete only an undergraduate degree to instead stay and complete a master's degree. Student cohorts are being formed by having participating students enroll in common junior and senior projects courses. Students are being supported by a seminar course specifically designed for scholarship recipients and by individualized mentoring from faculty members. Students are also being encouraged to take advantage of paid internship opportunities with a variety of local companies. The goals of the program include increasing the number of students from under-represented groups who complete a master's degree, increasing the number of graduating students who are successfully placed with local industries, and improving the professional development aspects of the participating engineering programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0966121</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zahorian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zahorian@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pitarresi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmp@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Summerville</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dsummer@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
      <CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
