<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Crystal Engineering Gordon Research Conference; Waterville Valley Resort, NH; June 6-10, 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda S. Sapochak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; In 2010, the Gordon Research Conference (GRC) series will present the first GRC in the rapidly emerging field of Crystal Engineering, one of the more contemporary areas of chemical research today. Crystal Engineering is the design and synthesis of functional solid-state structures based on a bottom-up approach from smaller building blocks such as neutral organic molecules and organic or inorganic ions. Crystal Engineering is developed and structured around three distinct and yet interconnected themes: (1) the study of intermolecular interactions; (2) the use of these interactions in a crystal design strategy and, (3) the fine-tuning of crystal structure for property optimization. The SSMC program provided funds for the 2010 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Crystal Engineering (June 6-10, 2010, Waterville Valley Resort, NH). The NSF funds will be utilized to provide registration fee and/or travel support for graduate students, postdocs and/or young faculty including, but not limited to, women and/or other minorities to participate in the conference. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON TECHNICAL&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Crystal Engineering is one of the more contemporary areas of chemical research today and is central to many fundamental problems that are currently facing society. It is expected that developments in this rapidly developing field will meet societal demands that are not currently being addressed by more conventional approaches to synthetic chemistry and materials science. Examples of areas where Crystal Engineering can address current societal challenges include the rational design and construction of hydrogen storage materials and efforts to control drug polymorphism. The SSMC program provided funds for the 2010 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Crystal Engineering (June 6-10, 2010, Waterville Valley Resort, NH). The NSF funds will be utilized to provide registration fee and/or travel support for graduate students, postdocs and/or young faculty including, but not limited to, women and/or other minorities to participate in the conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0966898</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gautam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Desiraju</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>GAUTAM_DESIRAJU@YAHOO.COM</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rogers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>RDRogers@as.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonard</FirstName>
      <LastName>MacGillivray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>len-macgillivray@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
