<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Open Frameworks of Transition Metals and Transition-Metal Complexes Linked with Multifunctional Linkers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Novel materials with neutral open-framework structures made of transition metals or transition-metal complexes that are interconnected with multifunctional organic linkers will be synthesized and characterized. The linkers will be mainly sulfonates or disulfonates, often combined with carboxy- and amino-groups, and phosphonates and carboxylates will be used as well. Many of the systems will involve multiple charge-assisted hydrogen bonding between cationic transition-metal complexes and the anionic sulfonates; others will also involve direct coordination to the transition-metal centers. This research, supported by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry program of the Division of Materials Research, aims at discovering diverse materials with new inorganic-organic framework structures that exhibit diverse properties based on their inorganic (magnetic, optical, mechanical and thermal stability, etc.) and organic (diversity, structural flexibility, etc.) parts. This potential integration of the properties makes these compounds of great interest for a wide range of potential applications. The synthetic techniques, structure characterization, and properties measurements will provide opportunities for training graduate and undergraduate students in cutting-edge tools and methodologies for doing research in both solid-state chemistry and solution chemistry. The project, in combination with the existing University of Notre Dame infrastructure and programs for recruiting students from underrepresented groups, will be used to attract minority and female coworkers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed novel materials with open-framework structures will impact various important areas of the economy such as the development of new catalysts, new membrane materials for separation and ion exchange, petroleum cracking, nanotechnology, and optical and sensor materials. Many of these applications will, in turn, lead to better chemical processing and to higher energy-use efficiencies. An example is the potential use of these materials as safe and environmentally benign containers for gas storage and transportation. The project will also provide highly educated and practically trained Ph.D. students and postdoctoral fellows to advance high quality research at the forefront of science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0968645</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Slavi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sevov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ssevov@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
      <CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
      <ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
