<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Problems in Weighted Inequalities, Phase Plane Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>292000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Hilbert transform is an mathematical object intimately related to physical situations such as charge distribution. It and related objects such as the Cauchy transform, occur in a range of analytical questions, from orthogonal polynomials to dynamics, to analytic function spaces and partial differential equations. The two-weight problem for the Hilbert transform concerns a characterization of those pairs of measures so that the transform maps Hilbert space of one measure into Hilbert space of the other. This problem has been solved by the proposer, Eric T Sawyer and Ignacio Uriate-Tuero, in work sponsored by the National Science Foundation. This has immediate application to for instance a long-standing conjecture of Sarason in operator theory. The goal of this proposal, is to build upon this success, turning to extensions of this characterization for other natural questions, such as that for the Cauchy transform, which is fundamental for the theory of analytic function spaces. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work seeks to detail subtle properties of transforms which closely model physical situations, such as electrical charge distributions. As such, the techniques will impact the range of analytical tools that can be brought to bear on these questions that entail fine knowledge about these operators. In addition, the proposer carries out a variety of roles in mentoring and training a next generation of scientific workforce. This includes: (1) The work of the investigator on an MCTP grant to recruit and train talented undergraduate majors at the Georgia Institute of Technology. (2) Directing two graduate students in their thesis work. (3) Mentoring a number of postdoctoral fellows. (4) Conference organization at research centers in the US, Canada and Europe. (5) Editorial work for the Proceedings of the American Mathematical Society and the Journal of Geometric Analysis. (6) Dissemination of research accomplishments and goals, including lectures at venues around the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0968499</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lacey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lacey@math.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
