<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Beyond Point Vortices: Moving Singularities and Wave Fields in Fluid Mechanics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>244360</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Massimo Ruzzene</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Kirchhoff's equations of motion for point vortices are a paradigm of reduction of an infinite-dimensional dynamical system, namely the incompressible Euler equation, to a finite-dimensional system. Yet the original incompressible Euler equation itself neglects physical phenomena such as compressibility that may be important in certain applications. In addition, one can also examine other generalizations of the point vortex singularity, such as dipoles, and the effect of boundaries. In this proposal, we aim to derive appropriate equations for such situations based on physical principles and examine the resulting nonlinear systems. The natural extension of point vortices to higher singularities using momentum conservation argument encounters difficulties: the resulting equations are not uniquely specified and there is an underlying ill-defined regularization. We tackle this problem using a complementary tool to integral arguments, namely by exploiting the very differences in scales to obtain equations governing the large-scale motion of the system while taking into account the small-scale behavior of the vortices where appropriate. This is an archetypal Matched Asymptotic Expansion (MAE) problem. These approaches will provide equations that are new tools for low-order models of fluid flows beyond the well-known point vortex equations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Vorticity has been a fundamental concept in fluid mechanics since its introduction by Helmholtz. The Scottish school, including Lord Kelvin, sought a theory of `vortex atoms' to explain the structure of matter. Understanding vorticity dynamics is critical to an understanding of turbulence, and essentially large-scale flows, whether environmental, are turbulent. Simplified models a critical tool in physics, mathematics and engineering to achieve this understanding and point vortices, two-dimensional singular structures, are an important such model. They have been called a ``classical applied mathematical playground'' and have been used to understanding problems in the control of fluid flows, biological locomotion and geophysics. This project aims to derive extensions of point vortices to more general systems using physical principles. Such models have applications in models of aircraft wakes for large modern aircraft by taking into account compressibility. Reduced-order models such as the ones presented here are an important first step in the modeling process as well as providing potential benchmarks to compare to complex CFD (computational fluid dynamics) calculations. The project will include an international collaboration between mathematicians and fluid dynamicists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0970113</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Llewellyn Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sgls@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7478</Code>
      <Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>034E</Code>
      <Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
