<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Measurements of the Parity Non-Conservation Amplitude in Atomic Cesium for Improved Tests of the Standard Model and Beyond</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>525000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research will provide a long-sought independent check of the Parity Non-Conserving (PNC) measurement in cesium, and especially of the nuclear spin dependence of these measurements. Tests of the Standard Model, the theoretical description of the physical world that unifies two of the four fundamental forces (the weak forces and electromagnetic forces), are critical to our understanding of matter at the atomic and nuclear level. New laboratory measurements of higher precision will allow for an even more precise determination of the weak charge, a fundamental quantity within the Standard Model. Even more important will be measurements of the PNC interaction on the different hyperfine transitions, which will probe higher-order effects such as the nuclear anapole moment. Prior measurements of nucleon-nucleon scattering in atomic systems have produced constraints of coupling constants that are at odds with those from high-energy scattering measurements, and the proposed measurements are designed to help resolve these discrepancies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will (1) advance our understanding of interactions beyond those typically encountered in atomic physics, (2) lead to advances in detection of weak interactions, and (3) provide educational opportunities for graduate and undergraduate students in disciplines of Physics and Engineering. In addition to mastery of topics of current interest, students in the laboratory learn important technical skills such as optics and lasers, electronics, data analysis, and computer programming. The PI is committed to education at the graduate and undergraduate level, promoting diversity in science and engineering, and integrating research and education. Participation by undergraduate students in the PI's laboratory is an active facet of this program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0970041</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elliott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>elliottd@ecn.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
