<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sliding Frequency Modelocking of Swept Laser</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence S. Goldberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;ECCS-0801412&lt;br/&gt;S. Yun, Massachusetts General Hospital&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective: The overall goal of this project is to understand and develop novel modelocking techniques in wavelength-swept lasers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: Sliding Frequency Modelocking (SFM) is a new technique for generating swept pulses using a unique mechanism to swept operation. A deeper understanding of SFM would greatly enhance our ability to develop a novel swept laser for new applications. This project aims to explore the fundamentals and technologies of SFM through theoretical and experimental investigations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The proposed research promises to make important contributions to the fundamental understanding of swept laser technology and modelocking. It will provides the following: (1) improved theoretical models of modelocked swept lasers, (2) understanding and implementation of traditional modelocking techniques, such as active phase modulation and Kerr lens modelocking in swept lasers, and (3) novel picosecond swept lasers and high-speed Ti:sapphire swept lasers. Mode-locked swept lasers may enable a variety of applications ranging from nonlinear imaging to time-resolved spectroscopy. This project provides an ideal opportunity to educate and train graduate students and research fellows in the highly innovative and collaborative environment at Harvard Medical School. Undergraduate students enrolled in the Harvard-MIT HST summer institute and summer internship will participate in this project. Our group has extensive collaborations with other research groups as well as with industry. Mode-locked swept lasers have a significant potential to become a powerful light source to enable and facilitate a variety of applications, particularly in biomedical imaging to advance health care.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0801412</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Seok (Andy)</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>syun@partners.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts General Hospital</Name>
      <CityName>Somerville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021451446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8572821670</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Management</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>097E</Code>
      <Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>101E</Code>
      <Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>103E</Code>
      <Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>109E</Code>
      <Text>Sys theory in biology &amp; medicine</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
