<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Multi-Wavelength Study of Polarized Foregrounds and Anomalous Emission in the ISM</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>231000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Edward Ajhar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Stephen Muchovej is awarded an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a program of research and education at the California Institute of Technology. Dr. Muchovej will perform a multi-wavelength study of the interstellar medium (ISM) incorporating the C-Band All Sky Survey (CBASS), with emphasis on characterizing polarized foregrounds and the nature of the "anomalous emission" component of current ISM models. CBASS is an NSF-funded, 5-GHz radio survey sensitive to total intensity and linear polarization that will produce the first all-sky map of polarized emission that can be reliably extrapolated to frequencies of interest to cosmic microwave background (CMB) polarization experiments. In conjunction with the CBASS map, Dr. Muchovej will combine public H-alpha (a tracer of free-free emission), Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP) (CMB radio frequencies), and Infrared Astronomical Satellite (IRAS) (dust) data to identify and study regions exhibiting dust-correlated anomalous emission at ~30 GHz. Infrared and microwave observations will be used to study the mechanisms producing the anomalous emission and its role in the ISM as a whole. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Muchovej will also develop a prototype for a millimeter-wave monolith integrated (MMIC) Array Spectrograph (MAS), the precursor to focal-plane arrays of detectors capable of wide-field imaging and spectroscopy from 30-100 GHz. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, Dr. Muchovej will conduct an outreach program targeted at teaching astronomy to children ages 4-12 through the development and implementation of hands-on activities that promote physical understanding on a wide range of topics in astronomy. Dr. Muchovej will translate his materials into Spanish and Portuguese and will implement them both near Caltech and in Latino community centers in the greater Los Angeles area.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0802363</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muchovej</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>04/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Muchovej Stephen J</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100277205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1609</Code>
      <Text>NSF ASTRON &amp; ASTROPHY PSTDC FE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7697</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
