<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Assistance Awards for Symposium Undergraduate Research in Polymer Science at 2008 Spring National ACS Meeting in New Orleans, LA, April 6-10, 2008</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070012</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual merit.&lt;br/&gt;By providing the opportunity for participating undergraduate students to display the&lt;br/&gt;results of their creative academic activities at the national level, the Symposium, which is&lt;br/&gt;specifically dedicated to recognize and celebrate the students' exceptional work, is one of the&lt;br/&gt;most effective means to motivate these students and intellectually stimulate their further interest&lt;br/&gt;in graduate education. The symposium will give participating students a chance to discuss their&lt;br/&gt;research projects and exchange ideas with other students, graduate researchers, faculty and&lt;br/&gt;professional scientists. In addition students will practice presentation skills and gain invaluable&lt;br/&gt;experience presenting research at a premiere, national level, professional scientific conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact.&lt;br/&gt;The symposium will serve to provide recognition to outstanding undergraduate students&lt;br/&gt;in polymer science and engineering, to foster networking and exposure, to introduce&lt;br/&gt;opportunities in graduate research and education and to help develop the careers of future leaders&lt;br/&gt;in both academia and industry. The symposium will also offer an occasion for students and&lt;br/&gt;supervising faculty to witness how student projects enhance faculty research and also serve the&lt;br/&gt;greater community. Additionally, it will provide motivation for future generations of&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate students. Those who are not engaged in these pursuits as yet can learn how their&lt;br/&gt;fellow students developed their research interests.&lt;br/&gt;"When does a scientist become a scientist? It is not when a person knows many facts and&lt;br/&gt;even understands in depth some aspect of the natural world. I would suggest the transition&lt;br/&gt;occurs when curiosity about a phenomenon leads to an inquiry for new knowledge. This can&lt;br/&gt;occur in a person with little or lots of knowledge about a subject. It is an attitude of inquiry".</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/09/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/09/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0802556</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sergei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nazarenko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Sergei.Nazarenko@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/09/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morgan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Sarah.Morgan@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/09/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern Mississippi</Name>
      <CityName>Hattiesburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>394015876</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6012664119</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2609 WEST 4TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
