<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: International Workshop on Imprecise Probability in Engineering Analysis and Design; held at Georgia Institute of Tech; Feb. 20-22, 2008</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30030</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christina L. Bloebaum</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides funding to conduct an international workshop February 20-22, 2007 at the Savannah campus of Georgia Institute of Technology. This workshop will bring together researchers to address, discuss and lay the groundwork for the development of new methods and tools to handle engineering analysis and design problems under uncertainty with a focus on problems that have incomplete or imprecise information. Topics of the workshop include uncertainty modeling with incomplete information, analysis and design of engineering systems with imprecise parameters and design-based decision making with imprecise information. A group of approximately 45 participants from various disciplines including mathematics, computer science, computational mathematics and engineering, are expected to attend. The Scientific Committee associated with this workshop includes distinguished researchers from around the globe which will facilitate participation from the international community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results from this workshop will have important implications for the economy of the United States. Reliable and dependable analysis and design are crucial for the health and safety of the U.S. population. More reliable analysis and design of our systems will contribute to our ability to respond to life threatening failures and disasters of engineered and natural systems. This grant will support the education of the next generation of scholars in this area by providing support for graduate students and mid-career faculty to attend the workshop. The results of this workshop will be disseminated broadly through the publication of the proceedings, a workshop web site and journal publications in an international journal. In summary, this grant has the potential to greatly enhance the infrastructure for research and education in the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/03/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0803597</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rafi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muhanna</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rafi.muhanna@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mullen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rlm@cec.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
