<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Conference on Modeling and Simulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leland M. Jameson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigators and their colleagues propose to organize an&lt;br/&gt;International Conference on Modeling and Simulation, which will be&lt;br/&gt;held from July 9-12, 2008 in Xi'an Jiaotong University, Xi'an, Shaanxi&lt;br/&gt;Province, China. In the last two decades, the rapid development of&lt;br/&gt;computer power and sophisticated computational methodology has&lt;br/&gt;permitted the application of high performance computing to simulation&lt;br/&gt;and modeling of unprecedented accuracy and scope applied to a wide&lt;br/&gt;range of important problems. These applications have had profound&lt;br/&gt;implications and applications in mathematics, science, engineering and&lt;br/&gt;industry. Scientific computing is in fact the only feasible tool for&lt;br/&gt;analyzing many different types of critical important phenomena such as&lt;br/&gt;flow and transport, weather prediction, wave propagation, novel&lt;br/&gt;material design, computational chemistry, genome sequencing and&lt;br/&gt;analysis. The proposed conference will bring prominent researchers&lt;br/&gt;from U.S. and Europe working in these active areas to Asia, as to&lt;br/&gt;enhance and facilitate contacts and dialogs between specialists of&lt;br/&gt;different fields dealing with modeling and simulation so that new&lt;br/&gt;concepts can be discovered and new methodologies can express their&lt;br/&gt;power.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the past quarter of a century, along with rapid economical&lt;br/&gt;developments and advancements in the Far East Asian countries,&lt;br/&gt;particularly the phenomenal growth in China, there has been ever&lt;br/&gt;increasing collaborations between U.S.- and Asia-based (also between&lt;br/&gt;Europe- and Asia-based) researchers in all fields of scientific&lt;br/&gt;research. Such a phenomenon and trend is clearly exemplified by what&lt;br/&gt;has taken place in mathematical sciences latterly (thanks to the&lt;br/&gt;effort and initiatives of the NSF). These cross-continental research&lt;br/&gt;collaborations have already made a large impact on many fields of&lt;br/&gt;scientific research, most noticeably, on the human genome sequencing&lt;br/&gt;project in biological sciences and on the proof of the Poincare&lt;br/&gt;Conjecture in mathematical sciences. The proposed conference will be&lt;br/&gt;a contribution to promoting, enhancing, and stimulating such&lt;br/&gt;cross-continental research interactions and collaborations in&lt;br/&gt;mathematical sciences, more specifically, in applied and computational&lt;br/&gt;mathematics,</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0803403</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tsorng-Whay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pan@math.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jiwen</FirstName>
      <LastName>He</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jiwenhe@math.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
