<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Particle Packing Problems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>235447</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Torquato&lt;br/&gt;0804431&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator and his colleagues study a variety of&lt;br/&gt;packing problems. The following five general areas are explored:&lt;br/&gt;(1) identification and characterization of dense packings of&lt;br/&gt;nonspherical particles for a wide class shapes in two and three&lt;br/&gt;space dimensions; (2) study of sphere packings of maximal density&lt;br/&gt;in high Euclidean dimensions; (3) identification of low-density&lt;br/&gt;jammed sphere packings in various dimensions; (4) studies of&lt;br/&gt;jamming on the unit sphere in arbitrary dimensions; and (5)&lt;br/&gt;pursuit of improved order metrics to characterize the degree of&lt;br/&gt;randomness in a packing. Important scientific advances and&lt;br/&gt;outcomes are likely to emerge from the proposed research. This&lt;br/&gt;very multidisciplinary project joins the applied mathematics,&lt;br/&gt;statistical and condensed-matter physics, materials science,&lt;br/&gt;engineering, and pure mathematics communities. Unifying these&lt;br/&gt;different perspectives and goals is a challenging task, but one&lt;br/&gt;that offers great rewards to the scientific community in general. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Packing problems, such as how densely solid objects fill&lt;br/&gt;space, have fascinated people since the dawn of civilization, and&lt;br/&gt;continue to intrigue scientists because of their connection to a&lt;br/&gt;host of problems that arise in the physical sciences,&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, engineering, and biology. While optimal packing&lt;br/&gt;problems are intimately related to solid states of condensed&lt;br/&gt;matter, disordered sphere packings have been employed to model&lt;br/&gt;the glassy state of matter. Sphere packings in high dimensions&lt;br/&gt;have relevance in communications theory. The way that viruses&lt;br/&gt;package DNA in protein containers is a packing problem. What are&lt;br/&gt;the densest packings of spheres in dimension greater than three? &lt;br/&gt;What are the densest packings of nonspherical objects in two and&lt;br/&gt;three dimensions? Can random packings ever fill space more&lt;br/&gt;densely than ordered packings (implying disordered or "glassy"&lt;br/&gt;ground states)? Can "randomness" of a packing be quantified in a&lt;br/&gt;meaningful and precise manner? A greater understanding of&lt;br/&gt;packing problems has implications for the synthesis of novel&lt;br/&gt;materials, our ability to efficiently design communications&lt;br/&gt;channels to send digital signals over large distances, and the&lt;br/&gt;design of new drugs, just to mention a few examples.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0804431</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Salvatore</FirstName>
      <LastName>Torquato</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>torquato@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
