<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Supramolecular Nano Assemblies for Energy and Electron Transfer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>374867</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With the support of the Organic Dynamics Program in the Chemistry Division, Professor Francis D?Souza of the Chemistry Department at Wichita State University will rationally design and study supramolecular nano-structured donor-acceptor assemblies for efficient photoinduced electron and energy transfer, and utilize them to develop photovoltaic devices. The proposed multidisciplinary research activity seeks a firm understanding of the design of porphyrin, fullerene, carbon nanotube and carbon nanocups - bearing supramolecular architectures for efficient electron transfer in a controlled manner. The multiple donor and acceptor entities in the proposed molecular/supramolecular architectures are specifically selected to understand the nature and kinetics of intra- and intermolecular interactions as a function of molecular structure and topology. The proposed research is expected to contribute significantly to the present understanding of self-assembly processes, creating long-lived charge separated states by means of supramolecular methods, electron transfer in functionalized carbon nanotubes and nano structures, and the role of noncovalent interactions on the mechanistic and kinetic aspects of photoinduced electron transfer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research by Professor D?Souza of Wichita State University describes a program of highly integrated research, education, and outreach in supramolecular nanoscience, relevant to harvesting solar energy. These nanohybrids will impact diverse applications in materials chemistry especially for building devices for light energy harvesting. Development of novel energy sources other than those based on fossil fuels or nuclear energy is a research topic that is of considerable scientific and societal importance. Research, teaching, mentoring, and leadership skills will be strengthened through innovative methods. Communication skills will be developed by domestic and international collaborations, and augmented by disseminating research findings through presentations at conferences and universities, and publications in peer-reviewed journals. Technical and problem-solving skills to help future members of the nation?s workforce gain employment in high technology areas will be improved by exposing personnel (including women and minorities) to a wide range of scientific techniques inherent to the multidisciplinary nature of the proposed research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0804015</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
      <LastName>D'Souza</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Francis.DSouza@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wichita State University</Name>
      <CityName>Wichita</CityName>
      <ZipCode>672600007</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3169783285</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1845 Fairmount</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
