<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Discrete and continuous geometry in group theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>229672</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Artin groups are a large class of groups commonly studied by geometric&lt;br/&gt;group theorists. They are related to Coxeter groups, they include and&lt;br/&gt;generalize the braid groups, and they have a natural definition&lt;br/&gt;involving complexified hyperplane complements. Despite these&lt;br/&gt;affiliations with well-known objects, very few Artin groups are&lt;br/&gt;currently understood, even at a basic level, and those that are belong&lt;br/&gt;to highly restrictive families defined primarily by the situations&lt;br/&gt;where existing techniques can be applied. The approach described here&lt;br/&gt;is fundamentally new and different. The goal of this proposal is to&lt;br/&gt;understand the natural, continuous geometric objects (recently&lt;br/&gt;introduced by the principal investigator and his collaborators) that&lt;br/&gt;have the potential to serve as a geometric foundation for the study of&lt;br/&gt;all Artin groups in a uniform fashion. These geometric objects,&lt;br/&gt;called factor geometries, are of interest in their own right. There&lt;br/&gt;is, for example, a natural continuous group G that has the orthogonal&lt;br/&gt;group as a quotient, contains the braid group as a subgroup, and is&lt;br/&gt;the fundamental group of a finite-dimensional metric simplicial&lt;br/&gt;complex whose universal cover is the contractible factor geometry with&lt;br/&gt;a building-like structure on which G acts. This unusual uncountable&lt;br/&gt;group and space, defined via the collection of minimal factorizations&lt;br/&gt;of spherical isometries into reflections, is a hybrid mix of Lie&lt;br/&gt;groups and metric simplicial complexes, and every Artin group acts on&lt;br/&gt;a similarly defined continuous geometric object. The eventual&lt;br/&gt;structure theory should resemble that of Lie groups and early&lt;br/&gt;indications are that these types of complexes carry geometric and&lt;br/&gt;combinatorial structures sufficient to resolve many longstanding&lt;br/&gt;conjectures about arbitrary Artin groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mathematical objects, like many physical objects, can be better&lt;br/&gt;understood when we fully understand the symmetries they possess. The&lt;br/&gt;algebraic structure that records how these symmetries interact is&lt;br/&gt;called a ``group'' and the groups under consideration here are a class&lt;br/&gt;of groups generated by ``reflections'' (a symmetry like the reflected&lt;br/&gt;image one sees through a mirror). The main goal of this project is to&lt;br/&gt;deepen our understanding of the relationship between symmetry groups&lt;br/&gt;built from reflections (specifically Coxeter groups) and a second&lt;br/&gt;class of symmetry groups, called Artin groups. The most famous&lt;br/&gt;example of an Artin group is the braid group, the group that keeps&lt;br/&gt;track of the distinct ways in which several strands of string can be&lt;br/&gt;braided together. Constructions involving Coxeter groups, Artin&lt;br/&gt;groups and braid groups proliferate throughout mathematics, including&lt;br/&gt;some recent mathematical physics. In many of these cases, the&lt;br/&gt;immediate connections are, strictly speaking, to Artin groups rather&lt;br/&gt;than Coxeter groups, but these connections have not been pursued&lt;br/&gt;partly because the theory of Artin groups is underdeveloped. Once&lt;br/&gt;this situation is rectified within geometric group theory, the next&lt;br/&gt;step will be to export the resulting structure theory to these&lt;br/&gt;neighboring domains</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0805716</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCammond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jon.mccammond@math.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
