<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multifunctional Mesoporous Silica Nanoparticles for Intracellular Controlled Release</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award in the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry program in the Division of Chemistry and the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials research supports Professor Victor Lin at Iowa State University to synthesize biocompatible, multi-functionalized mesoporous silica nanoparticle (MSN) materials with well-defined particle morphology and tunable surface properties for efficient penetration across different cell membranes. A series of pore-capping and uncapping strategies will be developed that can be triggered by cellular chemicals and enzymes for studying intracellular controlled release of a variety of guest molecules, such as drugs, imaging agents, peptides, proteins, and nucleotides, inside of animal and plant cells. The specific objectives are to: 1) Synthesize biocompatible mesoporous silica nanoparticles for controlling membrane trafficking, 2) Fine-tune surface properties of MSNs for loading and release of chemicals, 3) Develop an arsenal of different pore-capping and uncapping strategies, 4) Study mechanisms of endocytosis, intracellular transportation, and controlled release. Various interactions between the multifunctional MSNs with different particle morphologies and animal and plant cells will be studied in vitro. These interactions include: the adsorption of MSNs to cell membranes, the mechanism and kinetics of internalization, the intracellular localization of internalized MSN, the biocompatibility, and the effects of MSNs on cellular metabolism. A series of imaging, cytochemical, and cell sorting techniques will be employed to study the dynamics of cellular uptake of the MSNs and the kinetics of intracellular controlled release of biologically active molecules from MSNs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research offers new nanomaterials for chemists, biologists, and material scientists to study the chemical nature and biochemistry inside living cells. The interdisciplinary work will also provide valuable training to the students working on this project. Other broader impacts include: The development of new curricular materials for graduate and undergraduate courses and outreach to local elementary and high schools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0809521</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Trewyn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>btrewyn@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Trewyn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>btrewyn@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/05/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vsylin@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/05/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
