<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Software System for Algebraic Geometry Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Macaulay2 is a free computer algebra system dedicated to the qualitative &lt;br/&gt;investigation of systems of polynomial equations in many variables. It &lt;br/&gt;was developed by Daniel Grayson and Michael Stillman with NSF funding. &lt;br/&gt;Grayson and Stillman will continue the development of Macaulay2. They &lt;br/&gt;will upgrade existing algorithms, develop and publish new algorithms, and &lt;br/&gt;implement new algorithms. In particular, they will develop the interaction &lt;br/&gt;of the symbolic computations that are Macaulay2's strength with the new &lt;br/&gt;floating point algorithms in algebraic geometry that are now being &lt;br/&gt;developed by Andrew Sommese, Jan Verschelde, Anton Leykin, Frank Schreyer &lt;br/&gt;and others. It is anticipated that these will make a whole new class of &lt;br/&gt;problems accessible to experimentation and, in many cases, solution. &lt;br/&gt;Eisenbud will organize contacts for the extended integration with other &lt;br/&gt;systems and will engage other mathematicians in the development work that &lt;br/&gt;needs to be done. Central to the project are the continued expansion of &lt;br/&gt;the collaborations that have been the hallmark of Macaulay2 development. &lt;br/&gt;For this purpose two Macaulay2 Workgroup Meetings will be held in the &lt;br/&gt;course of the two-year grant. One particular research problem to be &lt;br/&gt;attacked is: the use of computational systems to (probabilistically) &lt;br/&gt;disprove, or suggest a proof of, the Jacobian Conjecture on polynomial &lt;br/&gt;automorphisms of affine spaces (this will require the use the new floating &lt;br/&gt;point algorithms). Other areas where new algorithms can make an impact &lt;br/&gt;include the study of numerical systems, fractions with specified types of &lt;br/&gt;denominators, ideal factorization, systems where the multiplication of the &lt;br/&gt;variables doesn't satisfy the commutative law, geometric optimization, the &lt;br/&gt;analysis of observations of gene expression levels over time, and &lt;br/&gt;bioinformatics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Macaulay2 is part of the infrastructure that supports mathematical &lt;br/&gt;research involving systems of polynomial equations in many variables. The &lt;br/&gt;study of such systems of polynomial equations is central in pure and &lt;br/&gt;applied mathematics and in physics, with recent new impacts in such fields &lt;br/&gt;as cryptography, robotics and string theory. Increasing computer power &lt;br/&gt;and the availability of programs like Macaulay2 are making a new level of &lt;br/&gt;experimentation possible. The experimental results found with Macaulay2 &lt;br/&gt;are helping in the formulation and development of tractable conjectures in &lt;br/&gt;mathematics as well as in physics. A measure of Macaulay2's impact is that &lt;br/&gt;at least 270 research papers have cited Macaulay2, several mathematicians &lt;br/&gt;have contributed code, and books and course materials are now using it. &lt;br/&gt;The PI's will develop the software further and will recruit developers &lt;br/&gt;from the research community. They will introduce graduate students and &lt;br/&gt;mathematicians to the use of computers in research mathematics and the &lt;br/&gt;requisite skills in programming and development of algorithms, through &lt;br/&gt;workgroups at Berkeley and through the appointments of graduate students &lt;br/&gt;as graduate assistants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0810918</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eisenbud</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>de@msri.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
