<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Grant: Computational Sciences and Robotics Education at North Carolina Central University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>148930</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT HRD 0811744&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project, based at North Carolina Central University (NCCU), is developing a Robotics concentration within an interdisciplinary program in Computational Sciences. Four courses are being developed in this concentration, one of which will serve as an introductory course designed to motivate students about computer science and engineering. Students enrolled in the Early College High School at NCCU are able to enroll in this course. In addition we are conducting summer workshops in Robotics for area high schools. In conjunction with faculty from the STEM disciplines, students have opportunities undertake research projects in areas of Computational Science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The program at NCCU will accomplish three objectives: (i) it will establish a computational science program grounded in research to influence undergraduates, minorities in particular, to consider graduate education in mathematics, computer science and engineering; (ii) it will establish a pipeline of students into graduate education at outstanding research universities, located in the area and beyond; (iii) it will enable the training of students who appreciate the problems inherent in these disciplines and who can contribute to the future of these areas. The program is creating long-term interdisciplinary training in the Computational Sciences, as well as collaborative projects and curriculum development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The STEM departments at North Carolina Central University (NCCU) are committed to increasing the opportunities for underrepresented minorities in the sciences. We seek to broaden participation in new degree programs and concentrations through revision of curricula and development of new courses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0811744</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>R</FirstName>
      <LastName>Uma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ruma@nccu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alade</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tokuta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>atokuta@nccu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Guodong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Guodong.Guo@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina Central University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277073129</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195307333</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Fayetteville Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
