<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Optimal Time Stepping Method for Computational Science Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>277789</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The focus of this proposal is on the mathematical analysis and efficient &lt;br/&gt;implementation of a new class of Krylov deferred correction accelerated &lt;br/&gt;"method of lines transpose" for time dependent PDE's. The method first &lt;br/&gt;discretizes the temporal direction using Gaussian type nodes and spectral &lt;br/&gt;integration, and the resulting coupled elliptic equations are preconditioned &lt;br/&gt;using deferred corrections, in which each correction procedure only &lt;br/&gt;requires the solution of a decoupled system using available fast elliptic &lt;br/&gt;equation solvers. The preconditioned nonlinear system is then solved &lt;br/&gt;efficiently using iterative Newton-Krylov techniques. Preliminary numerical &lt;br/&gt;experiments show that this method is unconditionally stable, very efficient, &lt;br/&gt;and can achieve arbitrary order of accuracy in both time and space. In &lt;br/&gt;particular, no CFL constraints have been observed and the time step size &lt;br/&gt;only depends on the smoothness of the solution and hence is "optimal". &lt;br/&gt;Highlights of the PI's preliminary results include (a) a time domain &lt;br/&gt;Maxwell equation solver which provides accurate results for a long-time &lt;br/&gt;electromagnetic wave simulation problem for which most existing time &lt;br/&gt;integration schemes fail; and (b) a symplectic Schrodinger equation solver &lt;br/&gt;which preserves the structure of a Hamiltonian system with singular &lt;br/&gt;potential while most existing numerical techniques quickly blow up. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is well known that inaccurate numerical algorithms have caused many &lt;br/&gt;costly project failures, examples include the sinking of the Sleipner A &lt;br/&gt;offshore platform in Gandsfjorden near Stavanger, Norway, on August &lt;br/&gt;23, 1991, which was due to inaccurate finite element analysis and resulted &lt;br/&gt;in a loss of nearly one billion dollars. The purpose of this proposal is to &lt;br/&gt;use advanced mathematical analysis and develop numerical techniques that&lt;br/&gt;can efficiently provide accurate and stable numerical simulation results &lt;br/&gt;to important science and engineering problems. In particular, the PI &lt;br/&gt;will study and implement a novel class of numerical algorithms for &lt;br/&gt;time dependent problems modeled by partial differential equations.&lt;br/&gt;The success of this project will bring new tools and techniques to a &lt;br/&gt;wide class of applications in science and engineering that are impossible&lt;br/&gt;to solve efficiently and accurately using existing techniques, examples &lt;br/&gt;including the design of optimal drug structures in biochemistry, the study&lt;br/&gt;of cosmos structure in astrophysics, and improved understanding of the &lt;br/&gt;physics that govern hydrologic processes in Earth system science. &lt;br/&gt;This project also focuses on the training of a new generation of scientists &lt;br/&gt;capable of developing advanced numerical tools using sophisticated &lt;br/&gt;mathematical theory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0811130</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jingfang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>huang@amath.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
      <CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
      <ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
