<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI-Small: An Integrative Framework for Communication and Motion-planning in Robotic Networks Operating in Fading Environments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Todd Leen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this project is to build a design framework for robust functionality of mobile cooperative robotic router networks in realistic communication environments. Most of the existing work on mobile cooperative decision-making uses oversimplified models for communication links by assuming either a perfect link or no link between any two agents. Such models do not embrace realistic wireless communication effects such as fading, shadowing and path loss and therefore will not be suitable for robust operation of robotic router networks. We propose novel motion-planning strategies where the agents constantly reconfigure themselves to optimally route the information through the network. In addition, the theoretical results and algorithms will be implemented on actual autonomous vehicles engaged in a wide range of tasks. By considering realistic communication unreliability, our proposed framework will result in the robust flow of information in the network. Emergency response, security and surveillance are examples of applications that rely on robust and intelligent operation of autonomous networks in harsh conditions and can benefit tremendously from the proposed work. This project also has a significant educational impact on the female high school students of Albuquerque by organizing learning summer camps at the University of New Mexico.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0812338</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yasamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mostofi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ymostofi@ece.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rafael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fierro</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rfierro@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
