<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Second Workshop on the Impact of Globalization on Electrical and Computer Curricula of the Future: Implementation. Workshop held on February 3-5, 2008 in Santa Clara, CA.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>48260</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Radhakisan S. Baheti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There is a recognized need to educate engineering students for competitive careers in a global economy. Educators need to carefully consider how to educate engineering students to prepare them for changes in the profession due to globalization and outsourcing. Educators also face the challenge of recruiting students into ECE programs in the face of the negative publicity of out-sourcing, and the perceived undercutting of the value of an engineering degree due to global competition. In response to this challenge the Electrical and Computer Department Heads Association (ECEDHA) and the International Engineering Consortium (IEC) organized a workshop on this topic that was held at the National Academy of Engineering in Washington D. C. on November 14 and 15, 2005. &lt;br/&gt;The second workshop will highlight on-the-job engineering experiences, best practices, and curricular development. There will be an attempt to compile information about the types of outreach activities in which ECE departments are currently engaged to address recruitment and retention of students and faculty in the face of globalization. Information on programmatic changes to improve global awareness and technical skills for global engineering will also be presented. The first day of the workshop will center around two invited panels, one a panel of experts from industry and the second a panel of experts from academia. Breakout groups will be charged to discuss issues raised by the panels and prepare reports on the most important lessons learned. These reports will be presented at the spring ECEDHA meeting in San Diego, March 14 ? 18, 2008 and a final report will be prepared for distribution to NSF and the ECEDHA membership. Opportunities to provide information electronically will be made available to those ECEDHA members who are not able to attend the workshop. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit of the second workshop centers on the urgency for ECE educators to modify ECE curricula in response to the increasing pressures of globalization in the ECE profession, to improve opportunities for continuing education, to motivate life-long learning in the ECE profession. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: &lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the second workshop is reflected in the international scope of the issues to be addressed at the workshop, and by the serious attention that the workshop will devote to recruiting, retaining, and mentoring undergraduate students, graduate students and young faculty, while drawing as much as possible from underrepresented groups in engineering (minorities and women in engineering).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0813800</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Connor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>connor@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bsullivan@ecedha.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjts@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>W. Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jenkins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jenkins@engr.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Seyed Hossein</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mousavinezhad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mousseye@isu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606066338</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3122838465</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>233 S Wacker Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0112000</Code>
      <Name>System Theory</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7607</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY,POWER,ADAPTIVE SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1653</Code>
      <Text>Adaptive &amp; intelligent systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
