<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integration and Commercialization of Micro and Nano Systems International Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Theodore L. Bergman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0813718, Zhang&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award partially supports the 2nd Integration and Commercialization of Micro and Nano Systems International Conference, which will be held in Hong Kong, China, on June 3-5, 2008. The purpose of this meeting is to bring together an international group of researchers and business people, including small businesses, to discuss frontier nanotechnology research and business opportunities. Within NSF, funding is provided by both the Thermal Transport Processes Program and the Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnerships Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to the intellectual merit of the conference, numerous directions are emerging for nanotechnology research. The Asian Rim nations are particularly active in this field, both in terms of research and in terms of commercialization opportunities. This meeting will allow a highly diverse group of individuals, representing the research and the business communities, to interact and to explore how nanotechnology science and technology advances can be translated into new products ready for commercialization. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the conference include partial support for a number of US-based junior researchers and students, with women and minority attendees especially encouraged to attend. This meeting presents a vital opportunity for engineering researchers and business people, from around the world, to interact so that new research discoveries can be commercialized and brought to the market more quickly than what typically occurs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/25/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0813718</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhuomin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhuomin.zhang@me.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
