<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developing Engineering Faculty as Leaders of Academic Change</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>486874</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Don L. Millard</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Engineering - Other (59)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is organizing a two-day national workshop of approximately 25 engineering education leaders to identify the knowledge and skills required to lead academic change processes and to design a delivery system to effectively impart the identified knowledge and skills to engineering faculty. The workshop includes interactive sessions to review major international developments that set the context for academic engineering leadership as well as relevant lessons learned from the pre-cursor activities by the workshop organizers, to identify the challenges before academic engineering educators and the skills needed to surmount the challenges, to distill a list of desired leadership skills and parameters by which to guide the development of programs of study by which to impart the desired skills, and to explore options for the design, delivery and sustainability of a new program for developing faculty capacity for academic change leadership. In post workshop activities, attendees are organizing activities on their campuses to engage 250 additional faculty members in further discussion of workshop topics. In addition, the organizers and a small group of engineering education faculty members are translating the workshop outputs into a framework for a formal post-graduate certificate program in academic change leadership that embodies the desired knowledge, skills, and delivery mechanisms identified in the workshop to be offered via Purdue's Butler Center for Leadership Excellence. In addition, they are identifying engineering faculty (and ideally departments or colleges) willing to participate in pilot implementations of the envisioned Engineering Academic Change Management post-graduate certificate program. The evaluation effort is assessing the effectiveness of the workshop and the on-campus follow-up activities, the variety and novelty of the developed ideas, and changes in the participants' attitudes. Results of the project are being disseminated by postings on a website, by presentation at the engineering education conferences, and by publishing and distributing the workshop proceedings. Broader impacts include the dissemination of the material especially through the post-workshop activities, which are engaging a much larger audience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0814328</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fortenberry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>N.Fortenberry@asee.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>04/08/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cady</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ecady@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7492</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
