<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Workshop to Focus on Regional Strategies for Improving the Public Understanding of Science, Tampa Bay Florida, spring 2008</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>16525</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of California Museum of Paleontology (UCMP) is requesting funds to support: A Workshop to Focus on Regional Strategies for Improving the Public Understanding of Science. Funds will be used to support a two-day workshop that will lay the groundwork for achieving a scalable and sustainable network structure for the Coalition on the Public Understanding of Science (COPUS). The meeting will focus on building stronger bridges among stakeholders and identifying strategies for sustaining efforts through the formation of regional and thematic hubs. The primary goals of the proposed workshop are (1) to examine different hub models, (2) to identify and articulate motivations, opportunities, advantages, and challenges of developing and maintaining a regional or thematic hub, (3) to share successes and best practices, (4) to focus on critical needs for a successful hub, including those that can best be met by COPUS, and (5) to discuss needs and strategies for long-term networking. The products of the workshop will include: (1) a Hub Toolkit that provides detailed guidelines for others interested in developing a regional or thematic hub, a suggested list of core activities around which to engage the community in science, strategies for enlisting community support for hub activities, and strategies for sustainability, (2) a procedural plan for the expansion of the hub systems within the COPUS network, and (3) a set of prioritized activities and support services to be provided by COPUS.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0814048</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Caldwell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rlcaldwell@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/21/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
