<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAR-PF: The Source and Composition of Refractory Dissolved Organic Matter Accumulating in Aquatic Environments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>160000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Stuart Goldberg is awarded an NSF Earth Science Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a program of research and education at Scripps Institution of Oceanography. Dr. Goldberg will determine the origin, age, composition, and accumulation mechanisms of dissolved organic matter from three lakes in the Lake Tahoe Basin. Dr. Goldberg will measure the abundance the carbon isotopes (12C and 13C) and hydrogen isotopes (H and D) in preferentially preserved lipids to infer the origin of the organic matter (for example, terrestrial plants, soils, or aquatic plants). The age of the organic compounds will be determined using 14C. The results from this research will contribute the understanding of the modern and past carbon cycle in terrestrial and aquatic environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, Dr. Goldberg will contribute to the scientific education of high school students and entry level graduate students. Dr. Goldberg will mentor two high school students on their science fair projects and he will lead graduate students in discussions and laboratory work relate to the study of natural processes using the isotopic composition of organic matter.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0815462</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stuart</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goldberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/28/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Goldberg Stuart J</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931055732</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
