<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Knowledge Synthesis on the Implementation and Effects of Revising High School Graduation Credit Requirements in Mathematics and Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249826</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Celestine Pea</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: This proposal addresses a topic of national interest about the effects of revising high school graduation credit requirements in mathematics and science. The aim is to provide policymakers with information about how mathematics and science courses are adjusted at the district and school level following policy mandates. The proposal will also address policy as it applies to graduation requirements for students historically underserved in STEM fields. It will also provide insights about conflicting research relative to the effect of these policy revisions on school funding, shortages of mathematics and science teachers, special students populations, dropouts, and career-technical education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research questions will include:&lt;br/&gt;(1) While all states are seeking generally more study of mathematics and science and better student achievement, what more specific purposes do states have in legislating revised graduation requirements for mathematics and science (if any)?&lt;br/&gt;(2) In district responses to policy changes, what is the range of implementation plans with respect to funding, mathematics and science courses offerings, staffing, addressing impacts on various student populations, etc?&lt;br/&gt;(3) How do implementation plans and their effects vary with the types of policy, i.e. unit-based versus content-based requirements, and the range of different content-based requirements?&lt;br/&gt;(4) How well does actual implementation at the school level conform to the intended policy outcomes with respect to key aspects like course offering and content, and student? course taking and achievement?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposer will analyze and synthesize data about these questions along four constructs: (1) empirical and descriptive studies published in peer-reviewed journals; (2) research published via other venues including online; (3) published expert knowledge and advice located in periodicals or on websites; and (4) current practice-based knowledge acquired through online experts. The synthesis methods will allow the proposer to systematically and intensively evaluate the methodological integrity and evidentiary utility of each research construct.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This proposal will advance knowledge in the field by becoming the first synthesis study of the impact of increased policy changes on the number of mathematics and science credits required for graduation in high schools across the nation. Therefore, this study could be transformative relative to how policy changes impact STEM education and will add significantly to the limited studies about this topic. An advisory board with strong representation in STEM education, the arts and sciences, and research and evaluation will assist with implementation. In addition to traditional pathways, dissemination will be augmented by other outlets such as R&amp; D Alerts newsletters to policymakers, coverage in Education week, and through collaboration with the National Commission on Teaching and America?s Future that has agreed to include the results of the study in the Weekly News Digest, an e-bulletin to thousand of policymakers and education leaders.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0816325</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Britton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tbritto@wested.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cathy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ringstaff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cringst@wested.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>WestEd</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941071242</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4156153136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>730 Harrison Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7625</Code>
      <Text>REAL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
