<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Measuring Detailed Abundances of Extragalactic Globular Clusters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>125988</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020415</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Donald M. Terndrup</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>AST-0507350&lt;br/&gt;Rebecca Bernstein&lt;br/&gt;University of Michigan Ann Arbor&lt;br/&gt;Measuring Detailed Abundances of Extragalactic Globular Clusters&lt;br/&gt;Our understanding of the formation and chemical enrichment processes of normal galaxies is largely&lt;br/&gt;constrained by evidence from one galaxy: the Milky Way. That evidence is largely revealed in the detailed&lt;br/&gt;abundance patterns of old stars, which bear the fossil record of the Galaxy's gas chemistry at the time they&lt;br/&gt;formed. It has never been possible to obtain similar evidence in even one other normal galaxy. This is simply&lt;br/&gt;because old stars beyond the nearest dwarf spheroidal galaxies of the Local Group are too faint to be&lt;br/&gt;observed at the high signal-to-noise and high spectral resolution needed for abundance analysis.&lt;br/&gt;Unlike single stars, high-resolution spectra can be obtained of unresolved globular clusters at distances as&lt;br/&gt;large as 4 Mpc with current telescopes. Globular clusters are bright enough and have low enough velocity&lt;br/&gt;dispersions that even weak lines could be detected in spectra of their integrated light. Detailed abundances&lt;br/&gt;have never been obtained for unresolved globular clusters only because current methods of abundance&lt;br/&gt;analysis only work for individual stars. A method for abundance analysis of integrated-light spectra will&lt;br/&gt;make it possible to measure detailed abundances in the massive galaxies of the Local Group and well&lt;br/&gt;beyond.&lt;br/&gt;To develop this technique, a training set of resolved globular clusters in the Milky Way and Large&lt;br/&gt;Magellanic Cloud will be created. In these training set clusters, color magnitude diagrams and fiducial&lt;br/&gt;metallicities from single stars can be obtained, supplying a wealth of information for developing and testing&lt;br/&gt;the proposed method for analyzing the integrated light spectra of unresolved globular clusters. Crucially, the&lt;br/&gt;training set includes globular clusters of a wide range of ages and abundances, so that the necessary&lt;br/&gt;strategies can be developed to deal with such variations in unresolved globular clusters.&lt;br/&gt;Preliminary results demonstrate the potential of this technique, with reasonable abundances being derived&lt;br/&gt;from the integrated spectra of NGC 6397 and 47 Tucanae. However, a number of additions/improvements&lt;br/&gt;will also be added here. These include incorporation of blended lines in the synthesis (including the effects of&lt;br/&gt;hyperfine splitting), profile matching of strong lines, and consideration of possible non-local thermodynamic&lt;br/&gt;equilibrium effects. In addition, issues which may affect the confidence of the results will also be explored:&lt;br/&gt;horizontal branch morphology and what constraints can be applied through spectral indicators (e.g.,&lt;br/&gt;hydrogen line widths), the sensitivity to the luminosity function of stars at the low mass end, as well as the&lt;br/&gt;giants, and the importance of assumed alpha-element enhancements in the modeling process.&lt;br/&gt;This method for measuring abundances will let astronomers study the detailed chemical enrichment histories&lt;br/&gt;of galaxies beyond the Milky Way for the first time. This will dramatically increase the pool of observational&lt;br/&gt;constraints on galaxy formation theories and therefore have broad impact on our understanding of galaxy&lt;br/&gt;formation. The training set spectra themselves will also provide abundances of Magellanic Cloud clusters&lt;br/&gt;which are not yet well known, provide a calibration library for line index systems, and help astronomers&lt;br/&gt;understand the initial mass function of stars in globular clusters and the nucleosynthetic yields of supernovae.&lt;br/&gt;The training set spectra will also be made available through existing database as soon as they are published.&lt;br/&gt;A majority of the funding goes to supporting the training and education graduate students using state of the&lt;br/&gt;art observational facilities and computational tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0817049</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bernstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rab@ucolick.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
