<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Genomic Analyses of Shoot Meristem Function in Maize</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5310987</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Michael Scanlon (Cornell University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CoPIs: Marja Timmermans (Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory), Gary Muehlbauer (University of Minnesota), Jianming Yu (Kansas State University), Diane Janick-Buckner, Jon Beck (Truman State University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaborators Dan Nettleton (Iowa State University), Doreen Ware (USDA-ARS/Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory), David Micklos (Dolan DNA Learning Center)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The shoot apical meristem (SAM) is responsible for development of all above ground organs in the plant. Despite its essential roles during organogenesis, the molecular mechanisms regulating SAM function are poorly understood. Owing to a unique combination of biological advantages and genomic resources, maize is particularly well positioned for investigations of the genetic networks underlying SAM structure, function, and heterogeneity on a genomic scale. This project will address five specific objectives: (1) genetic characterization of candidate genes implicated in the regulation of SAM gene function and maize leaf patterning; (2) use of laser microdissection and transcript profiling to identify genes expressed during SAM initiation and development ; (3) identification of small RNA-controlled networks in SAM meristem function; (4) identification of quantitative trait loci (QTLs) controlling SAM architecture; and (5) identification of novel alleles (haplotypes) contributing to complex leaf traits using linkage-disequilibrium mapping.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of proposed research: These genomic analyses of SAM function will provide the intellectual framework for a strategy of scientific training and public outreach designed to disseminate an understanding and appreciation of plant science. Undergraduates at Truman State University, a small, public liberal arts institution in Kirksville (MO) will be trained to perform bioinformatic annotations of novel SAM genes, and carry out genetic, phenotypic, and molecular analyses of maize SAM mutants generated during this project. The Dolan DNA Learning Center at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory will construct a public website/podcast entitled "Weed to Wonder" that will present the history of maize genetic research and celebrate its impact on human culture. All data generated during this project will be released to public databases include MaizeGDB (www.maizegdb.org) and Gramene (www.gramene.org), and seed harboring newly discovered maize mutations will be released for public distribution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0820610</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jianming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmyu@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muehlbauer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>muehl003@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Janick-Buckner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>djb@truman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scanlon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjs298@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marja</FirstName>
      <LastName>Timmermans</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>timmerma@cshl.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell Univ - State: AWDS MADE PRIOR MAY 2010</Name>
      <CityName>Ithica</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502488</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
