<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a High Resolution Optical Monochromator System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>132026</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award to a non-Ph.D. granting institution is for the acquisition of a high resolution 1.3-&lt;br/&gt;m optical monochromator system with fast gated CCD camera for incorporation into the Laboratory for&lt;br/&gt;Plasma Physics at Troy University. This instrument will expand the current research capabilities of the PI's&lt;br/&gt; Laboratory into high resolution spectral line broadening measurements for high-velocity plasmas, which &lt;br/&gt;requires linewidth resolution on the order of 0.01 nm or better. Spectroscopic studies in basic plasma&lt;br/&gt; sciences will also be conducted with the help of the instrument in determining plasma density and temperature information. &lt;br/&gt;The high resolution monochromator system with fast gated ICCD camera&lt;br/&gt;fills a crucial void in the PI?s Laboratory. The instrument will make possible the investigations of the&lt;br/&gt;effects of a weak shock wave (Mach 1-5) on plasmas as well as of plasmas behind a strong ionizing&lt;br/&gt;shock wave (Mach 20 or higher). This research will provide new insight into fundamental plasma&lt;br/&gt; processes involved in the electronic layers formed at the shock-front. The high resolution spectroscopic&lt;br/&gt; line broadening data measured in the laboratory plasma behind a strong ionizing shock wave&lt;br/&gt; (Mach 20 or higher) can have potential use for space and inter-stellar plasma diagnostics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0821467</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nirmol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Podder</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>npodder@troy.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Troy University</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>360820001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3346703102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
