<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: IEEE PerCom 2008 Student Travel Support</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alhussein A. Abouzeid</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>IEEE PerCom is a high quality conference and the premier technical forum dedicated to addressing the key challenges in Pervasive computing and aware networking including wireless, mobile, mesh and sensor networks, middleware, pervasive services and applications. This year the number of submissions in response to the CFP has been over 200; only 18 regular papers and 12 short papers have been accepted by the Technical Program Committee for presentation at the conference. The proceedings will be published by IEEE Computer Press. As in the past, selected (extended) papers will be invited for publication in a special issue of the Elsevier's Pervasive and Mobile Computing (PMC) journal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participation in conferences such as IEEE PerCom is an extremely important part of the graduate school experience, providing the opportunity to interact with peers and more senior researchers, thus having the opportunity to be exposed to leading edge work in the field of pervasive computing and aware networking, systems integration, aware services and applications. The travel support will enable US-based graduate students to attend and present their research results in this important IEEE conference. Since the travel support in most of the NSF awards is quite limited to students (who are authors), this fund will enable the awardees not to divert research funding for travel.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/15/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0822548</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sajal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Das</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sdas@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
