<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Electromagnetic Band Engineering for Novel THz Thermal Sources</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>289851</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Werbos</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: ECCS-0823864&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: Electromagnetic Band Engineering for Novel THz Thermal Sources&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI Name: Xin, Hao &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI Institution: University of Arizona&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Context:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research Objectives: The objective of this research work is to demonstrate a low cost and highly efficient thermal radiation-based THz source. The approach is to utilize advanced electromagnetic band engineering with electromagnetic crystals to modify the normal broad peak of the blackbody radiation in the infrared (IR) or higher frequency ranges to achieve a sharp radiation peak in the desired THz region. By incorporating semiconducting or liquid-crystal layers into the EBG structure, real-time tunable THz sources will also be considered. Novel modeling and simulation techniques that incorporate both the electromagnetic and thermal dynamics will be combined with state-of-the-art fabrication facilities and testing equipment to realize the optimized designs and experimentally demonstrate the basic ideas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merits: This research will explore several novel ideas of combining electromagnetic bandgap engineering with thermal sources to dramatically enhance their THz emission. The accurate modeling approaches, the advanced band engineering techniques, and tunable electromagnetic crystals to be studied will contribute significantly to the understanding and engineering of materials, blackbody radiation, and their applications in THz systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This research may lead to a completely new type of THz source and enable numerous interdisciplinary THz application concepts, including non-destructive medical imaging, remote sensing for transportation, bio-chemical agents and explosives detection for homeland security, all-weather high resolution radar, and high bandwidth communications. A concurrent and integrated research education component will include active participation of both graduate and undergraduate student and industrial researchers. It will emphasize outreach to underrepresented groups such as women and minorities and to local K-12 organizations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0823864</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ziolkowski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ziolkowski@ece.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hxin@ece.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7607</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY,POWER,ADAPTIVE SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>095E</Code>
      <Text>Photonic integration</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>101E</Code>
      <Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7219</Code>
      <Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY UNDERGRAD EDUCA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
