<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: P2C2--Continental Response to Abrupt Climate Change Post 70 ka: An Integrated Isotopic and Trace Element Study of Sierra Nevada Speleothems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>61555</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020108</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David J. Verardo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funding is provided to develop precisely dated, high-resolution speleothem-based records of climate change in the Sierra Nevada. The researchers are testing two hypotheses: (1) Sierra speleothems were precipitated in isotopic and geochemical equilibrium with drip waters, and thus archive short-lived changes in regional precipitation, temperature, and vegetation density; and (2) shifts in the position of the polar jet stream and associated winter storm tracks over mid-latitude western North America, forced by large-scale reorganization of the climate system, are archived in Sierra speleothem isotopic and geochemical compositions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To test these hypotheses, the researchers will: 1) complete in situ measurements of surface, soil and cave conditions; 2) analyze the isotopic and trace element contents in modern drip and source waters and recent calcite precipitates to define the natural intra- and inter-cave variability in drip-waters and speleothem calcites and to evaluate the presence of isotopic and trace element equilibrium precipitation of speleothem calcite; and 3) develop precisely dated (U-series with better than 2% precision) geochemical and isotopic time series (minimally multi-decadal-resolution) for stalagmites from three caves. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts involve improved understanding of the sensitivity of winter storm tracks and mean annual precipitation levels in the mid-latitudes of western North America to changes in northern high-latitude conditions with warming atmospheric temperatures. The project also helps support two graduate students involved with the research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0823541</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Warren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wsharp@bgc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Berkeley Geochronology Center</Name>
      <CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947091211</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106449200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2455 Ridge Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1530</Code>
      <Text>PALEOCLIMATE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1304</Code>
      <Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
