<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Interfacial Nucleation and Growth of Hierarchical Structures and Phases in Polymer Nanocomposites</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>196445</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert M. Wellek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: The research objective of the project is to investigate the basic physical mechanisms underlying the evolution of hierarchical structures and phases during pressure-induced crystallization of polymers containing dispersion of nano-particles. The research will address critical issues of nucleation and growth of polymer crystals at interfaces in polymer nano-composite systems. This will provide an insight into the adhesion process, which would point to methods to improve the interfacial properties of these material systems. Thermodynamic models with predictive capabilities will be developed for a wide range of nano-particle-reinforced polymer systems based on the nature of thermodynamically-driven interactions at the polymer-nano-particle interface. Successful completion of the research will provide generic guidelines governing pressure-induced processing of polymer nano-composites that fundamentally affect the structure and composition on a nanometer-size scale, in a manner similar to nano-grained metals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The understanding of physical processes will enable high strength-toughness combination to be achieved in polymer nano-composite systems, allowing use of thinner sections or components with consequent energy savings. Additionally, enhanced scratch resistance of nano-structured composites would promote their use in storage devices, biomedical components, and applications requiring optical transparency. Graduate and undergraduate engineering students will benefit through involvement in research and integration of research with existing curriculum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0824001</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Devesh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Misra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dmisra2@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Louisiana at Lafayette</Name>
      <CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>705032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3374826203</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 University Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
