<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Stratigraphic Controls on Freshwater Beneath the Continental Shelf</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>227002</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Janecek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will use high resolution multiple-channel (MCS) and chirp seismic data to characterize the stratigraphy and sedimentation patterns of continental shelf sediments off Martha?s Vineyard, Massachusetts. These sediments host an extensive freshwater aquifer which is out of equilibrium with its environment. The research will combine these geophysical methods with hydrological modeling to better describe the distribution, chemistry, and the emplacement mechanisms of this unique aquifer. From the modeling efforts quantitative predictions will be made of the forcing mechanisms that affect groundwater flow in such aquifers over geological time periods. Such aquifers have not received much study to date and could potentially provide a source of water and nutrients to marine coastal environments and thus be an important and overlooked component of the water cycle. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: Freshwater aquifers as these could potentially serve as an important resource for human consumption in coastal regions. The research will support graduate students at each of the institutions of the three PIs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0824497</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lizarralde</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>danl@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
