<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Femtosecond-Laser Processing of Hybrid Micro- and Nano-Structures in Glass</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399373</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to use femtosecond (fs)-laser processing to tailor-make nano-and microstructures in glass with a degree of precision and resolution unattainable by, for example, conventional patterning and lithography techniques. The approach is based on controlling the laser processing and subsequent heat treatment conditions to independently control the creation of structures on a range of length scales. Processing-structure relationships will form the central theme of this research project. The effect of fs laser processing variables on the bulk and interfacial structure of the beam-exposed zones will be investigated. Experiments will involve characterization of the structural modification using SEM and TEM as well as confocal Raman and fluorescence microscopy. An optimized set of processing parameters will be determined and used to fabricate merged three-dimensional architectures with features on micrometer and nanometer scales.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Developing the fundamental understanding of this hybrid fabrication process will lead to applications in optical device engineering (e.g. waveguides, couplers), while also making a positive impact on the broader field of nanomanufacturing (e.g. ablation machining, precision drilling) and microelectronics (e.g. ion-implanted semiconductors, photomask repair). This project will be highly synergistic in both the research and education components. On the one hand research students will focus on experiments that will build the foundations of fs-laser processing as a versatile tool to engineer micro and nano-scale architectures in glasses. On the other, the project will produce highly trained graduate students well prepared to work in a cross- disciplinary setting who will have received training in optical materials processing and engineering as well as sophisticated instrumentation, including ultrafast lasers and state-of-the-art electron microscopy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Materials Processing &amp; Manufacturing (MPM) Program, of the Civil, Mechanical, and Manufacturing Innovation (CMMI) Division, by the Thermal Transport Processes (TTP) Program, of the Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems (CBET) Division, and by funding provided from the Directorate for Engineering (ENG) to support Inter Divisional Research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0825572</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Denise</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krol</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dmkrol@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Subhash</FirstName>
      <LastName>Risbud</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shrisbud@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1402</Code>
      <Text>BIOCHEMICAL &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>080E</Code>
      <Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>081E</Code>
      <Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
