<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>New Methods for Measuring, Monitoring and Evaluating Post-Disaster Recovery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>288111</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dennis Wenger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NEW METHODS FOR MEASURING, MONITORING AND EVALUATING POST-DISASTER RECOVERY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A Research Collaboration between the University at Buffalo, ImageCat, University of British Columbia, University of Delaware and University of Memphis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Post-disaster recovery - one of the phases of the disaster management cycle - is a complex physical, social, economic, environmental, and political process. It lasts years, requires enormous financial and other resources, and can define the character of the affected communities for years to come. The literature includes a number of theoretical frameworks of recovery, and many empirical case studies of historic events. The empirical studies have often focused on a single dimension of recovery, such as households and housing, and they have typically relied on interviews, focus groups, and one-time surveys for data gathering. This literature offers rich cross-sectional insights into recovery at a given point in time, but limited views of changes over time or systematic, quantitative empirical descriptions of recovery over large areas. An excellent opportunity exists now to address some of these limitations using newly available high-resolution satellite imagery; previously underutilized statistical data, and advanced field survey techniques that capture a detailed geographically-referenced record of recovery through photographs, video, and observations. Given the importance of recovery, limitations of previous research on it, and new technological opportunities, this study will develop innovative methods for systematically and quantitatively measuring and monitoring post-disaster recovery. Using Hurricane Katrina as a case study, the proposed project will achieve the following objectives: (1) Develop methods to process and interpret remote-sensing data to describe the physical and socio-economic manifestations of post-disaster recovery; (2) Obtain and compile quantitative and qualitative recovery data from: remote-sensing, field reconnaissance surveys, secondary statistical sources, interviews, and surveys; (3) Develop methods to analyze and synthesize the recovery data to comprehensively measure and monitor recovery; and (4) Demonstrate application of the new methods within the case study area. Improved tracking of recovery will serve as a critical first step for future efforts to better explain and evaluate recovery by addressing questions such as:&lt;br/&gt;- For a disaster that has just occurred, over what timeframes and in what ways is recovery likely to unfold?&lt;br/&gt;- Why is recovery proceeding in a particular way?&lt;br/&gt;- How are recovery speed and character correlated with various pre- and post-disaster decisions and actions?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Enhancing our ability to address such questions will bring many practical societal benefits. Governments, policy makers, and local organizations can apply findings to examine the impact of their decisions and ultimately to improve plans for and actions supporting future recovery efforts. The systematic examination of recovery in both a qualitative and quantitative way using multi-source data can empower communities and give them evidence to support their experiences of the recovery process. It can open a new source of dialogue and discourse that could have practical repercussions for the creation of resilient communities, for the distribution of aid and resources, as well as theoretical discussions on the potential identification of different types of recovery, dependent on their initial conditions and key decisions post-disaster. Further, by augmenting existing ways of empirically measuring recovery, the project will advance the state-of-the-art in post-disaster recovery studies. It will support the continuing development of a theory of post-disaster recovery through verifying or modifying existing theories.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0825747</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sechang@interchange.ubc.ca</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eguchi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rte@imagecatinc.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Beverley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bja@imagecatinc.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davidson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdavidso@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arleen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aahill@memphis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
      <CityName>Amherst</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0304000</Code>
      <Name>Disaster &amp; Natural Hazard</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1638</Code>
      <Text>INFRAST MGMT &amp; EXTREME EVENTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>041E</Code>
      <Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>042E</Code>
      <Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
