<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Optimal Model Reduction for Aerodynamics Boundary Feedback Control</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Chiu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this proposal is to develop methods of model reduction and feedback control for aerodynamic flows, and in particular surface control of turbulent flows. The research will result in active flow control methods that are general enough to apply to nonlinear partial differential models, such as the Navier-Stokes equations that govern turbulence. The research plan progresses from the development of reduced order models for the two-dimensional Burgers? equation that govern a nonlinear convective flow, to unsteady flows governed by the Navier-Stokes equation. A systematic approach that allows surface actuation and sensing, such as in control of the air flow over an airplane wing, to appear in a natural way in the reduced models will be developed. Deliverables include methods for modeling, analysis, and design, demonstration of the methods via simulation and/or experimental measurements, and documentation of research results and engineering student education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research will provide an opportunity to integrate feedback control with active flow control with applications to drag and noise reduction, lift enhancement, and ultimately the ability to use flow control devices in place of traditional aircraft control surfaces through separation control or virtual aerodynamic shaping. Drag reduction will result in improved fuel efficiency of air and ground vehicles, and therefore increased range, loiter time, and payload. The research plan is complemented by an educational plan, with particular emphasis upon the cultivation of a diverse undergraduate and graduate population and inclusion of under-represented minorities. The plan includes improvements in essential courses and creation of undergraduate capstone design projects. Teaching techniques focus on increasing student involvement in the classroom by integrating teaching and research activities, utilizing student and mentor teams incorporating graduate and undergraduate students, and emphasizing both project-oriented integrated systems design and dissemination of results through presentations and publications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0825921</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Seddik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Djouadi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>djouadi@eecs.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
