<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nuclear Nano-Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360007</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce M. Kramer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In the last two decades, the nanotechnology revolution has led to a number of new materials, novel processing techniques, and complex nano-systems with extraordinary functionalities. This program will push nanotechnology into new frontiers in nuclear engineering. It explores interdisciplinary research opportunities that bridge nuclear engineering and nanotechnology. &lt;br/&gt;Novel nano-materials and nano-structures will be used to develop new means of harnessing nuclear energy and efficiently convert it into electric and optical energy. Long-life, miniaturized nuclear batteries will be developed to provide sustained ?ÝW-level power for support of mission-critical micro- and nano-systems. A contamination-free fabrication technique will be developed to monolithically integrate micro-scale radioactive isotopes with on-chip nano-devices. New devices for power generation and sensing will be explored for homeland security and biomedical applications. This program will also leverage recent advances in novel nanostructures for the detection of radioactive materials. &lt;br/&gt;This interdisciplinary research, fusing nanotechnology and nuclear engineering, will spark new opportunities in their respective areas of science and technology. Isotope micro-power sources will dramatically improve the operational life of micro- and nano- systems used for unattended applications, which span remote exploration, unmanned military operations and implanted devices. The chip-scale development of micro-isotope sources will enable detailed studies of radiation effects at the cellular level. This may lead to improved cancer treatment using radiation therapy. The use of novel nano-structures promises to speed the development of high-sensitivity radiation detectors for homeland security and for environmental protection. The proposed education efforts will offer students a refreshing perspective that bridges the small nano-world with giant nuclear power plants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0826289</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin Peng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kchen@engr.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1385</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL STUDIES AND ANALYSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7681</Code>
      <Text>ENG NNI SPECIAL STUDIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
