<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanoscale and Deterministic Doping of Semiconductors Via Molecular Monolayers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>243297</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce M. Kramer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>One of the major challenges towards scaling of the electronic devices to the nanoscale regime is attaining controlled doping of semiconductor materials with atomic accuracy. To overcome this challenge, the PI's group has recently developed a novel surface doping approach based on the self-assembled monolayer formation on the surface of silicon substrates. The purpose of this proposed project is to better understand the fundamental science associated with this doping approach while exploring its feasibility for the fabrication of future nanoelectronics by (i) carefully analyzing the impurity content incorporation, (ii) demonstrating ultrashallow, sub 10-nm junctions by using laser annealing for the diffusion of the dopants, (iii) mapping the dopant diffusion rates and mechanisms, and (iv) extending the process to non silicon substrates, such as gallium arsenide. &lt;br/&gt;The proposed project may lead the way for addressing the crucial need for nanoscale doping, and if successful, the monolayer doping method may have a major impact in the nanoelectronics field with the potential of every manufactured transistor and electronic device utilizing this approach. The project will involve the training of one graduate and one undergraduate student. Furthermore, the project will be show cased as part of an open lab on Cal Day, during which students from local high schools will be allowed to tour the PI's lab and learn about the project. The nature of this work and the training of the involved students will be highly interdisciplinary, bridging the fields of chemistry and electrical engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0826145</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
      <LastName>Javey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ajavey@eecs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
