<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Comparative Innovation Policy: Best Practice in National Technology Programs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>35000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04030005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>National Center For S&amp;E Statistics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence Rausch</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The global economy is characterized by increasing locational competition to attract the resources necessary to develop leading-edge technologies as drivers of regional and national growth. One means of facilitating such growth and improving national competitiveness is to improve the operation of the national innovation system. This involves national technology development and innovation programs designed to support research on new technologies, enhance the commercial return on national research, and facilitate the production of globally competitive products. The Board on Science, Technology, and Economic Policy (STEP) is studying selected foreign innovation programs and comparing them with major U.S. programs. The analysis includes a review of the goals, concept, structure, operation, funding levels, and evaluation of foreign programs similar to major U.S. programs, e.g., innovation awards, S&amp;T parks, and consortia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Statement of Objectives &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As part of this review of Comparative Innovation Policy, the STEP Board is convening a symposium on "Understanding Research Science &amp; Technology Parks: Global Best Practice." The conference will bring together leading figures from governments, universities, and science and technology parks, both from the United States and around the world. The goal of the conference is to &lt;br/&gt;increase policy makers' understanding of the role of S&amp;T parks as sources of innovation and regional growth, while also reviewing their contributions to government missions and to the commercialization of university research. An important characteristic of S&amp;T parks is their diversity. Accordingly, the conference will examine a broad range of S&amp;T parks, including both university- and laboratory-based parks as well as the large-scale industrial models often undertaken in Asia and Europe. While recognizing the diversity of objectives and the differences in scope and scale of activity, the conference will seek to identify common challenges faced by S&amp;T parks both in the U.S. &lt;br/&gt;and abroad, including evaluation and the need for appropriate metrics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Committee is assessing foreign programs using a standard template, convening a series of meetings to gather data from responsible officials and program managers, and encouraging a systematic dissemination of information and analysis as a means of better understanding the transition of university and laboratory research into commercial products with the goal of improving the operation of U.S. programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to generating greater awareness of foreign policies and programs, especially among Members of Congress and their staff, the study will produce an overview report that includes findings and recommendations addressing the issues outlined above at the conclusion of the overall study. These findings and recommendations will then be widely disseminated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0827103</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wessner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cwessner@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/21/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8802</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH &amp; DEVELOPMENT STATIST</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
