<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Biologically Inspired Robotic Microswimmers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>259800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitrios Papavassiliou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0828167&lt;br/&gt;Kim&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bacterial flagellar propulsion represents an extraordinary system in nature for generating motion at the micrometer scale due to their unique molecular polymeric structure adapting to different shapes, depending on the local chemical and flow conditions. Their motion induces a local flow that can be used to propel cells as well as much larger structures through a fluid environment. This collaborative research team plans to understand, to model and to exploit the physics of flagellar propulsion for use in engineered microfluidic systems. The objective of the program is to understand the fundamental scientific principles that govern the assembly and operation of flagella-propelled devices (both single swimmers and collectively-powered devices), as well as to demonstrate the enabling technologies necessary to harness polymeric protein nanostructures such as bacterial flagellar filaments on microstructures for use in micron-scale engineered propulsion systems. This collaborative proposal between Drexel University and Brown University is the first to focus on the specific characteristics associated with the polymorphic transformation of bacterial flagellar filaments to demonstrate the ability to move larger engineered elements through a microfluidic landscape in a controlled and directed manner. Fundamental scientific merits addressed by this proposal include using nanoscale flagellar filaments in engineered systems for micron-scale propulsion. Basic questions are to be answered regarding the mechanisms leading to self-coordination of flagellar filaments in responses to a variety of external stimuli. Possible coordination of flagellar filaments to transport microstructures in various microfluidic environments will be examined, thus enabling an entirely new class of swimming robotic systems with applications to bio-engineered actuators, drug delivery systems, and machines for micron-scale transport and assembly. Demonstration of the control of bacterial flagellar filaments at micro- and nanoscales and the ability to integration information technology with bio and nanotechnology will have great impact. The program will have an intensive outreach component, including active recruitment and training of women and underrepresented minorities engineers. The program will leverage and expand existing and proven programs already in place at Brown and Drexel. The PIs will additionally conduct outreach to inner-city high school student and teacher populations in both Providence and Philadelphia through the BROWNOUT (Brown) and INSPIRE (Drexel) programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0828167</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>MinJun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjkim@lyle.smu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>060E</Code>
      <Text>BIO-TRANSPORT &amp; FLUID MECH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
