<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>National Workshop on High-Confidence Automotive Cyber-Physical Systems. To be Held April 3-4, 2008 in Troy, Michigan.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29664</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Radhakisan S. Baheti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The purpose of this workshop, to be held April 3-4, 2008 in Troy, Michigan, is to provide an open forum for research leaders and visionaries to develop a roadmap for the deployment of cyber-physical systems (CPS) in the automotive sector. Participants come from academia, industry, and government. The workshop considers both the opportunities for transformative impacts of CPS in the automotive sector as well as the challenges presented to the CPS research community by demanding automotive applications. The goals of the workshop are to develop a vision, determine and highlight technical and scientific challenges, and identify promising research approaches.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to intellectual merit, the workshop addresses an important opportunity for an industry segment that is important to U.S. industrial competitiveness in the global market and that provides an opportunity to bring a demanding application domain into consideration by the cyber-physical systems researcher community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to broader impact, the workshop itself and follow-on research and other activities have the potential to have a significant impact on the competitiveness of the U.S. automotive industry, as well as on important societal issues including energy efficiency for automobiles and highway safety. The workshop also has the potential to provide engineering and computer science researchers with insight into an important and challenging application domain that can improve the intellectual depth and the practical application of university research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0829894</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ragunathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rajkumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rajkumar@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7423</Code>
      <Text>Energy collection &amp; storage</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
