<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Learning sparse representations for restoration and classification: Theory, Computations, and Applications in Image, Video, and Multimodal Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>305553</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cozzens</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Efficient signal representation is critical in virtually all &lt;br/&gt;disciplines of science. Sparse representations have recently drawn much &lt;br/&gt;attention from the signal processing community. The basic model &lt;br/&gt;consists of considering that natural signals admit a sparse &lt;br/&gt;decomposition as a combination of very few atoms in some redundant &lt;br/&gt;dictionary. Recent results have shown that learning overcomplete &lt;br/&gt;non-parametric dictionaries for image representation, instead of using &lt;br/&gt;classical off-the-shelf ones, significantly improves numerous image and &lt;br/&gt;video processing tasks. This research aims at developing a &lt;br/&gt;comprehensive theoretical, computational, and practical framework for &lt;br/&gt;learning sparse representations for numerous signal analysis tasks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;First, the research concentrates on learning sparse representations for &lt;br/&gt;global and local robust image classification tasks, proposing &lt;br/&gt;formulations with both sparse reconstruction and class discrimination &lt;br/&gt;components, jointly optimized during dictionary learning. Multiscale &lt;br/&gt;dictionary learning and investigating a number of critical optimization &lt;br/&gt;challenges are integral components of this project as well. The &lt;br/&gt;framework of learning multiscale sparse representations is then &lt;br/&gt;extended to multimodal data. As in the work with images and video, the &lt;br/&gt;energies proposed for multimodality consider both reconstructive and &lt;br/&gt;discriminative terms, learning the optimal representations both for the &lt;br/&gt;given data and the given tasks. In addition to image, video, and audio, &lt;br/&gt;other signal modalities studied include tensors, which are critical in &lt;br/&gt;diffusion MRI, and bring the additional challenge of developing sparse &lt;br/&gt;representations for non-flat data. The proposed work is also extended &lt;br/&gt;to learning to sense, where combined with the learning of the optimal &lt;br/&gt;dictionaries, the learning of the best linear sensing procedures is &lt;br/&gt;studied.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0829700</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Guillermo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sapiro</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>guillermo.sapiro@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>4720</Code>
      <Text>SIGNAL PROCESSING SYS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
