<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Group Travel Grant-7th International Symposium of ESIQIE - IPN, Mexico City, Mexico</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3206</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert M. Wellek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0829971&lt;br/&gt;Panagiotopoulos&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a group travel support ($4,508) for participation of four faculty members from U.S. universities in the 7th International Symposium of ESIQIE-IPN. The 7th International Symposium will take place in Mexico City, Mexico on the campus Institute Polytechnical National (IPN) from May 20-22, 2008.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual focus areas of the Symposium are the state of the Chemical and Metallurgical process engineering from both the industrial and academic point of view, and the energy needs for society in the 21st century. The potential broader impacts of sending a group of U.S. professors to this Symposium include (a) creation of new and strengthening of existing U.S.-Mexico academic research interactions, (b) enhancement of interactions of U.S. faculty with PEMEX, the Mexican Petroleum company as well as other industrial participants of the symposium (c) improved understanding of the impact of globalization and NAFTA on U.S. chemical manufacturing and (d) international dissemination of NSF-supported research results.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 7th International Symposium will be chaired by Prof. Luis A. Galicia-Luna. The U.S. participants to be supported are Prof. Ram B. Gupta (Auburn Univ.), Prof. Kenneth R. Hall (Texas A&amp;M), Prof. Athanassios Z. Panagiotopoulos (Princeton Univ.) and Prof. Philip E. Savage (U. of Michigan). As stated above, the focus of the Symposium is the state of the Chemical and Metallurgical process engineering from both the industrial and academic point of view, and the energy needs for society in the 21st century. The symposium is normally attended by close to 100 Mexican and other Latin American professors and students. Some of the non-USA participants ultimately attend USA Universities to initial and complete collaborative research projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ESIQIE - IPN Symposium organizers will provide support for local&lt;br/&gt;lodging, thus significantly reducing the net cost to the NSF of USA participation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/26/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0829971</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Athanassios</FirstName>
      <LastName>Panagiotopoulos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>azp@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
