<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Biomedical Innovations Using Implementation-Aware Agile Sensing and Signal Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cozzens</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Title: Biomedical Innovations Using Implementation-Aware &lt;br/&gt; Agile Sensing and Signal Processing&lt;br/&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Medical condition diagnosis is heavily based on sensor measurements &lt;br/&gt;and their processing. These measurements correspond to waveforms &lt;br/&gt;that propagate over the complex body environment and are transformed &lt;br/&gt;linearly or nonlinearly according to the characteristic environment properties. &lt;br/&gt;However, the medical community does not fully exploit the potentials of &lt;br/&gt;advanced processing matched to nonlinear structures or modern sensor &lt;br/&gt;technologies such as waveform agility that leads to significant estimation&lt;br/&gt;performance improvements. This research exploits advanced &lt;br/&gt;implementation-aware sensing and processing techniques to improve &lt;br/&gt;medical diagnosis by: (a) efficient processing using compressed sensing &lt;br/&gt;and nonlinear time-varying spectral methods; (b) estimation of environment &lt;br/&gt;descriptors and disease state parameters combined with waveform-agile&lt;br/&gt;sensing; and (c) mapping estimation and waveform-agile sensing algorithms &lt;br/&gt;onto field-programmable gate arrays. This framework brings revolutionary &lt;br/&gt;advances in diagnosing, treating, and tracking disease states that are &lt;br/&gt;otherwise difficult to obtain as advanced processing techniques are either &lt;br/&gt;not available or too costly. The investigators also design on-line software &lt;br/&gt;toolboxes with sensing experiments for use in outreach programs to recruit &lt;br/&gt;and retain freshmen and underrepresented student populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research integrates advanced signal processing, stochastic Bayesian &lt;br/&gt;estimation, and waveform-agile sensing with implementation-aware &lt;br/&gt;algorithms to improve estimation of disease states. The investigators study&lt;br/&gt;time-frequency techniques matched to nonlinear structures to process biomedical &lt;br/&gt;data. Compressive sensing methodologies are developed that reduce the&lt;br/&gt;number of required measurements and allow for alternative computational &lt;br/&gt;algorithms. Mathematical descriptors are designed to model disease states using&lt;br/&gt;time-varying transfer functions. Sequential Bayesian techniques and waveform &lt;br/&gt;adaptation are used to estimate information. Algorithm reconstruction procedures &lt;br/&gt;are developed that trade high performance for reduced implementation cost. &lt;br/&gt;Finally, the investigators design algorithms cognizant of complexity and memory requirements.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0830799</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spanias</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spanias@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chaitali</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chakrabarti</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chaitali@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Antonia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Papandreou-Suppappola</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>papandreou@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
