<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: NEDG: Throughput Optimization in Wireless Mesh Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph Lyles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This collaborative project investigates a number of fundamental &lt;br/&gt;problems that are very critical to wireless mesh network (WMN) &lt;br/&gt;throughput optimization. Wireless mesh networking is believed to &lt;br/&gt;be the most effective and efficient technology for the last-mile &lt;br/&gt;data connection to the Internet. The proposed research targets &lt;br/&gt;to solve the following challenges: 1) Throughput optimization in &lt;br/&gt;MR-MC WMNs: the complexity of throughput-optimal scheduling, &lt;br/&gt;real-time logical topology characterization and inference, the &lt;br/&gt;joint exploitation of both rate diversity and channel diversity, &lt;br/&gt;and game theory based throughput optimization. 2) Non information &lt;br/&gt;theory based approaches to throughput optimization in multi-hop &lt;br/&gt;MIMO-enabled WMNs: stochastically modeling different aspects of &lt;br/&gt;the mesh network, constructing Network Utility Maximization &lt;br/&gt;formulations, and applying Information Geometric Programming to &lt;br/&gt;solve global optimization problems. 3) Biologically-inspired WMN &lt;br/&gt;design for throughput optimizatio n. 4) A testbed to accomplish &lt;br/&gt;experimental tasks to validate the effectiveness of the design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is in nature multidisciplinary. It requires the &lt;br/&gt;joint effort from computer science, electrical engineering, &lt;br/&gt;mathematics, statistics, and biology, and therefore has the &lt;br/&gt;potential to inspire revolutionary methodologies that could be &lt;br/&gt;applied to many domains. In addition, the novelty of the proposed &lt;br/&gt;research has strong impact on wireless research. Furthermore, the &lt;br/&gt;success of this project is able to enhance the four universities? &lt;br/&gt;ability to educate, through the multi-disciplinary research effort, &lt;br/&gt;future scientists and engineers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0831852</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hyeong-Ah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Choi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hchoi@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiuzhen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cheng@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200522000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2029946255</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2121 Eye Street NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
