<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Molecular Programming Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1682665</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There is great potential for adapting biopolymer molecules such as RNA and DNA to meaningful computational tasks and purposes. Having the ability to program molecules at many orders of magnitude larger scale than at present using new algorithms and software analogues has the potential to change the way we analyze, understand and manipulate molecular systems. It can lead to practical applications of significant benefit to society across a wide range of national initiatives in materials, nano-biotechnology, tissue engineering, regenerative medicine, and many other emerging areas. This ambitious Expedition addresses the exciting challenge of developing initial foundational steps toward creating large-scale molecular programs. This experimental technology Expedition aims to develop a functional abstraction hierarchy to create molecular programming languages, compilers, tools and models; a theoretical framework for the analysis and design of molecular programs; validation of the above utilizing molecular programs with orders of magnitude higher scale of components than at present; and testing of the developed molecular programming technologies on real-world applications. This high-risk/high-payoff research will increase our understanding of the relationship between computation and the physical world, how information can be stored and processed by molecules, and the possibilities and limits of what can be computed and fabricated. Outreach includes summer undergraduate and minority student research fellowships, K-12 visiting days, boot camps, workshops and many other efforts to create a broader molecular programming research community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0832773</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Klavins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>klavins@ee.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7796</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7931</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7723</Code>
      <Text>EXPERIMENTAL EXPEDITIONS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
