<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The 52nd International Conference on Electron, Ion and Photon Beam Technology and Nanofabrication, 2008</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Shaochen Chen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is to request support in the amount $5000 to enable students to attend the 52nd International Conference on Electron, Ion and Photon Beam Technology and Nanofabrication, 2008, to be held in Portland, Oregon, May 27 to May 30, 2008. In the fields of nanofabrication, electron and ion-beam lithographies, photon and imprint lithographies, particle-beam optics, and forefront applications of nanofabrication, this conference is preeminent. The requested travel aid will enable students to present their research to a high level international scientific community. They will observe how scientists and engineers exchange innovative ideas and other information at conferences, and they?ll hear first-hand presentations of up-to-date research results in nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Learning how a technical conference serves as a venue for conveying information to other is an important element of a student?s education. &lt;br/&gt;Also important is leaning how to present, in a cogent and understandable way, the results of one?s research. The requested support will help to accomplish these ends. At the conference students will make important personal contacts and learn of employment opportunities. In a special student breakfast, to be held on Friday, the conference organizers will describe to the students how the conference program is put together and how papers are selected for oral or poster presentation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0834505</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hismith@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
