<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Second International Workshop on Design Creativity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>17660</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pamela L. Jennings</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Design creativity plays an essential role for development of new industrial and mission critical products and systems. Yet our understanding of design creativity and our ability to support creative design are very limited. This Design Creativity Workshop creates a forum for the key researchers around the world in the field of design and creativity to present and exchange their broad perspectives, argue about their similarities and differences, and discuss the future directions of both fundamental research on design creativity and practical development of creative IT tools for supporting creative design. The workshop participants present their ideas and research results on the following topics: Creative design and design creativity, Characteristics of creative thinking in design, Cognitive and computational models of design creativity, Collaboration and design creativity, Computational creativity for design, Bio-inspired creative design, Taxonomy of design creativity, IT tools for creative design, Design creativity &amp; education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0836254</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yjin@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
