<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.- Africa Workshop on Globalizing Engineering Education: Lessons Learned from US-Africa Partnerships</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>DeAndra Beck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award funds an international workshop with the following goals: to identify effective learning models that incorporate a global dimension in the education of engineering students, and to identify the infrastructure and resources required to maintain that global dimension. On October 17-18, 2008 the workshop will bring together invited engineering faculty from the United States, their African university partners, and participating students from the U.S. and Africa. The workshop will be held in Cape Town, South Africa prior to the American Society for Engineering Education's 7th Annual Global Colloquium and the International Federation of Engineering Education Societies' Global Summit. Many of the workshop's participants will also be attending the ASEE and IFEES meetings and so can immediately discuss the workshop's conclusions with engineering educators from around the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Engineering is increasingly becoming a globalized profession by involving multi-national teams in engineering design, technical services, and marketing. However, the typical undergraduate engineering curriculum is often too full of required technical courses to allow time for any foreign language or study abroad courses. The Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology (ABET) requires eleven outcomes of all accredited U.S. engineering programs, including one that says programs must demonstrate that their students attain "the broad education necessary to understand the impact of engineering solutions in a global, economic, environmental and societal context." Furthermore, the U.S. National Academy of Engineering predicts that "the engineer of 2020 will have to understand how to adapt solutions, in an ethical way, to the constraints of developing countries." &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In order to become more multi-culturally sensitive, globally competent, and globally competitive, the U.S. engineering profession must provide opportunities for aspiring young engineers to learn the requisite skills and attitudes. Despite widespread accolades from students on the benefits of international initiatives, these initiatives often flounder because of lack of resources, lack of institutional support, and logistical problems. At this workshop, participants will share knowledge gained from their experience in running engineering education projects in Africa, including NSF-funded activities such as Research Experiences for Undergraduate-Sites and International Research Experience for Students projects, as well as capstone courses, and other curricular initiatives such as partnerships with the Peace Corps. The workshop participants will summarize the lessons learned, challenges, and opportunities, and so contribute to a better understanding of how to globalize American engineering education and how to effectively partner for mutual benefit with engineering educators from other nations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is co-funded by NSF's Division of Engineering Education and Centers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0836873</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ward</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ward.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
      <LastName>Christy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>christy.14@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6142923732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
