<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Young Faculty and Graduate Students to Attend the Symposium on "Active and Responsive Surfaces" at the ACS National Meeting, 3/22-26/09, Salt Lake City, UT</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070012</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL: A central challenge in polymers research today is the creation of materials that can dynamically alter their structures and properties on demand, or in response to changes in their environment. Surfaces and interfaces represent a particularly attractive area of focus in the design of responsive materials, since the small amount of material that resides at an interface exerts disproportionately large effects on many properties such as wetability, adhesivity, optical appearance and bioactivity. Thus, remarkable changes in properties may be accomplished through the application of relatively mild stimuli to materials with responsive surfaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL: The purpose of this symposium is to bring together established leaders and rising stars in the area of active and responsive surfaces of five half-day sessions are planned, with a total of 30-35 oral presentations describing the preparation, characterization and application of responsive materials systems at surfaces and interfaces, including grafted polymer layers, self-assembled monolayers, multi-layer coatings, and micro fabricated structures. All of the funds from the NSF will be used to support travel of faculty members in the early stages of their careers, and graduate students, who might not have other funding to allow them to participate. Attention will be give to groups traditionally under-represented in science and engineering disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0838022</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hayward</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rhayward@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
