<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Geomagnetic Field as Recorded on Iceland and Jan Mayen: Key to Field Structure at High Northern Latitudes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>45402</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stephen S. Harlan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Some rocks as they form, act like magnetic tape, thus proving recordings of the Earth's&lt;br/&gt;magnetic field through time. Data from such records play an important role in a variety&lt;br/&gt;of geophysical studies of the Earth, including plate tectonic reconstructions,&lt;br/&gt;magnetostratigraphy, and studies of the behavior of the ancient geomagnetic field. Over&lt;br/&gt;the past four decades the fundamental assumption made in many studies using the&lt;br/&gt;magnetic vectors coaxed from rocks has been that the average direction of the Earth's&lt;br/&gt;magnetic field corresponds to one that would have been produced by a bar magnetic&lt;br/&gt;centered in the Earth that is aligned with the spin axis. This implies that the dip of the&lt;br/&gt;ancient magnetic field directions vary from horizontal near the (paleo) equator to vertical&lt;br/&gt;near the (paleo) poles. The assumption is that paleomagnetic data are of sufficient&lt;br/&gt;accuracy to enable their use in reconstructing the positions of lithospheric plates&lt;br/&gt;through time. Recently, researchers have begun to reexamine the fundamental data&lt;br/&gt;underlying models of the ancient geomagnetic field and are finding that the most glaring&lt;br/&gt;deficiency in the existing data base is a dearth of high quality data, including information&lt;br/&gt;about the field strength, from high northerly latitudes. It is possible that the solid inner&lt;br/&gt;core influences the generation of the Earth's magnetic field, which takes place in the&lt;br/&gt;fluid outer core. The convective regimes inside a cylinder parallel to the Earth's&lt;br/&gt;rotational axis that is tangent to the inner core (the tangent cylinder) are thought to be&lt;br/&gt;different. Therefore, data from north (or south) of the tangent cylinder are of special&lt;br/&gt;interest in the theory of geomagnetism and are key to testing the validity of one of the&lt;br/&gt;fundamental tenets of paleomagnetic study. Opportunities to sample such high latitude&lt;br/&gt;volcanics are few and far between. Researchers from Scripps Institute of&lt;br/&gt;Oceanography, in conjunction with their Norwegian collaborators, are conducting&lt;br/&gt;paleomagnetic sampling and analysis of suitable sites from Jan Mayen, a remote&lt;br/&gt;volcanic island in the Arctic along the mid-Atlantic rift, northeast of Iceland. Samples&lt;br/&gt;from this study are producing high quality paleomagnetic, paleointensity, and&lt;br/&gt;geochronological data from high northern latitudes that are essential to an enhanced&lt;br/&gt;understanding of paleosecular variation, the time averaged field and its long term&lt;br/&gt;variations. Geochronologic work for this study, conducted by collaborators from Oregon&lt;br/&gt;State University, is providing an enhanced understanding of the age and duration of&lt;br/&gt;mafic magmatic activity at this isolated volcanic island. In addition to the scientific&lt;br/&gt;objectives of this work, the project is contributing to the training and support of doctoral&lt;br/&gt;researcher at Scripps who is a member of an underrepresented group in the earth&lt;br/&gt;sciences, and results are being used in outreach activities that benefit in the&lt;br/&gt;development of K-12 teaching materials and web seminars for the National Science&lt;br/&gt;Teacher Association.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0838169</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koppers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>akoppers@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
