<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Junior Scientists to Attend a Workshop on the Transport Properties of the Lower Mantle</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robin Reichlin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The transport properties of the lower mantle, such as the electrical conductivity, thermal&lt;br/&gt;conductivity and viscosity are important to the understanding of mantle dynamics and thermal evolution of the mantle. An international workshop is scheduled to take place in northeastern Japan for 3 days between October 21 and 24. Agenda for the three days have speakers from the areas of experimental and theoretical mineral physics, observation electromagnetism, seismology, and mantle viscosity. The organizers are Kei&lt;br/&gt;Hirose from Titech, Japan David A. Yuen from University of Minnesota and David Rubie from Bayreuth Geoscience Institut, Germany. They anticipate attendance of around 50 to 55 scientists from around the world. Japanese funding for this event is substantial, around $36,000. Funds will cover the airfare of 5 to 6 junior scientists from American institutions. Findings of this workshop will be disseminated in a special issue of Physics of the Earth and Planetary Interior and put the abstracts on a website at the Minnesota Supercomputer Institute.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0838228</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yuen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>daveyuen@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
