<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Studies of Solar Wind -- Magnetosphere Interactions using Observations of ULF Waves at Manned Stations as Part of an Extensive Ground Array</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>269047</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vladimir O. Papitashvili</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). The proposal seeks funding to: (a) continue ongoing studies that compare ground observations of Pc 1-2 waves with waves and ions observed by Cluster and THEMIS spacecrafts, both on dayside closed field lines (especially in relation to geomagnetic storms, to characterize their role in depleting the ring current and radiation belt electrons) and in the lobe/mantle region, to investigate whether they can be used to monitor the transport of magnetosheath plasma toward the tail; (b) compare ground-based observations of Pc 3-4 waves at cusp and polar cap latitudes with data from Cluster and THEMIS to investigate their propagation from their upstream source into and through the dayside magnetosphere and polar cap; and (c) continue recent satellite-ground studies of Pi 1B pulsations and substorms, in particular by comparing multi-station ground data with data from FAST, Cluster, and THEMIS spacecrafts, and by quantitatively analyzing multi-station data to test methods for inferring source locations, and by using combined ground and satellite Pi 1B data to probe the physical link between the onset location and the ionospheric signature of substorms. It is expected that the project will continue to play a significant role in a variety of studies of geospace phenomena including the solar wind?magnetosphere interaction and geomagnetic storms and substorms. The analysis effort associated with this project is highly suitable for involvement and research training of both graduate and undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>269047</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0838917</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Engebretson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>engebret@augsburg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Augsburg College</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554541338</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6123301184</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2211 Riverside Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0311000</Code>
      <Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
