<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: An Uncooled Multi-color Resonant Tunneling Quantum Dot Infrared Photodetector</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a high-performance uncooled sensor to accommodate multiple spectral-band infrared detection at high operating temperatures. The photon detector will operate in the 3 to 5 and 8 to 10 micron spectral bands. In addition, the infrared sensor will be fabricated out of III-V nano-semiconductor materials. The nano-material will be composed of features, such as quantum dots and wells, and superlattices, for intra-band photon detection and dark current suppression. That is, detector materials and large format detector arrays will be design, constructed and characterized. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful the proposed uncooled high-performance sensor will be important for many commercial, scientific, and defense applications. In particular, the research and development activities will directly lead to a sensor product for high temperature operation (uncooled) and multi-color imaging. For example, the advanced sensors will benefit many industrial applications that include: environmental monitoring, biological and chemical detection, and medical imaging. Based on the advanced properties of the nano-material constituents, a number of unique detection and imaging capabilities will be realized.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0839160</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meisner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmeisner@titanoptics.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Titan Optics &amp; Engineering</Name>
      <CityName>Merrimack</CityName>
      <ZipCode>030542330</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6034885481</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>66 Parkhurst Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
      <StateCode>NH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
