<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>New, GK-12 Program at the University of Houston: Innovations in Nanotechnology and Nanosciences using a Knowledge, Applications, Research, and Technology (KART) Approach</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2963931</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Tankersley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>?Innovations in Nanotechnology and Nanosciences? using a Knowledge, Applications, Research, and Technology (KART) Approach&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant will (i) provide engineering graduate students engaged in state-of-the-art nanotechnology related research to learn the articulation of complex scientific and engineering issues in a GK-12 classroom environment through direct immersive interaction with students and teachers (for example, via interactive modules based on science behind Harry Potter), (ii) provide GK-12 teachers with recent knowledge and innovative learning activities in nanotechnology that are subsequently shared with GK-12 students to enable a deep understanding of the fundamentals of physical sciences. Special features of the program include: (i) active hands-on learning activities using the KART approach for GK-12 students and teachers led by graduate fellows, (ii) summer research experiences for teachers through current NSF funded RET: ?Innovations in Nanotechnology?, and (iii) joint participation by teachers and graduate fellows in journal publications and conferences. Thus, the intellectual merit of the proposed program lies in its unique approach to inculcate, communication skills, alternate career paths, community citizenship, and visionary educator qualities among highly motivated and dedicated graduate fellows conducting research with internationally recognized faculty in nanotechnology and nanosciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this program is that it will draw participants from a variety of schools across the Houston area with student bodies rich in diversity. Graduate fellows and teachers will disseminate the results of their teaching modules through appropriate conferences and journals. This grant is anticipated to significantly enhance the diversity and number of future research and development-oriented technological leaders thus helping to fill our nation?s need to establish and maintain a diverse, technological workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0840889</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eugene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chiappetta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>03/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pradeep</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>psharma@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hanadi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rifai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rifai@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stuart</FirstName>
      <LastName>Long</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>long@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Claydon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fclaydon@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7179</Code>
      <Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>121E</Code>
      <Text>GRAD-K</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7179</Code>
      <Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
