<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Advances in Difficult Aspects of Reference Resolution</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>109321</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tatiana D. Korelsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SGER: Advances in Difficult Aspects of Reference Resolution&lt;br/&gt;This exploratory project is investigating two difficult phenomena in the domain of reference resolution: (1) the resolution of plural pronouns that can corefer either with a single syntactic constituent or with a set of constituents from different places in the text: they, those two, all three, etc. and (2) the resolution of 3rd person singular and demonstrative pronouns that can corefer either with a single syntactic constituent or with a span of text: it, that, this, all of this, etc. These phenomena have been treated in limited ways to date because the methods that have been most widely deployed for reference resolution have expected the antecedent for referring expressions to be a single noun phrase in the preceding context. In the cases under study, the antecedent need not be constrained in this way. This work is aimed at achieving human-like intelligence to support, for example, sophisticated communication between intelligent agents and people. It is theoretically grounded but keeps practical concerns at the fore. The component algorithms can inform reference resolution in any domain by any system in the relatively near term, advancing known types of technology and not relying on any unexpected breakthroughs. Among the resources to be distributed to the community are system-independent reference resolution algorithms, a corpus of relevant examples and their semantic representations, a reference resolution engine, and a critical survey of accomplishments, outstanding issues, and paths for further development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/31/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0840579</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marjorie</FirstName>
      <LastName>McShane</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>margemc34@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland Baltimore County</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4104553140</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Hilltop Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
