<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Infrared Spectroscopic Studies of Plant Photosynthesis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>708640</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Protein dynamics play a key but poorly understood role in enzymatic mechanisms. The development of new methods to identify protein structural changes that facilitate chemical reactions will have a transformative effect on our understanding of biological catalysis. Photosynthetic reaction centers provide an example of biological reactions in which protein dynamics play an important role and in which the reactions are light-inducible. Therefore, the photosynthetic reactions serve as a model system in which kinetic mechanism can be investigated using laser flashes to synchronize and start reactions. To identify protein structural changes important in catalysis, novel, time-resolved spectroscopic studies of the oxygen-evolving complex (OEC) in photosystem II (PSII) will be conducted. PSII consists both of integral, membrane-spanning subunits and of extrinsic subunits. The OEC contains a tetranuclear manganese (Mn) cluster and accumulates the four photon-derived oxidizing equivalents necessary for oxygen production from water. The sequentially oxidized forms of the catalytic site are called the Sn states, where n refers to the number of oxidizing equivalents stored. Chloride plays an important but not completely understood role in the S state cycle. Despite decades of study, many aspects of the water oxidation mechanism remain to be elucidated. The intellectual merit of these activities is that new fundamental understandings of the role of protein dynamics in catalysis will result. The photosynthetic oxygen-evolving reactions are responsible for the maintenance of aerobic life on earth and thus are of intrinsic importance in biological chemistry. These reactions also serve as a model of other enzymatic reactions involving molecular oxygen. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACTS:&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of these activities results from the advancement of teaching, training, and learning, as well as from broadening the scientific participation of underrepresented groups. The principal investigator has had the privilege of training individuals from underrepresented groups, including both graduate and undergraduate students. Several of the principal investigator's former students and postdoctoral associates have gone on to teach at undergraduate or Ph.D.-granting institutions. The principal investigator has collaborations with individuals who teach at non-Ph.D. granting institutions, and these individuals are co-authors with the principal investigator on publications, which have been broadly disseminated to the scientific community. In addition, the principal investigator is program director for a new Georgia Tech Molecular Biophysics training program, which will enhance the infrastructure for research and training at Georgia Tech. The principal investigator teaches at both the undergraduate and graduate levels at Georgia Tech, and she incorporates research and literature-based exercises in these courses. Further, the principal investigator has been involved in outreach to the community through science fair activities. Plans for the next funding cycle include broadening graduate and undergraduate student involvement in the Molecular Biophysics research program by outreach to historically black institutions in the Southeast and Atlanta area. Also, the principal investigator will recruit summer students through the NSF REU program in the summer and through Georgia Tech research opportunities during the academic year.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0842246</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bridgette</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bridgette.barry@chemistry.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
