<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a stable isotope mass spectrometer for Earth science and ecological research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>376603</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0842367&lt;br/&gt;Kohn&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this proposal, the PIs request ~$376K to purchase a continuous flow isotope ratio mass spectrometer. Requested is either a Thermo Delta V+ or GV IsoPrime with H/D capabilities. Instruments will be fitted with gas, water, and carbonate digestion handling capabilities. An elemental analyzer will allow bulk carbon, nitrogen and sulfur isotope analyses. The system will also be fitted with a TC-EA pyrolysis unit allowing D/H, and water and phosphate oxygen isotope analysis. Due to the number and type of peripherals, the finished system will be extremely flexible in the type, number and matrix of sample analyses possible. The new system will be housed in the Department of Geosciences at BSU. Recent renovations (~$500K) have provided ample space and power resources. The PI (Kohn) will be the overall instrument administrator while day-to-day operation will be a technician?s responsibility. The technician will train new users, maintain, and operate the instrument. Scheduling will be done by the PI and technician. The tech will be funded ½ time by the University. Remuneration (~$10-$20 per sample) will be assessed for all users with priority given to funded sample analyses. Higher fees will be charged for samples requiring extensive oversight, preparation or instrument time. The PIs will use this instrument for research in a diverse array of scientific investigations. Broad scientific thrusts include paleoclimatology and paleoecology ? fossil bone and teeth are analyzed as a proxy for precipitation in regions with varying climate and rain dynamics. These measurements are coupled with other geochemical proxies in order to estimate mountain elevations. Isotopes are also used to understand the Eocene-Oligocene transition using the differential correlation between local water isotope ratios and bone and teeth records. Bone and teeth isotopes will also be used to infer mammalian dietary patterns in the Pleistocene. Pleistocene hominid ecology will also be assessed in terms of paleoclimatology. A coPI will use stable O and H isotopes as tracers for streamflow, precipitation, and catchments dynamics (inputs, outflows, residence time, etc). Paleozoic paleoclimate will be assessed using radiogenic isotopes and stable isotope biostratigraphy. In other work, stable isotopes will be used to understand trophic relationships in terrestrial habitats. A number of future research directions are presented which build on and expand themes presented above. Student training will span high school through PhD graduate students. This instrument will be incorporated into existing outreach programs and through seminars and laboratory tours. The PI recently received an Undergraduate Research Mentor of the Year award for incorporating undergraduates in laboratory efforts. The instrumentation will be incorporated into teaching curricula and research results will be disseminated through the literature and through collaborative efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0842367</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kohn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mattkohn@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Belthoff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbeltho@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>McNamara</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmcnamar@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davydov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vdavydov@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schmitz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>markschmitz@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Boise State University</Name>
      <CityName>Boise</CityName>
      <ZipCode>837250001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2084261574</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1910 University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Idaho</StateName>
      <StateCode>ID</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
