<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pacific Northwest Workshop on Neural Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Yu Oh</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The field of neural engineering aims to develop technologies that discover, rehabilitate or alter brain function while at the same time deriving inspiration from neurobiology to build artificial systems with adaptive capabilities similar to biological systems. The ultimate goal is to enhance quality of life both for disabled and healthy individuals. Neural engineering solutions will reduce the economic burden on families and communities and bestow a greater degree of freedom and confidence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is an opportune time to unite the efforts of academia and industry in the Pacific Northwest region and create a Center for Neural Engineering. As a first step, we propose to run a workshop in which local researchers can learn about each other and the plan for the center, listen to international experts in the field, and exchange ideas through brainstorming sessions. We have invited keynote speakers who are recognized experts and from outside the Pacific Northwest and others who may serve as future advisory board members for the center. Our aims include using the workshop as a launching pad for the center and leveraging the visibility gained to initiate the resource gathering process both regionally and nationally.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0843319</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yoky</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matsuoka</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yoky@cs.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
