<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: The Impact of Extreme Flooding on Mussel and Microbial Nutrient Dynamics at the Water-Sediment Interface</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75613</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030109</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Introduction: This proposal is prepared in response to the devastating floods in Eastern Iowa and nearly&lt;br/&gt;the entire Upper Mississippi River (UMR) basin during May-July 2008. In UMR Pool 16, above Lock and&lt;br/&gt;Dam 16 at Muscatine, Iowa, waters abruptly rose from a highly managed stage of approximately 10 feet&lt;br/&gt;to 20 feet and then to nearly 24 feet from May-June 2008. This historic flood event coincided with&lt;br/&gt;intense spring cultivation and nutrient application activities in the heavily farmed landscape of the&lt;br/&gt;Upper Midwest resulting in a significant pulse of agricultural contaminants to the UMR system. This has&lt;br/&gt;led scientists to predict an almost unprecedented delivery of sediment and nutrients to Pool 16, the&lt;br/&gt;broader Mississippi River and the Gulf of Mexico.&lt;br/&gt;This event presents a unique, and short-lived, opportunity to test scientific hypotheses related to a&lt;br/&gt;highly perturbed, large river ecosystem. This ecosystem of braided channels and natural backwaters is&lt;br/&gt;already known to inadequately process nutrients such as nitrate to the degree required to protect the&lt;br/&gt;Gulf from hypoxic episodes. Extreme, flood-related sediment deposition almost certainly impacts the&lt;br/&gt;nutrient processing cycle in the short and long term. It is also known that mussels and bacteria play a&lt;br/&gt;major role in nutrient cycling in the broad food web containing phytoplankton, zooplankton, microzooplankton,&lt;br/&gt;dissolved &amp; particulate organic matter, and benthos. Given this confluence of events, and&lt;br/&gt;the importance of understanding nutrient cycling, we wish to test the following hypothesis:&lt;br/&gt;Intense deposition of particulate organic matter from extreme flooding alters the freshwater mussel and&lt;br/&gt;microbial food webs through physical and chemical means.&lt;br/&gt;Immediate Need: The principal investigators feel this hypothesis can only be tested via the quickresponse&lt;br/&gt;Small Grants for Exploratory Research (SGER) funding mechanism since the highly perturbed&lt;br/&gt;ecosystem in question is actively returning to more steady-state conditions. The research team must be&lt;br/&gt;deployed very soon to study the perturbed nitrogen cycling rates such that comparisons with baseline&lt;br/&gt;nitrogen processing rates can be made in the future.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Floods occur around the world on a regular basis, but the frequency and extremity of&lt;br/&gt;these events will increase given the influence of global climate change. This research will contribute to&lt;br/&gt;the development of a ?theory of floods? that is proposed by colleagues at the University of Iowa. This&lt;br/&gt;theory will seek to unify research related to hydrology, ecology, socio-economic, environmental and&lt;br/&gt;human consequences and influences on flooding. The impact of such research can be expressed in&lt;br/&gt;billions of dollars, millions of acres of habitat, thousands of species, and centuries of human enjoyment.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This research will expand our knowledge of large river nutrient processing dynamics&lt;br/&gt;resulting from extreme flooding events and during baseline moments. Abrupt changes in nutrient&lt;br/&gt;loading and extreme shifts in algal compositions can influence food quality which may adversely affect&lt;br/&gt;desirable and invasive freshwater mussels. This work will further characterize the relation between&lt;br/&gt;nutrient conditions and food quality for mussels and other biota in an important reach of the Upper&lt;br/&gt;Mississippi River. Water quality, nutrients, and their effects of biological processes are key management&lt;br/&gt;concerns in the Upper Mississippi River.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0844112</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Parkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gene-parkin@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Just</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>craig-just@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Young</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nathan-young@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Iowa</Name>
      <CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
