<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Passivity-Based Distributed Frameworks for Multiuser Shared Haptic Collaboration over the Internet</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>455889</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Reid Simmons</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The main goal of this project is to develop theoretical foundations for robustly-stable and high-fidelity shared haptic collaboration among geographically-distributed multiple users over the Internet. For this, the project utilizes: 1) distributed architecture for real-time responsiveness of each user?s haptic feedback regardless of Internet?s latency; and 2) passivity (of total distributed architecture) as a means for robust-stability of haptic interaction with a wide-range of heterogeneous human users. More specifically, the project focuses and investigates the following three key research tasks: 1) discrete-time passive haptic simulation algorithms for consistent/scalable deployment of the shared virtual environment, particularly among (computationally) heterogeneous users; 2) haptically-convincing physics-based passive hierarchical model reduction frameworks to mitigate communication/computing burdens, particularly when the shared virtual environment is of large-scale; and 3) high-performance passive local replica synchronization frameworks over the Internet for crisp/stable shared haptic experience, and fundamental performance limitation given communication imperfectness.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By providing systematic and theoretical frameworks, this project will significantly advance the current state of the art, which is largely heuristic, ad-hoc and qualitative. This project is also expected to produce new results/perspectives/frameworks for general haptics/telerobotics as well as for adjacent research fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theoretical foundations laid by this project will make many powerful applications closer to reality (e.g. virtual collaborative surgical training, pre-manufacturing product evaluation, virtual collaborative sculpting, haptically-enabled networked games, etc). Perhaps more importantly, this project may fundamentally change how we interact with each other in the cyberspace. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Education/dissemination activities of this project will include: development of new hands-on and research-level robotics courses; student advising/mentoring, particularly for minority students; haptics summer camp for K-12, particularly for female students; seminars in local high schools and public demonstrations; project web site, international collaboration, and book writing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0844890</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dongjun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>djlee@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
