<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: A Multidisciplinary Approach to Network Architecture Design</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009(Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Internet was designed to operate in a trusted and closely knitted academic environment. Today, as the Internet has embraced more than a billion users worldwide, its old design faces significant security and economics challenges. First, it is extremely vulnerable to security attacks such as Denial of Service (DoS) attacks and prefix hijacking attacks. Second, the Internet suffers from the ``tussle of economics,'' in which different participants with competing interests strive to favor their own interests. One aspect of the tussle, the tussle between users and ISPs, has manifested itself in the recent net neutrality debates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to design, implement, and evaluate a clean-slate network architecture (SureNet) that is resilient to network-layer security attacks and provides control mechanisms for different network participants to express their economic interests. A main design principle behind SureNet is to make identify and trust a first-class network object. A strong notion of identity makes a source (or a network) accountable for its actions, which in turn enables a variety of security and resource management schemes that together make a network trustworthy and a fair playground for participants with conflicting interests. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This project will explore a practical and decentralized approach to establish strong host and network identity, develop mechanisms to isolate and punish misbehaving nodes, and design advanced resource allocation and pricing schemes that enable a network to allocate its resources to users that value them the most. It will foster inter-disciplinary collaboration between computer science and economics, and train both networking and multi-disciplinary graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>400000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0845858</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaowei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xwy@cs.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
