<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Multi-Scale Computational Evaluation of Wind Load on Buildings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400219</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kishor Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objectives of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) program project are to develop and validate new multi-scale modeling approaches appropriate for evaluating wind loads for low- and high-rise buildings. In particular, the project will seek to produce new computer/numerical models at larger and smaller scales needed to characterize the approaching wind flow specific to a particular location/terrain and to evaluate wind effects on a building with its immediate surroundings. To define the geometry of the large-and small-scale-numerical models, high resolution digital maps produced by recent technology as well as computer aided design tools will be utilized. The numerical models will be validated through detailed full-scale (by using the Wall of Wind, a unique full-scale testing facility at Florida International University - FIU) and model-scale wind tunnel experiments. Once validated, the project will provide a capability for evaluating wind loads on buildings for high wind speed cases (such as Category 4, 5 Saffir-Simpson hurricane scales). High resolution data coupled with animation, and other visual capabilities of the numerical model are expected to contribute to effective utilization of complex information. The results of the project will be used to improve building codes to advance safer, yet economical houses and for work with the insurance industry and government to develop mitigation implementation strategies and improved loss estimation models. It will enhance our preparedness and resiliency to hurricanes through designing of new wind-resistant buildings and hardening of existing house-stock.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research results will be disseminated through web-enabled open-databases, conference presentations, journal publications, workshops, and through our partners such as FLASH (Federal Alliance for Safe Home) and My Safe Florida Home. The validated computer models will be developed in an open-source environment to facilitate further research and design studies. The project will involve undergraduate and graduate students from various disciplines and will provide advanced training. FIU primarily serves minorities and the project will have tremendous impact on increasing the number of underrepresented students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0846811</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Girma</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bitsuamlak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bitsuamg@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida International University</Name>
      <CityName>Miami</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
