<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Heterogeneous Integration of Nano-Engineered Materials for High Performance, Flexible Sensor Tapes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) project is to develop a versatile strategy for the large-scale fabrication of high performance transistors and sensors on flexible plastics by utilizing nano-engineered materials. Specifically, the roll printing technology, recently developed by the PI?s group, will be used for the controlled assembly of semiconductor nanowire arrays on substrates to serve as the building blocks for the proposed device structures. The printing/transfer mechanism and the underlying nanoscale binding interactions will be explored, and complementary surface chemical functionalization will be utilized to further improve the printing outcome. Additionally, the performance limits of nanowire transistors on plastics will be explored. Finally, nanowire transistors and sensors will be integrated for signal detection and analysis, therefore, paving the way for the development of a printable sensor tape technology. &lt;br/&gt;The proposed work may have important implications in the development of a wide range of cost-effective, sensor tapes for health and environmental monitoring. This project will involve the training of one graduate, one undergraduate, and one high school student. The project will be show cased on the ?Cal Day?, during which students from the local schools will be invited to tour the PI?s lab. The nature of this work is highly interdisciplinary, involving the design of the molecular-scale chemical interactions as well as device innovation. In conjunction with the proposed research, the PI will develop a new course on ?Chemistry and Materials Science for Electrical Engineers?, focusing on the application of chemical and materials processes for engineering problems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0847076</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
      <LastName>Javey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ajavey@eecs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
