<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: New Metathesis Strategies for Organic Synthesis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>196316</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The focus of this project is the development of novel approaches to the total synthesis of Annonaceous acetogenin and hydropyranone natural products. The proposed strategies make use of elements of synthetic design (modularity, convergency, two-directional and tandem reaction sequences) that will simplify and provide practical routes to complex molecular structures. In addition to the potential this research offers for the preparation of biologically relevant natural products and analogues, these studies will also assist the ongoing development of important chemical reactions. A particular emphasis is placed on olefin metathesis, and the proposed research includes cross, ring-closing and tandem metathesis processes that will broaden the scope of this powerful methodology and provide insights into factors governing metathesis reactions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor Kevin J. Quinn of the Department of Chemistry at the College of the Holy Cross. Professor Quinn's research efforts are directed at the chemical synthesis of complex natural products, an area of long-standing importance in the pharmaceutical and agricultural industries. This research will provide an ideal training ground for undergraduate coworkers by exposing them to a broad range of experimental and spectroscopic techniques and by requiring them to develop a solid understanding of conceptual and practical aspects of synthetic chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848128</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Quinn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kquinn@holycross.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>College of the Holy Cross</Name>
      <CityName>Worcester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>016102395</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5087932741</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 College Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
