<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NEW ASYMMETRIC ORGANOBORANE CONVERSIONS VIA 9-BORABICYCLO[3.3.2]DECANES</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>132400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will continue work on the development of methods for the asymmetric formation of C-C bonds through organoborane reactions employing the stable and robust 9-borabicyclo[3.3.2]decanes (BBDs). While a wide variety of asymmetric organoborane conversions are known, prior to the development of the BBDs, the air-sensitivity and thermal instability of the available trialkylborane reagents has limited the discovery of new reagents and reactions. The present studies will focus on the invention of new organoborane chemistry based upon the recyclable and selective BBDs. The rates and enantioselectivities of the reactions of new 10-substituted BBDs will be compared to those of the reagents that have been previously examined. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor John A. Soderquist of the Department of Chemistry at the University of Puerto Rico. Professor Soderquist's research efforts revolve around the development of new asymmetric organoborane conversions for the selective formation of C-C bonds. Such chemistry will contribute to environmentally benign methods for chemical synthesis as all of the organoborane reagents are recyclable through simple procedures. Successful development of the methodology will have an impact on synthesis in the pharmaceutical and agricultural industries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848192</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Soderquist</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jas@janice.uprr.pr</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Puerto Rico</Name>
      <CityName>San Juan</CityName>
      <ZipCode>009313334</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7877656696</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Central Administration</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
      <StateCode>PR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1950</Code>
      <Text>METHODOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9223</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRON BENIGN CHEMICAL SYNTH &amp; PROCESS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
