<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Interparticle Nanoprobes Based on Magnetic Core@Shell Nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Chuan-Jian Zhong of SUNY at Binghamton is supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry to study the interparticle structures and properties of magnetic core-shell nanoparticles and assemblies. Methods for the synthesis of magnetic nanoparticle cores of controlled sizes, and for the subsequent coating of the particles with Au and Ag shells of controlled thickness will be developed. The particles will be used as SERS nanoprobes for application in bio-recognition. Functional ligands will be employed to assemble the particles into organized structures to investigate the effects of particle core size, shell composition, core-shell structure, surface ligands, and interparticle interactions on SERS activity. This research addresses the need for core-shell magnetic particles with nanoscale size and surface biocompatibility for applications in biomolecular separations, drug targeting, medical diagnostics, and biosensing. This research will be integrated with educational activities including training of graduate and undergraduate students, and outreach efforts directed at high school students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848701</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chuan-Jian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cjzhong@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
      <CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
