<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Nanomechanical Resonator Technology for Passive and Active Devices in Wireless Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>498500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II research project seeks to develop novel radio-frequency components for wireless communication using an innovative nanomechanical resonator technology platform. The team has developed the world's highest-frequency mechanical resonator and will use this device to create RF filters for wireless communications in the 100 MHz to 3 GHz range. Building on the simulation results and optimal device designs the team will fabricate, test and characterize nanomechanical filters for use in wireless communication devices. There is a significant problem that designers of cellular handsets and other wireless devices are facing when adding additional air interfaces such as WiFi, WiMax, Bluetooth and Global Position Service (GPS) into their products. Each additional air interface requires a new set of RF filters and as the number of air interfaces multiplies the number of conventional filters required increases dramatically. The goals of the Phase-II project are to (i) develop nanomechanical filters in the 100 MHz - 3 GHz range; (ii) test and characterize the device for optimal performance parameters; (iii) transfer the manufacturing process to a commercial foundry for wafer-level fabrication; (iv) package the devices using wafer-level packaging in an external foundry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful this technology will allow the replacement of existing discreet filters in cell phones and other mobile wireless devices with the ability to access many different air interfaces with excellent radio performance. This innovative technology will impact many industries that operate on wireless technology. Also the product will be used in cell phones thus having world wide impact.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848716</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pritiraj</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mohanty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mohanty@sand9.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/23/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gaidarzhy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alexei@sand9.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Sand 9, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021390000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6176991457</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Kendall Square</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
