<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Correlation of Molecular Architecture and Fluid Dynamic Properties within Solid-Fluid Interfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>605000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program supports the research program of Prof. Jeanne Pemberton at the University of Arizona. Prof. Pemberton and her students aim to determine the interfacial molecular structure in solid-fluid interfaces formed with simple and complex fluids and elucidate the dependence of interfacial fluid dynamic properties on that molecular structure. Control of solid-fluid interfaces necessitates development of an understanding of molecular structure-function relationships that govern the static and dynamic properties of these interfaces. Although the theoretical framework for interfacial fluid dynamics is in hand and recent computational and theoretical efforts have predicted interfacial fluid dynamic behavior in considerable detail, experimental investigations in which interfacial molecular structure is defined and correlated with interfacial dynamic properties are sparse. In this work, the role of surface chemistry and morphology, and interfacial molecular organization and structure in templating, unique interfacial fluid structure will be studied using optical spectroscopies and correlated with interfacial dynamics. These studies will also be extended to complex fluids, including polymers. Effects of altered dynamic properties within the interface in both the lateral and vertical directions will also be studied as will effects related to the entanglement of molecules within the interface.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This highly interdisciplinary effort serves as a fertile training ground for students who will see the direct relevance of their chemical research in areas as diverse as fluid physics, mechanical engineering, bioanalysis and biotechnology, and environmental science. Results of this work will be broadly disseminated, both orally and in writing, in venues frequented by these diverse communities. Since this work lays the foundation for a deeper molecular understanding of fluid properties, postdoctoral researchers and graduate students on this project will spend at least one semester working with local high school chemistry teachers to develop introductory modules on the molecular structure and dynamic properties of fluids appropriate for the regular high school chemistry and high school Advanced Placement chemistry levels.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848624</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pemberton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pembertn@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1972</Code>
      <Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
