<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITEL (Investing in Tomorrow's Engineering Leaders)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>574462</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katherine J. Denniston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Northeastern University (NU) ITEL Scholarship Program supports academically talented, financially constrained students receiving degrees in STEM, with a focus on engineering leadership. This program targets incoming freshmen from surrounding K-12 school districts and transfer students from partner Community Colleges. Targeted districts include but are not limited to Boston, Cambridge, and Medford. Partner Community Colleges include Mass Bay, Middlesex, Northern Essex Community College and Roxbury Community College. Special emphasis is made on recruiting and retaining traditionally underrepresented students in this program. Participants are identified through various partnership programs including but not limited to the Young Scholars Program, NU Advanced Placement Summer Academic Support Program, the SummerMath program in Pre-calculus, and the Northeastern University STEP-UP project. Potential candidates are also provided application assistance through the Admissions office. This program builds on the current support systems available for students in the Colleges of Engineering and Arts and Science. Academic mentoring and support activities and services are expanded through the involvement of affiliated faculty and students. Through coordinating services provided across institutional partners, scholarship recipients are provided the opportunity to belong to a distinguished research community. Additionally, Scholars participate in NU's Cooperative Education program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0849804</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ibrahim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zeid</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zeid@coe.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mohamad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Metghalchi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>m.metghalchi@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Claire</FirstName>
      <LastName>Duggan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c.duggan@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
