<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Analysis and Modeling of Convectively-Coupled Equatorial Waves and the Madden-Julian Oscillation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99515</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jay S. Fein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Tropical disturbances have a global impact on weather and climate and for this reason, it is important that their dynamics are well represented in general circulation models. The aim of the research is to study in detail the dynamical structures of two types of tropical atmospheric disturbances, convectively coupled equatorial waves (CCEWs) and the Madden-Julian oscillation (MJO), using observational and modeled data, and statistical analysis methods. Further, using a Lagrangian ocean model, upper ocean response to the MJO wind perturbations will also be studied. Three outstanding problems that will be addressed are (1) the existence of multiple conflicting theories for the mechanisms and interactions of CCEWs and the MJO, (2) the inadequacy of representations of CCEWs and MJOs in global models, and (3) uncertainties in the behavior of oceanic Kelvin waves forced by MJO-related wind perturbations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: The PI will perform: (1) the analysis of the existence of multiple conflicting theories for the mechanisms and interactions of CCEWs and the MJO; (2) evaluate the inadequacy of representations of CCEWs and MJOs in GCMs; and (3) the analysis of uncertainties in the behavior of oceanic Kelvin waves forced by MJO-related wind perturbations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The research will improve our observational understanding of CCEWs and will lead to improved general circulation model simulations. This project will prepare two graduate students for careers in atmospheric sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/03/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0849323</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haertel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>patrick.haertel@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
