<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Mathematics, Science and Engineering Transfer Scholarships (M-SETS)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>655249</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Through its "Mathematics, Science and Engineering Transfer Scholarships (M-SETS)" program, Cañada College, a member of the California Community College System and one of three colleges in the San Mateo Community College District, is providing scholarship awards to academically talented, financially needy students working to transfer to a 4-year university to complete an undergraduate degree in an engineering, mathematics or science major. M-SETS awards are offered for up to three years of full-time academic study at Cañada College and in the first semester that a student transfers to a 4-year university. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;M-SETS is an exceptional opportunity for low-income students to focus full-time on their studies. Mathematics, science and engineering faculty are mentors to students with the goal of increasing student self-efficacy in mathematics and science, furthering their success at Cañada College, and preparing them for work in mathematics, science and engineering professions. In addition, M-SETS recipients benefit from a support system provided through Cañada College's Math, Engineering &amp; Science Achievement (MESA) program which offers academic and extracurricular support in numerous ways, such as:&lt;br/&gt; a) Academic Excellence Workshops and study groups to support students who are clustered in core mathematics, science and engineering courses so that they can excel academically, learn to study in a group and develop relationships based on common academic goals. &lt;br/&gt; b) A MESA Study Center which provides a place for students to study as well as being a focus area for MESA workshops, on-campus seminars and STEM-related student clubs. &lt;br/&gt; c) A MESA Student Lounge which serves as a center of social activities and student-faculty interaction outside the classroom. &lt;br/&gt; d) A MESA tutoring program which provides tutors for core mathematics, engineering and science courses and the College's Tutorial Center which offers tutors for other subject areas. &lt;br/&gt; e) A MESA Counselor, with specific expertise focused on STEM majors, who provides academic advising and develops an individual education plan for each student given their major and the 4-year universities where they intend to transfer. &lt;br/&gt; f) Transfer Agreement Guarantees with nearly every university in California which enables MESA students to gain early guaranteed admission to a 4-year university during the fall of their final year at Cañada College. &lt;br/&gt; g) Field trips to industry and MESA panels featuring scientists, doctors and engineers to help students clarify their academic and career goals. &lt;br/&gt; h) Visits to 4-year universities which provide students the opportunities to evaluate campuses and to make connections to people and programs. &lt;br/&gt; i) Student leadership retreats, professional conferences and participation as student members in professional societies which build students' leadership skills and motivation while developing relationships with other students and industry professionals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0849660</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeanette</FirstName>
      <LastName>Medina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>medinaj@smccd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amelito</FirstName>
      <LastName>Enriquez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>enriquez@smccd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lipe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lipec@smccd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stringer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>janets@bcm.tmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Mateo County Community College District</Name>
      <CityName>San Mateo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>944023699</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6503586869</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3401 CSM Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
