<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU SITE: Sustainable Energy in Chemical Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Esther Bolding</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal: 0851997&lt;br/&gt;PI Name: John W. Weidner&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of the REU Site program is "Sustainable Energy in Chemical Engineering" with technical emphasis on nanoscience, catalysis and hydrogen technology (i.e. production, storage and use of hydrogen for the hydrogen economy). It will engage ten students for a ten-week summer program in cutting-edge research. A number of active researchers on the faculty are engaged as mentors, which provides the students with exposure to leading-edge research topics. The program will provide close personal mentoring of the students. The objective is to encourage them to consider careers in research and continuing study at the post-graduate level.&lt;br/&gt;In order to enhance the research experience, the REU program will include several group activities for the participants. The goal of these activities will be to enrich the participants' educational and research experience and facilitate collaboration and long-term relationships between them. The group activities will include a Research Communication Studio (RSC), tours of industrial sites, participant-led laboratory tours, workshops on graduate studies, a welcoming reception and final research symposium, and a variety of social activities. Participants will present their findings in a final poster session and technical presentation. The content and format of these posters and presentations will be like that used at technical conferences, such as the Annual and Regional student meeting of the American Institute of Chemical Engineers.&lt;br/&gt;The Principal Investigator (PI) will recruit participants nationally among rising juniors and seniors majoring in chemical engineering. Special emphasis will be placed on recruiting underrepresented minorities, as well as attracting students who would otherwise not have an opportunity to participate in cutting-edge research. Participation in this REU program will: (1) encourage students to continue their studies and seek research careers; (2) enhance professional development and communication skills; and (3) provide an enriching experience by exposing them to non-classroom faculty-student interaction.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>300000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0851997</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weidner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weidner@engr.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/27/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>WILLIA84@engr.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/27/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>WILLIA84@engr.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gatzke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gatzke@sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
