<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering at the University of Kentucky</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Esther Bolding</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal: 0851708&lt;br/&gt;PI Name: Regina Hannemann&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three year Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site program at the University of Kentucky will engage students in research focused in the fields of Electrical and Computer Engineering. The program objectives are as follows: 1) provide underrepresented students and those from institutions with limited research opportunities a research experience that will increase their confidence and ability to contribute to the body of engineering knowledge; 2) improve student understanding of the nature of research practice and scientific reasoning; 3) provide students with a collegial partnership experience with faculty, peers, and research staff; 4) increase student appreciation of the importance of coursework to the understanding of engineering research; 5) improve oral and written comprehension and communication of technical knowledge; 6) expose students to research instrumentation, measurement techniques, documentation, and laboratory management; and 7) motivate students to pursue graduate studies and research careers.&lt;br/&gt;In addition, students will participate in weekly seminars, professional development workshops, field trips to local industry, and social events. The 8-week summer research program will culminate in a Departmental Research Symposium where students will present their work in written an oral forms. Two students from each summer cohort will be awarded travel grants to enable them to present their work in conjunction with their research mentor at the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) and Frontiers in Education (FIE) conferences. &lt;br/&gt;Recruitment efforts will target women, underrepresented minorities, and students from academic institutions with limited opportunities for research. Results will be disseminated through presentations at conferences, journal publications, and potential workshops regarding recruitment and retention of underrepresented minority students.&lt;br/&gt;In addition to fostering the integration of research and education through an immersive research experience, this REU program will develop student's critical thinking, collaboration, and presentation skills as well as provide students with an appreciation for the advantages of long-term collegial relationships, advanced degree studies, and lifelong learning.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>300000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0851708</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ingrid</FirstName>
      <LastName>St. Omer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>istomer@engr.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Regina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hannemann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>regina.hannemann@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
