<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative research: RUI: Seismicity and Velocity Structure of Lo`ihi Submarine Volcano</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>89511</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bilal U. Haq</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Lo`ihi is an active submarine volcano and the newest volcano in the Hawaiian Chain. As the only example of the submarine phase of Hawaiian volcanism, Lo`ihi represents an excellent opportunity to understand the evolution and activity of a young hot spot volcano. However, while a great deal has been learned about Lo`ihi's morphology, petrology, chemistry and microbiology, previous studies of Lo`ihi seismicity and internal structure have been hindered by poor data quality or a lack of instrumentation. Consequently, there is a major gap in our understanding of what has been described as one of the world's best-studied submarine volcanoes. The primary goal of this project is to investigate earthquake activity and the internal structure of the undersea Lo`ihi volcano by installing a network of ocean bottom seismometers on the volcano to perform the first high resolution study of Lo`ihi's seismicity, including a detailed 2-D tomographic image of its internal structure. The project is a pilot study to learn more about Lo`ihi with the goal of eventually performing a combined active and passive source seismic study of the region to perform a full 3-D tomographic study of Lo`ihi and the surrounding area and image the connection between this submarine volcano and the Hawaiian plume ? a rising column of hot material that is thought to be the cause of volcanism in Hawaii. The broader impacts of this study focus on undergraduate research and education. Undergraduates will participate at all levels of the project, from serving as watchstanders on the cruises, to participating in data quality control, and analyzing data. As part of their research experience, the undergraduates will act as guest instructors in introductory geophysics courses, teaching their peers about seismic analysis. Their work will culminate in the presentation of their research at local or national conferences. Data from the project will also be used in introductory geophysics curricula at the lead institution. Two masters students and a postdoctoral fellow will also participate in the project. Also significant are the fact the Western Washington University is a principally undergraduate institution and that this project will support an early career female investigator.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>89511</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0851205</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Clifford</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thurber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thurber@geology.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
