<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sphere-Sphere and Sphere-Surface Interactions in Viscoelastic Fluids</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299950</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0851552&lt;br/&gt;R. Phillips&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The important problem of how particles suspended in non-Newtonian fluids interact with each other and with nearby surfaces remains relatively unstudied in comparison with similar problems involving Newtonian fluids. These interactions between particulates in polymer solutions and melts can result in aggregation, chaining, and movement toward or away from the walls bounding a flow. Even such seemingly simple questions such as whether two spheres sedimenting along their line-of-centers will move together to form a doublet, or move apart, remain unanswered. Similarly, the limited published experimental data on the rate of fall of a sphere perpendicular to (i.e., toward or away from) a flat surface disagrees qualitatively with theoretical predictions. These two problems, the axisymmetric sedimentation of two spheres and the movement of a sphere normal to a planar surface, are of practical importance in applications such as the processing of composite materials, the use of proppant particles in oil recovery, and the application of "lab-on-a-chip" microelectronic devices. They are also ideal candidates for fundamental research, because their axisymmetric geometry makes them accessible to both experimental measurement and numerical calculations. In the proposed research, particle image velocimetry (PIV) will be used to measure velocity fields in planar regions around two sedimenting spheres and spheres moving normal to interfaces. Particle velocities will also be measured directly, by using charge couple device (CCD) cameras. Experiments will be performed in polymer solutions that exhibit elasticity with negligible shear thinning (i.e., Boger fluids), solutions that are strongly shear thinning but exhibit very weak elasticity, and solutions that are both strongly elastic and shear thinning. The sizes and densities of the spherical particles will be such that the Deborah numbers are of order unity, but the Reynolds and Stokes numbers will be small, isolating the effects of the non-Newtonian rheology relative to inertia. Numerical calculations of viscoelastic flow around spherical particles will be performed by an approach that accounts for the hyperbolic nature of the constitutive equations and the elliptic nature of the momentum conservation equations. The proposed methods are capable of resolving the stress boundary layers and regions of severe polymer stretching that are present in viscoelastic flow around particles at finite Deborah numbers. Preliminary calculations show the formation of a negative wake, or region where the fluid moves in the direction opposite to that a sedimenting sphere, in flows with strong elasticity as well as shear thinning. The formation of a negative wake is qualitative agreement with experimental measurements of two-sphere sedimentation performed by PIV.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work consists of carefully chosen experiments in the simplest possible geometries that are still relevant to nearly all flows of non-Newtonian suspensions. These experiments will involve quantitative measurements of velocity profiles that can be compared quantitatively to calculations done by our group and by others. The students involved will gain an appreciation for both experimental and computational work, as well as the importance of establishing a close connection between these two avenues of research when dealing with complicated materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will provide an excellent educational opportunity for graduate and undergraduate students. It has applications in a wide range of areas, including developing new composite and nanocomposite materials, improving oil recovery, and designing new "lab-on-a-chip" microdevices. Undergraduate students will be recruited from underrepresented groups, both to help with the research and to create instructional materials to be used in classroom teaching</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0851552</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Phillips</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjphillips@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1415</Code>
      <Text>PARTICULATE &amp;MULTIPHASE PROCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>055E</Code>
      <Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
