<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IRES: International Experience for Students: U.S.-Ukraine Collaboration on Discrete and Nondifferentiable Optimization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>81687</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maija M Kukla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>OISE 08-53804 OISE 08-53997&lt;br/&gt;Sergiy Butenko Oleg Prokopyev&lt;br/&gt;Texas Engineering Experiment Station University of Pittsburgh&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;International Research Experience for Students: U.S.-Ukraine Collaboration on Discrete and Nondifferentiable Optimization&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This US-Ukraine project provides US undergraduate and graduate students opportunities to conduct research at the Glushkov Institute of Cybernetics in Kyiv, Ukraine. The research activities are focused in the areas of discrete and nondifferentiable optimization and their applications. The principal investigators are Sergiy Butenko from the Texas Engineering Experiment Station, Oleg Prokopyev from the University of Pittsburgh and Ivan Sergienko from the Glushkov Institute of Cybernetics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The US students spend three-week periods at the Glushkov Institute where they work in teams involving US graduate and undergraduate students, as well as Ukrainian students. The Ukrainian senior researchers serve as mentors. Students are offered a variety of research project ideas to choose from. They may also propose their own problems to work on. The problems to be solved include some well-known ones, as well as novel combinatorial optimization problems that have numerous applications. An example of a project topic offered is developing metaheuristic approaches for solving fractional 0-1 programming problems with application in biclustering of DNA microarray data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project fulfills the program objectives of providing US students with a global perspective and opportunities for professional growth through international cooperative research training, networking and mentoring. This activity is continuation of a previous IRES project supported by NSF award # 0553513.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>81687</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0853804</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sergiy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Butenko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>butenko@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7727</Code>
      <Text>IRES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5998</Code>
      <Text>UKRAINE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
