<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TT Virus: A Potential Indicator of Human Enteric Viruses in Source and Drinking Waters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>255677</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;0853459&lt;br/&gt;Long&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is widely recognized that bacterial indicators do not co-occur with infectious viruses, nor do they respond in the same manner to environmental or engineered stressors. Thus, a more appropriate indicator for health risks of infectious viruses is needed. The principal objective of this proposal is to study the utility of the Torque Teno (TT) virus as an alternative viral pathogen indicator. TT virus is a small, non-enveloped DNA virus that likely exhibits similar transport characteristics to pathogenic enteric viruses. TT virus is unique among enteric viruses in that it appears to be present ubiquitously in humans; elicits seemingly innocuous infections; does not exhibit seasonal fluctuations or epidemic spikes; is transmitted primarily via the fecal-oral route; and can be assayed using rapid, molecular techniques. This research will be conducted in four phases: (1) to develop a robust TT virus assay, (2) to monitor the density and occurrence of TT virus in sources and source waters, (3) to assess the co-location of TT virus with bacterial indicators, male-specific coliphage, norovirus and adenovirus:, and (4) to compare TT virus data to occurrence and survival data for coliforms, coliphages and enteroviruses. This project will greatly expand the understanding of viral pathogen risk and the utility of TT virus as an indicator system by assessing an as yet untested indicator, and will potentially develop a completely new, reliable, efficient indicator system for viral pathogen risk. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will include support of students and will offer a multi-disciplinary experience for each. The students will have the opportunity to present results at conferences. , and the investigators are women and have involved underrepresented students in their work previously. The project is expected to contribute to improving public health, and the results will be broadly disseminated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>255677</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0853459</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeanine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Plummer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jplummer@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Long</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sharon.long@slh.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0313040</Code>
      <Name>Water Pollution</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0316000</Code>
      <Name>Trace Contaminants</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
