<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Research Fellowship Program: Characterization and Optimization of Compost Produced from Ecological Latrines in Three Geographical Settings in Bolivia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>81542</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Tsapogas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0853097&lt;br/&gt;McKinley&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The International Research Fellowship Program enables U.S. scientists and engineers to conduct nine to twenty-four months of research abroad. The program's awards provide opportunities for joint research, and the use of unique or complementary facilities, expertise and experimental conditions abroad.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will support a twenty-four-month research fellowship by Dr. James W. McKinley to work with Dr. Alvaro Mercado at Centro de Aguas y Saneamiento Ambiental, Universidad de Mayor de San Simon in Bolivia and with Dr. Robert Siegrist at the Colorado School of Mines in the US.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Composting latrines are a cost-effective and increasingly popular sanitation alternative used in developing countries. The compost that is produced from these latrines can be used as fertilizer for local crops, which is an attractive alternative to traditional latrines in communities with little or no sanitation infrastructure. Bolivia has been using the composting latrine technology in order to increase its population?s access to adequate sanitation. However, previous research indicates that in some environments and communities, the compost may not be completely mature, making it dangerous for human handling and a poor fertilizer. In order to better understand the scientific processes that lead to the safe treatment of human waste and to the formation of compost, composting latrines in Bolivia are being studied over a two-year period. Research is conducted in three geographically distinct regions in Bolivia: the Altiplano (12,140-14,760ft), the steep-sided valleys of the south (4,920-9,840ft), and the subtropical lowlands (1,310-1,640ft). Each region has a distinct climate which is hypothesized to have a significant impact on the operation of composting latrines. The analytical research consists of three components: 1) Characterization of the compost and quantification of the effectiveness of pathogen inactivation, 2) Manipulation of latrine operation to produce optimal fertilizer for local crops, and 3) Investigation of the effect of different composting latrine designs on composting effectiveness. Using the results of the compost characterization and community survey work, ten composting latrines are being constructed to study how to optimize composting in various geographic and cultural areas. Design modifications include elevated collection pits for better drainage and urine inclusion in arid environments. These latrines are sampled and analyzed for the same suite of parameters described above. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All research is conducted in conjunction with local governments, non-governmental organizations, and the Environmental Engineering Master?s Program at the Universidad Mayor de San Simün in Cochabamba, Bolivia. This collaboration will ensure that the results are shared with the next generation of environmental engineers in Bolivia. Active participation by students in the grant research will be invaluable in promoting broader dissemination of the results and improved design and use of composting latrines in the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>81542</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0853097</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>McKinley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>McKinley James W</Name>
      <CityName>Denver</CityName>
      <ZipCode>802183166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber></PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress></StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
