<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Near-net Shape Processing of Functionally Graded Structural Material</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>260789</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to optimize through mathematical and physical modeling, a method for near-net shape production of porous structural materials with accurately controlled properties. The method, pressure-assisted combustion synthesis (PACS), combines conventional self-propagating high-temperature synthesis and foaming in one operation. The research approach has theoretical and experimental components. A multi-scale mathematical model of the process is developed to quantify the microstructure-property relationship and establish the parameter space for production of the desired microstructure. PACS is then used to synthesize porous intermetallic material, utilizing the processing conditions obtained from the mathematical model. The materials produced are subjected to microscopy and mechanical testing, and the results are used to validate the mathematical model, identify deficiencies and optimize the process. Deliverables include modeling and analysis tools across dimensional scales, student education, and documentation of research results in reports, journals, and theses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research, if successful, will provide a cost-effective, energy efficient and environmentally benign method for producing porous structural materials with desired microstructure and mechanical properties. Example application includes optimization of the production of net-shape biomedical structural implants to improve the outcomes of prostheses procedures, reduce costs, reduce failure rates, and enhance the quality of life of patients with prostheses. The methodology is also applicable to a wider class of complex materials processes involving non-linear coupled transport-reaction phenomena with moving interfaces. Many such processes are relevant to critical defense and commercial needs for materials such as near-net shape monolithic ceramics or ceramic composites for the High Speed Civil Transport combustors. Undergraduate and graduate students will be engaged in the research, and will benefit from classroom instruction and the multidisciplinary training in diverse fields of materials processing, reactive engineering, thermal science and numerical methods.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0854208</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Olusegun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ilegbusi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ilegbusi@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
