<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Test of QCD Symmetries via Study of Light Pseudoscalar Mesons</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>266464</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gail Dodge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is designed to integrate important contributions to the ongoing research at Jefferson lab (Jlab) with an educational experience for promising undergraduate students. A UNCW group with a team of undergraduate students and one full time faculty member has been actively involved in Jefferson lab research in the past seven years. The primary goal of this project is to optimize the undergraduate experience while making important contributions to our understanding of the fundamental properties of QCD at low energy by studying the three lightest neutral pseudoscalar mesons, pion-zero, eta and eta'. This research project consists of several experiments to measure the radiative decay widths and transition form factors of these three particles via the Primakoff Effect, and development of new experimental program to search for eta and eta' rare decays. The results of these measurements will have a significant impact on fundamental aspects of QCD. It will open a new window to determine the fundamental parameters of QCD in a model-independent manner, such as the light quark-mass ratio and the mixing angle of eta-eta' mesons. In addition, the measurements of branching ratio or upper limits for various rare and forbidden decays of eta and eta' will provide sensitive probes to test fundamental symmetries (P, PC and C), and search for new physics beyond the Standard Model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will engage undergraduate students as key contributors. It will create a research-enriched learning environment, explore new approaches to recruiting prospective students, and develop new courses which are research related. Students working in an international collaboration will enhance their international experience and gain global perspectives. As a woman physicist active in research, the PI will be a role model to attract female students into science. The involvement of undergraduates has become one of the trademarks of the UNCW research group and matches the university's commitment to provide a high quality undergraduate learning experience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0855578</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ganl@uncw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Wilmington</Name>
      <CityName>Wilmington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>284033201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9109623167</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 South College Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1232</Code>
      <Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
