<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI:Black Holes in Anti-de Sitter Space</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>123034</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). This award supports research focusing on the study of the classical and quantum mechanical properties of black holes and black-hole-like entities. The structure of special types of black holes will be investigated in detail using a variety of recently developed techniques. These black holes will serve as theoretical laboratories to develop understanding of how to unify gravity and quantum mechanics. The search for a consistent theory of quantum gravity is one of the outstanding open problems in theoretical physics. It is likely that understanding the classical and quantum properties of black holes in all dimensions will play an important role in the development of a successful theory of quantum gravity. Undergraduate students will be fully engaged in all aspects of research. Significant learning outcomes for the students will be available, thus facilitating a successful transition to graduate school or future career. An extensive outreach program to middle grade and high school students will be developed, including the construction of a webpage on black hole physics aimed at high school students, and undergraduates.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>123034</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0855133</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mokhtari</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Susan@science.csustan.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Danny</FirstName>
      <LastName>Birmingham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbirmingham@deltacollege.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State University-Stanislaus</Name>
      <CityName>Turlock</CityName>
      <ZipCode>953820256</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2096673493</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One University Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
