<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Multi-University I/UCRC Center on Intelligent Storage</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Planning Grant for an I/UCRC for Intelligent Storage &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;0855729 University of Minnesota; David Lilja &lt;br/&gt;0855906 University of California-Santa Cruz; Ethan Miller &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center, comprised of the University of Minnesota (lead institution) and the University of California-Santa Cruz, proposes to manage and preserve large volumes of data and to be able to locate those data in an efficient manner. The goals are to develop innovative storage systems and new storage architectures, solve the long-term data preservation issues, develop efficient benchmarking, tracing, performance management and tuning tools for I/O and input systems, propose solutions that ensure data/information privacy and security, and to explore ways to save energy in data center. The proposed Center will build on the respective University's research talent and technology transfer skills to attract industrial partners who will subsequently play a significant role in planning, selecting, and implementing the output of the research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the potential research outcomes includes fostering the advancement of science and technology, making the society more efficient and secure, providing better health-care delivery, and better ways of preserving information. The industry participation will enhance the students' educational experience by providing a pipeline for talented engineers and scientists to industry. The proposed Center is committed to enhancing the education process by bringing input from industry, developing new courses at both undergraduate and graduate levels, and emphasizing the diversity of the student population. The Center also has plans to recruit more female and under-represented minority students and faculty into its research group.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0855906</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>elm@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Darrell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Long</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>darrell@cse.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0400000</Code>
      <Name>Industry University - Co-op</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1049</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>122E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
