<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Surface Engineering of Gallium Nitride with Biomolecules</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>268413</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gary Fischman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to develop a versatile method to engineer the surface properties of gallium nitride (GaN), a semiconductor material used for the fabrication of different microelectronic devices. The work will start by utilizing a Grubb?s catalyst previously used in polymer synthesis. The Grubb?s catalyst will enable to modify the surface with a variety of different functional groups using an olefin cross metathesis reaction. The availability of a general route to place different chemical functionalities on the surface is essential for the development of (bio)sensors. The work progresses from the development of the catalysis reaction on the GaN surface to the optimization of all the reaction conditions so that several classes of biomolecules can be anchored on the GaN surface while still retaining their recognition properties and specificity. Deliverables of this award will include an empirical model for selectivity of olefin cross metathesis on GaN. The model will be derived by performing a set of surface characterization tests in order to quantify chemical, morphological and mechanical properties of the modified GaN.&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will increase the understanding of the possible ways to enhance the properties of GaN. The knowledge can be used to design new types of devices and interfaces that utilize a more robust and functional GaN. For example, GaN based transistor devices can benefit from high chemical stability and be used in more reliable and label free biosensor schemes if desired chemical groups are present on surfaces. Undergraduate and graduate students, as well as underrepresented minorities such as women majoring in engineering will be engaged with the research efforts as well as an outreach program with local middle school students. Through the outreach activities associated with this work, the students will be to educate the audience on their research efforts, to convey the excitement of their scientific investigation, to portray a positive image of their research and to provide role models for the younger attendants (middle and high school students).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0856391</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Albena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ivanisevic</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ivanisevic@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
