<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Electrowetting Micro Array Printing System for Bioactive Tissue Construct Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>284980</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George A. Hazelrigg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this collaborative research project is to investigate the process of electrowetting on dielectric as an advanced manufacturing technology for tissue engineering. An electrowetting-based microfluidics array printing system will be created to rapidly print chitosan hydrogel and other biomaterials to build micro porous scaffolds with predefined structures, cells, and growth factors. The project addresses fundamental challenges to biocompatible dispensing of hydrogels, living cells, and growth factors, to mimic tissue extra cellular matrix architecture and support cell proliferation. Specifically, the investigators will: (1) characterize chitosan hydrogel, in terms of its mechanical strength, rheology, solidification, manufacturability, biocompatibility, and ability to support cell proliferation; (2) model, design, and demonstrate the generation of sub-nanoliter hydrogel droplets from an on-chip reservoir through electrowetting, addressing issues of biocompatibility and droplet dispensing; and (3) demonstrate and characterize the sterility, biocompatibility, and manufacturing precision of an intelligent system including software control, actuation, multiple reservoirs, and printing arrays, to manufacture scaffolds based on a computer-aided design model of myocardial tissue. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this project will enable tissue engineers to optimize mechanical, transport, material, and biological properties of a soft tissue engineering scaffold, with a degree of structural control, fine resolution (&lt;10 microns) and embedded cells and growth factors not currently available. In this project, a group of graduate and undergraduate senior students will be trained in advanced manufacturing technology and tissue engineering. Several project-based learning modules will be created to strengthen the undergraduate mechanical and biomedical engineering curricula. The project will also be used in outreach workshops for local high school and community college students, including many underrepresented minority students, to showcase high-tech mechanical and electrical engineering applications in biotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0700139</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lelkes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pilelkes@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhoug@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
