<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fabrication, Property and Function of the Nanostructured Surface Barrier for Hydrogen Storage</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>312000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George A. Hazelrigg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to fabricate nanostructured materials in a massive way on metallic surfaces resulting in unique performance applicable to hydrogen storage infrastructure which will minimize hydrogen loss and embrittlement. The goal is to realize the hydrogen economy from a compelling vision of a clean energy future. The research approach is to develop a top-down surface nanocrystallization technique to fabricate the nanostructured surface layer on metallic liners. The basic relationships between nanostructures, microstructural evolution, and surface integrity will be characterized. A multiscale finite element simulation model will be developed to reveal mechanisms of microstructural evolution and surface integrity. Finally, the effects of nanostructured surface barriers on hydrogen loss and embrittlement will be evaluated using the coupled experimental and mechanistic approaches.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will create a new knowledge base of massive production of nanostructured materials to meet production needs. The broad impact includes an efficient and cost-effective surface nanocrystallizing process for manufacturing hydrogen storage infrastructure and various metallic components for automotive, aerospace, transportation, machinery, and tooling industries. The discoveries from this research would boost competitiveness of the U.S. hydrogen economy for strengthening national energy security and reducing air pollution. This research will provide educational materials for nanomanufacturing and hydrogen economy, enhance research and education infrastructure, and promote collaboration and technology transfer between educators in academia and researchers at Lawrence Livermore National Lab and hydrogen tank industry. In addition, this research will foster outreach activities including the partnership with Shelton State University and Stillman Community College in Alabama to involve underrepresented groups in science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0700468</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
      <LastName>Woodbury</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>keith.woodbury@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuebin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yguo@eng.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
