<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Conference on Algebra and Related Areas</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There will be an international conference on Algebra and Related Areas&lt;br/&gt;held in Beijing during August 18-20, 2007. The conference will be&lt;br/&gt;supported by Qinghua University, Institute of System Sciences, Chinese&lt;br/&gt;Academy of Sciences and National Science Foundation of China. The funding&lt;br/&gt;from the NSF will support American mathematicians who will speak or participate&lt;br/&gt;in the conference. There will be 18 talks by prominent people covering&lt;br/&gt;topics of current interest such as infinite dimensional Lie algebras, vertex operator&lt;br/&gt;algebras, representation theory, algebraic geometry, number theory,&lt;br/&gt;computational group theory, combinatorics, and application of algebra in&lt;br/&gt;other fields. The goal of the proposed conference is to present some of&lt;br/&gt;the most important advances in algebra and related areas and to discuss&lt;br/&gt;future research directions. A major part of the conference focuses on&lt;br/&gt;bringing mathematical leaders together with students, postdoctoral fellows&lt;br/&gt;and young academics in a stimulating environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference has chosen two women professors from US universities as&lt;br/&gt;main speakers so the broad participation can be achieved.&lt;br/&gt;Also the senior mathematicians from US institutions can attract and&lt;br/&gt;recruit best Chinese students to do graduate study in US. The&lt;br/&gt;conference will help to strengthen the communication and cooperation&lt;br/&gt;between algebra communities in US and China.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0701554</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chongying</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dong@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
