<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Texas LSAMP Phase IV</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5074500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dr. A. James Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Texas A&amp;M University System (TAMUS) LSAMP Phase IV will extend an&lt;br/&gt;alliance of three institutions: 1) Texas A&amp;M University (TAMU), a Tier I research&lt;br/&gt;institution, 2) Prairie View A&amp;M University (PVAMU), a Historically Black College&lt;br/&gt;and University, and 3) Texas A&amp;M University-Corpus Christi (TAMUCC), an&lt;br/&gt;Hispanic Serving Institution. To sustain gains made during Phase I, II, and III of the&lt;br/&gt;TAMUS LSAMP, alliance institutions will develop strong ties with 5 community&lt;br/&gt;colleges, which each have large underrepresented minority (URM) student enrollment.&lt;br/&gt;The community colleges are Palo Alto College (San Antonio); North Harris Montgomery&lt;br/&gt;College, both the North Harris and Cy-Fair campuses; Houston Community College-&lt;br/&gt;Northeast campus; and Del Mar College (Corpus Christi).&lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT - TAMUS LSAMP IV has a GOAL of broadening the&lt;br/&gt;participation of underrepresented minorities (URM) in science, technology,&lt;br/&gt;engineering or mathematics (STEM) disciplines to the successful completion of a&lt;br/&gt;bachelor's degree and who are well prepared and ready to matriculate into a&lt;br/&gt;doctoral program.&lt;br/&gt;Objectives include:&lt;br/&gt;1. Enhance community college partnerships for recruitment of URM students into&lt;br/&gt;STEM majors through integrated interactions with alliance institutions.&lt;br/&gt;2. Expand retention efforts for STEM URM undergraduates with a focus on firstyear&lt;br/&gt;and transfer URM students at alliance institutions.&lt;br/&gt;3. Promote and encourage URM student pursuit of doctoral degrees and building of&lt;br/&gt;a community of scholars from the undergraduate to graduate school levels and&lt;br/&gt;across alliance institutions.&lt;br/&gt;4. Provide international experience for a select group of TAMUS LSAMP IV&lt;br/&gt;students for increasing and diversifying the pool of globally trained STEM&lt;br/&gt;graduates&lt;br/&gt;PI Dr. Karan Watson, Dean of Faculties and Associate Provost, and Regents&lt;br/&gt;Professor of Electrical Engineering, TAMU, will be joined by co-PIs: Dr. David Prior,&lt;br/&gt;Executive Vice-President and Provost, TAMU; Dr. Karen Butler-Purry, Professor of&lt;br/&gt;Electrical Engineering, TAMU, and current TAMUS LSAMP Phase III Project Director;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Milton Bryant, Dean of Engineering, PVAMU; and Dr. Frank Pezold, Dean of&lt;br/&gt;Science and Technology, TAMUCC. These research faculty will seek to advance&lt;br/&gt;discovery of successful mechanisms to increase URM student retention, graduation and&lt;br/&gt;pursuit of doctoral degrees, and URM student involvement in international study abroad.&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACTS - The involvement of PVAMU, a Historically Black College and&lt;br/&gt;University, and TAMUCC, an Hispanic Serving Institution, will broaden the participation&lt;br/&gt;in STEM of URM groups, as will participation by TAMU, as research intensive&lt;br/&gt;institution, and 5 community college partners since all enroll large numbers of URM&lt;br/&gt;students. LSAMP IV will benefit society by increasing participation of URM groups in&lt;br/&gt;STEM, and by providing opportunities and activities at the undergraduate and graduate&lt;br/&gt;levels that lead to educational and career enhancements of URM students.&lt;br/&gt;LSAMP IV will also enhance the infrastructure of research and education by&lt;br/&gt;advancing undergraduate research and pursuit of graduate and doctoral STEM degrees at&lt;br/&gt;alliance institutions and through the replication and dissemination of successful models&lt;br/&gt;for URM community college transfer students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0703290</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prior</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>d-prior@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/06/2008</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jerry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strawser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbaxter@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/01/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kendall</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harris</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ktharris@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Milton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bryant</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>M_Bryant@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/06/2008</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Watson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>watson@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pezold</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>frank.pezold@tamucc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Butler-Purry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>klbutler@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9133</Code>
      <Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7204</Code>
      <Text>DoE-NSF LABORATORY FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
