<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSUMS: Theory, techniques, and research in computational mathematics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>848882</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Li&lt;br/&gt;0703532&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; This CSUMS project links faculty from the departments of&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, computer science, and applied science at William and&lt;br/&gt;Mary to create a computational mathematics component in the&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate program. Project personnel modify freshman and&lt;br/&gt;sophomore courses to place greater emphasis on computational&lt;br/&gt;issues, thereby preparing undergraduates for special upper&lt;br/&gt;division courses and eventual participation in undergraduate&lt;br/&gt;research. Students do research projects on theoretical and&lt;br/&gt;practical problems from numerical linear algebra, quantum&lt;br/&gt;computing, optimization, dynamical systems, and mathematical&lt;br/&gt;biology. Typically, students in the program start doing research&lt;br/&gt;in their junior year and the following summer, and continue their&lt;br/&gt;work during their senior year through carefully supervised honors&lt;br/&gt;theses. In addition, academic year activities include special&lt;br/&gt;computational mathematics seminars and visitors, plus an annual&lt;br/&gt;workshop in which students present their discoveries. Important&lt;br/&gt;scientific findings are submitted for publication in professional&lt;br/&gt;journals and presented at scholarly conferences. In addition,&lt;br/&gt;students discuss their results and experiences in local high&lt;br/&gt;schools, in the Virginia Governor's School for Science and&lt;br/&gt;Mathematics, and in regional two-year colleges. Such outreach&lt;br/&gt;presentations should attract a larger and more diverse population&lt;br/&gt;of younger students into further study of computational&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, and give research students in the program additional&lt;br/&gt;practice in communicating mathematics to others. To broaden the&lt;br/&gt;perspective of the students in the program, and to encourage the&lt;br/&gt;interchange of ideas, there are visits to other institutions and&lt;br/&gt;research agencies in the U.S. and abroad. A website is set up&lt;br/&gt;to facilitate communication with other research groups and&lt;br/&gt;computational mathematics programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; At the base of modern computer and information technology is&lt;br/&gt;an interdisciplinary field called computational mathematics. &lt;br/&gt;This project unites the skills and knowledge of faculty from the&lt;br/&gt;departments of mathematics, computer science, and applied science&lt;br/&gt;to create a new computational component within the undergraduate&lt;br/&gt;curriculum. It prepares students to participate in undergraduate&lt;br/&gt;research projects in the theoretical and practical aspects of&lt;br/&gt;computation, and it builds linkages between the computational&lt;br/&gt;mathematics programs at William and Mary and similar programs&lt;br/&gt;nationally and abroad. Successful experiences in this program&lt;br/&gt;attract students to further study in computational mathematics&lt;br/&gt;and to careers in the field. The diverse research backgrounds of&lt;br/&gt;the program's faculty interact to break down the intellectual&lt;br/&gt;compartmentalization that stands in the way of progress for both&lt;br/&gt;our students and our faculty. The new ideas developed in the&lt;br/&gt;program are disseminated through conference talks and scholarly&lt;br/&gt;publication by our students and their faculty mentors. Through&lt;br/&gt;outreach to high school and community college programs, they&lt;br/&gt;attract a larger and more diverse group of pre-college students&lt;br/&gt;into computational mathematics programs here and elsewhere. The&lt;br/&gt;project is supported by the MPS Division of Mathematical&lt;br/&gt;Sciences, the MPS Office of Multidisciplinary Activities, and the&lt;br/&gt;EHR Division of Undergraduate Education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0703532</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chi-Kwong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ckli@math.wm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Torczon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>va@cs.wm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/29/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stathopoulos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>andreas@cs.wm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/29/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Junping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shij@math.wm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lewis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>buckaroo@math.wm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>College of William and Mary</Name>
      <CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>231878795</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7572213966</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7335</Code>
      <Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7624</Code>
      <Text>CSUMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
