<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>National Center of Excellence in Welding Education and Training (NCWET)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4999922</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David B. Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The National Center for Welding Education and Training (NCWET), also known as WELD-ED, is increasing the number of science and engineering welding technicians to meet workforce demands. The Center furthers comprehensive reform in welding education by providing technologically current educational materials and professional development opportunities to two-year colleges and other educational institutions. The focus is on welding technician education at community colleges, but secondary and university education are being advanced with a 2+2+2 model of vertical articulation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The welding industry in the United States is economically large, technically diverse, and has documented educational needs and considers technician education and training as essential to advanced manufacturing. The Center envisions education driven by industry needs through a network of nine regional partner colleges. The project team represents five major corporations, four industry associations, ten educational institutions, two government facilities, and one professional society. One of the corporate advisors directs a large commercial educational facility with ties to union training facilities. National conferences, print media, and web casts supplement faculty workshops at convenient regional locations and online courses. Faculty are being exposed to state-of-the-art welding equipment and welding methods in modern factories where their students will work. Development of a contemporary welding technician curriculum is providing the curricular foundation for the Center. Joining the partner colleges is the American Welding Society (AWS), the primary professional society for welding worldwide. AWS has ready-made dissemination networks through its education committees and a professional development program for educators. The AWS Foundation plans to commit proceeds of a future endowment to sustain the Center. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Collaboration with the Manufacturing Skills Standards Council (MSSC) and other employers and educational institutions assures that the education of welding technicians for the modern workforce is the priority of the Center. Allied modern processes such as brazing, soldering, cutting, and thermal spray (coatings) are being considered as well as robotic welding and process control. Organizations and initiatives interested in increasing the diversity of the workforce (including the The Dream It! Do It! Campaign of the National Association of Manufacturers' (NAM)) are partnering with the Center to recruit and retain students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0703018</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pfarr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mpfarr@aws.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pfarr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mpfarr@aws.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/10/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pollock</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cpollock@aws.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/21/2008</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zelesnik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kzelesni@lorainccc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Annable</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tannable@lorainccc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksmith@lorainccc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/10/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ernest</FirstName>
      <LastName>Levert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Ernest.levert@lmco.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lorain County Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Elyria</CityName>
      <ZipCode>440351613</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4403655222</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1005 N Abbe Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
