<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: GHz-THz Dynamics of Nanostructured Ferroelectric Thin Films</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>397904</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070009</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Our project aims to understand how to control the properties of ferroelectric materials at near-atomic dimensions, by controlling the shape of the surfaces on which these materials grow. Ferroelectric materials have the potential to replace ferromagnetic materials for next-generation storage media, because they can be controlled at smaller scales than their magnetic counterparts. By stretching these materials over corrugated substrates, it will be possible to alter their properties significantly. State-of-the-art imaging techniques capable of resolving switching of ferroelectric "bits" at speeds that are fundamentally and technologically important. &lt;br/&gt;An important component of this research will be collaboration with Seagate Research in Pittsburgh. Graduate and undergraduate students working on this project will collaborate with scientists and engineers at Seagate, which is actively looking for alternative technologies to replace magnetic hard disk drives. There is enormous potential to capitalize on scientific and materials advances in templated ferroelectric materials, which could be used for ultrahigh-density storage applications. Collaborations with researchers at Argonne National Laboratory will give students a broad exposure to interdisciplinary collaborative research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Levy will investigate lattice and domain dynamics of ferroelectric thin films that have been patterned or templated at nanoscale dimensions. The goal is to determine how nanodomain structure, switching speeds, microwave response and soft phonon modes are influenced by nanoscale boundary conditions. These boundary conditions will be manipulated either during growth of oxide ferroelectrics or afterwards through electron-beam induced etching or focused ion beam patterning. Levy has developed a variety of high spatial and temporal resolution optical probes spanning the GHz-THz range that will provide local information about the ferroelectric soft mode and polar dynamics. To assist current and future students in learning many of the prerequisite concepts related to the proposed research, Prof. Levy will collaborate with Prof. Singh (also at the University of Pittsburgh) who has been developing tutorials in advanced undergraduate and graduate-level subjects such as quantum mechanics. Prof. Singh will work with Prof. Levy and his students to develop tutorials on relevant topics, e.g., notions of crystal symmetry, tensor notation, principles of scanning probe microscopy, and nanofabrication techniques. An explicit aim for these tutorials is to reduce barriers often encountered by students, especially women and minorities, entering science and engineering disciplines by providing scaffolding and support. &lt;br/&gt;An important component of this research will be collaboration with Seagate Research in Pittsburgh. Graduate and undergraduate students working on this project will collaborate with scientists and engineers at Seagate, which is actively looking for alternative technologies to replace magnetic hard disk drives. There is enormous potential to capitalize on scientific and materials advances in templated ferroelectric materials, which could be used for ultrahigh-density storage applications. Collaborations with researchers at Argonne National Laboratory will give students a broad exposure to interdisciplinary collaborative research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0704022</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Levy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlevy@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
