<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Heegaard Floer homology and Low Dimensional Topology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>627001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The main theme of this project is the application of Heegaard Floer homology&lt;br/&gt;and gauge theory for problems in low-dimensional topology &lt;br/&gt;and knot theory. New surgery formulas in Heegaard Floer homology allow the PI &lt;br/&gt;to study applications for surgery problems in three-manifolds, and surgery &lt;br/&gt;characterization for knots.In a different direction Floer homology is used to &lt;br/&gt;investigate unknotting numbers for knots in the 3-sphere. The project includes &lt;br/&gt;foundational problems for knot Floer homology and the study of combinatorial &lt;br/&gt;techniques as well. In a different direction, gauge theoretical techniquesare used &lt;br/&gt;in the search for small exotic 4-manifolds. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project studies three and four dimensional spaces and some central problems&lt;br/&gt;in knot theory and low dimensional Topology. One of the main tools is a relatively &lt;br/&gt;new theory called Heegaard Floer homology. This theory has close ties to gauge &lt;br/&gt;theoretical invariants that originated from interactions between Mathematics &lt;br/&gt;and Mathematical Physics. It is expected that advances in Heegaard Floer homology &lt;br/&gt;will lead to a better understanding of these gauge theoretical invariants as well.&lt;br/&gt;Another integral part of the project is the study of unknotting numbers for knots.&lt;br/&gt;While this is a classical invariant in knot theory, the unknotting process is also &lt;br/&gt;relevant in the study of knotted DNA. A way to measure the complexity is to &lt;br/&gt;study how many times the strand has to be cut by an enzyme and recombine itself to &lt;br/&gt;be unknotted.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0704053</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zoltan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Szabo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>szabo@math.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
