<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Infrared Spectroscopy of High-Tc Superconductors in High Magnetic Field</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>345000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniele Finotello</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical:&lt;br/&gt;This individual investigator award will support continued infrared magneto-optical studies of high-Tc superconductors. The proposed experiments: 1) will deliver critically important insights into the emergence of the conducting state in doped Mott insulators, 2) will produce a detailed experimental picture of the high-energy effects at the onset of superconductivity - which is directly related to the behavior of the energetics of the superconducting state and 3) will provide new information on the vortex state response of high-Tc cuprates. The proposal outlines concrete steps to disentangle materials-specific properties of cuprates from the intrinsic characteristics generic to all high-Tc superconductors. The integration of research and education within a challenging program will aid the preparation of highly skilled personnel with expertise spanning condensed matter physics, optics and materials science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical:&lt;br/&gt;This proposal describes a comprehensive program for infrared (IR) magneto-optic studies of high-Tc superconductors in high magnetic fields. The problem of high-Tc superconductivity in cuprates is surpassed by few, if any, other unresolved problems in contemporary physics - in view of its richness, complexity, impact on other fields and potential technological importance. This proposal outlines new opportunities for making significant advances in this challenging problem. A successful completion of the proposed program is enabled by a confluence of several factors including recent progress in the development of instrumentation for IR magneto-optics and newly emerging availability of well characterized single crystals of novel high-Tc materials which are ideally suited to address a number of specific long standing issues. Equally important for the success of the program is dedicated effort of the PI to recruit talented graduate students for research in his group, including students belonging to groups currently underrepresented in graduate education. The latter task will be accomplished by engaging in research undergraduates from institutions with a large fraction of students belonging to underrepresented groups. Furthermore, the PI will develop a course on "Ethics in physics" that will be offered to upper division undergrads and graduate students at UCSD. The purpose of this course is to inspire, from the very beginning, an ethical vision of scientific work thus raising students' awareness of the tremendous impact their work can have in society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0705171</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dimitri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Basov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbasov@physics.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1710</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
