<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ring Spectra, DGAs and Derived Equivalences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>273694</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0706877&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Brooke E. Shipley&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to study algebraic derived equivalences using&lt;br/&gt;methods from homotopy theory. Specifically, the main project&lt;br/&gt;proposed here is to consider when an equivalence between derived&lt;br/&gt;categories can be realized by an underlying richly structured&lt;br/&gt;equivalence. The PI and Dugger have shown that certain derived&lt;br/&gt;equivalences of differential graded algebras (DGAs) can only be&lt;br/&gt;realized by "topological equivalences" (involving tilting&lt;br/&gt;spectra) which arise by considering DGAs in the broader context&lt;br/&gt;of ring spectra. One goal of this project is to produce simple&lt;br/&gt;invariants for detecting topological equivalences of DGAs.&lt;br/&gt;Another goal is to extend the study of topological equivalences&lt;br/&gt;to DG-categories. In on-going joint work with Dugger, the PI is&lt;br/&gt;also investigating an exotic example of two derived equivalent&lt;br/&gt;DGAs with no underlying structured equivalence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research projects involve the interplay beween the&lt;br/&gt;study of algebraic structures and topology, the study of shapes&lt;br/&gt;or spaces. Algebraic topologists use algebraic structures to&lt;br/&gt;describe and simplify topological phenomena. In a project on&lt;br/&gt;realizing derived equivalences, the investigator hopes to use&lt;br/&gt;techniques developed in algebraic topology to attack questions&lt;br/&gt;which originate in algebra. The PI also plans to organize&lt;br/&gt;conferences which will help to train graduate students as well as&lt;br/&gt;disseminate results. In addition, the PI will continue to be&lt;br/&gt;involved with several organizations which promote the&lt;br/&gt;participation of women in science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0706877</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brooke</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shipley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shipleyb@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
