<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Systematic Atomic and Molecular Layer Control of Schottky Barrier Height</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>370117</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Z. Charles Ying</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical: This project studies control of Schottky barrier heights at metal-semiconductor interfaces at the atomic/molecular level. The Schottky barrier height control for inorganic semiconductors and the contact formation on organic materials are significant technological challenges for microelectronics, photonics, and sensors industries. The project focuses on the fundamental mechanism of Schottky barrier formation. It includes the following research subtopics: investigation of interface dipole formation in response to changes in the interlayer chemistry at semiconductor surface; study of the effect of deposition temperature on the Schottky barrier height and the microstructure of the interfaces; investigation of Schottky barrier height control by the use of self-assembled monolayer molecules to new molecule-semiconductor systems; evaluation of the soft-landing instant cool beam technique in parallel with the variable temperature indirect thermalization deposition technique in forming metallic contacts on organic materials; creation and study of self-assembled monolayer with artificially designed porosity by focused ion beam (FIB) for Schottky barrier height control; utilization of self-assembled metal islands in the fabrication of hybrid metal/molecular-layer structures for low resistance contacts; and theoretical investigation of the role played by the chemistry of the interlayer between the semiconductor and the metal. &lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic research issues in a topical area of materials science with high technological relevance. If a control scheme of Schottky barrier height proposed for this project is successfully developed, the benefit to industries could be significant with potential impact on the society at large. The project provides Ph.D. students with excellent opportunities being trained in a wide span of physical, chemical, materials science, engineering, and computational research areas of current scientific and technological interest. It also includes research opportunities for undergraduate and high-school students, enhancing the Brooklyn Outreach for Scientific Careers and other programs in the Brooklyn College, which has a large minority and urban enrollment. The PI will continue his participation in the Minority Access to Research Careers program, which introduces and encourages minority students to pursue careers in scientific research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0706138</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tung</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rtung@brooklyn.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Brooklyn College</Name>
      <CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
      <ZipCode>112102889</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7189515622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research &amp; Sponsored P</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
