<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Complexity and Variational Problems in Differential Geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>144720</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>I am interested in quantitative aspects of Geometric Calculus&lt;br/&gt;of Variations. In 1951 J.P. Serre proved that every two points&lt;br/&gt;on a closed Riemannian manifold can be connected by an infinite set&lt;br/&gt;of distinct geodesics. I would like to prove that the lengths of the first&lt;br/&gt;k of them admit an upper bound of the form f(n,k)d, where n is the dimension&lt;br/&gt;and d is the diameter of the manifold. I am interested in similar &lt;br/&gt;curvature-free upper bounds for the length of the shortest periodic geodesic&lt;br/&gt;and the smallest area of a minimal surface. I am also interested&lt;br/&gt;in distribution of geodesic segments between a fixed pair of points&lt;br/&gt;and geodesic nets on a manifold. In another direction I would like to extend&lt;br/&gt;my previous results on fractal features of Morse&lt;br/&gt;landscapes of Riemannian functionals to scale-invariant Riemannian&lt;br/&gt;functionals involving a lower bound for the Ricci curvature. This would&lt;br/&gt;involve proving some new results about Riemannian manifolds with Ricci&lt;br/&gt;curvature bounded from below.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The notion of a closed Riemannian manifold is a higher dimensional&lt;br/&gt;generalization of a closed surface, like the surface of a donut, or a sphere.&lt;br/&gt;We plan to study connections between ``sizes" of various extremal&lt;br/&gt;objects on a closed Riemannian manifold and the ``size" of the manifold.&lt;br/&gt;Examples of extremal objects include geodesic segments (i.e.&lt;br/&gt;straightest curves between two points), periodic geodesics (i.e.&lt;br/&gt;straight curves on manifolds that smoothly close on themselves), geodesic&lt;br/&gt;nets (objects that arize when one tries to connect three or more points&lt;br/&gt;by a shortest tree) and minimal surfaces (i.e. mathematical models&lt;br/&gt;of soap bubbles). In another direction we plan to study&lt;br/&gt;"optimal" shapes of higher dimensional manifolds. Our approach to this last&lt;br/&gt;question involves ideas coming from different areas of Mathematics,&lt;br/&gt;including Computability Theory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0706803</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Petrunin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>petrunin@math.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nabutovsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nabutov@math.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/02/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
