<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Interstellar Astrophysics of the Intergalactic Medium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>546799</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas S. Statler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>AST-0707474&lt;br/&gt;Shull&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is a broad theoretical study of the fundamental astrophysical processes used to understand the formation of the first stars and galaxies, the production and distribution of heavy elements, and the physical state of the intergalactic medium at early times in the history of the Universe. Star formation, chemical history, ionization processes, transport of heavy elements, cooling and heating of the gas, formation and destruction of molecules, and the production and transport of ionizing radiation from the first stars and quasars, will all benefit from the developed modeling algorithms, which will be incorporated into publicly accessible numerical simulations. This research will help to understand the evolution of galaxies, stars, and gas in the high-redshift Universe, including current and future observations at optical, ultra-violet, infrared, and sub-millimeter wavelengths.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal investigator (PI) and his team members will continue their long record of giving numerous educational and public presentations of research and general-interest astronomy. The PI has sponsored high school students in summer projects, and expects to continue doing so. He is also active in graduate and postdoctoral training, and national and professional service organizations. Previous research by this group has promoted several general tools, including new simulation codes and the application of atomic and molecular physics to interstellar and intergalactic studies, as well as to spectrum formation codes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0707474</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shull</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael.shull@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1217</Code>
      <Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1206</Code>
      <Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
