<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Some Nonlinear PDEs from Material Science, Biological Sciences, and Fluid Mechanics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>97000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Su&lt;br/&gt;0708479&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The purpose of the project is to study several types of&lt;br/&gt;nonlinear partial differential equations that arise in material&lt;br/&gt;science, solid mechanics, and cell biology. In particular, the&lt;br/&gt;goals of project are to study the relation between a variety of&lt;br/&gt;plate theories and three-dimensional elasticity theory by&lt;br/&gt;deriving the asymptotic limit of three-dimensional nonlinear&lt;br/&gt;elasticity, to justify the limit of a singularly perturbed&lt;br/&gt;functional as an Aviles-Giga functional, to investigate the&lt;br/&gt;evolution of interfaces in multi-phase polymer crystals growth by&lt;br/&gt;addressing the stability of moving fronts, and to deepen&lt;br/&gt;understanding of the homogenization limit of parabolic equations&lt;br/&gt;and of systems of elliptic equations in cell biology and polymer&lt;br/&gt;sciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator studies nonlinear pertial differential&lt;br/&gt;equations that describe important behaviors of systems in&lt;br/&gt;polymers, materials, and cell biology. Clear understanding of&lt;br/&gt;the stability of moving interfaces helps control the interface&lt;br/&gt;between the melt and crystal to ensure high quality of polymer&lt;br/&gt;production. Theoretical guided computation of the Young modulus&lt;br/&gt;in polymer nanocomposites is important to measure the strength of&lt;br/&gt;micro-packaging material for computer chips. Identifying the&lt;br/&gt;corrected diffusion process for protein IP3 from cell membrane to&lt;br/&gt;highly convoluted endoplastic reticulum can save huge amounts of&lt;br/&gt;money and time in fundamental scientific research in cell&lt;br/&gt;biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0708479</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Su</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bosu@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
