<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NER: Synthesis and Modeling of Novel Hybrid Organic-Inorganic Nanoporous Membranes for Fuel Cell Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>129575</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET - 0708368&lt;br/&gt;Ilya Zharov&lt;br/&gt;University of Utah&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NER: Synthesis and Modeling of Novel Hybrid Organic-Inorganic&lt;br/&gt;Nanoporous Membranes for Fuel Cell Application&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Much research interest globally is centered on the development of fuel cell power sources for a variety of applications with special emphasis on transportation. The proton-conducting membrane that separates fuels while conducting protons from the anode to the cathode is a key component of fuel cells. For efficient operation, the membrane needs to have high proton conductivity, low electronic conductivity, good mechanical properties, and thermal and electrochemical stability. Finding such materials has proven to be problematic. This project seeks to overcome the limitations of current fuel-cell membranes by a combination of experimental and modeling studies to provide proof-of-concept for a new class of membrane materials: hybrid organic/inorganic nanoporous opal membranes, in which synthetic opals produced by self-assembly in solution from silica nanospheres form an inorganic matrix containing ordered arrays of nanopores. Proton conduction is achieved through nanopore surface modification with organic molecules carrying acidic functional groups. Advantages of proposed novel membranes include: (1) self-assembly from solution; (2) highly ordered arrays of nanopores with controlled sizes; and (3) potential to allow a large variety of surface chemistries. The inorganic matrix of the membranes provides mechanical stability, and high proton conduction is provided by the surface-bound organic molecules. In addition to experiments to synthesize and test the characteristics of such membranes, multiscale modeling study of molecular structure and morphology inside the nanopores will be conducted. A graduate student and several undergraduates will be involved in the research, and public outreach activities are planned.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0708368</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dmitry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bedrov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>d.bedrov@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ilya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zharov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>i.zharov@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oleg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borodin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Oleg.Borodin@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0316000</Code>
      <Name>Trace Contaminants</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
