<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Approximation and Learning in High Dimensions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Petrova&lt;br/&gt;0708470&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator and her colleagues organize a workshop on&lt;br/&gt;learning theory to stimulate interactions between the disciplines&lt;br/&gt;of probability, approximation theory, and numerical algorithms as&lt;br/&gt;they affect the development of learning theory and learning&lt;br/&gt;algorithms. The workshop emphasizes the following topics: &lt;br/&gt;concentration of measure inequalities and their application to&lt;br/&gt;probability bounds in learning, kernel methods of approximation&lt;br/&gt;and their role in support vector machines and other learning&lt;br/&gt;algorithms, and fast algorithms for the sparse approximation of&lt;br/&gt;high-dimensional data. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Understanding intelligence and how it manifests itself in&lt;br/&gt;learning and in assimilating information is one of the great&lt;br/&gt;scientific challenges. It is a key to designing systems that&lt;br/&gt;efficiently analyze data and extract essential information. The&lt;br/&gt;scientific discipline that studies this aspect of intelligence is&lt;br/&gt;called learning theory. Central tasks in analyzing data are&lt;br/&gt;regression, which describes the relationship between variables&lt;br/&gt;whose sampled values are part of the data (for example, the&lt;br/&gt;locations and speeds of an object and the times when these are&lt;br/&gt;observed), and data classification, which categorizes each&lt;br/&gt;element of the data set in terms of the values of components of&lt;br/&gt;the datum. This workshop emphasizes particular aspects of&lt;br/&gt;learning theory: probabilistic bounds to help select good&lt;br/&gt;representations of scattered data, particular approximation&lt;br/&gt;methods and their relation to a general family of classification&lt;br/&gt;techniques called support vector machines, and fast computation&lt;br/&gt;methods for the sparse approximation of high-dimensional data. &lt;br/&gt;The workshop advances the nation's capabilities in scientific&lt;br/&gt;learning theory by bringing together researchers from diverse&lt;br/&gt;disciplines to consider these topics. Learning theory sits at a&lt;br/&gt;crossroad between aritificial intelligence, statistical&lt;br/&gt;inference, and mathematical data analysis. It has a myriad of&lt;br/&gt;existing and potential applications in both the defense and&lt;br/&gt;civilian sectors. Typical of these are the navigation of&lt;br/&gt;unmanned vehicles, the fast classification of data for such&lt;br/&gt;applications as homeland security, and modeling the human visual&lt;br/&gt;system.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0708470</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ward</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>joe.ward@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zinn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jzinn@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Narcowich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fnarc@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Guergana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Petrova</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gpetrova@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bojan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Popov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>popov@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
