<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Knot concordance and Heegaard Floer homology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>298301</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal aims to study knot and link concordance using tools from&lt;br/&gt;Heegaard Floer homology, a powerful set of techniques in low dimensional&lt;br/&gt;topology introduced in 2000 by Ozsváth and Szabó. In its short lifespan,&lt;br/&gt;Heegaard Floer homology has already been used to solve numerous problems in&lt;br/&gt;topology, many of which had resisted mathematicians' efforts for decades.&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, it has provided new insight into knot theoretic questions&lt;br/&gt;related to the Seifert genus, fibered knots, Legendrian and transversal&lt;br/&gt;knots, the 4-ball genus of knots and the smooth concordance order. Knot&lt;br/&gt;concordance, introduced by Fox and Milnor in the 1960s, spans the whole&lt;br/&gt;spectrum (of dimensions) of low dimensional topology: concordance studies&lt;br/&gt;knots, 1-dimensional objects in 3-dimensional spaces, up to an equivalence&lt;br/&gt;relation (concordance) which is defined using surfaces and 4-dimensional&lt;br/&gt;manifolds. Despite many efforts, very little is known about the structure of&lt;br/&gt;the concordance group. This project will apply tools from Heegaard Floer&lt;br/&gt;theory to a number of aspects of knot concordance. We will study smooth&lt;br/&gt;concordance of topologically slice knots, concordance of two-component&lt;br/&gt;links, torsion in the knot concordance group. We will also generalize the&lt;br/&gt;current Heegaard Floer techniques by utilizing higher fold branched covers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Topology is the study of abstract spaces, called manifolds, of various&lt;br/&gt;dimensions. Low dimensional topology focuses on spaces of dimensions up to&lt;br/&gt;four. Knot theory is the study of knottings of loops in 3-dimensional&lt;br/&gt;space. With a long history reaching back to the 19th century, it is&lt;br/&gt;fundamental to many areas of mathematics and physics, and also has&lt;br/&gt;applications in biology and chemistry. Knot concordance encompasses the&lt;br/&gt;study of a series of questions about knots and surfaces bounded by knots.&lt;br/&gt;Heegaard Floer techniques grew out of a synergistic interaction between&lt;br/&gt;mathematics and physics, specifically gauge theories from quantum physics.&lt;br/&gt;Research in the last 30 years has shown that low dimensional topology is in&lt;br/&gt;many ways more mysterious than topology in higher dimensions. The study of&lt;br/&gt;knot concordance reflects much of this complexity inherent in low&lt;br/&gt;dimensions, and advances in our understanding of concordance are likely to&lt;br/&gt;have far-reaching impact in topology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0709625</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Herald</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>herald@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Swatee</FirstName>
      <LastName>Naik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>naik@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stanislav</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jabuka</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jabuka@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
