<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Understanding the origin and rapid diversification of the genus Anthurium (Araceae) integrating molecular phylogenetics, morphology and anatomy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10840</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maureen M. Kearney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Epiphytes and herbs from the lower slopes of the northern Andes and southern Central America comprise about half of Neotropical plant diversity. These groups have undergone recent explosive speciation and adaptive radiation apparently in response to dramatic changes in geology and climate in the last 6 million years. The primarily epiphytic genus Anthurium (Araceae, "philodendron family"), with 800 species distributed from Costa Rica to Ecuador, will be used to test this hypothesis of rapid and recent speciation. This project will analyze molecular, morphological, geographic and fossil data from Anthurium and closely related genera to examine the evolutionary relationships, biogeographic history and timing of diversification in the group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Studying the pattern of diversification of recent and rapidly evolving plant groups will improve our understanding of the tempo and mode of evolutionary change of the Neotropical flora and contribute to resolving the mystery of its extraordinary species richness. This study will enhance systematic knowledge of an ecologically and horticulturally important plant group and will allow integration of systematic research with study of fossils, distribution and evolution. This project will include student training, building a collaborative network between specialists, botanical gardens and ornamental plant growers; and disseminating results through conferences, publications and websites.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0709851</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stevens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stevensp@umsl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Saint Louis</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3145165897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ONE UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
