<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Studies in Relativistic Physics and Astrophysics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>382817</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Donald M. Terndrup</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The study of relativistic compact objects addresses some of the most important and fundamental problems in physics and astrophysics, including the properties of matter under extreme conditions, the character of strong gravitational fields, the properties of neutron stars and black holes, and the generation of gravitational radiation. This award will enable Professor Lamb to continue his research on these problems, building on results obtained with prior support from the NSF. Specific research topics will include accretion onto relativistic objects; the masses, spin rates, and magnetic fields of neutron stars and how they evolve with time; the nuclear processes that occur in accreting neutron stars; the production and evolution of accretion- and nuclear-powered pulsars; astrophysical constraints on the equation of state of neutron-star matter, and whether spinning neutron stars produce significant gravitational radiation. These problems will be addressed by detailed analytical studies and scaling arguments as well as by numerical computations on workstations and supercomputers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to carrying out theoretical analyses and numerical computations, Dr. Lamb will continue to participate in planning and analyzing observations designed to probe the properties of dense matter and strong gravitational fields and to test theoretical predictions about them. The research program will take full advantage of rapid advances in computational capabilities and the wealth of new information on black holes and neutron stars currently being provided by the Rossi X-ray Timing Explorer, Chandra Observatory, and X-ray Multi-Mirror-Newton satellites, and will provide theoretical results relevant to detection of gravitational radiation from rotating neutron stars. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will also help support the NSF Sponsored Research Experiences for Undergraduates team in relativistic and computational physics and astrophysics that Dr. Lamb supervises. In addition, a graduate student and a postdoctoral research associate will be trained in theoretical physics and astrophysics, numerical computation, and scientific visualization.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0709015</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lamb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fkl@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1215</Code>
      <Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1206</Code>
      <Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
