<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Characterization of MHC-dependent Mate Choice in Satin Bowerbirds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11910</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nancy J. Huntly</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The major histocompatibility complex (MHC) is a gene family whose protein products identify pathogens for initiation of the immune response. Genetic variation of the MHC may also be influenced by factors such as mate choice, which has been tested in several vertebrate species with mixed results. This research tests for MHC-dependent mate choice in satin bowerbirds (Ptilonorhynchus violaceus) using a unique, existing behavioral dataset. This dataset includes a very large sample of observations of females attending bowers and selecting males for mating, and blood samples from each bird. A molecular technique will be applied that assesses MHC diversity at multiple genes. MHC diversity will be compared among females and males that are accepted and rejected.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results from this work will inform a wide range of disciplines, including disease and behavioral ecology, and evolutionary and conservation biology. The study of factors that influence disease resistance is relevant to human public health and to conservationists, as diseases have affected many wild avian populations. In addition, this proposal will examine how sexual selection affects trait evolution. The bowerbirds are charismatic, and the interplay of DNA, evolution and mate choice will make this of strong interest to the public, and will be incorporated into public programs at the National Zoo.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0710292</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fleischer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fleischerr@si.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borgia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>borgia@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Smithsonian Institution</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>222023709</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026337110</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1174</Code>
      <Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1174</Code>
      <Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
