<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Miniaturized 10 MHz-500 MHz Single-Chip Multi-Frequency MEMS Filters for Electronic Communication</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I research aims to investigate the feasibility of producing miniaturized, multi-frequency, single-chip filters from 10 MHz to 500 MHz using aluminum nitride (AlN) micromachined-electromechanical-system (MEMS) piezoelectric resonators. The resonators for this work have their fundamental frequency set by lithographically defined features. This enables the design of arrays of multi-frequency filters directly at the Computer-Aided Design (CAD) layout level, without the need for any extra etching or deposition steps. Lithographic frequency definition also desensitizes this resonator to variations in film uniformity, which promises significant yield and cost advantages. In comparison to legacy Surface Acoustic Wave (SAW) and dielectric filters, these filters exhibit higher performance and are processed on silicon substrates, which will ultimately provide advantages in cost and form factor. It is anticipated the results of this research project will demonstrate the AlN contour filters can surpass the demanding specifications required of commercial IF filters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IF filter solutions proposed here offer up to several orders of magnitude reduction in size and weight, enabling lower power consumption via reduced filter insertion loss, costing substantially less, and exhibiting equal or better performance than their surface acoustic wave (SAW) filter competitors. The addressable market for these IF filters and resonators includes the communications, aerospace / military, consumer electronics, automotive, and industrial sectors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0712578</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Black</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>justin@harmonicdevices.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Harmonic Devices Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947041517</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5103164166</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2342 Shattuck Avenue #232</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
