<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Direct Modeling Approach for Phylogenetic Comparative Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>178893</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maureen M. Kearney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The funded research aims to provide practical tools for biologists who &lt;br/&gt;use cross-species comparisons to identify significant functional, &lt;br/&gt;ecological, or historical factors shaping the patterns of diversity &lt;br/&gt;among species. For example: is the evolution of HIV virulence related &lt;br/&gt;to rates of transmission among hosts? Which environmental factors most &lt;br/&gt;strongly influence the rate of evolution, and what are the strengths &lt;br/&gt;and directions of evolution? This broad class of questions all involve &lt;br/&gt;adaptive evolution (i.e., the direction and strength of natural &lt;br/&gt;selection). All existing methods share the significant shortcoming in &lt;br/&gt;using a completely neutral model of evolution. That is, previous &lt;br/&gt;methods fail to account for natural selection, despite the fact that it &lt;br/&gt;is the central feature of interest. The method developed here is the &lt;br/&gt;most comprehensive to date. It simultaneously accounts for random &lt;br/&gt;evolutionary fluctuations (such as genetic drift), common ancestry, and &lt;br/&gt;natural selection (under multiple adaptive regimes). Methods are &lt;br/&gt;provided for formulating scientific hypotheses as explicit mathematical &lt;br/&gt;models, each of which can then be fit to the data. Modern &lt;br/&gt;model-selection theory is then to identify the best-support model or &lt;br/&gt;models. Because in this approach, the causal factors of interest are &lt;br/&gt;explicitly modeled and tested directly against data, scientists will be &lt;br/&gt;able to use these methods to identify which aspects of the evolutionary &lt;br/&gt;process are most important, describe the relative strengths and &lt;br/&gt;directions of these evolutionary forces, and understand how they have &lt;br/&gt;influenced the tempo and mode of evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The comparative method is a fundamental tool in organismal, &lt;br/&gt;evolutionary and ecological biology. It is used to identify and study &lt;br/&gt;the factors which have been important in producing the diversity of &lt;br/&gt;life we see today. Understanding the significant environmental, &lt;br/&gt;functional, and genetic mechanisms operative in the past is critical &lt;br/&gt;for planning conservation strategies for the future. It is also &lt;br/&gt;important in planning effective strategies to control human disease. &lt;br/&gt;For example, two fronts in the battle against HIV, predicting the &lt;br/&gt;spread of drug-resistance and immune-escape mutations, rely on an &lt;br/&gt;understanding of how HIV evolves in response to natural selection and &lt;br/&gt;how HIV evolution differs within and among hosts. Beyond the &lt;br/&gt;environmental sciences, it is now widely appreciated that studies of &lt;br/&gt;function (at the organismal, biochemical, or gene level) require the &lt;br/&gt;application of the comparative method.The funded research will provide &lt;br/&gt;practical tools to enable comparative biologists to make stronger tests &lt;br/&gt;of their hypotheses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/12/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/12/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0712618</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marguerite</FirstName>
      <LastName>Butler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mabutler@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/12/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
