<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III: SpatioTextual Extraction of Document on the Web for Digital Government Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>802745</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Search technology today is dominated by search engines such as the one provided by Google where for a given query string s , a set D of documents is retrieved with the aid of an algorithm that ranks the elements of D on the basis of how many other documents link to it. This research will investigate the issues involved in the development of a search engine that supports geographic location retrieval, and its deployment in a setting involving digital government applications where it is also desirable to retrieve documents on the basis of spatial proximity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: (1) Identifying geographic references in documents is a challenging issue and is necessary for advanced search applications. This is especially true in the case of users who want to browse large collections of documents that are not necessarily on the web and to explore and discover spatial relationships either in the same document or in a collection of documents. (2) Increasingly, users are looking for documents that contain spatially proximate content. Thus the traditional method of ranking by the link structure of the web is not appropriate. Determining the geographic focus of a document is a difficult task but is necessary in applications such as those dealing with documents on the hidden web, which is a set of documents, usually proprietary, that is for internal use of an organization and is often not available on the Internet. This means that there are few, if any links to these documents, and thus popular internet search strategies are not applicable. (3) Treating spatial content of documents as a first-class citizen, in the sense that a geographic scope is reported for each document that is retrieved regardless of whether the query has a spatial component, is difficult given the need to resolve issues related to aliasing (realizing that ''''Los Angeles'''' and ''''LA'''' are the same) and ambiguity (different interpretations for ''''London''''). (4) Developing query optimization and execution strategies for queries that involve both a textual and spatial component. (5) Developing effective techniques for measuring spatial similarity other than proximity, as well as techniques for measuring combinations of spatial and textual similarity. This includes the adaptation of the skyline operator. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broad Impacts: The ability to retrieve documents on the basis of spatial proximity makes for a better search experience and will lead to more relevant results. The tools to be developed will also extend the reach of search engines from being restricted to documents on the internet to documents that reside on the hidden web. The deployment of these tools in government web sites via collaboration with the grant''s digital government partners has the effect of empowering citizens to find out what their government is doing, thereby leading to a more informed citizenry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0713501</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hanan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Samet</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hjs@umiacs.UMD.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Doermann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>doermann@umiacs.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
