<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for Graduate Students in the Annual Arctic Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>163735</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William J. Wiseman, Jr.</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Pfeffer&lt;br/&gt;OPP-0713864&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The Principal Investigator will be funded to continue Office of Polar Programs (OPP) support for graduate student participation in the annual Arctic Workshop, for years 2008-2010. The Arctic Workshop first met in 1970, and since 1993, NSF-OPP has supported the operation of this conference through support of student attendee expenses and operational costs. The meeting location alternates between the University of Colorado at Boulder and other locations in North America and Europe. Attendance numbers over the past six years have varied between 70 and 120 participants. A major effort is made in the Arctic Workshops to provide graduate students with a forum for their research and to establish the appropriate "network" with other professionals in their fields. The composition of the Arctic Workshops typically consists of about 55% professional scientists (academic and government), and 45% graduate students. The Workshops have developed an increasing broad range of disciplines and attract attendance from several countries including USA, Canada, Norway, Iceland, Sweden, Germany, Austria, France, and the UK. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts Resulting from the Proposed Activity: The Arctic Workshops are one of the leading venues internationally for scientific communication specifically dedicated to Arctic research and provide established professionals as well as graduate students a unique opportunity to meet with colleagues from around the world in a stimulating, productive, and informal environment. The long history of the Arctic Workshops provides continuity of communication, as researchers have the opportunity to report on their work to an audience with detailed knowledge of the context and history of their projects. Finally, the Arctic Workshops provide graduate students with an opportunity to meet peers as well as potential future advisors and colleagues. This is a great 'networking' benefit for a community which is small in numbers but widely scattered geographically, and promotes career development of young scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0713864</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>W. Tad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pfeffer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tad.pfeffer@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5280</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC NATURAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
