<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Histopathological Examination of the Brain of the Amnesic Patient H.M.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>246887</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynne Bernstein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to preserve and image the brain of one of the most famous patients in the history of psychology, H. M. Now 80 years old, he underwent an experimental operation in 1953 for the relief of medically intractable epilepsy; since that time, he has been profoundly amnesic. Reports from the surgery indicate that the resection included the amygdala, most of the hippocampus, and surrounding parahippocampal cortex in both hemispheres. The results of experiments in which he participated revolutionized the study of learning and memory. Although we have many magnetic resonance images of his brain, the limits on the resolution of those images make it important for us to preserve the brain itself. H. M. is on his deathbed, and this project will allow the time-sensitive preservation of his brain once death occurs. (The tissue starts to deteriorate almost immediately, so the work has to happen quickly.) The dozens of studies that have already involved H. M. will be seen in a new light once this project is complete. The brain basis of memory will be much clearer then.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Having the brain of this famous patient preserved so that details not visible in current MRI scans will be available will be of great value to the fields of memory and brain research. A wide range of scientists will be interested in the scans that will arise from this tissue preservation. This patient is famous world-wide, and having this database will be an asset to the U.S.'s position within the scientific field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0714660</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacopo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Annese</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drjannese@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1699</Code>
      <Text>COGNEURO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
