<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometry in String Theory , Geometry in General Relativity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Earle L. Lomon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Geometry plays an important role in any theory of quantum gravity, such as string&lt;br/&gt;theory. Recent advances in string theory have demonstrated the importance of new&lt;br/&gt;types of geometrical spaces that previously have not been much studied. For string&lt;br/&gt;theory constructions of phenomenologically realistic models of elementary particles via&lt;br/&gt;compactifying extra dimensions,the presence of fluxes for fixing moduli, and hence&lt;br/&gt;determining coupling constants and masses, has now been deemed essential. With&lt;br/&gt;fluxes, the generic internal geometry is no longer Calabi-Yau, but involves non-Kahler&lt;br/&gt;manifolds with torsion. Yet much of the structure of non-Kahler geometries is not known.&lt;br/&gt;In a rather different direction, there has been considerable progress recently in&lt;br/&gt;understanding the gravity/gauge theory (AdS/CFT) correspondence in quite a rich class&lt;br/&gt;of geometrical backgrounds. In particular, our understanding of Sasaki-Einstein&lt;br/&gt;geometry has improved greatly, and there are now a number of infinite families of&lt;br/&gt;Sasaki-Einstein AdS/CFT duals where both sides of the duality are known explicitly. In&lt;br/&gt;general, the AdS/CFT correspondence predicts a fascinating relationship between&lt;br/&gt;geometry and properties of conformal field theory. This project has two main&lt;br/&gt;components. The PI will investigate the geometry of flux compactifications in heterotic&lt;br/&gt;string theory. The objective is to understand the underlying mathematical structure of&lt;br/&gt;non-Kahler geometries of interest so that important physical questions like the number&lt;br/&gt;of massless particles and their interactions can be answered. Besides geometrical&lt;br/&gt;analysis, the application of string dualities and string worldsheet methods will be utilized&lt;br/&gt;in the investigations. In addition, the PI will further develop Sasaki-Einstein geometry,&lt;br/&gt;with application to the AdS/CFT correspondence and conformal field theory. Goals&lt;br/&gt;include formulating, as a precise mathematical statement, the map from geometry to&lt;br/&gt;conformal field theory, and addressing the important issue of existence and uniqueness&lt;br/&gt;of Sasaki-Einstein metrics. Another goal is to describe the geometrical structures&lt;br/&gt;underlying more general AdS/CFT backgrounds with fluxes, and also to study the&lt;br/&gt;geometric description of renormlization group flows. The proposed project is at the&lt;br/&gt;frontier of string theory research and is expected to make a substantial contribution to&lt;br/&gt;the understanding of physics beyond the Standard Model, conformal field theory, and&lt;br/&gt;string theory dualities. This will be achieved by addressing some of the foundational&lt;br/&gt;mathematical problems that have arisen in the recent development of string theory. It is&lt;br/&gt;expected that the results of the proposed program will also have a profound impact in&lt;br/&gt;different areas of mathematics, such as differential geometry and algebraic geometry.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: A central aspect of this project is the training of graduate students and&lt;br/&gt;postdoctoral fellows in applying the modern tools of mathematics to theoretical physics&lt;br/&gt;and developing new mathematics to solve physical problems. The PI has a strong&lt;br/&gt;record in organizing workshops and conferences, including the annual Strings 2006&lt;br/&gt;conference in Beijing, for the string and mathematical physics community. He will also&lt;br/&gt;continue to reach out to the media to publicize and educate the general public on the&lt;br/&gt;research of the math and physics communities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0714648</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shing-Tung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yau@math.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Harvard University</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
