<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Bering Ecosystem Study Data Management</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>224841</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William J. Wiseman, Jr.</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Moore 0714605&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funds are provided for the handling of data from initial field collection, through quality control and into an archive for the 2007 field activities of the multidisciplinary Bering Sea Ecosystem Study (BEST). Such a process is essential for the success of BEST. This activity will enhance the ability of the BEST investigators to analyze and integrate their data and serve to preserve the richness of this diverse and unique information in the long-term. The PI proposes to complete the following data management tasks in support of 2007 BEST activities:&lt;br/&gt;1. Coordinate with the PIs in developing a comprehensive data management plan and data policy for BEST.&lt;br/&gt;2. Provide tools for data perusal, access and documentation of project activities.&lt;br/&gt;These tools will include the EOL (Earth Observing Laboratory) data and metadata archival and distribution system (EMDAC), and an on-line field catalog onboard the USCGC Healy during the 2007 BEST cruise.&lt;br/&gt;3. Provide data access and archival services for the social science component of&lt;br/&gt;BEST, including a customized GIS mapserver application. This application&lt;br/&gt;will provide an interactive map with links to data and other information based&lt;br/&gt;initially on Nelson Island site locations.&lt;br/&gt;4. Collect preliminary and final datasets from project PIs participating in the&lt;br/&gt;2007 cruise for interim archival at EOL. Once collected, all final datasets and&lt;br/&gt;accompanying metadata will be staged to the appropriate long-term archive&lt;br/&gt;center.&lt;br/&gt;5. Collect and archive supplementary data from other shipboard instruments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0714605</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmoore@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stossmeister</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gstoss@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3090 Center Green Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5280</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC NATURAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5286</Code>
      <Text>BEST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
