<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Math off the Shelf</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2039788</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dennis Schatz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Math off the Shelf is an innovative four-year project that is designed to develop an infrastructure for math learning utilizing libraries and afterschool programs. Primary partners include the American Library Association, National Institute on Out of School Time (NIOST), Center for the Mathematics Education of Latinos/as, and statewide library agencies. Deliverables include six to ten culturally responsive, bilingual (English and Spanish) interdisciplinary projects and 15-20 short math/library games for children and their families. Each project includes a theme, a mathematical focus, math related books, interdisciplinary activities, take-home materials for families, and outreach and training materials for informal educators. Project materials build on activities developed in the NSF-funded Mixing in the Math project (04-06675) and will be accessible on the Internet. Regional network leaders will be selected from partner sites in AZ, CA, CT, FL, NY, MA, and MO. TERC staff will work with regional network leaders to train children''s librarians in the use of Math off the Shelf materials. Librarians then train afterschool educators to incorporate topics such as number and operation, geometry, algebraic thinking, measurement, and data analysis into activities for K-6 students and their families. A culminating family event enables students to showcase their math knowledge for community members. Dissemination occurs via citywide, regional, and statewide networks. The project will strategically impact the field via the development of culturally-responsive mathematics materials for families. Additionally, the extensive national dissemination plan incorporates a comprehensive evaluation designed to address curriculum development, audience participation, and institutional impact. It is anticipated that this project will reach 900 children''s librarians and afterschool educators and 9,000 children and their families.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0714537</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marlene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kliman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marlene_kliman@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>TERC Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021401339</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6178739600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2067 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
