<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: Evolution of Motor Patterns on June 5-6, 2007 at Arlington, VA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>46141</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>J. Steven de Belle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Motor patterns are the sequence and intensity of muscle use that coordinate the movements characteristic of the sophisticated behaviors that animals are capable of, such as locomotion, feeding and vocalization. While motor patterns are seen as a foundational element of behavior, the difficulties associated with learning about their molecular, cellular and developmental basis have limited our ability to understand their evolution. A workshop will be convened to discuss this problem in the light of recent advances in developmental genetics, genomics, and comparative biology. About 20 experts in related disciplines will meet for two days to address basic problems and recommend promising directions for understanding the mechanistic basis of motor pattern evolution. It is expected that particularly promising animal systems for integrative approaches will be identified, and that recommendations will be made regarding which methods can provide key insights into this aspect of nervous system evolution. The workshop will produce a review article to be published in a high-profile scientific journal and a glossy format workshop report that will be suitable for broad distribution to individual educational units and at scientific conferences. These publications will help to identify and direct future research efforts, and will reach out to educate a broad audience about the fundamental nature of behavioral evolution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0716834</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wainwright</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pcwainwright@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7659</Code>
      <Text>ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
