<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A New Approach to Analytical Chemistry: The Development of Process Oriented Guided Inquiry Learning Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>498825</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Herbert H. Richtol</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A group of analytical chemists is developing Process Oriented Guided Inquiry Learning (POGIL) materials that impart widely accepted analytical chemistry principles while engaging students as active learners and in communication. POGIL facilitates their development in process skills such as critical thinking, advanced problem solving and teamwork. The range of institutions and student populations represented by the analytical members facilitates the production of POGIL materials that are broadly applicable and readily adoptable by instructors in a variety of institutional settings. These analytical chemistry classroom POGIL activities are being used collectively in traditional analytical chemistry courses as well as individually in an assortment of other courses that include analytical chemistry concepts. Evaluation of this project includes peer and student assessment of the written POGIL materials, as well as assessment of student learning, student attitudes, and student process skills. The project culminates in the production of a book of analytical chemistry POGIL activities for commercial distribution, along with an instructor's guide, which includes implementation and assessment strategies for instructors who adopt the activities. Dissemination occurs through a national outreach effort by the analytical chemistry members and the national POGIL group.&lt;br/&gt;.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0717492</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Renee</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cole</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>renee-cole@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Juliette</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lantz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlantz@drew.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drew University</Name>
      <CityName>Madison</CityName>
      <ZipCode>079401434</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9734083067</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>36 Madison Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7492</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
