<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Peroxide Reaction Mechanisms</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>549000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program supports the work of Professor Ned A. Porter of Vanderbilt University. This research will involve investigation of how fats and oils, particularly the polyunsaturated fatty acids, the so-called omega-6 and omega-3 fatty acids, undergo a reaction with molecular oxygen known as lipid peroxidation. The research is intended to provide an understanding of this important chemical reaction at the fundamental level. Among the questions that the research addresses are the following: What are the products of reaction? What biological activities do these products exhibit? (some of the products are known to be pro-inflammatory, others anti-inflammatory) What is the reactivity of different lipids towards this reaction? How can antioxidants stop these harmful reactions? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of the broader impacts, this research is quite important since there is evidence implicating increased dietary intake of the omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty esters present in fish oil in the prevention and treatment of a number of diseases in which environmental and lifestyle factors play a role. These include atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease, neurodegenerative disorders, diabetes and cancer, among others. Understanding the chemistry involved could lead to ways to prevent these diseases. In addition, the research will involve students in a broadly interdisciplinary program, with studies on fundamental mechanistic chemistry problems relevant to biological problems. The research will involve women and minority students and there is a student volunteer science outreach programs at Vanderbilt that some of the students will be involved with. There will also be collaborative studies with investigators at the Vanderbilt University Medical School.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0717067</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ned</FirstName>
      <LastName>Porter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>n.porter@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
      <CityName>Nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1944</Code>
      <Text>BIMOLECULAR PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1158</Code>
      <Text>BIOMOLECULAR PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
