<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Negative Regulation of TGFß Signaling by a Fast1-Groucho Corepressor Complex</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>279798</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anthea Letsou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An important step in embryonic development is the formation of the primary germ layers, endoderm, mesoderm and ectoderm, which give rise to the many different cell types of the organs and tissues of the body. This proposal focuses on the genetic pathways that regulate mesoderm formation, which forms the heart, muscles, blood, bones and kidneys. Fast1, a gene that regulates the expression of other genes, controls mesodermal development in the embryo. The goal of this project is to define the role of Fast1 in mesoderm formation by determining when and where Fast1 functions, by identifying other genes regulated by Fast1, and by defining proteins that together with Fast1 control mesoderm formation. Using amphibian embryos as a model, biochemical and molecular approaches will be used to examine Fast1 function, and manipulation of the frog embryo will be used to determine the developmental function of Fast1. The proposed studies will reveal new functions of Fast1 in the formation of embryonic mesoderm. The significance of these studies is in defining the basic mechanisms of embryonic development. In addition to yielding insight into embryonic development, this project will have a broader impact by providing research-training opportunities for undergraduate scientists, and for under-represented minorities at the undergraduate and graduate levels. Students will receive the direct benefit of hands on training at the bench, and exposure to the scientific method. In this way, the proposed research will accomplish the goals of teaching and training young scientists, and of broadening the participation of under-represented groups in basic research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0718961</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kessler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kesslerd@mail.med.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
