<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Physical Chemistry of Macromolecules as Probed by High Resolution Solid State NMR</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>504250</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this award, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Kurt Zilm of Yale University and his graduate and undergraduate research students will continue experiments to develop novel Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) methods. The proposed work is aimed at developing new NMR tools to monitor chemical events in proteins and to determine their structures using submicron sized crystals. Four model proteins and several isotope labeled peptides will serve as platforms for the investigation of new methods including NMR relaxation as a means for determining very long distances, the design of novel low electric field NMR resonators, and development of new sample spinning technology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed investigations will expand the biophysical chemistry toolbox for the study of important macromolecular systems. This work should impact areas ranging from the design of chemical sensors, chemical catalysis, self-assembly of biomaterials, and protein misfolding. Along with producing students who will be instrument building experimentalists at the interface of biology and chemistry, Professor Zilm is actively involved in the recruitment of underrepresented groups in natural science research through the Yale University Science and Technology Research Scholars (STARS) program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0718796</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kurt</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zilm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kurt.zilm@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
