<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of NMR and MRI using hyperpolarized krypton-83 and similar spin systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>427106</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Division of Chemistry, Professor Thomas Meersmann of Colorado State University and his postdoctoral, graduate and undergraduate student colleagues will develop methods to use hyperpolarized gases for use in NMR and MRI investigations. Specifically, Meersmann and his group will develop methods of creating hyperpolarized Kr-83 as a sensitive probe of the chemical composition of surfaces. In addition, Prof. Meersmann and his team will develop a means of producing nuclear spin-polarized gas molecules for in situ monitoring of high temperature reactions such as combustion. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Magnetic resonance imaging is a powerful, non-invasive method for obtaining chemically-specific images of materials. Its use in materials and medical imaging are ubiquitous. Prof. Meersmann and his young colleagues will develop new methodologies for these imaging methods using hyperpolarized probe gases. One potential application of the methods developed in the Meersmann laboratory would be the use of chemically-inert Kr-83 as a MRI contrast agent for in vivo imaging of lung surfaces -- a potentially important tool in diagnosing certain types of respiratory diseases. Besides the broader scientific and societal impact of the research supported in this award, Prof. Meersmann will continue to train a diverse group of young scientists in modern magnetic resonance methods.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0719423</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van Orden</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vanorden@lamar.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meersmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>meer@lamar.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/16/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1960</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURE AND REACTIVITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
