<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSR-AES: Adaptive Optimization for Dynamically Discovered Hardware and Software Resources</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Krishna Kant</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project pursues the vision of a community that shares resources in an open&lt;br/&gt;manner. Similar to today's web publication and discovery of documents, computer&lt;br/&gt;applications, machine cycles, and databases can be announced openly and used by&lt;br/&gt;others worldwide.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A big issue in realizing this vision is to create facilities that help manage&lt;br/&gt;the diversity of available resources and adapt them to the users' needs. Thus,&lt;br/&gt;published software modules may be adapted to compose new application programs;&lt;br/&gt;discovered programs may be tuned to the user's platform; distributed&lt;br/&gt;applications may run at high performance, as they adapt to changing bandwidth&lt;br/&gt;and latency characteristics of the target environment. This project develops&lt;br/&gt;such facilities. Building on results of prior NSF support, an adaptive&lt;br/&gt;engine will dynamically improve the performance of distributed computer&lt;br/&gt;applications; it will adaptively compose software modules from components; and&lt;br/&gt;it will support computer applications that roam across discovered machine&lt;br/&gt;platforms. These components are being integrated in the iShare Internet sharing&lt;br/&gt;system, which provides the environment for resource publication, discovery, and&lt;br/&gt;remote use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Components of this system are being created in related NSF projects, which synergistically complement the present project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work addresses a fundamental problem in computer system and software&lt;br/&gt;design: optimal design decisions are often impossible because insufficient&lt;br/&gt;information is available at design-time. The adaptive engine moves design&lt;br/&gt;decisions to the time application software executes, when this information becomes&lt;br/&gt;available.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is expected to yield significant performance improvements of the&lt;br/&gt;involved compilers, composers, and application software, substantially facilitating the way the involved resources can be shared by the global community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0720471</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rudolf</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eigenmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eigenman@ecn.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
