<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SDCI NMI Improvement: Open Grid Computing Environments Software for Science Gateways</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1698347</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniel Katz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>National Science Foundation&lt;br/&gt;NSF Software Development for Cyberinfrastructure (SDCI) Program&lt;br/&gt;Office of Cyberinfrastructure&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 0721656&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Marlon Pierce&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Indiana University&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: SDCI NMI Improvement: Open Grid Computing Environments Software for Science Gateways&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Open Grid Computing Environments (OGCE) project will develop, integrate, package, and distribute software to TeraGrid science gateways and related science portal efforts. Science gateways support scientific research communities and their outreach efforts. They consist of Web-based user and application programming interfaces that provide high-level access to Cyberinfrastructure middleware and translate middleware capabilities into scientific use cases. The OGCE works to provide these gateway development groups with the reusable software they need. OGCE portal software and component libraries currently provide client support for numerous Grid middleware tools, including the Globus Toolkit, Condor, MyProxy, and GPIR information services. The portal software is packaged and easily installable, allowing portal developers to build a functioning Grid portal in a single step. The current funding award will extend this work to provide several additional features as well as maintenance of the current software suite. Previous versions of the OGCE releases concentrated on client components for remote job and file management through a common, high-level Grid programming interface. In the project extension, the OGCE will build on this to address the information and metadata management needs of both scientists and gateway providers with the following tools: personal and resource metadata catalogs; enhanced system information tools, including access to batch queue prediction services; and gateway auditing, accounting, and logging libraries. The OGCE will also provide improved support for adding science applications to gateways. Efforts here will include computational experiment builder interfaces to workflow engines for end users, application factory services for application providers, and portlet XML tag libraries for portal developers. Finally, the OGCE identifies ?Web 2.0? approaches as potentially revolutionary to the gateway building process and will lead these developments within the gateway community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0721656</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gannon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gannon@cs.indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/04/2008</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marlon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pierce</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marpierc@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilkins-Diehr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wilkinsn@sdsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suresh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marru</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smarru@iu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7683</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE DEVELOPEMENT FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
