<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Signal Analysis Equipment for High Frequency Electrical and Optical Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>257762</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andreas Weisshaar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merits: This NSF Major Research Instrumentation Program supports fundamental experimental research in the areas of optical and electrical communications and basic atomic properties. Specifically, the instrumentation will (1) measure the phase and frequency of electronic and optical signals and (2) generate complex electronic and optical signals. These experimental capabilities are required to investigate a new class of analog fiber optic links and low phase-noise optoelectronic oscillators for use in advanced communications systems, the development and characterization of low-noise solid state microchip lasers for emerging frequency modulated analog fiber optic links, and the investigation of phase noise mechanisms in advanced mixed-signal phase-locked loop and crystal oscillators circuits -- vital components of almost every communications system. The equipment will also support the measurement and characterization of fundamental atomic properties using laser spectroscopy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Electronic and optical telecommunications play a significant social and economic role in modern information-based societies. The development of novel techniques, circuits, and materials to support new telecommunications applications is critical to maintaining innovation in the telecommunications field, thereby allowing more people access to greater amounts of information. The investigators are committed to involving undergraduates in their research; this grant will enable them to train undergraduates in the use of advanced equipment and experimental methods and to prepare students for entry into outstanding graduate programs as well as the electronics and communications industry workforce. The equipment will also be used for in-class demonstrations to show students state-of-the-art measurement techniques and it will be made available to collaborators at local universities in an effort to enhance the educational and research opportunities for the investigators and their undergraduate students through collaboration with colleagues and graduate students at these institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0722610</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jemison</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wjemison@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kortyna</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>akortyna@enter.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weyt@lafayette.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lafayette College</Name>
      <CityName>Easton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>180421768</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6103305029</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>109E</Code>
      <Text>Sys theory in biology &amp; medicine</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9141</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD. INST - EQUIP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
