<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CPATH CB: Building a Platform for Learning - A Learner Centered Approach to Computer Science Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harriet G. Taylor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CNS-0722362&lt;br/&gt;PI: Carlos Jensen&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Oregon State University&lt;br/&gt;Title: CPATH CB: Building a Platform for Learning , A Learner Centered Approach to Computer Science Education&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CPATH project builds a community around integrating a Platform for Learning model into the computing education of undergraduate students. The model is based on a successful similar paradigm used within electrical engineering education at the lead university. Curriculum revision is based on four major themes: multi-core programming, graphics and animation, software engineering fundamentals, and open-source contributions. A key element of the project is the continued development and evaluation of an open-source community of code repository to support software development and the student community of learners as well as the broader academic community at other institutions. The project includes community outreach to university, community college, and industry partners within the state of Oregon as well as on a national scale. It also includes developing a community of practice involving students, faculty, and professionals from other disciplines engaging non-traditional interdisciplinary projects. National outreach takes place through organized activities at the National Center for Women and Information Technology alliance meeting and other national meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project lies in the expertise and experience of the project team in educational innovation and in the development of significant tools and resources to support that innovation. The main focus areas, particularly the multi-core programming aspects of the project are timely and clearly respond to national needs for research-based innovation in computing education. The project has clear potential for success and significant contribution to the computing education field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project should emerge from the community building around the understanding of the needs of computing professionals and the development of resources that support the community. The community of code model is of current interest among computing educators. The combination of strong industry support and the involvement of the broader academic community points to the potential to impact the computing education of a large, diverse group of students and to better prepare them for the challenges of the modern computing professional workplace.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0722362</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fiez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Terri.Fiez@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paulson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paulson@eecs.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jensen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cjensen@eecs.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Budd</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>budd@eecs.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bailey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjb@eecs.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7640</Code>
      <Text>CPATH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
