<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a Pulsed High Frequency Quasioptical Electron Spin Resonance Spectrometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>254685</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vicki Martin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is an award for developing a pulsed high-field quasioptical Electron Spin Resonance (ESR) spectrometer for research, education, and training in biotechnology and nanomaterials. Five faculty will use the instrument to carry out research in several areas as follows: Electrostatic mapping of proteins by high-field spin labeling; Characterization of novel materials for spintronic devices; Measurements of interfacial interactions in nanocomposite fuel cell and catalytic membranes; Characterization of protein-based nanodevices. The extension to pulsed methodology will provide important capabilities that will lead to new applications in biotechnology and materials science. These include (1) detailed characterization of spin-spin distances and distance distributions on the molecular scale using double electron-electron resonance (DEER) spectroscopy, (2) the ability to measure the microscopic local electric field at a label introduced into a protein or nanostructure using the linear electric field effect (LEFE), (3) high resolution of detailed dynamic behavior in macromolecules and nanostructures via spin relaxation measurements. The instrument will be operated as a continuation of the existing continuous-wave high-field ESR facility at the university. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will implement a training program for the rapidly growing research area of high-field ESR. Internships will be available for students to increase the breadth of their training in new high-field ESR methods. The university has a co-op education program, and qualified undergrads will do their co-op semester in the ESR facility. The university has many outreach programs for underrepresented groups, including students in the inner city area.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0723001</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary Jo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ondrechen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjo@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heiman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>d.heiman@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Budil</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbudil@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Constantinos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mavroidis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mavro@coe.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sanjeev</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mukerjee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>s.mukerjee@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
