<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Test-bed for Next Generation Cognitive Radio Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>220000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal #: CNS 07-23263&lt;br/&gt;PI(s): Kumar, Sunil&lt;br/&gt; Nagaraj, Santosh V.; Sarkar, Mahasweta&lt;br/&gt;Institution: San Diego State University &lt;br/&gt; San Diego, CA 92115-1338&lt;br/&gt;Title: MRI/Acq.: Test-bed for Next Generation Cognitive radio Wireless Networks&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Proposed:&lt;br/&gt;This project, acquiring a state-of-the-art cognitive radio test bed on which the protocols that exploit the merits of cognitive radios at the physical, MAC, transport, and routing layers can be tested, includes verification on a practical testbed or prototype to validate the theoretical and simulations work needed for the development of wireless networks, especially cross layer architectures. The work involves &lt;br/&gt;. Addressing the needs of commercial platforms that often do not allow any changes in the underlying framework and seldom provide researchers full control of the RF, PHY, and lower MAC functionalities. &lt;br/&gt;. Obtaining new and realistic models for spectrum hole detection and spectrum usage pattern providing real data depicting trend and patterns of spectrum usage which will contribute significantly in building prototypes (Simulation results are only as good as the models that use them.)&lt;br/&gt;. Recreating concepts from a model of primary users studying the characteristics in licensed bands and then recreating those primary users in the ISM bands by emulating their characteristics for testing the dynamic spectrum access algorithms.&lt;br/&gt;Intelligent cognitive radios sniff the radio frequency (RF) medium and identify bands of unused spectrum. These bands are then "scavenged" and information can be transmitted over them utilizing orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) loading possibly non-contiguous bands of available frequencies. Federal Communication Commission (FCC) has recognized the importance of cognitive radio in spectrum management in the coming years, and has even opened the television band for the purpose of cognitive radio networks. Thus, the project creates a hardware platform to investigate cognitive radio systems and builds a test bed to analyze the physical, MAC, routing and transport layers to enable research in the area. The models are developed for hole detection and spectrum usage patterns. The overall approach combines modeling and re-creation (in the ISM bands) via emulation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This test bed enables many applications such as pervasive networks, remote patient monitoring, inter-vehicular communications, emergency communications, airborne networks, and surveillance systems. Dissemination of results should have major impact on research and development in the areas of cognitive radio networks. Research will be transferred to wireless communication industry on San Diego through SDSU's industry partnerships. Curricular improvements are expected to enhance the technological skills and employment prospects of students (many from underrepresented groups).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0723263</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sunil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>skumar@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Santosh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nagaraj</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>snagaraj@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mahasweta</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sarkar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>msarkar2@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
