<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improving the Understanding of the Properties and Retention Behavior of Chemically Bonded Stationary Phases Employing Spectroscopic and Chromatographic Characterization Techniques</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>345000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry supports the collaborative research program of Prof. Joseph Pesek at San Jose State University and Prof. Klaus Albert at the University of Tuebingen. This award coordinates with a collaborative award funded by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) through a joint program between the NSF and DFG that funds collaborative projects between US and German investigators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The focus of the collaboration is to better understand how molecules are separated based on their chemical and physical properties using materials based on silica. The separation media will be studied mainly by nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, a technique that can measure how various types of compounds interact with the silica surface. Varying degrees of interaction between the surface of silica particles and the molecules present in a mixture result in separation of these compounds and provide a means of analysis. Modification of silica surfaces can be used for controlling the separation of various types of mixtures. Understanding these processes will lead to the development of better separation materials to be used in the analysis of complex mixtures encountered in pharmaceutical, clinical, environmental and biological samples. A key component in the collaboration will be the involvement of students who will have an opportunity to work in a multi-disciplinary international research project. Exchanges of students between the two laboratories will enhance the collaborative research experiences of the participants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award is co-funded by the Office of International Science and Engineering at NSF.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0724218</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pesek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pesek@sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1974</Code>
      <Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1974</Code>
      <Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5936</Code>
      <Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5980</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
