<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Downside to Disease Resistance in Arabidopsis: The Trouble with LOV</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>535758</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael L. Mishkind</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The overall objective of this research is to understand the physiological basis of plant disease susceptibility. To accomplish this, a disease in the model plant, Arabidopsis thaliana is being investigated because of its genetic simplicity. The disease is conditioned by a single dominant host gene and is caused by the fungus Cochliobolus victoriae whose virulence depends on the production of a "toxin" called victorin. If a victorin-producing isolate encounters a plant carrying the gene for susceptibility, disease occurs. In all other cases, such as a lack of victorin production, or a plant lacking the susceptibility gene, disease does not occur. Because susceptibility is completely dependent on a single gene, understanding the function of that gene should contribute to understanding plant disease susceptibility. In Arabidopsis, susceptibility is conferred by a gene called LOV (for locus orchestrating victorin sensitivity) which encodes a CC-NBS-LRR type protein. Ironically, the only known function for this type of protein is in conferring disease resistance. Nonetheless, LOV conditions disease susceptibility. The identification of LOV presents a fundamentally different perspective on plant resistance gene function and implies that the induction of resistance can entail physiological changes that actually increase a plant's vulnerability to pathogens. The work to be conducted will investigate this possibility through a combination of approaches that will determine whether known resistance responses can lead to disease susceptibility and conversely, whether the response conferred by LOV can confer disease resistance. We anticipate that both outcomes are likely. The broader impacts of this effort will be integrated into both undergraduate and graduate level education. For example, the plant response will be used as the basis for a laboratory exercise in an undergraduate course. Also, the research will provide experiences for graduate and postdoctoral researchers whose results will be disseminated through publications and seminars.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0724954</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wolpert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wolpertt@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
