<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on the Interface between Atomistic and Continuum Theories</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Chen&lt;br/&gt;0724936&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator and co-investigator organize a conference&lt;br/&gt;on the topic "The Interface between Atomistic and Continuum&lt;br/&gt;Theories" under the auspices of the Society for Natural&lt;br/&gt;Philosophy. The conference themes address mathematical issues&lt;br/&gt;that arise in the development of continuum-level governing&lt;br/&gt;equations (balance laws and constitutive equations) for materials&lt;br/&gt;based on atomistic considerations. The focuses are on the&lt;br/&gt;relationships between the relevant physical principles used at&lt;br/&gt;atomic and continuum levels, as well as consistency of the&lt;br/&gt;resulting theories. Basic understanding of the characteristics&lt;br/&gt;of the theories across different length scales is essential for&lt;br/&gt;developing analytical and computational models that are capable&lt;br/&gt;of describing a broad range of material behaviors. The speakers&lt;br/&gt;invited to participate in the conference are leading researchers&lt;br/&gt;in mathematics, physics, chemistry, and engineering. These&lt;br/&gt;speakers present their current research on analysis, modeling,&lt;br/&gt;and simulations for various material systems. The conferences of&lt;br/&gt;Society for Natural Philosophy have a history of being&lt;br/&gt;cross-disciplinary endeavors. The works presented at these&lt;br/&gt;conferences have embraced a broad spectrum of research topics,&lt;br/&gt;with common emphasis on the application of rigorous mathematical&lt;br/&gt;analysis to the study of physical systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The conference contributes directly to building a solid&lt;br/&gt;theoretical foundation for rapidly developing technological areas&lt;br/&gt;such as nanotechnology, novel materials, and large-scale material&lt;br/&gt;simulations. As many nations are heavily investing in these&lt;br/&gt;technological areas, the most significant and lasting&lt;br/&gt;developments can only result from progress at fundamental levels. &lt;br/&gt;The theme of the conference reflects the current trend of using&lt;br/&gt;advanced mathematical tools to address critical problems arising&lt;br/&gt;in the modeling of material behavior across widely varying length&lt;br/&gt;and time scales. The conference promotes the participation of&lt;br/&gt;junior researchers and students, and exposes them to a novel,&lt;br/&gt;important, and rapidly expanding area of science and technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0724936</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yi-Chao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chen@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eliot</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fried</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>budd@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
