<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III: "Visualizing Network Dynamics" -- Competition at the International Conference on Network Science 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11890</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports the "Visualizing Network Dynamics" Competition intended to cull some of the world's best dynamic network visualization results to be exhibited at the 2007 International Workshop and Conference on Network Science (NetSci07), held in the New York Hall of Science, May 20 - 25, 2007.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The competition is designed to attract researchers, practitioners, and educators from such diverse disciplines as anthropology, sociology, history, social psychology, political science, human geography, biology, economics, communications science but also art and design to submit the best-of visualizations of evolving networks, activity patterns over networks or combinations of the two. Competition applications comprise of large resolution static images or video footage together with a detailed explanation of datasets used, analysis or modeling techniques applied, and the visualization design. Applicants are also asked to list and explain major insights gained and to discuss the value the visualization may have for educational purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The competition plans to feature the winning entries that support insight and decision making network dynamics visualizations (as opposed to purely artistically appealing images or videos). In addition, it aims to raise the bar for the documentation and communication of the process applied to generate those visualizations, and to sensitize people to the importance of visualization for education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The winning entries will be recognized and all valid entries will be made available online via the NetSci07 Web site (http://www.nd.edu/%7Enetsci/) as a general, free resource for anybody interested in the study or communication of dynamic networks. Online dissemination is expected to improve diverse network science related scientific, engineering and/or educational activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0724282</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>katy@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Uzzo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>suzzo@nyscience.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
