<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Silicon-germanium quantum well-quantum dot nanostructures for integrated light emitters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Tsybeskov, 0725443, Proposal &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to develop novel, CMOS compatible light-emitting nanostructures based on Si/SiGe quantum well-quantum dot systems and demonstrate feasibility of integrated optical interconnects. The approach is focused on a nanoscale strain field and energy band structure engineering by using Ge-rich SiGe nanoclusters as local stressors for composition-designed SiGe quantum wells.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: The technical goals of this project are: (i) fast radiative electronic transitions at 1.3-1.6 um spectral region associated with the enhanced dynamic type I energy band alignment at Si/SiGe hetero-interfaces, (ii) high quantum efficiency and (iii) near room-temperature device operation. Theoretical modeling of electronic transitions in these composition-controlled quantum dot-quantum well Si/SiGe nanostructures with focus on the suppression of Auger recombination will be performed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this program include comprehensive training of NJIT students in the strategically important area of semiconductor nanoelectronics and nanotechnology, integration of research and education, and promotion of international partnerships between a public university in New Jersey, USA and leading research institutions in Canada and Japan. An important component of this proposal is public education on nanotechnology and outreach efforts to underrepresented groups in science and technology via lectures, demonstrations, laboratory tours and summer research programs for undergraduate and high-school students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0725443</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tsybeskov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tsybesko@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>323 DOCTOR MARTIN LUTHER</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
