<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Scale Effect in Nanoscale Mechanical Resonance System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>259219</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Clark V. Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project aims for the thorough investigation of the scale effect and the associated energy dissipation in nanoscale mechanical resonator operated in air. An integrated research program is proposed which combines unique experimental approaches with advanced research tools and appropriate theoretical analyses. Nanoscale beam resonators integrating individual nanostructures will be developed. An all-electronics approach will be realized for the driving and sensing of the resonance. The experimental study will be further corroborated with theoretical analysis in order to gradually develop a comprehensive and solid understanding of scale effect and energy dissipation in such a nanosystem. &lt;br/&gt;The study of nanoscale mechanical resonator systems has previously mostly limited to vacuum environment or cryogenic temperature. The proposed study, besides providing fundamental knowledge on an interesting scientific subject, namely the scale effect in mechanical resonance system at the nanoscale, can ultimately lead to the development of novel nanoscale devices for high sensitivity mass and biomolecular sensing in ambient environment. A multifaceted educational program coupled with the proposed research provides also a perfect learning and training opportunity for the active participation and effective education of students and the public, which facilitates the wide dissemination and transfer of scientific knowledge and ultimately benefits the society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0726878</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Min-Feng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>minfeng.yu@ae.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1630</Code>
      <Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>027E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
