<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>More STEM Majors in Central Appalachia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>937920</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Geoffrey Prentice</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Appalachian College Association (ACA), a non-profit organization of 36 small, private, liberal arts institutions enrolling over 41,000 students in the Appalachian areas of five states (Kentucky, North Carolina, Tennessee, Virginia, and West Virginia) is awarding $6,000 scholarships to upcoming sophomores, juniors and seniors with declared majors in STEM areas. The program offers research/internship opportunities to students and provides support to recipients through personal and internet communication with other scholars, career planning assistance, and mentoring. Most of the ACA students are from Appalachia where the per capita income is 34.2% below the national average and the unemployment rate is 123.8% of the national average. The ACA is using this project to provide students with faculty support at a level and magnitude that is far greater than would happen if the individual institutions were not collaborating. This project is having a positive effect on the students, the schools they attend, and central Appalachia, with four expected outcomes: more students are majoring in STEM areas; scholarship recipients are learning about potential careers in Appalachia; research institutions are broadening recruitment efforts at ACA schools and more ACA students are pursuing post-baccalaureate studies; and the work force qualifications of recent college graduates in the Appalachian states are improving with the addition of more students who have skills crucial to attracting industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0727524</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aliceb@acaweb.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>julie.tan@ucumberlands.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Early</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>joee@acaweb.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Appalachian College Association</Name>
      <CityName>Berea</CityName>
      <ZipCode>404031733</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8599864584</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Center Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
