<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Comprehensive Scholarship Program for Mathematics, Physical, Biological, and Computer Science Majors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>584197</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Finger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Sixty-two academically talented, financially disadvantaged juniors and seniors majoring in STEM fields are being awarded annual scholarships of $4,000 enabling them to complete their degree requirements and graduate. Overall, 127 years of scholarship support are being awarded. The scholarships are increasing the number students from underrepresented groups graduating with a degree in a STEM field. All S-STEM scholars participate in the Science Educational Enhancement Services (SEES) program. SEES is an umbrella organization that functions as a learning community. SEES maintains student study and meeting rooms, computer facilities, as well as, a kitchen area. A variety of student services including faculty advisement, a Freshmen Orientation Course, a mentoring program, leadership and professional development guidance, and the Academic Excellence Workshop are available through SEES. The Academic Excellence Workshop provides peer-led academic support in science and mathematics and tutoring services.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0727137</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Burke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baburke@csupomona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cal Poly Pomona Foundation, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Pomona</CityName>
      <ZipCode>917682557</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9098692951</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3801 West Temple</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
