<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Partnership to Advance Retention and Success (PARS)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>31517</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ron Buckmire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project is providing scholarships to community college students majoring in science, technology, or mathematics during years 2-5 of the program after an initial year to accommodate setup. The project, serving a rural, remote area of 21,158 square miles in northeastern Arizona, is recruiting at least 48 student scholars, with 50% or more of these from populations underrepresented in the STEM disciplines. The aim is that at least 70% of these students complete their associate degrees during the grant period. Scholarship amounts will be allocated based on unmet need, with a maximum of $4,000 per student per academic year. The project emphasizes individualized, timely support services administered through a cohort system. Recruitment efforts target participants beginning in tenth grade. A seminar class, team-taught by faculty from STEM disciplines and from Student Services, as well as area STEM professionals, includes topics such as college success skills, career exploration, and university matriculation. Additionally, the seminar class provides a means for faculty to quickly identify struggling students and intervene. Other activities include job shadowing, professional mentoring and internship experiences, and university field trips to provide scholars with investment in their educational and career plans and to emphasize the connection between college and career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this work lies in the potential for the scholarships to recruit, educate, and mentor students from populations underrepresented in STEM fields, especially Native American students. The project is located in a region marked by poverty, and many of the scholars are the first in their families to attend college. Although academically talented, they are at-risk due to socioeconomic factors. The project is also teaming up with regional workforce partners, providing collateral benefit for employers who have an ongoing need for individuals qualified in the STEM disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0728405</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vest</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mvest@npc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Randy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Porch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rporch@npc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Canary</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pcanary@npc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northland Pioneer College</Name>
      <CityName>Holbrook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>860250610</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9285247610</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 610</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
