<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>In Situ Nanomanufacturing Process Control Through Multiscale Nanostructure Growth Modeling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cerry M. Klein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of the proposed research is to generate knowledge of in situ nanomanufacturing process control through multiscale nanostructure growth modeling and growth of metal-oxide nanowires with excellent optical properties. Standard statistical quality control (SQC) faces new challenges of scale effects which is unique to quality control of nanofabrication processes. Particularly, key process variables, varying with location and time, are measured at macro/micro scales. The quality characteristics of nanostructures would better be characterized as space-time random field measured in nanoscale. Relating macroscale process variables to nanoscale critical quality characteristics and defects requires multiscale model integration for in situ process control. The research therefore aims to model nanofabrication process, more specifically, nanostructure growth for in situ quality control in nanomanufacturing. Novel metal-oxide nanowires will be synthesized and characterized for wide applications in nanoscale electronic and optoelectronic devices.&lt;br/&gt;Toward this goal, we propose an interdisciplinary research plan including: (1) modeling of nanostructure birth and growth processes by integrating space-time random field models with nanostructure growth mechanisms, (2) multiscale in situ quality control of nanostructure growth through macroscale modeling of growth rate difference between substrates and nanoscale modeling of growth rate difference between locally homogeneous regions within individual substrates, and (3) controlled growth of novel metal-oxide based nanowires with excellent optical properties. The experimental work will provide data for multiscale modeling of nanostructure growth processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work is probably the first of its kind to control nanomanufacturing process quality through multiscale modeling of nanostructure growth processes. Successful completion of the proposed research may assist to expedite the transfer of fast-developing nanotechnology from the laboratory to industry application at lower cost. The proposed metal oxide nanowire fabrication research will provide promising building blocks for novel nano devices. A new breed of nanomanufacturing engineers will be educated through an integrated education plan.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0728100</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ashok</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kumar@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qiang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qiang.huang@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1786</Code>
      <Text>MANFG ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>073E</Code>
      <Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
