<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Expanding Undergraduate Educational Opportunities in Science, Mathematics, and Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599342</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joyce B. Evans</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With the goal of increasing the number of graduates qualified for careers in science, mathematics, engineering, and technology (STEM), this institution is awarding 14 four-year scholarships to full-time students in the class of 2012 who demonstrate financial need, show academic promise, and declare an intent to major in one of the eligible disciplines (Biology, Chemistry, Computer Science, Engineering Sciences, Mathematical Sciences, and Physics). The project builds upon the lessons learned from a previous NSF-funded CSEMS scholarship program. In particular, fewer but larger awards are being given so that efforts can be focused on a small group of students. While fewer students are participating, this approach is improving the chances that any one of these students will succeed. The course of study includes a demanding curriculum in the major as well as a strong grounding in the liberal arts. This background provides not only disciplinary expertise, but also the critical thinking and communication skills needed to succeed in today's global workplace. A cohort is being established among the students through participation in a first-semester course designed to orient them to college life and the sciences. In subsequent semesters, they are meeting in sessions to talk about science and their research interests with the other STEM scholars and science faculty. Some of the scholarship students are participating in mentored summer research experiences through the Loyola-sponsored Hauber Fellowship program. Others are taking advantage of internship opportunities coordinated by the college's Internship Coordinator. Throughout their academic careers, these students will be closely monitored and advised by the PI and the CoPIs, with appropriate support services provided. Student success is being carefully tracked in terms of grades, scholarships and awards, and student surveys.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0728492</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rpond@loyola.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbarr@loyola.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rsj@loyola.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dipa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sarkar-Dey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dchoudhury@loyola.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roberta</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sabin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>res@loyola.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Loyola University Maryland, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212102699</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4016172004</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4501 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
