<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Tech Scholars Program II</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>460000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joyce B. Evans</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Tech Scholars Program II (TSP-II) is recruiting and supporting qualified science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) students utilizing strategies that proved effective in a prior project. Targeted peer community-building and support services are being provided to recipients to increase opportunities for education, increase retention to baccalaureate degree achievement, and improve employability of low-income, academically talented students in Computer Science, Engineering, Mathematics, Physics, and Chemistry transfer programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The project is capitalizing upon an established network of committed TSP faculty, financial aid, and student services personnel. TSP-II scholars benefit from extensive academic support systems currently available in the college's Learning Center, including free tutoring and drop-in Mathematics, Science, Writing, Reading, and Study Skills assistance. TSP-specific support services are scholarships, the popular Tech Scholars Center (a designated room to hang out, study together, and get academic assistance), and monthly seminars providing relevant academic and career information. The project enhances the previous program by including additional majors, increasing award maximums to $5000, and establishing major-specific study groups to foster lasting cohorts that support students when they move beyond the college. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The project is addressing the need to increase the number of scientists and engineers because there is strong community support, robust transfer programs in targeted majors, and extensive articulation with high schools. The college provides a critical entrance into higher education for over half the district's high school graduates who choose college immediately after graduation. This project joins with the newly established TRIO program to strengthen the college's commitment to attract and retain students from groups underrepresented in scientific and technical areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0728689</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kidd</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.kidd@linnbenton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fred</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haynes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haynesf@linnbenton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Linn Benton Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Albany</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973213755</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5419174999</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6500 S W Pacific Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
