<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Eleventh and Twelfth Annual Meetings for the Society for Behavioral Neuroendocrinology 11-June 21-24, 2007 Los Angeles, CA-Twelfth Annual Mtg July 9-12, 2008 Netherlands</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>41006</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cedric L. Williams</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Society for Behavioral Neuroendocrinology is a multidisciplinary society that promotes research and education concerning hormones, the brain and behavior. The annual conference brings together scientists from many fields, with a focus on the integration of cellular and molecular concepts into functional frameworks that improve our understanding of human and animal behaviors. This grant will support significant initiatives to foster participation by undergraduate students, graduate students, and post-doctoral fellows at society meetings. Funds will support the following trainee activities: (1) Young Investigator's Symposium. Outstanding senior graduate students or post-docs are chosen to present talks in a dedicated symposium. This format recognizes the accomplishments of such trainees, facilitates their movement into more advanced positions, and motivates younger scientists. (2) Career Development Workshops. Workshops educate trainees on important career development topics and retain trainees in the sciences. (3) Travel Awards. Funding for travel to meetings is provided for trainees. This allows trainees to present their work in a supportive environment and gain exposure to the breadth and depth of the field. (4) Meet-The-Professor Lunches. Small groups of trainees have lunch and discussion with senior members of the society. Trainees thus gain insight into the research enterprise, create new relationships, and find strong mentors. (5) Trainee Poster Competition. Posters presented by undergraduates, graduate students, and post-doctoral fellows are judged, based on the scientific merit of the research, the effectiveness of the presentation and the trainee's role in the research. The competition is thus an educational experience for all and it also provides an opportunity to encourage and reward success at each level. Funding for trainee events at the SBN meeting will play a key role in the attraction and retention of the brightest and best-trained interdisciplinary scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0729560</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sunny</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boyd</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>boyd.1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
      <CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
      <ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
