<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Enhanced Performance Membranes by High Throughput Modification</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Title: Enhanced Performance Membranes by High Throughput Modification&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: CBET-0730449&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Georges Belfort&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main objective of this project is to develop a fast, efficient, and reproducible high throughput platform (HTP) modification method with photoinduced graft polymerization (PGP) that will allow synthesis, evaluation, and quick selection of the best polymer from many hundreds of functionalized surfaces. This work will also provide insights in analyzing the mechanism of grafting to guide design of surfaces for membrane separations. There is a need in the biotechnology, food, and wastewater treatment industries for new, low biofouling synthetic membranes. The scientific basis, for which surface or functional characteristics are needed to reduce membrane protein fouling, is largely empirical. The four specific aims for this research are: 1. To use a high throughput 96 membrane-well format for photo-grafting a large library of available commercial vinyl and amine monomers onto poly ether sulfone PES membranes. 2. To use the same high throughput 96 membrane-well format to test and screen for the best performing graft polymerized membranes from Aim 1 using single-solute filtration. 3. To use a high throughput 96 membrane-well format to optimize and fine-tune the grafting and filtration conditions for model proteins and three relevant biotechnology feeds. 4. To investigate from structure-property relationship modeling and from structural, kinetic and binding studies, the underlying mechanistic reasons why the successful monomers were able to perform best. The proposed study will have broad impact with respect to biochemical processes in the industries mentioned above. A new HTP method for materials development and elucidating some of the major requirements for a grafted protein resistant layer will be important outcomes. The best monomers for grafting PES that exhibit optimal performance with single protein feeds will be sought. Three of the most relevant biotechnology feeds, E. coli broth, Chinese hamster ovary cell culture, and bovine serum, will be used. Graduate and undergraduate students working on this project will be exposed to modern high throughput technology, interfacial science, analytical chemistry, correlation analysis and bioprocessing. Each year high school seniors will visit the PI's laboratory for a evaluation of the essential aspects of this research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0730449</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Georges</FirstName>
      <LastName>Belfort</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>belfog@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
