<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fifth Interdisciplinary Transport Phenomena Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Theodore L. Bergman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Fifth Interdisciplinary Transport Phenomena Conference &lt;br/&gt;Conference Chair: S.S. Sadhal&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conference Objectives and Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The main objectives of the conference are to disseminate and exchange new technical information and ideas among the various scientists and engineers working in Science and Technology with Fluid, Thermal, Biological, Materials and Space Sciences, and focusing on Transport Phenomena. Under this common theme, the conference will provide for the exchange of information on new scientific results, particularly concerning interdisciplinary aspects. Transport Phenomena encompassing both heat and mass transfer is indeed ubiquitous to many areas in the natural sciences, as well as engineering. While research over the last two decades has provided significant new insight into various physical phenomena, the new and upcoming scientific problems have brought about the interdisciplinary dimension to modern scientific research. There is at present a need to provide direction for research in which fluid flow and other transport processes to form a common basis for many investigations. For example, in physiology and medicine, as well as materials processing, fluid, thermal and mass-transport aspects have gained primacy among various researchers, and the sharing of expertise has become a necessity for technical and scientific progress. &lt;br/&gt;Impact &lt;br/&gt;Funding from NSF will enable some of the key US-based organizers to participate in the conference, and also provide support to attract some top-level keynote speakers, and additionally give some support to students, women and under-represented minorities. The organizers have recognized the importance of providing a forum for the exchange of ideas from a diverse group of researchers belonging to various types of research organizations. The proposed conference will provide for the free flow of ideas under this common theme of "Transport Phenomena" to promote healthy new research programs, and seek to bring interaction whereby scientists may be able to compliment each others' diverse expertise in new areas of interdisciplinary character.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0732124</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Satwindar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sadhal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sadhal@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/16/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
