<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Large-scale simultaneous multiple alignment and phylogeny estimation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>668640</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, a team of investigators will develop new algorithms and software to simultaneously align DNA sequences and reconstruct phylogenetic trees. This methods and theory-oriented project addresses an important problem in phylogenetic reconstruction: relatively poor performance of existing tools in the face of insertions, deletions, and duplications in large datasets. This project will develop a simultaneous approach to DNA sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis that will allow researchers to overcome these problems. Specific goals for the project will be to develop a portal and open-source software for simultaneous alignment and phylogenetic analysis, develop new simulators to model DNA sequence evolution, establish a working group on alignment methods with the Assembling the Tree of Life (AToL) community, and develop training programs in alignment and phylogeny estimation with outreach activities to minority institutions. The project includes many members of the Cyberinfrastructure for Phylogenetic Research (CIPRES) project and will provide significant new analytic capabilities for that data resource. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By making simultaneous alignment and phylogenetic analysis feasible for very large datasets, this project will provide software tools that will serve a broad community of researchers conducting phylogenetic analyses of DNA sequence data. These tools will enable consideration of DNA regions for phylogenetic analysis that cannot be aligned using existing tools. An open-source, portal interface will open multiple sequence alignment and tree-building to a broader range of users and engagement of existing AToL users will provide input and evaluation early in the software development process.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0732920</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Holder</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mtholder@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7689</Code>
      <Text>ASSEMBLING THE TREE OF LIFE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7689</Code>
      <Text>Assembling the Tree of Life</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
