<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of Geophysical Instrumentation for Enhancing Peatlands Research and Training of a Diverse Student Population in New Jersey</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>118334</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grants supports acquisition of near surface geophysical equipment that will facilitate research on biogenic gas reservoirs and fluxes from northern peatlands and arctic bogs. Specific equipment to be purchased includes: 1) a handheld frequency-domain electromagnetic system; 2) a time-domain, 10 channel resistivity/induced polarization system; and 3) upgrade of an existing ground penetrating radar (GPR) system to allow for simultaneous collection of data from two antennas operating at different frequencies (100 and 200 MHz). The equipment will allow for higher spatial resolution and time-series subsurface imaging of free phase gas (primarily bubble pockets of methane) in northern latitude peatlands. Research facilitated will support a better understanding of the temporal controls of carbon gas fluxes and estimation of reservoirs of ancient carbon pools in these systems that are could be released to the atmosphere as a consequence of global warming (a positive feedback resulting from anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions. The instrumentation will support undergraduate and graduate student experiences with state-of the-art geophysical equipment at both Rutgers University-Newark and New Jersey City University (NJCU), both located in urban areas with high percentages of underrepresented students (NJCU is a Hispanic Serving Institution). The PIs plan to involve students in industry-impacted regional subsurface investigations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0732250</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
      <LastName>Slater</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lslater@newark.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Montgomery</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wmontgomery@njcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University Newark</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>071021896</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9739720283</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Blumenthal Hall, Suite 206</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
