<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel for 21st Association of Computing Machinery Symposium on Operating Systems Principles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>27500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 21st ACM Symposium on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP 2007) is scheduled for October 14-17, 2007. This conference, spanning the last 40 years, has been the leading forum for innovative research in operating systems. SOSP 2007 brings together leading researchers in the field and features the best and brightest of the Ph.D. candidates in computer systems. The conference limits distractions and participants focus on the presentation and discussion of the latest results and trends in the field. Topics include the performance, functionality, and security of kernels, file systems, and networks, ubiquitous and mobile computing, sensor networks, overlay and peer-to-peer communications, and power management. The present NSF proposal requested funding to support the attendance of 22 US-based graduate students. Participation in leading conferences is an extremely important part of the graduate school experience, providing the opportunity to interact with more senior researchers and to be exposed to leading edge work. The support requested in this proposal makes possible the participation of students who would be otherwise unable to attend. Some supported students will also be presenters and co-authors of the select set of papers accepted into the conference program. Others actively participate through the poster and work-in-progress sessions of the program. This conference is an important part of the pipeline of researchers as they progress from graduate students to researchers known to others in the field, and continue to research careers in both academia and industry research labs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0733112</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bressoud</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bressoud@denison.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Denison University</Name>
      <CityName>Granville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>430230607</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7405876679</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O Box 713</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
