<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CogSci2007 Conference: Workshop on Computational Cognitive Modeling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vincent R. Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Across the sciences, computational modeling is one the most widely-used methods for linking different levels of analysis, to show how processes at one level can interact to produce emergent system behavior at another level. Within the cognitive science, computational modeling has been used to link neural, mental, and behavioral levels of analysis, for instance. Computational modeling has also served as a common ground for drawing links across the various disciplines that comprise the cognitive sciences, such as cognitive neuroscience, linguistics, computer science, psychology, anthropology, philosophy, and education. Computational modeling has clearly become a valuable and oftentimes needed skill in the cognitive sciences, yet there are barriers to acquiring and practicing this skill for students and junior investigators entering the field. To encourage the practice of computational modeling, the National Science Foundation will support student training in computational modeling at the 2007 Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society. Support is aimed at getting students interested and involved in computational modeling, and providing tutorials that might spur them to seek further training opportunities through their institutions and other resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0733493</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schunn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schunn@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
