<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2007 Applied and Environmental Microbiology Gordon Research Conference to be held in Mt. Holyoke College, S.Hadley, MA on July 15-20, 2007.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Applied and Environmental Microbiology will be held held July 15-20 at Mt. Holyoke College, S. Hadley, MA. The program covers a wide range of topics, seeking to investigate several areas of science that are in the midst of intellectual change and exciting new discoveries. The conference brings together two traditionally separated groups: basic and applied research microbiologists. The basic research aspect of the meeting is high-lighted by presentations on subjects such as mechanisms of electron transfer in the environment, new approaches to sequencing and genomics, community structure, microbial diversity, proteomics of natural communities, hydrogen-mediated ecophysiology, and new methods for visualizing cells and sub-cellular components of microbes. Applied lectures emphasize subjects such as microbial fuel cells, new types of biosensors, and new methods of cultivation of microbes of industrial interest. In many sessions basic research and applications talks are back to back to stimulate exchange. Speakers have been asked to present only state of the art new material, to leave ample time for discussion, and to challenge the audience with new ideas. Speakers and attendees will include both USA and foreign scientists. NSF funds will be used in particular to support young investigators, students, postdocs, and speakers and conferees from underrepresented groups in science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0733447</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nealson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>knealson@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1089</Code>
      <Text>MICRO OBS &amp; MICRO INTER &amp; PRO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9104</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1089</Code>
      <Text>MICRO OBS &amp; MICRO INTER &amp; PRO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
