<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Halophiles-2007: 7th International Congress Exploring Life at High Salinity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is an international travel grant to help cover the costs of students, postdoctoral researchers and other young investigators to attend the Halophiles-2007: 7th International Congress Exploring Life at High Salinity, 2-6 September 2007, University of Essex, Colchester, UK.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Halophiles 2007 meeting is a multidisciplinary international congress, with a strong history of regular triennial meetings since 1978. While focusing on halophilic organisms from all three domains of life and viruses, the conference also addresses commonalities between high salinity and other conditions in which water activity is reduced (e.g. desiccation, freezing, high organic solute concentration). The overarching aim for this meeting is to draw on expertise from numerous disciplines in order to enable advances in our understanding of life in high-salt environments, and in turn for the improved understanding to enhance other areas of science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In particular, this meeting is aimed at young scientists: A number of Assistant Professors have been added as invited speakers and will be given free passage and an opportunity to present. To this end, the organizers will increase the participation of US undergraduate students, graduate students, and post-doctoral researchers by offering them travel grants to defray the cost of their expenses. The application process will be aimed at members of underrepresented groups</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0735025</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bonnie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baxter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbaxter@westminstercollege.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Westminster College of Salt Lake City</Name>
      <CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841053617</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8014847651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1840 South 13th East</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
