<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Antarctica: Exquisite Light and Dark</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Winifred Reuning</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lisa Blatt (0735138)&lt;br/&gt;Antarctica: Exquisite Light and Dark&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"Antarctica: Exquisite Light and Dark" conceptualized by artist, Lisa Blatt is a photographic project that will result in a body of poetic, conceptual artwork that goes beyond the typical photographer working to simply document place. The artist will use a minimalist, non-traditional style of photography and video to draw the viewer into Antarctica's aesthetic beauty and use that as an ecological and scientific resource to educate viewers about the larger issues of Antarctica. The work will underscore the fragile Antarctic landscape's aesthetic, political and scientific importance. The artist's imagery will be combined to form an installation that will allow both the experience and feeling of place in the physical and emotional sense. She notes that this body of work will fit in with her larger body of landscape work that examines perception, the intersection of nature and culture and the junction of the still and moving image. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The artist plans to exhibit her work in a variety of venues in the United States and abroad that include a number of public outreach and education opportunities and has already secured commitments from a number of venues. As an early career artist, Ms. Blatt has done a remarkable job of getting her work shown in significant venues, consistently finding support and an audience for her projects. As such, the work, enthusiasm, and success demonstrated by the artist speaks well of the potential impact of the final project and the audience it will reach.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0735138</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blatt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Blatt Lisa K</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941231753</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0311000</Code>
      <Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
