<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Grant for International Conference on Algebraic Topology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposal envisions supporting travel to an international conference on algebraic topology to be held in Djerba, Tunisia, October 19-24, 2007. The principal focus of the conference will be on recent advances in homotopy theory connected with the study of classifying spaces, mapping spaces, p-compact groups, p-local finite groups, and unstable modules over the Steenrod algebra. Several of the areas of interest transcend research boundaries: the study of p-compact groups touches on geometry, the study of p-local finite groups involves finite group theory and modular representation theory, while the study of unstable modules over the Steenrod algebra impinges on invariant theory. The purpose of the conference is to consolidate these recent advances, facilitate communication between researchers in these areas, set directions for future research, and strengthen the connections with other fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two of the main themes in mathematics are geometry and algebra. Geometry, and its variants, such as topology, involve the study of higher dimensional shapes and their frequently subtle distinguishing qualities. Algebra, on the other hand, deals with ordinary numbers and their generalizations. Algebraic topology is a hybrid area which essentially looks for ways to extract interesting numerical information from shapes. Recently there have been major advances in the part of algebraic topology that is concerned with studying geometrical symmetries. The purpose of this proposal is to provide support for travel by researchers to an international conference devoted to presenting and discussing these advances. The conference will also contribute to establishing and reinforcing contacts between US, European, and North African mathematicians.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0735448</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dwyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>William.G.Dwyer.1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
      <CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
      <ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
