<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Design and Evaluation of a Pen-Based Tutoring System for Statics Instruction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>394338</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kenneth C. Whang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intelligent tutoring systems have been widely studied and applied to a variety of subjects. Most systems are based on traditional computer interfaces involving windows, icons, mouse, and pointer. Research shows that transfer from training to testing is greater when testing and training environments are similar, suggesting benefits from creating and evaluating tutoring systems with interfaces that match real-world problem-solving environments. This project aims to create pen-based tutoring systems that scaffold students in the same way they would ordinarily solve problems with paper and pencil. This goal is consistent with recent research comparing student performance across different user interfaces, demonstrating that the interfaces matching familiar work practice enhanced student performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;From a technology perspective, the project will produce basic algorithms and user interfaces for creating pen-based tutoring software. From an education perspective, the project will develop and evaluate innovative pedagogical principles for individualizing statics instruction in pen-based environments. Statics is a critical field required for engineering and science majors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will create computational techniques and tutoring systems for both tablet and pentop computers, and will assess the strengths and limitations of the two platforms. Comparisons will also be made with paper-and-pencil and traditional computer interfaces. A tablet computer has an LCD display with an integrated digitizer; the user writes directly on the display using a stylus. A pentop is a pen with an integrated digitizer and embedded processor. A pentop uses paper preprinted with a grid that allows the system to locate the pen tip and digitize pen strokes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The tutors build upon two prototype, pen-based tutoring systems recently developed by the research team. The first, Newton's Pen, is a statics tutor implemented on the LeapFrog FLY pentop computer. The second, Kirchoff's Pen, uses a tablet computer to help students apply Kirchhoff's current and voltage laws. Preliminary studies with Newton's Pen show it is an effective teaching tool. The prototypes uncovered several important research issues that will be ad-dressed by the proposal. The project will: (1) develop new techniques for interpreting hand-written input to enable more fluid interaction with pen-based devices, (2) develop improved, pedagogically-sound user interface design principles for pen-based tutoring systems, (3) expand the class of statics problems beyond those investigated with Newton's Pen, (4) assess the educational value (both learning and transfer) of the tutors, and (5) identify the relative strengths and weaknesses of tablet and pentop platforms for instruction.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0735695</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Calfee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robert.calfee@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stahovich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stahov@engr.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
