<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel to the World Forum on Smart Materials and Smart Structures Technologies 2007; China</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070010</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harsh Deep Chopra</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL: The World Forum on Smart Materials and Smart Structures Technology (SMSST'07) will be held in Chongqing and Nanjing, China from May 22-27, 2007. Chongqing University (CQU), Nanjing University of Aeronautics and Astronautics (NUAA), and Hong Kong Polytechnic University will jointly host the forum. The objectives of SMSST'07 are: (a) to update the state-of-the-art with new knowledge gains, (b) to analyze technological innovations and achievements, (c) to assess the potential impact for transforming Engineering Practices, (d) to promote international engagement through cooperative platforms (US-Europe, US-China, US-Japan), (e) to form partnerships with industry, and (f) to broaden the outlook for revolutionizing student and education programs. It is also intended to involve young U.S. scientists to expose them to different social, technical, and cultural perspectives in China through active participation in this world forum. SMSST'07 is a major worldwide event that will highlight the major advancements in smart materials and their applications to sensors and smart structures. It will also allow the world's top experts to map out future challenges in research and innovation, as well as analyze, critique, and finalize the reports submitted by the US-Europe, US-China, and US-Japan joint task groups. This student travel request asks for a fund to provide partial support to let six graduate students travel to China and attend SMSST'07. The intellectual merit of this project is embedded in providing a premier opportunity for scientific, professional, and industrial colleagues worldwide to share ideas on the most recent and advanced developments, identify common research problems, and promote international cooperative research in the emerging technologies of smart materials and structures. The collaborative research activities are expected to develop smart materials and smart structures, innovative utilization of sensor systems and mechatronics approaches in smart structural systems, reduction of disaster risks through the utilization of smart devices and systems, and effective prognostic and diagnostic evaluation of mechanical and civil systems by smart materials and smart structures. NON-TECHNICAL: SMSST'07 is designed to have a broad impact in the areas of integrated sensor systems, mechatronics, and smart materials and smart structure technologies for aerospace, civil and mechanical systems through international collaborations both in terms of research and education. The workshop will invite, and make every effort to include, the participation of young and underrepresented groups of researchers to enhance the diversity of representation and their involvement in scientific activities. SMSST'07 will also promote the international collaboration to leverage resources, and share technical data and research ideas for the mutual benefit of the United States and European and Asian countries. Students participating in SMSST'07 are likely to be future leaders in the area of smart materials and smart structure technologies. They will have an opportunity to meet and be exposed to world leaders in the area as well as to experience different social, technical, and cultural perspectives in China through active participation in this world forum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0737775</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Masayoshi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tomizuka</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tomizuka@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/22/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
