<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pathways to Meaningful Learning</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Finger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Engineering (59)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal focuses on understanding the relevance and importance of engineering and its impact on society. The proposal features community-based projects and experiential learning tied to the content of the newly approved core curriculum. The addition of concept maps and community based service learning helps to make connections to things which interest the students on a personal level and improves learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The complex engineering problems confronting students today require solutions that take into account the multi- dimensional aspects of their lives and environment. This project defines options for educational pathways that integrate material from a variety of courses with a common theme. Students intentionally construct a pathway that situates new knowledge into an existing framework helping them to develop the skills of self-monitoring and reflection.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project design provides meaningful learning through a curriculum that requires students to intentionally select a set pathway of STEM core courses related by a theme of interest to the student. The project establishes faculty development workshops; a community outreach office to support community-based projects and experiential learning as well as course development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0737110</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ruth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdavis@scu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shoba</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krishnan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>skrishnan@scu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Santa Clara University</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Clara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950530250</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4085544764</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 El Camino Real</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
