<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Workshop on Molecular and Materials Sciences; Cuernavaca, Mexico, October 9-11, 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harold Stolberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Americas Program award will help to support a workshop at the Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico (UNAM) in Cuernavaca, Mexico, October 9-11, 2007. Organized by Dr. David A. Micha of the University of Florida and Prof. Jose Recamier of UNAM-Cuernavaca, the workshop will address applications of theoretical and computational methods of quantum mechanics and statistical mechanics to several important areas, including biology, electronics and energy, simulations of complex materials and biological systems, and atomic and molecular collisions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The requested funds will support the travel of seven senior graduate students and three recent Postdoctoral Associates residing in the US to this workshop. The purpose is to promote scientific contacts between US junior researchers and other scientists from the countries of the Americas, leading to long term collaborations in the areas discussed at the workshop. Workshop results will be disseminated through posting of abstracts of presentations on the web and publishing results in refereed journals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0737952</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Micha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>micha@qtp.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
