<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Forum on Materials Science and Engineering Education for 2020, November 26-30, 2007, Boston, MA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070002</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Uma D Venkateswaran</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Materials Research Society (MRS) holds two meetings (the Fall meeting in December and the Spring meeting in April) each year. These meetings are attended by a large number (about 6,000 or more) of materials researchers and educators. Since 1996, nine Materials Education related symposia have been held at MRS meetings. These symposia have become a major forum where materials educators present results of innovative curriculum development, the use of new educational and pedagogical methods, lab and multimedia modules; discuss important current issues; and exchange ideas pertaining to Materials Science and Engineering (MSE) education. The topics discussed in these meetings have also included increasing the public awareness and understanding of materials, and outreach methods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Fall 2007 MRS meeting will be held in Boston from November 26-30, 2007. The ?Forum on MSE Education for 2020? at this meeting will consist of invited and contributed presentations on current Materials Education related activities and two panel sessions. Invited speakers and participants include faculty from high school, community colleges, and undergraduate and graduate institutions as well as science museum directors. The organizers will strive to have a diverse set of speakers from around the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS: The topics for discussion in this forum include several key issues concerning materials science education: (i) novel undergraduate and graduate curricula and courses, (ii) outcomes from selected NSF programs, (iii) approaches for increasing diversity in MSE programs, (iv) outreach through Nanoscale Informal Science education Network and other opportunities, (v) integration of cyber infrastructure, digital libraries and e-science, and (vi) international activities. Panel sessions planned will focus on ?Building infrastructure to support education initiatives,? and ?Addressing 'pipeline' issues through informal and K-12 science education.?</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0738610</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pachavis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pachavis@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>M. Grant</FirstName>
      <LastName>Norton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>norton@mme.wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
      <CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
