<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Biophotonics: Membranes as Motors: Investigating Nanoelectromechanical Characteristics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>185124</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0522862&lt;br/&gt;Anvari&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The applicant's main objectives are to understand the mechanism(s) of the electrically-induced piconewton level force generation in cell membranes and the molecular basis for modulation of this process through membrane electrical/mechanical properties and the interaction of transmembrane proteins such as prestin and anionic amphipathic agents such as solicyate.&lt;br/&gt; Specific objectives include: &lt;br/&gt;(1) Investigate the effects of membrane surface charge and tension on electrically-induced force generation in the absence of both prestin and the cytoskeleton; &lt;br/&gt;(2) Investigate the contribution of prestin to the overall electrically-induced force generation using model wildtype human embryonic kidney (HEK) cells, and HEK cells transfected with: (a) prestin, (b) mutated prestin, and (c) other proteins closely-related to prestin; and &lt;br/&gt;(3) Investigate electromechanical reciprocity using a voltage sensitive fluorescent dye incorporated into the membrane.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0738820</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bahman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Anvari</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anvari@engr.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
