<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Workshop on Structural Health Monitoring 2007; held at Stanford Univ.; September 11-13, 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Shih-Chi Liu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal is to request funding to support the International Workshop on Structural Health Monitoring to be held at Stanford University, Sept. 11-13, 2007. Structural health monitoring is an emerging technology, which integrates advanced sensing technology with diagnostics, prognostics, and knowledge of material/structural damage characteristics to estimate the health status of the structures, while in service, to prevent structural catastrophes, minimize downtime and sustain performance, and reduce maintenance cost. It is particularly important and attractive for sustaining operational readiness of national civil infrastructures, highways, critical facilities, and emergency hospitals, and power plants due to natural and man-made disaster while prolonging the life span of these structures in standard service. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Owing to the significant progress of the technology in recent years, the theme of the 2007 IWSHM will focus on "Quantification, Validation, and Implementation." The objectives of the Workshop are to acknowledge the progress of the current rapid development in the technologies related to the field, identify key and emerging issues in research and development, and promote exchanges and cross-fertilization across disciplines such as sensors, sensor systems, networking, computing, data mining, integrated design, diagnostics, prognostics, signal processing, multifunctional materials, and applications such as civil infrastructures, ground/air/space transportation vehicles, and marine structures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Experts from industry, academe, and government will be invited to participate and deliver lectures and presentations. Product exhibition and technology demonstrations will also be held. The workshop will conclude with panel discussions on key issues and concerns identified during the workshop. The workshop will result in proceedings of the technical presentations as well as in the formation of a technical committee consisting of key personnel from government, industry, and academe. Appropriate guidelines and recommendations for government agencies and industry to promote structural health monitoring development will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0738402</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fu-Kuo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fkchang@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
