<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthetic Chemical Models of Ammonium Arene Interactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/09/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174428</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research program focuses on the design and synthesis of molecules which will allow analysis of the interactions between cationic ammonium ions and arene rings. A combination of gas-phase (mass spectrometric), solution-phase (NMR), and solid-phase (x-ray crystallographic) analyses will be carried out on synthetic compounds placing ammonium ions in close proximity to arene rings in order to define the parameters involved in this cation-pi type interaction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award from the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program supports the research of Professor George W. Gokel, of the Department of Molecular Biology and Pharmacology at Washington University. Through the design, synthesis, and study of model compounds, Professor Gokel is exploring the potential interactions between the positively-charged groups found in some amino acids and the benzene-type rings found in other amino acids. Such interactions, while individually subtle in nature, may collectively play a significant role in determining the structure, properties, and function of polypeptides.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0739207</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gokel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gokelg@umsl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Saint Louis</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3145165897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ONE UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1948</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
