<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Experimental Investigation of Magma Generation in Subduction Zones: Hydrous Liquidus Phase Relations of Primitive Magmas from the Trans-Mexican Volcanic Belt</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>344732</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030107</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit. There is strong evidence from experimental petrology and olivine-hosted melt inclusions that H2O is important in the formation of supra-subduction zone mafic magmas. However, despite the increasing sophistication of geochemical and geodynamic models based in part upon these data, there is still a major gap in our knowledge of the P-T-XH2O conditions of magma generation in mantle wedges above subducting slabs. This project will test some fundamental ideas about arc magma generation by addressing the following questions:&lt;br/&gt;1. Do primitive magmas from the TMVB saturate with a lherzolite, harzburgite or pyroxenite assemblage at mantle pressures under hydrous conditions?&lt;br/&gt;2. Are there differences in the pressures at which H2O-rich magmas (probably formed by flux melting) and H2O-poor magmas (probably formed by decompression melting) last equilibrated with a mantle assemblage? Such differences could relate to transport and storage of subduction derived components within the wedge (e.g. do H2O-rich melts derive from closer to the slab).&lt;br/&gt;3. Are mantle equilibration temperatures and pressures for the H2O-poor primitive magmas consistent with advection and upwelling of hotter mantle from behind the arc?&lt;br/&gt;4. How do equilibration temperatures and pressures compare with predictions for the thermal structure of the mantle wedge based on 2D and 3D geodynamic models?&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide important constraints for evaluating the relative roles of fluid-flux and decompression melting in arcs and for testing geodynamic models of subduction systems by providing data on temperatures and H2O contents at various depths within the mantle wedge.&lt;br/&gt;Liquidus phase relations will be determined for five primitive melt compositions from the Trans-Mexican Volcanic Belt (TMVB) as a function of H2O content at mantle wedge pressures. Starting compositions span much of the global range of K2O and H2O for primitive arc magmas. Compositional effects of deep crustal fractional crystallization such parental basalts will be evaluated to test whether more evolved compositions can be "back-corrected" to primary melt compositions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. This project will integrate research and education through the involvement of a Ph.D. student at the University of Oregon. The student will participate in all aspects of the experimental research and will learn a spectrum of modern analytical and imaging techniques (FTIR, electron probe, SEM). An undergraduate student will also be involved in a senior thesis project. The interpretation of results will involve collaboration with a young scientist in Mexico, Dr. Vlad Manea (UNAM, Juriquilla, Mexico and Caltech), who is working on geodynamic modeling of subduction zones. John Donovan, a highly regarded electron beam instrument operator, will be involved in developing robust methods for analyzing hydrous run products.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0739065</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wallace</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pwallace@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>A. Dana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnston</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>adjohn@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1573</Code>
      <Text>PETROLOGY AND GEOCHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
