<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR PHASE I: Validation of Remotely Powered and Interrogated Microwire Temperature Sensors for Composites Cure Monitoring and Control</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cheryl F. Albus</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will refine a temperature sensing system comprised of a wireless reader capable of remote, simultaneous interrogation of multiple, uniquely identified amorphous microwire temperature sensors that can be embedded permanently beneath layers of carbon fiber. Current manufacturing methods for carbon fiber reinforced polymer (CFRP) composites do not employ real time temperature feedback from the critical interior of thick parts because no practical wireless temperature sensors exist. The results from this project will contribute to a better understanding of this sensing system for composites curing, as well as a new autoclave control system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial aircraft industry's rapidly expanding use of CFRP composites is driving marketplace demand for curing process enhancements. Thus, aerospace companies and suppliers are immediate targets for commercialization of the microwire temperature sensing system and its resultant enhanced curing control system. Anticipated improvements to the speed of microwire-enhanced curing processes may also accelerate the use of CFRP composites within the automobile industry. Furthermore, their extremely low thermal mass and resultant fast thermal response should allow faster composite curing devices employing real time feedback, such as microwave ovens for initial cure and induction heaters for repair cure, further speeding global CFRP composites use.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/08/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/08/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0740294</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clothier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clothier@thermalsolutions.tv</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Thermal Solutions, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Wichita</CityName>
      <ZipCode>672262617</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3166300471</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8441 E 32nd St. North</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
