<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:Development of Critical Hydrogen Halogen Technologies for Efficient Energy Storage, Hydrogen Production and Carbon Dioxide Sequestration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99938</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cynthia A. Znati</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to better understand the fundamental technologies relating to the hydrogen/chlorine regenerative fuel cell system through a series of laboratory experiments, and will be the first step along a product development pathway leading to the creation of hydrogen generation, energy storage, and novel atmospheric management products. The project will conduct research involving laboratory cells to collect parametric data to assist in modeling the system as it relates to these important applications. A well qualified team will address key technical limitations identified in previous research; including enhancing hydrogen electrode durability during shutdown periods, elimination of parasitic shunt currents through novel bipolar plate designs, and optimization of mass transport at the halogen electrode through flow field optimization. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential from this technology will be efficient hydrogen production, energy storage and carbon dioxide sequestration. The diversity of product applications that can be addressed through the development of this technology is very large.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/30/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0740319</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Trent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Molter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>trent.molter@sustainableinnov.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Sustainable Innovations, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Glastonbury</CityName>
      <ZipCode>060331709</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8609185432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>114 Harvest Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1417</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL &amp; BIOLOGICAL SEPAR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9163</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
