<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Formaldehyde Measurements During BEARPEX (Biosphere Effects on Aerosols and Photochemistry Experiment) at Blodgett Forest 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34944</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric J. Hintsa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to investigate gas phase formaldehyde (HCHO) in a forested environment during summer/fall 2007 through an opportunity that recently arose. The novel technique of quantum cascade laser (QCL) absorption spectroscopy will be applied to HCHO measurements and the study of photochemical oxidation of hydrocarbons in Blodgett Forest, California, as part of the Biosphere Effects on Aerosols and Photochemistry Experiment (BEARPEX). If successful, this research could lead to significant advances in understanding of the atmospheric processing of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) and their concurrent HCHO production, and could help to validate the hypothesis that the pine forest at Blodgett is emitting a large flux of organic carbon in the form of highly reactive VOCs that are oxidized within meters of the forest canopy. Investigation of the formaldehyde budget at Blodgett will also provide insight into the formation rates of secondary organic aerosols and ozone in forests.&lt;br/&gt; This research will help to fulfill the goals of BEARPEX, and could lead to new results on atmospheric oxidation and the radiative and climate impacts of secondary organic aerosols and ozone formation. The work will be primarily conducted by a graduate student, and will promote the integration of research and education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0741375</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Faloona</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>icfaloona@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
