<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ACM WUWNet Workshop 2007: Student Travel Awards, will be held in Montreal, Quebec, Canada on September 14, 2007.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zygmunt J. Haas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Integrative, Hybrid and Complex Systems&lt;br/&gt;Jun-Hong (June) Cui&lt;br/&gt;University of Connecticut&lt;br/&gt;ACM WUWNet Workshop 2007: Student Travel Awards&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project supports travel for U.S. students to the Second ACM International Workshop on Underwater Networks (ACM WUWNet 2007). The travel support is for students who might not otherwise be able to attend the workshop. This workshop has emerged as an important workshop on underwater communication and networking, which is an increasingly important topic area due to a growing need for underwater monitoring for environmental and security applications. The workshop seeks to encourage the participation of graduate students from electrical engineering, computer engineering, computer science, and other related disciplines. Students present their work in technical presentations, posters, and demonstrations and also participate in workshop organization and logistics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The travel support can improve the education of graduate students through participation in the workshop and associated interaction with leading researchers and other students. The selection process emphasizes support for those students who might not otherwise be able to attend the workshop. The selection process also considers the student's research activity in underwater communication and networking. Preference will be given to women and other students from underrepresented groups, thus addressing the need for increased diversity in research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0741844</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jun-Hong (June)</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cui</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jcui@cse.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
