<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: Force Feedback Control of a Shape Memory Alloy Active Catheter for Minimally Invasive Micro-Surgery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>184110</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I research project extends the capability of a novel dexterous endoscope by providing force feedback to the operator in minimally invasive surgery. The project builds on innovations in sensing, actuation, manufacturing, and control of the MicroFlex Scope (MFS) and adding capabilities for integrated force sensing, design, simulation, and testing of a bilateral teleoperation architecture suited to the unique MFS shape memory alloy actuator characteristics, user evaluation on tissue in representative procedures, and preliminary design of a cost effective force feedback manipulative. The project investigates the feasibility of two types of integrated force sensing in the MicroFlex tip, as well as force feedback architectures and control designs appropriate to the shape memory alloy actuation in the MicroFlex device. Design of a cost-effective force feedback manipulative will also be carried out, based on the requirements determined from the simulation and test results.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Force Feedback MicroFlex Scope technology extends the reach of minimally invasive surgery to previously inaccessible locations in the body, and simultaneously improves the dexterity and control of endoscope motions in those locations. This enables new surgical procedures for previously inoperable conditions. It also enables existing procedures to be conducted with less patient trauma, reducing discomfort and recovery time, and allowing many more procedures to be conducted in outpatient and office settings, rather than in expensive operating rooms. Medical specialties that would benefit include: neurology, neonatology, pulmonology, gastroenterology, urology, and rhinology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/09/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0741015</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
      <LastName>VonOhlsen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jonvo@quest-corp.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/09/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Quest Product Development Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Arvada</CityName>
      <ZipCode>800077570</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3036705088</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6833 Joyce Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
