<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: MusicianLink Platform for Audio Collaboration and Real-time Distributed Audio Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ian M. Bennett</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Research (STTR) Phase I project is to develop a low-latency network-based quality of service (QoS) framework, for hosting a new class of distributed audio signal processing algorithms. The technique reveals connection quality using high-quality audio streaming as a closed-loop resonant probe. Users "pluck" a bidirectional stream much as if it were a guitar string in which sound waves travel in a recirculating manner. Network round-trip time is the natural pitch of the "string" while jitter and packet loss cause vibrato and interferences in the sound. Any path supporting any application consisting of low-latency interactive flows can be tuned according to qualities revealed by the resulting tone. Immediate and intuitive, the sound is a complement to graphical and statistical techniques for monitoring connection&lt;br/&gt;quality. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed technique is one example of a wider class of applications involving real-time distributed signal processing over the Internet. This Phase I STTR proposal addresses the technology transfer aspect of the technology, and initiates a joint university/small business research venture. The intended outcome puts into broad use the first commercially-available example of this class of applications in music collaboration, telepresence, and teleconferencing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0741278</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Willyard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dwillyard@musicianlink.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>MusicianLink, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951281310</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4089851777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2401 Cory Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
