<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Nano-Optoelectronics Workshop (i-NOW): Graduate Student Travel Support will be held in Beijing and Lanzhou, China on July 29-August 11, 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric G Johnson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ECCS-0741345&lt;br/&gt;Constance J. Chang-Hasnain, Univ of California-Berkeley&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;The technical scope of iNOW focuses on multidisciplinary research areas covering a wide span of traditional disciplines, including physics, chemistry, biology, electrical engineering, material science and engineering, mechanical engineering, optoelectronics and system integrations. The key element that brings scientists from this vast spectrum of disciplines together is nano-science and nano-technology, which are key research and development thrusts world wide. In addition to many active research efforts taken place in the US, it is critical for the students to understand the research currently being actively pursued in the world. The iNOW will feature the state-of-the-art in nanoscale semiconductor processing and synthesis; new physics on the tailorable optical, electrical and thermal properties; advanced characterization techniques; novel devices with new functionalities; and system applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: &lt;br/&gt;One major iNOW mission is to establish bridging and networking opportunities for students and researchers. A unique part of iNOW is a schedule with ample amount of time for interaction, discussion and cultural experiences. Three student poster and three rump sessions are planned for this purpose. The rump session topics include Strategic Research and Engineering Innovation, Market and Business Opportunities, and Success Stories. We expect exciting discussions, invigorating debates and interactive opportunities. We hope they will stimulate future collaborations and spark ideas for future breakthroughs. The interdisciplinary cultural experience will be invaluable to graduate and undergraduate students who will attend iNOW.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0741345</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Constance</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chang-Hasnain</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cch@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
