<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposia on Anthropology, World's Fairs and Anthropology Archives, at the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Pacific Division Conference; Waimea, HI; June 2008</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Deborah Winslow</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides partial travel support for some participants in four symposia to be held at the annual meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Pacific Division, June 15-16, 2008. The goal of the symposia is to bring together senior researchers and doctoral candidates in anthropology who conduct research in Southeast Asian countries to consider the history and current status of anthropology in those countries. Topics to be discussed include the impact of foreign conquest, regime change, and cultural change on the science of anthropology in Japan, Korea, China, Vietnam, and the Philippines. Because many of the participants are scholars and graduate from the countries being discussed, the symposia will contribute to international scientific cooperation and education, as well as to anthropological science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742024</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
      <LastName>Christianson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rchristi@sou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Oregon University</Name>
      <CityName>Ashland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>975205001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5415528662</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1250 Siskiyou Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
