<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Virtual Organization for Cyber Design</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>190000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Award CMMI-0742730 &lt;br/&gt;Engineering Virtual Organization for Cyber Design&lt;br/&gt;PI: Mark F. Horstemeyer, Mississippi State University&lt;br/&gt;Participating Institutions: Mississippi State University, University of California San Diego, Tuskegee University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of the proposed 'Engineering Virtual Organization for CyberDesign' is to integrate disparate, independent, research areas at different locations to accelerate agglomeration of structure-properties relations into material models for simulating design and manufacturing processes. These disparate areas include material characterizations performed at the University of California San Diego (UCSD), experimental mechanical properties such as high-rate stress-strain relations performed at Tuskegee University (TU), and computational mechanics performed at Mississippi State University (MSU). The results of such an agglomeration of a wide variety of information with complex interactions at different locations will lead to predictive science models to help higher fidelity, validated designs of structural components. &lt;br/&gt;This project will bring about broader societal impact, falling into three categories. First, it will provide an interdisciplinary environment for integrating the frontiers of material science, mechanics, and computer science. An example is the new Integrated Computational Materials Engineering (ICME) initiative that has recently started. We envision that this initial VO will be extended by incorporating other new disciplines, for example, biomechanicians and biologists to study the mechanical structure-human body interactions to improve the safety of designs. Second, it will provide an example of applying state-of-the-art information technologies for scientific discovery that can be replicated in different application domains, such as astronomy, or archeology. Finally, the proposed VO provides an opportunity to revolutionize the way in which our future engineers are trained. For example, a student at UCSD will be able to characterize material structure locally but garner mechanical information remotely from TU and use theoretical models remotely from MSU.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/18/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742730</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Horstemeyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mfhorst@me.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tomasz</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haupt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haupt@cavs.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
      <CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1403</Code>
      <Text>PROCESS &amp; REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7231</Code>
      <Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>047E</Code>
      <Text>REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
