<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Peru Workshop: International Collaborations in Cyberinfrastructure-enabled Genomics Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13308</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Garie A. Fordyce</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Buell&lt;br/&gt;0742699 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This 3-day workshop is to be jointly sponsored by NSF and the science agencies of Latin America (Peru, Chile, Brazil, others). The workshop will explore opportunities, challenges and breakthrough activities to help bring international collaborative genomics research to a new level. The meeting will include 30-40 invited genomics researchers, CI technologists, and funding agency representatives. It will focus on identifying activities that will enable North and Latin American partnerships, with an eye towards a more inclusive western hemisphere approach. Outcomes will include recommendations for follow-up activities and suggestions for investments to promote international genomics-CI research, education and outreach collaborations. Key foreign collaborators in Peru are Dr. Gisella Orjeda, Head of the Genomics Research Unit, and Dr. Jose Segovia Juarez, professor, department of Physics, Informatics and Mathematics.at the University Peruana Cayetano Heredia. This workshop will be jointly supported by the Office of International Science and Engineering, the Office of Cyberinfrastructure, and the Directorate for Computer and Information Science and Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742699</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>C. Robin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>buell@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
