<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Synthesis and Structural Characterization of Lanthanide-Based Silicides and Germanides</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>538956</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to understand the relationships among the composition, structure, and electronic structure in complex intermetallic compounds and their properties. Using rationally designed syntheses, we will seek to develop new classes of intermetallic compounds that are based on the lanthanide elements and the heavier carbon analogues, Silicon and Germanium. This research will involve thorough and systematic crystallographic studies (single- crystal and powder X-ray and/or neutron diffraction) of the complicated crystal chemistry and the possible stoichiometry breadths of many of these phases. The derived principles will be then applied for rationalization of the structures of more complex ternary phases and the corresponding phase equilibria. The fundamental goal of these investigations will be gaining better understanding of the structural relations together with the effect they have on the magnetic and electronic properties. Ultimately, the comprehensive knowledge gained from these studies will be used as a foundation for the reasoned tuning of properties of interest of the newly synthesized materials. It is anticipated that this project will advance the P.I.'s group to the forefront of this research and will allow the principle investigator to make significant contributions to the fast growing field of solid-state and materials chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The efforts outlined in this proposal are broadly aimed at establishing the fundamentals and the infrastructure for solid-state and materials chemistry education and research within the Department, the College and the University of Delaware as a whole. The proposed studies are highly interdisciplinary, encompassing chemistry, physics, and materials science, and will give excellent training in solid-state research to graduate and undergraduate students. Special attention will be paid to recruiting students from traditionally under- represented backgrounds and encouraging their active participation in the project development and advancement. This will allow them to be more competitive on the job market by going on to various careers and actively contributing to the nation's scientific progress. Also, the successful outcome of the research program discussed in the proposal is anticipated to boost the scientific presence of the University of Delaware in the solid-state chemistry arena, and to have a direct positive impact on intra- and inter-departmental collaborations across campus.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0743916</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Svilen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bobev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bobev@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
