<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: An International Synthesis of Precipitation Change Experiments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>44005</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010209</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Human-induced global climate change is rapidly emerging as one of the most important global societal concern of the 21st century. Scientists have made considerable progress in understanding how ecosystems will be affected by global warming, yet less is known about how they will respond to related changes in rain and snowfall. The goal of this workshop will be to synthesize the growing body of knowledge on precipitation impacts on ecosystems. Specific objectives are: (1) to integrate data from numerous field experiments on the effects of precipitation change on key ecosystem characteristics, (2) to identify interactions between changing precipitation patterns and other forms of environmental change such as increasing air temperatures, increasing levels of carbon dioxide, and other air pollutants, and (3) to identify ecological processes and geographical regions that may be particularly vulnerable to future changes in precipitation. These objectives will be addressed by conducting a statistical comparison of results from 53 ecosystem-scale precipitation experiments that have been conducted around the world. This will be accomplished through a series of activities, including: participation of key international scientists, development of an integrated database of experimental results, statistical analyses of key ecosystem responses, and science meetings to review analyses, formulate new hypotheses, and produce publications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Changing precipitation patterns are likely to have a variety of effects that will be of concern to society including causing changes in biodiversity, altering wildfire risk, and modifying the supplies of freshwater for human uses. As public concern heightens over the impacts of global climate change, an urgent need exists for a sound scientific basis on which to formulate policies regulating greenhouse gas emissions in order to avoid dangerous interference with the Earth?s climate system. This workshop effort will contribute significantly to meeting these information needs. In addition, this activity will strengthen international scientific relations, promote the participation and leadership of women in global climate change science, and contribute to the training of the next generation of global climate change scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0743050</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Loik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mloik@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
