<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transcriptional control of neuronal differentiation in drosophila</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James O. Deshler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The ability of humans to think, learn, remember and move relies on the formation of networks of specific connections between neurons. Neurons are specialized cell types in the nervous system that extend projections called axons, through which neurons communicate with each other. A principle question in neurobiology is to understand how precise connections between neurons arise during development. But, even in simple nervous systems like that of the fruit fly Drosophila melanogaster, the patterns of connections between most neurons have not been characterized. As a result, it has been difficult to investigate the roles of genes that function in establishing the overall morphology and projection patterns of neurons. The goals of the proposed research are (i) to identify molecular markers that label the projection patterns of individual neurons in the fruit fly central nervous system, (ii) to establish a detailed map which correlates the projection patterns of these neurons with the expression patterns of proteins known to control neuronal development, and (iii) to understand how these proteins, which act as transcription factors in the nucleus to turn on or off the expression of other genes, control the interconnections and functions of individual neurons. This work will provide insight into how precise networks of connections between neurons arise during development, resulting in a better understanding of the cellular and molecular control of simple and complex behaviors. In addition, the proposal integrates research at a research university with the biology curriculum of a liberal arts college, creating over 90 opportunities for undergraduates to contribute to scientific research, and providing exceptional training for potential careers in the biomedical sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0744261</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Skeath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jskeath@genetics.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kirsten</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gussk@dickinson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University School of Medicine</Name>
      <CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Campus Box 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
