<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nuclear Mechanisms that Influence Mitochondrial Genome Stability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen C. Cone</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The plant mitochondrial genome has acquired, during its evolution, several distinguishing features that are not well understood mechanistically or in evolutionary context. One of these is a process of asymmetric (non-reciprocal) recombination that appears to directly influence plant reproduction. Until now, our understanding of these processes has been hindered, in part, by the unavailability of effective model systems for investigating nuclear gene influence on the process. The effects of three nuclear genes, MSH1, OSB1 and RECA3, have recently been analyzed on mitochondrial genome stability. RECA3 and MSH1 function in distinct but overlapping pathways, while OSB1 cooperates with MSH1, to regulate the appearance of specific recombination products in Arabidopsis mitochondria. The principal investigators have recently shown that MSH1 functions similarly in tobacco, tomato, soybean and millet, but MSH1 RNAi knockdowns in these species also condition cytoplasmic male sterility. The principal investigators are now in a position to analyze the mitochondrial genome changes that occur when mutations in these nuclear genes permit normally rare recombination activity to occur at high frequency, and to compare the consequences of this recombination in multiple plant species. The central hypothesis is that MSH1, OSB1, and RECA3, together with specific breakage sites in the genome, represent components of an interacting network that operates in plant mitochondrial recombination-dependent replication initiation. The principal investigators propose that double-strand DNA breaks occur at specific locations within the mitochondrial genome to initiate recombination and replication, and that MSH1, OSB1 and RECA3 are involved in preventing recombination between repeats that are shorter than a few hundred bases. The principal investigators test these hypotheses by identifying double-strand breaks in repeated sequences, and in the Atp9, Atp6, CoxII and Rpl16 genes, in which there is evidence of recombination activity. This analysis is complemented by studies of inducible changes in tobacco, tomato, soybean and millet mitochondrial genomes that occur with MSH1 suppression and male sterility induction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a unifying model for recombination-dependent replication of plant mitochondrial genomes, and provide insights into the mechanisms for the induction and suppression of cytoplasmic male sterility, a phenomenon of agricultural importance that leads, in nature, to the gynodioecious reproductive strategies of approximately 5% of world plant species. The minority student training opportunities associated with this proposal will involve alignment with the Young Nebraska Scientist (YNS) Program, in which an undergraduate YNS student will participate in this research each summer.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0744104</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sally</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mackenzie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smackenzie2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Arrieta-Montiel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmontiel2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Christensen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>achristensen2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/15/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1116</Code>
      <Text>EUKARYOTIC GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9109</Code>
      <Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
