<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Control of Fission Yeast Cell Morphogenesis by Rho GAP Rga4 and the Conserved Protein Kinase Orb6</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>535000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Although substantial progress has been made in understanding cell morphogenesis, many of the molecular mechanisms involved in this process are still unknown. This project investigates the molecular basis of cell morphogenesis, especially how the dynamics of the cytoskeleton is spatially controlled within the cell. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fission yeast ser/thr protein kinase, Orb6, which is required for maintenance of cell polarity, belongs to the NDR/LATS family of AGC kinases, whose members play a key role in the control of cell morphology and cell proliferation in several organisms. Currently, there is a very limited understanding of the cellular functions of this conserved kinase family and no knowledge of its target effectors in the control of cell morphogenesis. The objective of this project is to establish the function of Orb6/NDR kinase in the spatial control of Rho GAP Rga4, using a combination of genetic, biochemical and microscopic approaches. The results of this research project will provide targets/effectors of a conserved signaling pathway with implications for morphogenesis and growth control in higher organisms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of this project will be to provide training opportunities for students of different backgrounds and educational levels, including graduate, undergraduate, high school, as well as those participating in a K-8 science outreach program. Because of the specific geographical location of Miami, many students are from different minority backgrounds. The laboratory provides a resource for other researchers in 2-hybrid analysis, yeast genetics and microscopy techniques.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0745129</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fulvia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Verde</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fverde@miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami School of Medicine</Name>
      <CityName>Coral Gables</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
