<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: The Role of Early Splicing Factors in Tissue-specific Alternative Splicing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>164049</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen C. Cone</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The process of messenger RNA splicing, whether general or alternative, regulates gene expression in a highly conserved manner from flies to humans and maximizes the number of proteins that one gene can produce. Yet little is known about the earliest and most critical steps of splicing regulation, when intron and exon borders of pre-mRNA are first recognized and defined by the spliceosome. Although over 200 proteins associated with the spliceosome have been identified, exactly how these proteins function with one another in a living organism remains unclear. The testis of the fruit fly Drosophila melanogaster provides an ideal in vivo model system to examine splicing regulation in a tissue specific manner. This project takes advantage of the wide spectrum of genetic manipulations and biochemical analysis possible in flies to examine the function of proteins integral to tissue specific splicing. The overall aims are: 1) to detect alternative splicing events in these fly testis tissue, 2) to identify transcripts that are responsive to reductions in the level of early splicing factors and 3) to identify regulatory splicing proteins associated with the early spliceosome.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The experiments listed above will be conducted primarily by undergraduate science majors during summer/academic year research experiences outside of normal coursework at Widener University. The University provides free summer housing to students engaged in summer research and will grant release time from the principal investigator's normal teaching load to supervise research students. In the past five years at Widener, a significant number of student researchers have been women, underrepresented minorities or first generation college students. All of these demographics are represented in the students in this new principal investigator's first research group. In addition to providing supplies, equipment and salaries, this RUI project will expose underrepresented groups to the research process and allow them to attend and present their research at meetings such as the Annual Drosophila Research Conference. The project will provide support for undergraduate students to actively participate in an important research problem and their results will greatly enhance the understanding of splicing within the framework of a living organism.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0745788</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>ALEXIS</FirstName>
      <LastName>NAGENGAST</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nagengast@pop1.science.widener.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Widener University</Name>
      <CityName>Chester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>190135700</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6104994396</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One University Place</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1116</Code>
      <Text>EUKARYOTIC GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1154</Code>
      <Text>GENE EXPRESSION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
