<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Unusual neuromodulatory control of spinal cord function</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>359998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Tyramine, octopamine, and tryptamine belong to a family of endogenous amines called trace amines (TAs) that have structural and metabolic similarities to the 'classical' neurotransmitters serotonin, dopamine, and nor-epinephrine. While receptors for TAs were recently identified, their physiological relevance remains elusive. This project seeks to reveal that these substances control leg movements by acting on the spinal cord circuits responsible for locomotion. TAs are applied directly to the spinal cord to characterize their modulation of neural circuit function. In addition, electrical recordings from limb muscles are coupled with video-based analyses of limb movements to allow quantitative study of locomotor cycle-based activity patterns, detailing the effects of TAs on motor performance. The advances made will spur investigations that impact our understanding of how the spinal cord is 'engineered' to control locomotion. Overall, this project establishes ground-breaking science and methodology that incorporates cross-disciplinary mentoring of underrepresented engineering students from the Georgia Institute of Technology with training in the biological sciences at Emory, and a broadening of their activities through participation in conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0745164</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hochman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shochm2@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Emory University</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
