<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Heterogeneous Cell Carriers to Promote Gradiated Tissue Formation Under Mechanical Loading - An Integrated Education and Research Study</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Friedrich Srienc</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0746209&lt;br/&gt;Temenoff&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Interfaces between different tissue types are found throughout the body and are crucial to the proper functions of all major organ systems. However, in many cases, it remains unclear how these interfaces form, making it extremely difficult to recreate appropriate interactions between disparate tissues after injury. An anticipated outcome of this project is that a controlled, three-dimensional coculture system as a model for interface development in orthopaedic tissues will be developed. This project is significant because the model system will provide key information about the role of cell-matrix interactions in promoting a gradient of phenotypic expression by mesenchymel stem cells (MSCs) under tensile loading, such as that experienced at the bone-ligament interface in vivo. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The education project includes the creation of new and innovative teaching materials at the high school, college, and graduate levels that will advance understanding and appreciation of the complex processes required to assure safety of modern biomaterials, and highlight limitations of current biomaterials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0746209</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Johnna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Temenoff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johnna.temenoff@bme.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
