<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Exploratory Investigation into the Wave Disc Engine Principle</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Phillip R. Westmoreland</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Number: CBET-0746263 &lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Mueller, Norbert H. &lt;br/&gt;Affiliation: Michigan State University&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: SGER: Exploratory Investigation into the Wave Disc Engine Principle&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to use analytical and numerical models to investigate fluid behavior in wave-disc engines, particularly for a novel micro-scale engine. In these wave engines, external or internal combustion generates a shock wave that can enhance combustion and transmit energy similar to that between the turbine and compressor in a regular gas turbine. However, wave engines appear to offer higher efficiency with fewer moving parts than in conventional turbines. Conventional steady-state turbomachinery loses efficiency as it shrinks in size due to wall effects on convective flow velocities, and the proposed micro-wave engine would not suffer such losses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this exploratory work, a new analytical model will be created and then validated using a commercial computational fluid dynamics software package, FLUENT(R). An unsteady-flow model will be combined with classical turbomachinery principles, including jet propulsion at the channel outlets. In the wave engine, the wave rotor is the sole source of energy for the system; therefore, the channels must extract energy from the flow in order for the rotor to spin and produce power. The technical challenge is to combine Euler?s equation for turbomachinery with shock-wave and duct-flow principles in order to produce a model that predicts energy transfer in the system accurately. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of the research is to develop increased understanding of the principles that govern micro-scale turbomachinery and micro-scale unsteady-flow devices. In addition to enhanced efficiencies for microscale engines, devices such as the wave engine may be used in future to create electrical power. These devices could replace batteries or allow compact, mobile power generation units including such as for hybrid cars.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0746263</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Norbert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mueller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mueller@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
