<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Investigations of Zirconium-Catalyzed Phosphorus-Element Bond-Forming Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>653900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic, and Organometallic Chemistry Program and the Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR) to Professor Rory Waterman of the University of Vermont and State Agricultural College addresses catalytic methodologies used to form bonds between phosphorus and other main-group elements. The research has particular relevance due to the importance of phosphorus-containing molecules in biology, fine chemicals (including chiral phosphine ligands), polymers, and materials science. Specifically, the research will investigate zirconium-mediated reactions that catalytically activate phosphorus-hydrogen bonds to form new molecules in useful and selective ways. Catalytic reactions that build phosphorus-element bonds are quite rare yet, but with a greater understanding of the fundamental processes that govern these bonds, new catalysis reactions are envisioned which will improve selectivity and afford novel products. Through a Project SEED program established by the PI at the University of Vermont, economically disadvantaged and underrepresented minority high school students will be encouraged to participate in summer research alongside University of Vermont graduate and undergraduate students. The PI will also develop a new general chemistry course directed at educating undergraduates in civic science literacy with the goal of reducing the difference in understanding practical science between science and non-science majors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0747612</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Waterman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Rory.Waterman@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Vermont &amp; State Agricultural College</Name>
      <CityName>BURLINGTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>054050160</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8026563660</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>85 SO. PROSPECT ST.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Vermont</StateName>
      <StateCode>VT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
