<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Industry Workshop on Nanotechnology for Cement and Concrete; held September 5, 2007; Arlington, VA.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>lawrence bank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The primary objective of the workshop is to provide direction on areas of priority interest and opportunities for collaboration between industry, university and public agencies for research into nanotechnology for cementitious systems and concrete products. The workshop will bring together national and international researchers and practitioners dealing with cementitious construction materials to discuss applications of nanotechnology. The primary focus will be on identifying the needs of the construction industry and how these needs can be met by nano-engineering at the materials level. Emphasis of the discussions will be on how nanotechnology can be brought into useful applications in construction as quickly as possible, based on sound fundamental research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cementitious materials are the most commonly used class of materials in the world and hence even a small improvement in efficiency can have a major impact. The proposed mix of national and international researchers from universities, public agencies and industries has a very good potential for initiating an active research program in nano cementitious materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0749499</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bjorn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Birgisson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbirg@ce.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ells</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cackler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tcackler@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
