<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Spectroscopic Studies of Copper (I) Phenanthroline Molecular Assemblies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>425000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award in the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry program supports Professor Dominick J.Casadonte at Texas Tech University for research focused on the photochemistry and photophysics of localized molecular assemblies containing 1,10-phenanthroline (phen) and 2,9-dimethyl-1,10-phenanthroline (dmp) with varying dimensionalities afforded by substitution at the (3,8), (4,7), and (5,6) positions on the phenanthroline ring system. The long-term goal involves an understanding of the spatial requirements for photoactive and optoelectronic molecular systems. Fundamental photonic and electronic studies will be conducted on a series of Cu(I) oligomeric and polymeric assemblies containing substituted diimine ligands bound together via acrylate or ethynyl linkages. The proposed poly-(Cu(I)(dmp- 5-acrylate)2 and poly-(Cu(I)(dmp-5-acrylate)(PPH3)2 compounds will be linked at the 5 position of each of the phenanthroline ligands in a sigma-bonded fashion. Photoexcitation of the MLCT bands of these molecular aggregates will lead to charge separation throughout the network. The Cu(I) polyacetylenic phenanthroline materials will be fully pi-conjugated throughout the lattice. Excitation of the MLCT bands will produce electron flow through the polymer or oligmer chains. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research aims to set the stage for the fabrication of molecular electronic circuit elements. Students will not only develop a consideration of aspects of synthetic and photochemistry, but will also be actively involved in cutting-edge outreach in rural and disadvantaged areas in the West through the development of education modules in light, optics, photochemistry, and electricity that will be posted on YouTube, iTunesU, and the PI's website.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0749070</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dominick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Casadonte</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dominick.casadonte@TTU.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
      <CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
      <ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1968</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICAL INORGANIC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
