<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase II: Integrating Online Analytical Processing (OLAP) and Ontologies to Discover Inconsistencies in Expectations for Supply and Demand</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>937000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Errol Arkilic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This STTR Phase II project aims to produce a software application that dramatically improves a manager's ability to allocate resources to productive uses. With advances in Online Analytical Processing (OLAP) and ontology technology, the tool has the potential to enable the discovery of future supply and demand imbalances for teams of business analysts. The objective is to produce at least one Investable Inconsistency per day by the end of the research period. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Phase I project produced unanticipated innovations that may have broad utility in both the OLAP field and the ontology field, and with these innovations, the software platform shows promise for transforming the essential practice of analysis in the field of market research in support of investment decisions. The Phase II project, if successful will result in technology that extends this promise to a broad audience, educating users in best practices for investment analysis and enabling them to materially improve their allocation of resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0750543</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Musen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>musen@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peter@clados.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clados Management LLC</Name>
      <CityName>San Mateo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>944012806</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6502310494</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>133 Saint Matthews Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
