<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Group actions on homogeneous spaces, Euclidean buildings, and moduli spaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/18/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>73915</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is aimed at relating properties of group actions on&lt;br/&gt;homogeneous spaces, Euclidean buildings, and moduli spaces. Specific&lt;br/&gt;topics for investigation include: (1) Quasi-isometries of discrete&lt;br/&gt;subgroups of semisimple Lie groups. (2) Finiteness properties of&lt;br/&gt;function-field-arithmetic groups (with Kai-Uwe Bux). (3) Dehn functions of&lt;br/&gt;arithmetic groups (with Gregory Margulis). (4) Unipotent flows on spaces&lt;br/&gt;of abelian differentials (with Kariane Calta).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Homogeneous spaces are geometric objects that can be used to analyze &lt;br/&gt;arrays of numbers that satisfy certain equations. Euclidean buildings are &lt;br/&gt;also geometric objects, and they can be used to study arrays of &lt;br/&gt;generalized kinds of ``numbers''. Moduli spaces are geometric objects that &lt;br/&gt;can be used to parameterize spaces related to equations of complex &lt;br/&gt;numbers. Much effort has been put into comparing and contrasting these &lt;br/&gt;three objects, as each plays a significant role in the field of &lt;br/&gt;mathematics. The goal of this project is to continue to examine links &lt;br/&gt;between these three fundamental objects with the hope that a deeper &lt;br/&gt;understanding of the relationships between the three will bear insights &lt;br/&gt;for each as individuals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0750032</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wortman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wortman@math.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
