<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Future of Data Analysis and Visualization as a Knowledge Discovery Tool in Science and Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>109900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barry I. Schneider</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>OCI 0751267&lt;br/&gt;Kelly P. Gaither&lt;br/&gt;U. of Texas at Austin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recognizing the growing importance of digital data in research and education and the advancement of science, NSF's Cyberinfrastructure Vision for 21st Century Discovery describes a vision for the future "in which science and engineering digital data are routinely deposited in well-documented form, are regularly and easily consulted and analyzed by specialists and non-specialists alike, are openly accessible while suitably protected, and are reliably preserved." A 5-year goal to achieve this vision is to support development of a new generation of tools and services facilitating data mining, integration, analysis, and visualization essential to turning data into new knowledge and understanding. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This two-day workshop will gather critical consumer stakeholders that rely upon visualization as a part of their critical thinking and problem solving processes, developing a clear picture of the needs, challenges, and gaps in current visualization and analysis techniques that impede solution of grand challenge science problems. The resulting report is intended to serve as a call to arms for the visualization and analytics communities at follow-on workshops, including one to be co-located with IEEE Visualization 2007. This workshop thus represents a key initial step in achieving the goal articulated in the Vision document.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0751267</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gaither</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kelly@tacc.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
