<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for First GENI Engineering Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>C. Suzanne Iacono</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Global Environment for Network Innovation (GENI) is an experimental facility intended to support research in a wide variety of areas including communications, networking, distributed systems, cyber-security, networked services and networked applications. The goal of GENI is to enable researchers to experiment with radical network designs in a way that is far more realistic than any alternative available today. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GENI Engineering Conference will be the GPO's regular open working meeting to support design, planning, construction and operation of the GENI facility. It is the place where researchers, developers, industrial and international partners and the GENI Project Office will regularly meet to advance GENI facility planning and prototyping, as well as to engage in interdisciplinary conversation and mutual education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;GENI will be a vital resource for communications research in coming years. Results from experiments on GENI are expected to enable new types of research, reveal new ideas and insights in communications, influence the design of products, and create new opportunities for industry. The GENI Engineering Conference has a central role to play in ensuring that this broader impact occurs. The conference serves as a place where industry, new researchers and students, researchers from diverse backgrounds, as well as the established communications research community can come together to discuss visions of the future of research, how we will achieve that future, and how we will carry those visions and achievements into the wider world. The inaugural meeting supported by this project will express this vision by offering extensive travel grants to make the community richer in its diversity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0751954</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brig 'Chip'</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elliott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>celliott@bbn.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Raytheon BBN Technologies Corp.</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021381119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6178738325</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 Moulton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>024F</Code>
      <Text>GENI CONCEPT/DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
