<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>First International Conference on Stem Cell Engineering: Benchtop to Bioprocess, January 20-23, 2008; Coronado, California</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Fred G. Heineken</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>First International Conference on Stem Cell Engineering: Benchtop to Bioprocess&lt;br/&gt;January 20-23, 2008; Coronado, California&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;David V. Schaffer&lt;br/&gt;University of California-Berkeley&lt;br/&gt;(CBET - 0752605)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a timely response to the rapidly expanding field of stem cells, and to the escalating involvement of engineers in this field, the Conference Organizers are instituting and organizing the First International Conference on Stem Cell Engineering (ICSCE). This meeting, to be held every two years, will cover the breadth of Stem Cell Engineering and serve to promote, shape, and refine the definition of the field as a whole. The Theme of the first meeting will be "Benchtop to Bioprocess"; the conference Aims are to provide a venue: &lt;br/&gt;1. For scientific presentations from a diverse group of leading biology and engineering researchers who cover the breadth of Stem Cell Engineering. &lt;br/&gt;2. For interactions between academic and industry researchers, who bring different approaches and perspectives to the field. &lt;br/&gt;3. For active participation by Ph.D. students and postdoctoral researchers, who represent the future of stem cell biology and engineering. &lt;br/&gt;4. For bringing biologists and engineers together can help to provide an atmosphere and venue for both to discuss their disciplines and approaches, which will lead to a better understanding of the field by all. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The three major topics of the Conference will be: &lt;br/&gt; 1. High throughput technologies for the discovery of novel regulatory signals; &lt;br/&gt; 2. Systems biology approaches towards understanding stem cell regulation; and&lt;br/&gt; 3. Development and synthesis of stem cell culture and implantation platforms.&lt;br/&gt; The scientific program will include 9 invited talks, approximately 20 contributed talks, and 2 poster sessions for graduate students, postdocs, and junior faculty to showcase their research, as well as panel discussions to discuss and debate the current issues of this field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0752605</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schaffer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schaffer@cchem.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/26/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
