<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Operation of a National Ocean Sciences Accelerator Mass Spectrometry Facility at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8605776</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for continued operation and maintenance of the National Ocean Sciences Accelerator Mass Spectrometer (NOSAMS). NOSAMS carries out analysis of carbon isotopes (primarily radiocarbon, 14C) via accelerator mass spectrometry. It also carries out research and development in new AMS radiocarbon sample preparation techniques and accelerator operations. It has operated since 1993 under cooperative agreements (0228996, 9807266, 9301015) between WHOI and NSF, and was acquired, tested and put into operation with NSF support (8802509) beginning in 1989. The present cooperative agreement was implemented in 2003, and has an anniversary date of 4/1 annually. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When it began operations, water samples collected for the World Ocean Circulation Experiment (WOCE), a major international field program involving very substantial NSF support, comprised the majority of samples analyzed by NOSAMS. Most of the original WOCE radiocarbon analyses were completed within the operations of the 1998-2003 cooperative agreement. Beginning in about 2003, samples collected as part of Climate Variability (CLIVAR) and Carbon Cycle programs supported by programs in the Division of Ocean Sciences have made up a significant portion of the sample submissions to NOSAMS. For the current award, approximately 1,000 CLIVAR-related analyses are planned for Year 1, and it is anticipated that NOSAMS will carry out approximately 1,000 such analyses annually for the next five years, subject to continued review and approval by NSF. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funding for five years of operation and maintenance the NOSAMS and for a variety of instrumentation upgrades necessary for continued improvement of the measurements and sample preparation systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0753487</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jenkins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wjenkins@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
      <LastName>McNichol</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amcnichol@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
      <LastName>von Reden</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kvonreden@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roberts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mroberts@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
