<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: University of Michigan REU Site in the Chemical Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>211800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry (CHE) supports the renewal of a successful Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site at the University of Michigan (UM) Ann Arbor for the summers of 2008-2010. This site will be managed by Brian Coppola with assistance from Melanie Sanford both from the Department of Chemistry at UM. Thirteen individuals from around the United States, typically rising sophomores and juniors, will comprise the central component of this site. Eight students will be supported by NSF-REU, three will be supported by University funds, and two will be supported by the Intel Corporation, a leader in the computing and communcations industry. The REU students have access to all of the research groups associated with the chemistry department, including interdisciplinary programs in materials chemistry, chemical biology, life science, medicinal chemistry, and environmental chemistry. In addition to departmental seminars and symposia other non-research program activities include: training on laboratory safety and environmentally safe laboratory practices, the use of on-line Chemistry library resources (SciFinder, Beilstein, etc.), ethics, chemical instrumentation, field trips to local chemical industry, mentoring for applying to graduate school, and career mentoring including science career options, job searches, interview preparation and resume writing. Each research group will require oral presentations as a natural part of their scientific activities and all students will write a final progress report. Finally, a regional research symposium will be held at one of the REU Site-holding schools where undergraduates from across the area will gather to present their work.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0754639</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coppola</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bcoppola@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Melanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sanford</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mssanfor@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
