<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>InP-Based Spintronic Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anupama Kaul</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;ECCS-0754367&lt;br/&gt;P. Bhattacharya, University of Michigan Ann Arbor&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective: The objective of this research is to realize high-temperature (&gt;200K) spintronic devices with InP-based hetrostructures grown by molecular beam epitaxy. The reasons of choosing InP-based hetrostructures are the following : (i) these are used for high frequency transistors and for fiber-optic communication at 1.3 and 1.55 µm; even for future CMOS-based VLSI, InAs and InSb on silicon are being investigated for the superior carrier transport properties therein; (ii) very little is experimentally known regarding spin injection in InP-based alloys. The approach is to investigate and realize three specific devices: (a) spin valves for the study of spin injection, transport and detection; (b) semiconductor-ferromagnet based memory devices; and (c) spin lasers and their modulation with spin torque devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Spin-based ferromagnet/semiconductor heterojunction devices are particularly attractive, compared to all-metal spintronic devices, due to the versatility and the long spin coherence time in semiconductors. However, till date, practical semiconductor spintronic devices that can operate at or near room temperature do not exist. The proposed program of research will address this critical need.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The proposed program is interdisciplinary in nature and will provide a broad impact to science and society beyond technical merits. The economic impact of the research and its outcome will be felt as the proposed devices complement or selectively replace traditional microelectronics. This work combines spintronics with other fields in science and engineering for real applications. Outreach projects for women and underrepresented minorities are proposed to provide research experience for undergraduates and expose high school students to scientific and engineering disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0754367</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pallab</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bhattacharya</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pkb@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
