<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometry and Physics on Graphs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>233361</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dean M. Evasius</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Department of Mathematics and Statistics at Canisius College will host an eight week summer research program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Minority and women are strongly encouraged to apply.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main objective of our program is to introduce the participating undergraduates to deep ideas in mathematics, and to mentor them through the passage to independent research. We believe that graph theory and related areas provide a good setting for this. Graphs appear as discrete analogues of geometric objects, descriptions of algebraic and combinatorial situations, toy models in physics and in many other settings. We will use and develop tools from geometry, analysis and combinatorics to study graphs and related groupoids as purely combinatorial objects, as discrete analogues of continuous spaces (topological and smooth manifolds), and as combinatorial representations of algebraic structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Eight undergradute students, in two teams, will work closely with faculty mentors on related projects investigating combinatorial properties of graphs and groups through specific examples. The goal is to produce original research results that can be submitted for publication to a mathematics journal or presented in conferences in mathematics. A secondary goal is to create tutorial reports that will provide a foundation for future student research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Some of these reports will be accessible on the wiki website&lt;br/&gt; http://wiki.canisiusmath.net/&lt;br/&gt;created and maintained by the participants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0754059</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Byung-Jay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kahng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kahngb@canisius.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bisson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bisson@canisius.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Canisius College</Name>
      <CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142081098</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7168882103</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2001 Main Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
