<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Gas Phase Nanoxerographic Nanomaterial Integration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nanomaterials the building blocks of future nanotechnological devices are most commonly fabricated using solution chemistry or gas phase chemistry and can provide a variety of functions. The use of nanomaterials as building blocks, however, requires novel integration concepts to enable the creation of functional devices and systems that go beyond the single device level. This proposal aims at developing a parallel concept to enable the integration of functional materials at desired locations on a surface. Different from prior work on liquid phase assembly this proposal aims at developing gas-phase nanomaterial assembly systems, which are orthogonal the PIs prior work and most of the ongoing research by others on solution based printing methods. Supported by a recent Monte Carlo simulation the PI propose the development of Nanoxerographic printing concepts that focus on gas phase processes and aerosols that run at atmospheric pressure and intermediate vacuum. The computational analysis predicts that it should be possible to integrate nanomaterials with sub 10 nm precision and control over the amount of materials that is locally deposited. Considering the revised scope and budget the effort will center on the main goal of the original proposal which was to demonstrate this in experiment. The design of new nanomaterial assembly module is proposed to achieve this goal. The educational goal aims at fostering a cross-disciplinary education and outreach to a broad community. A new course Introductory Nanotechnology Course will be established as well.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0755995</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heiko</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hjacobs@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
