<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High-Frequency Nanofluidics of Bio-NEMS: Theory and Experiments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Horst Henning Winter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0755927&lt;br/&gt;Ekinci&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study is a combined theoretical and experimental investigation of the fundamental fluid-dynamics of high frequency bio-functionalized nanoelectromechanical systems (Bio-NEMS) in aqueous solution. Most high impact applications of Bio-NEMS involve nanoscale cantilevers or doubly-clamped beams resonating in aqueous biochemical solutions. Optimization of Bio-NEMS operation in biochemical aqueous solutions is crucial for future sensing applications involving proteins, DNA, cells, chemicals, etc. Unfortunately, a Bio-NEMS resonator loses almost all of its stored energy to the fluid. This causes a significant reduction of the available signal from the device. Recent experiments and theory by the investigators have shown that, as the frequency of oscillations increase, the Newtonian fluid approximation breaks down, resulting in a transition from viscoelastic-like behavior to elastic-like behavior with an accompanying reduction in dissipation. This suggests that, at high frequencies, the effective fluidic dissipation can be reduced by changing the fluid relaxation time. Here, various approaches for increasing the relaxation time of aqueous solutions and the effects on fluidic dissipation of Bio-NEMS will be investigated. This project will train both graduate and undergraduate students in a wide cross-section of engineering and physics, including nanoscale engineering, nanometrology, and fluid dynamics. The investigators plan to remain involved in outreach events sponsored by Boston University, such as Science Saturdays, LENS and FIRST robotics. The investigators have a substantial amount of experience in organizing such programs, and the events will be coordinated in close collaboration with the Boston University Learning Resource Network (LERNet). The investigators will also disseminate research results through graduate- and undergraduate-level courses on Nanotechnology and Fluid Dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0755927</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yakhot</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vy@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kamil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ekinci</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ekinci@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
