<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Crystal Growth, Structure and Property Relationships of Yb Intermetallics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda S. Sapochak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project aims to grow and characterize single crystals of rare earth intermetallics, correlate their structure and properties, and look for new phenomena. The synthesis of these materials in single crystalline form will be addressed as one of the primary driving forces of basic research in the chemistry of new materials. To understand physical properties of novel materials clearly, it is essential to grow crystals that are large (at least 2-5 mm3) and of high quality for the measurement of properties. Training future crystal growers to interact with collaborators in national labs as well with international scientists is vital to advancing materials research. Students involved in this project will continue to be involved in educational activities such as doing hands on demonstrations and developing materials-related demonstrations. The PI will also continue with outreach efforts to under-represented minorities at the high school, undergraduate and graduate level. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The exchange mechanisms and spin correlations mediated by itinerant electrons have attracted much interest due to the emerging field of spin electronics. A goal for this project is to grow single crystals of cerium and ytterbium and ytterbium intermetallic phases in the lanthanide-copper-X (X = gallium, tin, antimony) systems in which the phenomena and/or implications of heavy fermion behavior, superconductivity, magnetism and/or magnetoresistance may be observed and studied. New families of intermetallics will be investigated with the motivation of correlating structure and properties, in particular uncovering emergent ordered phases arising from quantum fluctuations. Students will perform hands on demonstrations and will develop materials-related demonstrations for incorporation into Chem Demo programs. The PI will also develop outreach projects for under-represented minorities at the high school, undergraduate and graduate level. Students will interact with collaborators in national labs as well with international scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0756281</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Julia.Chan@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1762</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
