<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dynamics and Control of Process Networks with Energy Integration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>292284</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Luke Achenie</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0756363, Daoutidis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Efficient energy utilization is a critical need for the process industries, and for existing and emerging energy production technologies. Energy efficiency is exemplified by energy integration, achieved by transporting energy from where it is generated to where it is needed or can be safely dissipated. The design and optimization of energy-integrated process networks has been an area of rich activity in process systems engineering, with notable impact in industrial practice. However, the advanced control of energy-integrated process networks has received rather limited attention, especially in the context of transitions between different operating states. Yet, this is a critical task for the smart, flexible operation for such networks, and also a challenging one given the ?energy feedback" loops that give rise to a core, typically nonlinear, dynamics in such networks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research aims at a comprehensive dynamic modeling, model reduction and control framework for process networks with tight energy integration. The emphasis is on the core network dynamics induced by the energy integration: its documentation and rigorous characterization; the derivation of nonlinear reduced-order non-stiff models of these dynamics; and their effective use within a hierarchical control framework.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit promises the development of generic modeling, analysis and control platforms and methods, applicable to a broad range of energy-integrated networks, such as heat-integrated reactors, heat-integrated and thermally coupled distillation columns, heat exchanger networks, and reactor - fuel cell networks. These will enable the development of practically implementable (low- order) robust nonlinear supervisory controllers, and will thus facilitate the efficient and flexible operation of such networks, complementing the existing design and optimization methods. These contributions can potentially impact on the operation of most modern plants featuring tight energy integration, e.g. in the traditional process industries, pollution prevention technologies, air separation technologies, and emerging fuel cell applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide a setting for the effective training of graduate students in fundamental research with a timely and important application component. The students will also interact with industrial partners through summer internships. The research results will be broadly disseminated through publications and presentations, and through their integration to the teaching of process dynamics and control, whereas the software and web site that will be developed will further enhance the infrastructure for research and education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0756363</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Prodromos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Daoutidis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>daout001@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
