<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Marrakesh International Conference and Workshop on Mathematical Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Ann Horn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funding for this project will support the participation of senior speakers, junior faculty and graduate students from the United States in the Marrakesh International Conference and Workshop on Mathematical Biology. The themes of this conference and workshop include cellular dynamics, mathematical epidemiology, mathematical modeling of cancer, and mathematical ecology. This meeting will explore new directions for the area of mathematical biology that will have significant influence in years to come and will be of particular benefit for the young participants in this conference. The workshop will provide an agenda for future collaborations between US and African scientists. It will expose junior and senior U.S. scientists and students to opportunities for collaboration with African researchers in developing and applying the tools of multi-scale modeling to questions arising from the tremendous health problems caused by such diseases as HIV/AIDS, tuberculosis and malaria, as well as drug-resistant tuberculosis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is co-funded by the Division of Mathematical Sciences and the Office of International Science and Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0756669</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Khalid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boushaba</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>boushaba@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
