<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Southwestern Indiana STEM (SwISTEM) Initiative</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1179362</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amy Chan Hilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of Southern Indiana and Ivy Tech Community College Southwest Indiana are partners in the Southwestern Indiana STEM (SwISTEM) initiative. The SwISTEM Initiative consists of four components: 1) development and implementation of an Early Undergraduate Research Program; 2) formation of the Pathways Leading to Undergraduate Success in the Sciences (PLUSS) Program which offers developmental courses in mathematics and the sciences; 3) an Outreach Program targeting high school students; and, 4) a Professional Development program for pre-college and college faculty. SwISTEM is increasing the number and quality of students selecting STEM majors; providing opportunities to engage students early in hands-on research opportunities; developing a more nurturing and team oriented approach to STEM education; providing enhanced academic and career advising for students majoring in the STEM areas; improving the retention and graduation rates for STEM students; improving the success rates in key introductory mathematics and science courses; providing professional development for regional faculty; and, developing community partnerships to generate additional interest in STEM careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0756978</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gordon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sgordon@usi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/01/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shelly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blunt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sblunt@usi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/01/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern Indiana</Name>
      <CityName>Evansville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>477123534</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8124651630</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8600 Univ Blvd Box 6227</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
