<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Plant Genome Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375050</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Plant Genome Research Program at Boyce Thompson Institute and Cornell University will provide a 10-week internship for 12 undergraduates each summer. The laboratories hosting REU students are at the forefront of plant molecular biology research, contributing to the latest advances in genomics, proteomics, metabolite profiling, plant transformation, and others. Basic and applied research projects include studying biofuels production, plant defense against pathogens and insects, biosynthesis of primary and secondary metabolites, phosphate uptake, metal tolerance, light perception, root development, and chloroplast function. These projects incorporate not only important crops such as maize, rice, and tomato, but also genetic model plants such as Chlamydomonas reinhardtii, a single-celled alga, the legume Medicago truncatula, and the small crucifer Arabidopsis thaliana. Students work on supervised independent projects with their chosen mentor. Students also participate in weekly faculty research lectures, tours of Cornell facilities, and presentations at the end-of-summer symposium. In addition, two half-day discussion forums are included on ethical issues that students will likely encounter in the course of their scientific careers. The internship serves to introduce undergraduates to plant molecular biology research and encourages them to pursue graduate degrees and future careers in this field. Students admitted to the program are given a stipend, housing, meals and airfare. Under-represented minorities and students from colleges with limited research opportunities are particularly encouraged to apply. More information is available at http://bti.cornell.edu/pgrp/, or by contacting Georg Jander (Program Director) or the Program Coordinator at pgrp-outreach@cornell.edu, phone 607-254-6732.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0756560</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scanlon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjs298@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Georg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gj32@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Boyce Thompson Institute Plant Research</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148531801</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072541248</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>533 Tower Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7226</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7744</Code>
      <Text>RAHSS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
