<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Theory of Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Processes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>287268</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ann Orel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal addresses comprehensive theoretical investigation of a broad range of&lt;br/&gt;atomic, molecular, and optical (AMO) processes of current significance in science and&lt;br/&gt;technology. The proposed activities will build on both of our past efforts and the new&lt;br/&gt;development of nonperturbative theoretical formalisms and high-precision&lt;br/&gt;computational methods for accurate treatment of both the electronic structure of highly&lt;br/&gt;and multiply excited states as well as the multiphoton dynamics and coherent control of&lt;br/&gt;atomic and molecular processes in the presence of intense external fields.&lt;br/&gt;Emphasis in the first part of this proposal concerns the ab initio theoretical exploration of&lt;br/&gt;the frequency comb structure and coherence within each order of the high-order&lt;br/&gt;harmonic generation (HHG) spectrum in the high-frequency VUV/XUV regime. Two&lt;br/&gt;approaches will be developed for the study of frequency comb projects: (a)&lt;br/&gt;time-dependent generalized pseudospectral method (TDGPS) for accurate and efficient&lt;br/&gt;solution of the time-dependent Schrdinger equation (TDSE) in space and time, and (b)&lt;br/&gt;many-mode Floquet theory (MMFT). The second part of this proposal will deal with the&lt;br/&gt;study of the coherent control of population transfer in Rydberg atoms via sequential&lt;br/&gt;transitions or via multiphoton adiabatic rapid passage. In the last part of the proposal,&lt;br/&gt;several longer range projects will be presented, including (a) the development of a new&lt;br/&gt;TDGPS method in hyperspherical coordinates for fully ab initio 6D treatment of doubly&lt;br/&gt;excited resonance states and double photoionization dynamics of two-electron atoms in&lt;br/&gt;the presence of external fields, and (b) the further development of the&lt;br/&gt;self-interaction-free time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) for the&lt;br/&gt;exploration of many-electron Rydberg atom dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0757194</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shih-I</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sichu@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1284</Code>
      <Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
