<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Particle Physics at High Energy Colliders</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>785000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Randal Ruchti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests continuing support for a program of research for the Huston.Bromberg group at Michigan State University (MSU) in experimental elementary particle physics based primarily on the CDF experiment and proposed NOvA experiment at the Fermilab Tevatron collider and the ATLAS experiment at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For the past few decades, physicists have been able to describe with increasing detail the fundamental particles that make up the Universe and the interactions between them. Much of this success has been due to the Tevatron program at Fermilab with D0 and CDF making major contributions. This understanding is encapsulated in the Standard Model of particle physics, but it contains gaps and cannot tell us the whole story. To fill in the missing knowledge requires more and different experimental data, and the next big step to achieving this is with the LHC. This MSU group has made major contributions to the CDF experiment in its design, construction and operation of parts of the calorimeter and tracker and in the physics questions proposed as well as in many leadership roles. This group is now transitioning into the ATLAS program where it will parlay its wealth of experience in W/Z + jet final state(s) into a leadership role in such analyses. Such events serve as both a signal channel and background in Standard Model and Beyond the Standard Model physics. The group also has major responsibility in the design, installation and operation for parts of the calorimeter system including thee L1 trigger. This group works closely with phenomenologists with Huston serving as co-spokesman for the 24 member Coordinated Theoretical-Experimental Project on QCD (CTEQ) and one of the organizers of its workshops.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bromberg also is participating in the NOvA R&amp;D program with his group having responsibility for quality assurance of the 13,000 km of WLS fiber. Finally, he has also joined the group testing a 250-liter LArTPC at Fermilab. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On Broader Impacts, the group will continue its work primarily within the QuarkNet program as well as employing undergraduates in the research. Expansion of the Cosmic Ray Detector units into other schools is underway with the goal of coordinating time stamps between high schools to look for wide area cosmic ray showers. Science Days and permanent exhibits in an atrium setting at MSU related to the ATLAS program are planned.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0757758</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huston</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>huston@pa.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bromberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bromberg@pa.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1221</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
