<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Florida - Georgia LSAMP 2012-2017</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3684570</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dr. A. James Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Florida-Georgia LSAMP (FGLSAMP) is seeking to continue to employ its current program model while enhancing and focusing upon critical junctures for successful matriculation through the STEM academic pipeline. Given its mission to significantly increase the number of baccalaureate degrees awarded to underrepresented minorities in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics FGLSAMP will focus greater attention on utilizing effective models and best practices for expanding the pipeline of community college students matriculating into STEM disciplines at the university level. In conjunction with the emphasis on community college students, two additional areas of focus include expanding participation in international research experiences and enhancing means of growing the number of students entering STEM PhD programs. These additions to FGLSAMP will enable FGLSAMP to build upon its successful track record and will allow FGLSAMP to achieve its goals for 2012-2017.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;FGLSAMP proposes to significantly expand its STEM talent pool through greater collaboration among the 14 partner institutions and enhanced practices that result in: 1) student retention and graduation in STEM disciplines; 2) effectively preparing and matriculating FGLSAMP community college students to pursue baccalaureate degrees in STEM disciplines; 3) providing significant STEM international research opportunities 4) preparation of FGLSAMP undergraduate participants for STEM graduate education opportunities. FGLSAMP will augment its current STEM socialization practices to achieve these key guide posts, which are at the heart of all FGLSAMP academic enhancement and professional development activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The targeted metrics for our five-year program period also include:&lt;br/&gt;- Expand the talent pool of institutional underrepresented minorities awarded STEM undergraduate and graduate degrees by 15% annually (2,247 baseline) &lt;br/&gt;- Place at least 75% percent of FGLSAMP B.S. degree recipients into STEM graduate programs &lt;br/&gt;- Maintain a STEM retention rate of greater than 80% among FGLSAMP undergraduates at ASU, BCU, FAMU and FIU&lt;br/&gt;- Achieve 5 year time-to-graduation rate of 85% &lt;br/&gt;- Place more than 20 annually students into international research programs by 2014</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1201981</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ralph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Turner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ralph.turner@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/17/2017</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maurice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edington</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maurice.edington@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/17/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University</Name>
      <CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323073200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8505993531</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lee Hall Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9133</Code>
      <Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1593</Code>
      <Text>PRES AWDS FOR EXCELL IN SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7204</Code>
      <Text>DoE-NSF LABORATORY FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
