<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: How Internet Engagement Shapes Social Movement Organizational Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7980</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saylor Breckenridge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES-1203716&lt;br/&gt;Kim Voss&lt;br/&gt;Jen Schradie&lt;br/&gt;University of California, Berkeley&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Doctoral Dissertation Research: How Internet Engagement Shapes Social Movement Organizational Dynamics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;How is the digital age affecting democratic practices within social movement organizations (SMOs)? The "iron law" of oligarchy (Michels) poses that all organizations eventually become more centralized and hierarchical. In contrast, scholars of online activism have argued that the Internet allows for less hierarchical, and implicitly more democratic, organizations to emerge. This dissertation compares existing SMOs which all target the same issue but have varying levels of online engagement. The project is grounded in literature on social movements, organizations, and new media. The methodology includes interviews, observations, and digital content analysis. The central hypotheses are that (1) digital engagement both overcomes and exacerbates iron law dynamics at the organizational level, and (2) this effect is moderated by the social class and political ideology of the SMOs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;Findings from this research are intended to deepen our understanding of the relationship between democracy and technology. Especially given the increasingly visible role of new media in shaping political movements around the world, findings from this study may be of interest to the general public, as well as policy makers and governments. Findings may also inform policy efforts that regulate Internet access around the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1203716</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Voss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kimvoss@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schradie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schradie@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
