<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Glacial Retreat and the Cultural Landscape of Ice Floe Sealing at Yakutat Bay, Alaska</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>264108</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anna Kerttula de Echave</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This multidisciplinary study of the ancient, historical, and contemporary harvest of harbor seals at icefloe pupping grounds near Hubbard Glacier in Yakutat Bay, Alaska models the reshaping of both an environment and a human hunting system in response to Late Holocene climate change. The project joins indigenous knowledge, language, and oral heritage with the material and chronometric evidence of&lt;br/&gt;archaeology, geology, and paleoenvironmental studies to document the cultural history and landscape of Yakutat Bay, where dramatic glacial recession after C. E. 1100 attracted major concentrations of harbor seals and opened the fiord for Sugpiaq, Eyak, Ahtna, and Tlingit settlement. The research team proposes that a clan-based system of local and external access rights developed around Yakutat sealing because of its economic centrality for peoples of the eastern Gulf of Alaska; that sealing camps shifted from the outer&lt;br/&gt;to the inner bay over time to follow the receding glacial front; and that the locations, artifact assemblages, faunal remains, and spatial layouts of camps express the cultural and social organization of hunting in different eras. They hypothesize that situated knowledge of Yakutat Bay?s human and environmental history is encoded in living oral traditions and multilingual toponyms that richly delineate this nine-century cultural landscape, and that oral heritage can be chronologically correlated with archaeological and geological data. The study leads from the past to the present day, when the continuity of sealing and of the community?s cultural and linguistic heritage are matters of urgent local concern. The methodologies and results of this study are highly relevant to questions of human adaptation and resiliency in the changing North and to the challenge of building coherence between indigenous and scientific knowledge systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1203417</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crowell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crowella@si.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Smithsonian Institution</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>222023709</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026337110</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5221</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5221</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
