<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Schools, Families and Children's Food Allergies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5479</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saylor Breckenridge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Summary &lt;br/&gt;Doctoral Dissertation Research: Schools, Families and Children's Food Allergies&lt;br/&gt;Peter Conrad&lt;br/&gt;Vanessa Lopes Muñoz&lt;br/&gt;Brandeis University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;About 4% of children reported a food allergy in 2007-an increase of nearly 18%&lt;br/&gt;during the course of a decade. Preventing and responding to severe allergic reactions can&lt;br/&gt;require the involvement of many actors in schools, restaurants, and childcare centers. By&lt;br/&gt;examining how multiple actors adhere to food allergy policies and guidelines, this study&lt;br/&gt;seeks to fill an existing gap in sociological studies of health and illness.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. A longstanding concern in sociology and in medicine is explaining&lt;br/&gt;under what conditions, and to what ends, people adhere to medical regimens. Conrad and&lt;br/&gt;others have argued that ill persons make decisions about following medical regimens&lt;br/&gt;largely based on their everyday lives, making the case that daily social interactions are at&lt;br/&gt;least as important as doctor-patient relationships. Conditions that are managed primarily&lt;br/&gt;through lifestyle changes,such as changes in diet,raise questions about the role of&lt;br/&gt;multiple actors in managing health conditions. To address these questions, this study&lt;br/&gt;examines how families and schools adhere to food allergy policies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact. This study would expand knowledge about the management of health&lt;br/&gt;conditions that are rising in prevalence-food allergies. Results from this study may&lt;br/&gt;inform health policies related to an array of conditions that require intensive lifestyle&lt;br/&gt;changes, such as asthma, diabetes, and food intolerances. Findings may also be of interest&lt;br/&gt;to healthcare professionals, families, and school administrators. This research will be&lt;br/&gt;used for a doctoral dissertation and in undergraduate teaching.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1203390</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Conrad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>conrad@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vanessa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Munoz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vmunoz@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brandeis University</Name>
      <CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7817362121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>415 SOUTH ST MAILSTOP 116</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
