<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Factors Related to Teacher Retention in Arctic Alaska, an Integral Part of the Circumpolar North</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499848</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anna Kerttula de Echave</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a three-year research project to do indepth quantitative and qualitative research on teacher retention in rural schools in Arctic Alaska. Rural Alaskan schools are populated by over 90% Alaska Native students and are in majority Alaskan Native communities. One of the key issues in these school systems, not just in Alaska but throughout the circumpolar North, is how to retain teachers. Up until now, teacher retention studies focused on the statistical analyses of how many teachers stayed in rural community schools and for how long. And although there has been research on the effects of teacher retention and student achievement, findings showing that student performance is directly connected to teacher retention, no substantive scientific research has been done that explains why retention rates are so low in Alaskan Native communities. Using an explanatory design, the study will triangulate findings by looking at multiple qualitative and quantitative indicators related to teacher retention, comparing them and using qualitative evidence to shed light on the quantitative patterns. Teachers in the region will be surveyed using electronic and interview survey methods. Attempts to contact teachers who left the district within the past 2 years will be made for purposes of semi-structured telephone interviews. Alaskan Native researchers will conduct focus group field interviews of a purposefully selected, weighted, and stratified sample of teachers, school board members, Elders, and Tribal Council members. The goals of the research project are: 1. To identify the degree of school and community integration, which influence teacher retention; 2. To identify school workplace characteristics, including recruitment practices, which influence teacher retention; 3. To identify teacher preparation practices which influence retention; 4. To identify key unknown variables for understanding teacher retention in Arctic Alaska.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1203132</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ute</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaden</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ukaden@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Healy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhealy7@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>barbara.adams@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Beth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leonard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brleonard@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5221</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5221</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9151</Code>
      <Text>EPSCOR OUTREACH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
