<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Trends in ecological analysis and synthesis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98853</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010209</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports a panel symposium scheduled over two days in March 2012 that will examine trends in ecological analysis and synthesis since the establishment of the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis, or NCEAS, in 1995. The symposium has several objectives, including recognition of the intellectual impacts of NCEAS and the contributions of individuals to these; consideration of lessons learned from the NCEAS experience in cross-disciplinary synthesis research methods, data and information management, communication and outreach; consideration of emerging trends and opportunities for synthesis research in ecology and related fields; and discussion of the impact of networking technologies for accelerating synthesis research, training and outreach. The symposium will engage a diverse group of leading thinkers in ecology, data management and informatics, and scientific journalism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This symposium is designed to raise awareness of the growing impact of synthesis research in ecology and other fields of science. The agenda is designed to stimulate intensive, wide ranging discussion among the participants on key issues that must be addressed to increase the long term benefits of synthesis research efforts. Participation by some leading scientific journalists will assure that important insights and ideas are communicated to a broad audience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1205724</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fd@bren.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1181</Code>
      <Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1181</Code>
      <Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
