<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>UTEP/UCSB PREM: Molecular and Interfacial Phase Design for Improved Photovoltaics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3302000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Caro</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>UTEP-UCSB PREM: Fundamental Molecular and Interfacial Design for Next Generation Photovoltaic Systems&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A synergistic interdisciplinary research approach to the advancement of the basic understanding of the molecular and interfacial structures essential for efficient solar energy conversion will be conducted. In this project, an innovative, student-centered, inter-campus program called "UTEP-UCSB PREM" will be created to manage the scholarly activities of the participating students. Prof. L. Echegoyen from UTEP and Prof. C. Hawker from UCSB lead this institutional partnership in which eight UTEP and eight UCSB scientists and engineers (chemistry, materials, physics, and electrical and mechanical engineering) and one from Sandia National Laboratories form collaborative research teams that focus on the following key fundamental aspects of solar energy photovoltaic research: (1) theoretical calculations to predict mechanisms and guide the design of new active compounds, (2) development of high-yield novel systems with tunable properties for next-generation solar cells, (3) crystal engineering to establish structure-function relationships for improved cell efficiencies, (4) semiconductor nanocrystal growth simulations to predict function, and (5) development of new interfacial transparent materials with well-characterized composition and structure, to establish structure-function relationships and guide the design of next-generation interfaces for solar cells. The world-class instrument facilities at the UCSB MRL will enable and catalyze the exploration of the basic science of solar cells and provide unique opportunities for cross-fertilization of ideas, mentoring, and multidisciplinary training. The collaborative teams will hold research-focus group meetings via real-time video teleconferencing and hold an annual symposium hosted by each institution, revolving yearly. This will foster a high-level of research intensity and a well-orchestrated student-centered organizational environment. Ultimately, this research partnership will increase our understanding of the fundamental mechanism of solar cells and pave the way for the next generation of decentralized energy production in the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Texas at El Paso (UTEP) is a major research university located in the Southwest region of the United States and has a student body composed of 78% Hispanic-Americans and 55% women out of which a large portion are low-income first-generation college students. The proposed UTEP-UCSB PREM partnership will promote and enhance the participation and advanced degree attainment of over 20 Ph.D. and over 30 B.S. students, most of whom will be from underrepresented minority groups. Students will develop expertise in the broad areas of green energy and sustainability while acquiring a strong set of multi-disciplinary skills in fundamental research. The participating students will carry out this research at both academic institutions and will be mentored by faculty from several disciplines. Mentoring of junior and mid-career faculty will also be fostered. This PREM program will allow UTEP to significantly accelerate its emergence as a focal center for materials research and develop a long-lasting collaborative partnership with UCSB's MRL. The research results under the UTEP-UCSB PREM partnership will be disseminated in peer-reviewed journals and conferences, and to the public at large via a dedicated web portal and frequent presentations at local K-12 schools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1205302</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dorothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pak@geol.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hawker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hawker@mrl.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Irwin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdirwin@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/16/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Echegoyen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>echegoyen@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gabby</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gandara</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gabby@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at El Paso</Name>
      <CityName>El Paso</CityName>
      <ZipCode>799680001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9157475680</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ADMIN BLDG RM 209</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7913</Code>
      <Text>PREM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
