<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International summer school and research conference on Schubert calculus</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>44200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant will support a cooperative effort with the Mathematical Society of Japan and other Japanese funding sources to hold the International Summer School and Conference on Schubert Calculus from July 17-27, 2012, in Osaka, Japan. Schubert calculus is a wide-ranging mathematical discipline that blends many fields. It has been used to solve problems in computational geometry, optimization, mathematical biology, and cryptography, among other important applications. While Japanese mathematicians are not very active in Schubert calculus, many are experts in closely related fields. The conference will bring US researchers and open problems in Schubert calculus to Japan, and bring specialized Japanese expertise and techniques to questions in Schubert calculus; this synergy has the potential to transform the field. NSF funds will be used to support travel and limited local expenses for about 20 US mathematicians at early stages in their careers, when the potential impact on their mathematical development is highest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference will foster mathematical leadership in the next generation of researchers, and also encourage established researchers into the the field, via educational programs like the summer school and resulting publications (online, video, and traditional conference proceedings). The conference webpage is located here: http://www.math.ed.okayama-u.ac.jp/msjsi12/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1205283</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Megumi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harada</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Megumi.Harada@mcmaster.ca</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julianna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tymoczko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jtymoczko@smith.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Smith College</Name>
      <CityName>Northampton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010636304</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135842700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 ELM STREET</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7970</Code>
      <Text>Combinatorics</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
