<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Control of Epitaxial Graphene Layers on Silicon Carbide</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>265810</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Z. Charles Ying</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Description: The research performed in this project aims to understand and improve the formation of graphene on the (000-1) surface of SiC (the C-face). Prior work has identified a new interface structure for graphene on the C-face, occurring when the graphene is formed in a low-pressure disilane environment. Further research of this graphene formation mechanism is performed in this project. Decoupling of the C-face interface layer from the SiC is also studied, using hydrogen or oxygen gases. The electronic properties of the graphene are characterized, in collaborative studies with other scientists. Insulating layers such as boron nitride are epitaxially deposited on the graphene, as a first step towards the formation of graphene-insulator-graphene junction. Methods are explored for further deposition of a second layer of graphene on the boron nitride.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Description: Graphene, a two-dimensional monolayer of carbon, has been intensively studied for the past decade because of the unique transport properties of electrons in the material. For large-area production of graphene (as needed for electronic devices and circuits), a leading method is the formation on silicon carbide (SiC). This research project focuses on formation mechanisms for graphene on SiC, particularly on its C-face. The project also provides broad multi-disciplinary training to graduate students in the nanotechnology field. Additionally, the PI presents annual lectures to middle and high school students on nanotechnology, as well as teaching an undergraduate course on Nanoscience and Nanotechnology. The graphene-related research of this project is used to enhance the content of these lectures, providing the students with an apt example of a current topic in nanoscience and nanotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1205275</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feenstra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>feenstra@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
