<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>San Antonio College Server Virtualization Center Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>284819</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Erlinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The San Antonio College (SAC) Department of Computer Information Systems (CIS) is developing an Enhanced Skills Certificate in Server Virtualization to increase the number of technicians who enter the workforce with competencies in server virtualization and cloud computing. Students learn how to use Microsoft Hyper V and VMware software, open-source virtualization software, SQL Server 2008 and SharePoint 2010. In addition to addressing the growing need for virtualization technicians across Texas and the nation, this project allows SAC and Texas A&amp;M University at San Antonio and St. Mary's University to establish a pathway to BAAS degrees at both universities through articulation agreements for all courses within the proposed certificate. The PIs are developing curricula and laboratory activities with input from a nine-member industry Advisory Board.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to providing industry-responsive virtualization curricula and laboratory activities for replication, widespread dissemination of project evaluation results is contributing to the nation's knowledge of how to best develop technician education programs in collaboration with industry and four-year institutions, how to best train faculty who educate technicians and how career and technical programs at two-year colleges can work with four-year institutions to establish seamless transfer pipelines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a Hispanic-Serving Institution, SAC is poised to broaden participation of Hispanics in the IT workforce through this project. This project is also improving SAC's infrastructure by strengthening its ties to industry through the SVC Project Advisory Board, increasing student transfer opportunities through new articulation agreements with universities and expanding faculty's professional networks through dissemination efforts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1205026</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carswell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rcarswell@alamo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Troy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Touchette</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ttouchette@alamo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/27/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Santana</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>isantana@alamo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/08/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matuszek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmatuszek@alamo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jiang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sjiang@alamo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yu-Pa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yng@alamo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/08/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Antonio College</Name>
      <CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782124201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2104860748</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1300 San Pedro Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
