<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pan-Pacific Advanced Studies Institute. Genomic Applications to Marine Science and Resource Management in SE Asia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98993</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Akaysha Tang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Title: Pan-Pacific Advanced Studies Institute. Genomic Applications to Marine Science and Resource Management in Southeast Asia&lt;br/&gt;Abstract &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The emerging field of Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) is expanding capabilities for cutting-edge scientific genomic research, with applications that can improve sustainable management of natural resources. This Advanced Study Institute will draw together leading scientists from both sides of the Pacific to understand the potential of the emerging field of NGS to marine science and resource management in Southeast Asia. It aims to build on the knowledge gained by traditional Sanger sequencing methods that are beginning to identify corroborated patterns of marine population structure in the Southeast Asian region. These patterns test hypotheses about the ecological and evolutionary origins of the high marine biodiversity in the region and provide guidelines on how to protect and sustainably manage these resources. Advanced genomics has demonstrated potential to greatly enhance this line of research. Participants will come together from Southeast Asia and the United States to present lectures, guide computer tutorials, and hear from experts in next generation molecular ecology with an emphasis on marine ecology, conservation genetics, and resource management. The institute will focus on six main topics: a) Genetic diversity in natural populations, phylogeography, and applications to marine management in Southeast Asia; b) Genetics of local adaptation; c) Genomic signatures of natural selection; d) Functional ecology based on global gene expression profiling; e) Restriction-site Associated DNA sequencing (RAD-seq) approaches to marine and conservation sciences; and f) Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms versus microsatellites in population ecology. Synthesis workshops will recommend a program of NGS applications to marine science and resource management in Southeast Asia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The success of this institute will pave the way for future workshops spanning the Pacific basin. It will demonstrate how a collaborative research base can be catalyzed between scientists in the United States and Southeast Asia This broader impact will work synergistically with the overarching goals of research and education started by the ongoing National Science Foundation -supported Coral Triangle-PIRE project. The Coral Triangle-PIRE project objectives of training a new international cohort of young scientists focused on Southeast Asia and of establishing long-lasting research collaborations will be directly amplified by this institute. The institute will help to dissolve barriers for United States researchers in Southeast Asian countries, while facilitating the transfer of cutting-edge and powerful molecular ecology methodologies to emerging research teams and institutes in these countries. Such exchanges will allow developing nations to benefit rapidly from these advances that will help preserve imperiled food stocks and centers of biodiversity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1206614</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carpenter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kcarpent@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
