<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>First Conference of the International Society for NonParametric Statistics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gabor J. Szekely</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A 5-day international conference,``The First Conference of the International Society for NonParametric Statistics'' is being planned to be held in Halkidiki, Greece, June 15-19, 2012.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NonParametric Statistics is not a new subject. Nevertheless, it has become more prominent in the 21st century since data have become abundant, and the computing power to analyze them is generally available. The aim of the PI and his collaborators is to bring together researchers from the U.S., Europe and other parts of the world in order to foster research on nonparametric inference with special emphasis on emerging fields such as:&lt;br/&gt;a) Nonparametric methodology for high dimensional data.&lt;br/&gt;b) Bootstrap, Empirical Likelihood, and related methods.&lt;br/&gt;c) Data depth and and related multivariate nonparametric methods.&lt;br/&gt;d) Dimension reduction, model selection, and related methods.&lt;br/&gt;e) Nonparametric machine learning.&lt;br/&gt;f) Nonparametric models for high dimensional mixed and random effects designs. &lt;br/&gt;g) Empirical process and semiparametrics.&lt;br/&gt;h) Bayesian Nonparametrics.&lt;br/&gt;i) Nonparametric methods for time series and Econometrics.&lt;br/&gt;j) Nonparametric methods for spatial processes.&lt;br/&gt;k) Wavelets and nonparametric functional estimation.&lt;br/&gt;l) Nonstandard Asymptotics in nonparametric inference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of the conference is to facilitate the exchange of research ideas on all actively growing areas of nonparametric statistics, thereb giving the development of this important field of statistics a timely boost. This will also be the first conference of the newly formed International Society for NonParametric Statistics (ISNPS) whose mission is "to foster the research and practice of nonparametric statistics, and to promote the dissemination of new developments in the field via conferences, books and journal publications." ISNPS has a distinguished Advisory Committee that includes R.Beran, P.Bickel, R. Carroll, D. Cook, P. Hall, W. Hardle, R. Johnson, B. Lindsay, E. Parzen, P. Robinson, M. Rosenblatt, G. Roussas, T. SubbaRao, and G. Wahba, as well as a Charting Committee consisting of over 50 prominent researchers from all over the world. In particular, theprogram will provide a forum for junior and senior researchers alike to gain valuable experience interacting with leaders in their respective sub-areas,and for building new collaborations between researchers in Nonparametric Statistics from the US with researchers from all over the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1206522</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dimitris</FirstName>
      <LastName>Politis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dpolitis@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
