<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Underground Astrophysics Research Activities at Black Hills State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>65320</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James J. Whitmore</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports the continuing research program at Black Hills State University in underground astrophysics research. The focus is mainly on dark matter and neutrinoless double-beta decay experiments planned for the Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF) at Homestake, SD. For the dark matter experiments, DARKSIDE and MAX, BHSU is designing, building, and optimizing a continuous wave custom cavity ring-down spectroscopy (cw-CRDS) system for measuring the level of impurities in argon gas. This is important for the success of the depleted argon-based dark matter detectors. With this award the BHSU group expects to improve upon the sensitivity of commercial CRDS systems by at least an order of magnitude. The BHSU group will setup the facilities needed to clean the ancient lead bricks to be used for shielding the double-beta decay experiment, MAJORANA. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: Every summer the BHSU group involves South Dakota undergraduates in hands-on research. The BHSU QuarkNet Center, established in 2009, is one of the most active QuarkNet Centers in the country. Last year five teachers brought about 30 students to participate in an LHC Masterclass held at Homestake. As the group enters their 4th year, they expect to add about four new teachers to the Center. In addition, the BHSU group is working with representatives from Oglala Lakota College, in an effort to establish the first QuarkNet Center at a Tribal College or University (TCU).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1207879</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Keeter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kara.keeter@bhsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Durben</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dandurben@bhsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brianna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mount</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Brianna.Mount@bhsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Black Hills State University</Name>
      <CityName>Spearfish</CityName>
      <ZipCode>577990001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6056426111</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 University St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
