<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NRI-Small: Cooperative Underwater Robotic Networks for Discovery &amp; Rescue</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>567719</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to develop a cooperative underwater robotic network for underwater discovery and rescue. With technological advancements, human involvement in underwater activities has increased. Vulnerable oceanic engineering systems, however, can have drastically negative environmental and economic consequences. The oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico in 2010 was a case in point for the impact of underwater infrastructure has on marine ecosystem and local economy. Compared to manned systems, underwater robots, also called autonomous underwater vehicles (AUVs), have inherent advantages by eliminating the need of life support systems and potential risk of human life. Further, an AUV network (with a swam of AUVs) can offer more benefits in efficiency and cost in underwater exploration, discovery and rescue. In this project, innovative algorithms, methods and techniques in autonomous underwater vehicle (AUV) design, cooperative control and underwater acoustic communication networks are proposed to ensure the AUV network's performance in highly uncertain environments. Deliverables for this project include key enabling technologies for the AUV networks and the demonstration of a network including several prototype AUVs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A high performance, energy efficient and autonomous AUV network is significant to science, economy and society. It will have significant impact to underwater infrastructure inspection, wildlife and habitat monitoring, and search and rescue missions. It can also be leveraged for oceanography data collection and water pathway monitoring. Beyond the research significance, this project has important impact on education and outreach by supporting undergraduates, women and other under-represented groups, as well as promoting multi-disciplinary collaboration across departments, campuses, and institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1208499</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chengyu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccao@engr.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jun-Hong (June)</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cui</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jcui@cse.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kazem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kazerounian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kazem@engr.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1632</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8013</Code>
      <Text>National Robotics Initiative</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>030E</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>031E</Code>
      <Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>034E</Code>
      <Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8086</Code>
      <Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
