<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Materials World Network: Visible Light Nanocomposite Photocatalysts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>385761</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tania Paskova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION&lt;br/&gt;A new class of visible-light nanocomposite photocatalysts will be developed. These photocatalysts are composed of metal oxide and metal nanoparticles embedded in a polymer film, and have tuneable properties. This work will lead to new advances in the areas of great economic and societal importance, including the removal of outdoor pollutants, improvement of indoor air quality, wastewater treatment, and decontamination of chemical warfare agents on equipment, including vehicles and clothing. The development of these materials also has applications in other technologies including sensing, optoelectronics, drug delivery and biotechnology. The project is a collaboration with Damien Lenoble, Centre de Researche Gabriel Lippmann, Luxembourg (funded by Fonds National de la Recherche) and provides the foundation for a cutting-edge international research collaboration between the University of Texas at Dallas and the Centre de Researche Gabriel Lippmann. The project advances the education and training of graduate and undergraduate students, and post-doctoral scholars by integrating them into an international research team, and providing them with skills valuable in many technologically important industries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION &lt;br/&gt;A new class of visible-light nanocomposite photocatalysts is being developed by layering metal oxide, titanium dioxide and zinc oxide, metal nanoparticles in a plasma polymer matrix. These photocatalysts have many advantages over currently available titanium dioxide photocatalysts. They are flexible, can be employed to conformally coat a variety of surfaces, including clothing and vehicles, and can be used in continuous flow systems. The use of metal nanoparticles also introduces new synergistic reaction pathways, making this new class of materials more catalytically active than traditional photocatalysts. These photocatalysts provide a simple, robust method for the removal of outdoor pollutants, improvement of indoor air quality, wastewater treatment, and decontamination of chemical warfare agents on equipment, including vehicles and clothing. The development of inorganic-organic nanocomposite materials with tunable properties also has applications in other technologies including sensing, optoelectronics, drug delivery and biotechnology. To accomplish these goals, the project brings together international experts in plasma deposition (Goeckner), the formation of 3D inorganic-organic and materials characterization (Walker), the formation of inorganic nanostructures (Lenoble) and photocatalysis (Lenoble and Walker). This work provides a foundation for a comprehensive international collaboration between the University of Texas at Dallas and the Centre de Researche Gabriel Lippmann, Luxembourg focused on the development of inorganic-organic nanocomposites. The program advances the training and education of graduate and undergraduate students, and post-doctoral scholars by giving them experience in different scientific cultures and providing them with skills valuable in many technologically important industries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209547</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goeckner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>goeckner@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amy.walker@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
      <CityName>Richardson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1774</Code>
      <Text>CERAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7222</Code>
      <Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1774</Code>
      <Text>CERAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7222</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF SPECIAL PROGRAMS-DMR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7488</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
