<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Australia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5836</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Jaylene Ollivierre of Northeastern University to conduct a research project, entitled "Understanding how protein-protein interactions in bacteria regulate cell survival" during the summer of 2012 at the University of Wollongong in Wollongong, New South Wales, Australia. The host scientist is Nick Dixon.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project is to understand the basic mechanisms of the DNA damage response in bacteria, not only for increasing basic knowledge of the biology of bacteria but also for possible use in developing new strategies for dealing with bacterial infections. Mechanisms under study include DNA replication and repair and the coordination of the SOS response.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209544</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jaylene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ollivierre</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ollivierre Jaylene</Name>
      <CityName>Stoneham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021803743</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
