<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on Finite Groups</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tie Luo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There will be a conference on finite groups and related areas held at the University of Cambridge on September 27 - 30, 2012. See www-bcf.usc.edu/~guralnic/JGT80 for more details. The conference is timed to mark the 80th birthday of John Thompson. The study of local group theory proved of fundamental importance in the study of finite groups; it has recently resurfaced in the study of fusion systems and related topological ideas. The classification of finite simple groups is having profound influence in a number of areas of mathematics. At the same time, there is considerable amount of work on the revision of the classification, with significant streamlining and new ideas being brought to bear. The connections to algebraic groups have played central role in the study of groups of Lie type, as well as representation theory in the study of groups and algebras. Developments in all these subjects will be discussed at the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Thompson revolutionized group theory, starting in the late fifties and having central influence ever since then. His odd order paper with Feit, his series of N-group papers and other papers of lasting importance introduced new concepts and ideas which played essential role in the monumental achievement in the subject, the classification of finite simple groups. Thompson won a number of awards, including The Fields Medal, The Abel Prize, and the National Medal of Science. The aim of this research conference is to bring together leading researchers and young mathematicians in these areas. The speakers will include Aschbacher, Capdeboscq, Glauberman, Kessar, Liebeck, Malle, Robinson, Serre, Sin, Smith, Tiep and Thompson. It will be an excellent opportunity to discuss recent developments and plan the way forward for the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209471</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guralnick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>guralnic@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
