<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Korea</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5836</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds William Sharpee of NC State University to conduct a research project, entitled "Dissecting the molecular mechanisms that cause Rice Blast Disease," during the summer of 2012 at Seoul National University in Seoul, Gyeonggi provence, Korea. The host scientist is Yong-Hwan Lee. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project lies in determining at the molecular level how the fungus Magnaporthe oryzae causes Rice Blast Disease, a particularly devastating disease of rice. Current methods to control this organism are insufficient, resulting in the loss of millions of acres of rice each year. Research into how M. oryzae overcomes its host will lead to novel control methods and result in more sustainable, high yielding rice crops. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209888</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharpee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Sharpee William</Name>
      <CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957251</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5942</Code>
      <Text>KOREA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
