<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Japan</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Nicholas DiRienzo of University of California, Davis to conduct a research project, entitled "Hormonal regulation of personality in the field cricket, Gryllus bimaculatus," during the summer of 2012 at Hokkaido University in Sapporo-shi, Hokkaido. The host scientist is Dr. Hitoshi Aonuma.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many animals exhibit personalities, defined as behavioral traits that are correlated across contexts. Crickets possess bold and shy personalities, such that bold individuals are less cautious during potentially dangerous situations. The consistency of these personalities suggests there is an underlying mechanism responsible for their expression. Biogenic amines such as octopamine and serotonin can act as neurohormones when released into the hemolymph and have been shown to influence cricket aggression and escape behavior. Differential regulation of biogenic amines could act as a regulatory mechanism underlying bold and shy personalities. To investigate this, adult male field crickets (Gryllus bimaculatus) are being subjected to a boldness assay followed by an aggression assay to determine if the behavioral differences of bold and shy crickets are due to a difference in the amount of, or regulation of biogenic amine hormones.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209156</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>DiRienzo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>DiRienzo Nicholas</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956161346</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber></PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress></StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
