<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in New Zealand</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6126</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Stephen Budy of the University of Arizona to conduct a research project, entitled "Structure and Mechanical Properties of Fluorinated and Non-fluorinated High Performance Polymers," during the summer of 2012 at the University of Auckland in Auckland, New Zealand. The host scientist is Prof. Jianyong Jin.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project is the investigation of the structure and mechanical properties of fluorinated and non-fluorinated polyphenylene using meta- and para-isomer monomers in order to tailor the mechanical properties (rigid-rod versus random coil, modulus, strength, toughness, and strain). The comparison of these polyphenylene materials allows, for the first time, structural and mechanical characterization which can be compared to other known polymers, e.g., Kevler® and Nomex®, and various biopolymers, including muscle fiber, spider silk, deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA), and collagen.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Polyphenylenes, the parent polymers to those under study, are used as high temperature lubricants, hydraulic fluids, heat-transfer agents, and coolants for nuclear reactors. The fluorine-containing polymers have been used in the personal care, automotive, aerospace, energy, biomedical, telecommunication, and military market. This research promises new tailorable architectures and new configurations of the meta-to-para ratio conformation to allow for more sophisticated processing. Potential new uses include asymmetric membranes for gas separations, tailored protective coatings, proton exchange membranes (PEM) for fuel cell applications, n-type semiconductors for organic light emitting diodes (LED), and field effect transistors (FET).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1210024</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Budy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Budy Stephen M</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857210012</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5941</Code>
      <Text>NEW ZEALAND</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
