<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in China</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5836</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Christopher T. Cirone of University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign to conduct a research project, entitled "Investigating residential air conditioning systems powered by renewable solar energy and the reuse of waste heat," during the summer of 2012 at Zhejiang University in Hangzhou, Zhejiang. The host scientist is Dr. Guangming Chen.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project is to characterize the potential for integration of absorption refrigeration systems with a solar thermal generator and waste heat sources in residential buildings. This practice is desirable due to the primary energy conservation this pairing can offer to the residential building sector. It is important to discover specific applications where waste or renewable heat driven absorption refrigeration can be used to reduce building energy consumption and to understand the specific limitations where this technology is inadequate in comparison with other conventional systems. Continuing to identifying feasible applications and limitations is important to invigorate continued research on this progressive system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1210069</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cirone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cirone Christopher T</Name>
      <CityName>Urbana</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618011535</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
