<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Molecular Basis of Cryptic Genetic Variation in Evolved Lines of Caenorhabditis remanei</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Scheiner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>How do organisms survive in and adapt to novel, stressful conditions? Genetic variation that is not exposed in a normal environment (called cryptic genetic variation) may nevertheless be exposed through phenotypic plasticity in novel environments. A key gap in our understanding of cryptic genetic variation is the identification of its molecular basis and evolution. When exposed to ecologically relevant stressful environments in the lab, the nematode Caenorhabditis remanei evolves rapidly in response to selection, and populations alter their response to alternative environments. The PIs will use next-generation sequencing technology to identify the key genetic and transcriptional changes that have occurred in these evolved lines, enabling the identification of genes and developmental pathways that expose cryptic variation in new environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently little is known about how the exposure of this cryptic genetic variation by a new environment can impact evolution in natural populations. As global climate change rapidly alters habitats and creates novel environments, many species of economic and conservation concern are faced with new environmental challenges. Thus it is becoming increasingly important to understand how environmental factors interact with genes in populations to direct evolutionary change. This research improves our understanding of this process.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1210922</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cresko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wcresko@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sikkink</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksikkink@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
