<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Japan</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5836</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Haley Amanda Ohms of Oregon State University to conduct a research project, entitled "Temperature effects on body size and maturation timing in a freshwater fish," during the summer of 2012 at Hokkaido University in Sapporo Japan. The host scientists are Dr. Seigo Higashi and Dr. Itsuro Koizumi.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project is the advancement of the understanding of how fish may respond to increased ambient water temperatures, due to climate or other change. Body size at maturation and timing of maturation are key components of an individual's reproductive output and ultimately control population-level responses to change. The research focuses on temperature and maturation relationships between ten populations of Dolly Varden charr that live in the Sorachi River located on Hokkaido Japan. The Sorachi River contains tributaries with distinct thermal regimes and provides a unique opportunity to investigate temperature influences on size and timing of maturity in distinct, but closely related populations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1210173</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Haley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ohms</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohms Haley A</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973305959</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
