<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Adaptive or Maladaptive Variation in the Adrenocortical Stress Response within a Heterogeneous Urban Environment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10473</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle M. Elekonich</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In urban habitats animals face unique challenges to survival and reproduction, including disturbance from human activity and noise. Thus, in urban environments only species or individuals with a particular suite of traits may persist. Therefore one of the major challenges is to understand how human expansion and increased urbanization impacts other animals. Further there is not only the impact of urbanization but also the fact that levels of activity vary with in different urban areas, such as city centers being very active while other areas my present refuges from urban activity. The goal of this study is to determine the successful utilization of these different urban regions based upon response to stress, as measured by stress hormone levels. The hypothesis being that species which are better able to handle stress are more likely to be able to occupy urban areas with high levels of activity. These researchers will examine stress response and measure reproductive success in the song sparrow based upon location relative to urban environments. The proposed research will provide STEM research experiences for under-represented minorities and inner city students. The work provides the unique opportunity to bring science and the lab to the urban environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1210425</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rotenberry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.rotenberry@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grunst</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mgrun002@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
