<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITAMP/B2 Institute Winter Graduate School in AMO Physics to be held January 8-20, 2012 in Tucson, Arizona</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides partial support for students to attend the Winter Graduate School on Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics: Ultracold and Ultrafast Atomic Physics, January 8-20, 2012. The school, organized by ITAMP (Institute for Theoretical Atomic, Molecular and Optical Physics) and the B2 (Biosphere 2) Institute, seeks to enhance the training of students in two of the major research areas in contemporary atomic, molecular and optical (AMO) sciences -- "Toward absolute zero" and "Extreme light" -- identified in "Controlling the Quantum World," one of the volumes in the 2010 NRC Decadal Physics Review. This inaugural winter school allows students to interact with eminent scientists in a relaxed atmosphere, away from the distractions of everyday life. Multiple lectures are given on subjects associated with "ultracold atomic and molecular physics" and "ultrashort and ultrastrong coherent physics" in an environment that fosters interaction and discussions, with plenty of opportunities for teachers and students to mingle outside the classroom, and the possibility for initiating new collaborative projects. The meeting is aimed primarily at graduate students representing a broad spectrum of interests in experimental and theoretical research in AMO physics and who come from diverse backgrounds and programs across the nation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1210523</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hossein</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sadeghpour</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>HSADEGHPOUR@CFA.HARVARD.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Smithsonian Institution Astrophysical Observatory</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021381516</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6174967924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>60 Garden St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
