<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Australia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6126</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Morgan Levy of the University of California, Berkeley to conduct a research project entitled "Reconstructing Historical Agricultural Water Use from Crop Records to Observe Changes in Agricultural Water Use Efficiency and Productivity" during the summer of 2012 at the Fenner School of Environment and Society at the Australian National University (ANU) in Canberra, Australia. The host scientists are Dr. Karen Hussey (Chair, ANU Water Initiative) and Professor Stephen Dovers (Director, Fenner School of Environment and Society).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research responds to well-documented gaps in knowledge about historical trends in agricultural water use efficiency and productivity. The research aims to provide important, missing historical water use information based on empirical analyses, rather than upon generalized models. The aim of this research is to better inform sustainability-focused policy and management efforts targeting agricultural water use. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research improves the understanding of technology and policy impacts on agricultural water use efficiency and productivity in water-scarce environments. It uses methods from hydrology, environmental systems science, and statistics to develop agricultural water use estimation methods, as well as policy-relevant data analysis to aid in the assessment of regional-scale water management decisions in developed and developing countries alike.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1210102</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Morgan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Levy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Levy Morgan C</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941103216</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
