<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Large Scale Structure with 21cm Intensity Mapping</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>407675</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard E. Barvainis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This collaborative program will conduct a multi-year project to make precise measurements of the large scale structure of the universe using recently developed 21 cm intensity mapping techniques. The program will create spectral maps of 500 square degrees, spanning the frequency range 700 to 900 MHz (0.58 &lt; z &lt; 1). The principal goal is to measure the baryon acoustic oscillation feature at these redshifts in an innovative program which is complementary to, and competitive with, optical galaxy surveys. The acoustic scale provides a standard ruler which measures the Universe's expansion, providing an observational handle on Dark Energy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of the work include training of graduate student, and outreach to the public via a planetarium show called "The Hydrogen Sky" produced in English, French and Chinese, and distributed worldwide. Additional outreach activities include tours of the night sky through the Universe in the Park program in Wisconsin and teaching electronics to under-represented groups through CMU's Summer Academy for Math and Science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1211777</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peterson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbp@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
