<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Comparative Analysis of Transfer RNAs by Mass Spectrometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>496967</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Patrick Limbach and his group at University of Cincinnati are developing instrumental approaches based on mass spectrometry for the identification, sequencing and analysis of an important class of biomolecules, namely transfer ribonucleic acids (tRNAs). Because tRNAs are involved in the fundamental process of protein translation, it is important that new tools and approaches be developed that enable the sensitive and accurate determination of tRNA population and extent of modifications to the original tRNA sequence. This research will significantly advance the field of tRNA characterization by establishing the techniques required for multiplexed characterizations of tRNA populations. The advantage of multiplexed characterization is that significantly more information on tRNA identity and sequence modification can be obtained in a shorter time period and from less sample, as compared to current methods that analyze one tRNA at a time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project is multidisciplinary, involving the areas of chemistry, biochemistry and molecular biology, thus undergraduates and graduate students working on this project will gain key instruction and insights into the field of modern biological mass spectrometry. These activities continue a long-standing emphasis of Professor Limbach on expanding the number of engaged underrepresented minorities in science, in general, and mass spectrometry, in particular.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1212625</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Limbach</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pat.limbach@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
      <ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1982</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
