<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Preparation of polymeric phase change materials based upon Diels-Alder chemistry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program and the Chemical Catalysis Program support the work of Professor Philip J. Costanzo of California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo towards the preparation of polymeric phase change materials based upon Diels-Alder chemistry. This research focuses on developing and incorporating new Diels-Alder linkages into thermally-responsive matrix materials that will be used for multiple applications including, responsive guest-host systems, renewable resins and rheological modifiers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project provides interdisciplinary research training for graduate and undergraduate students. Outreach programs, which intertwine undergraduate research and teaching, will impact undergraduate students, K-12 students and teachers. Undergraduates will be involved in the creation and instruction of teaching modules for K-12 students. Through the outreach activities, K-12 participants will be exposed to material science which stimulates their curiosity for science. The K-12 students are also exposed to a college experience, which can help encourage them to see themselves as college graduates. In addition, Cal Poly undergraduates are given an opportunity to have an early field experience using inquiry based tools. It will also help to refine their knowledge of material and polymer science. Finally, K-12 teachers may increase their content knowledge by attending workshops and increase their available resources via Cal Poly Science Kits for Teachers Library (SKTL), a durable-lending library.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1213331</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Costanzo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pcostanz@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Polytechnic State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Luis Obispo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>934070830</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8057562982</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Grand Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
