<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Mentoring Consortium at the International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multi-Agent Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Todd Leen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports the travel of U.S. doctoral student researchers to the premier international conference on autonomous agents and multi-agent systems and their participation in the Doctoral Mentoring Consortium held in conjunction with it. The Eleventh International Joint Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multi-Agent Systems (AAMAS 2012) will be held in Valencia, Spain, June 4-8, 2012. All students awarded stipends will participate in a Doctoral Mentoring Consortium in which they will present their research to other student researchers as well as experienced researchers and receive in-depth feedback from a group of invited senior researchers. Travel stipends will be awarded through an application process that includes submission of a two-page extended thesis abstract, a one-page personal research statement, a short CV, and a recommendation from the thesis advisor. In selecting students to be given stipends, the committee will consider resources available to them to attend the conference, their exposure to international research, and their level of participation in the conference (e.g., paper, poster, workshop presentation); it will also consider the diversity of the potential participants. The travel stipends will allow the selected students to present their research results and participate in valuable discussions that will likely shape the future of this critically important field. The AAMAS technical program is complemented with an array of workshops, tutorials, and other events. The wide variety and significance of the topics typically presented at AAMAS, in the technical and other programs, provide opportunities for students to share, exchange, and learn from each other.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1216361</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gini@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
