<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Anti-Jamming Techniques for Secure Communications in Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>380000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Jamming attack is one of the most commonly used techniques for limiting the effectiveness of an opponent's communication in wireless networks. Along with the advent of user configurable intelligent devices, such as cognitive radios, jamming is no longer limited to military related events, but has become an urgent and serious threat to civilian communications as well. Motivated by this observation, this project is devoted to the development of multi-layer anti-jamming techniques for secure communications over wireless networks. First, we introduce a systematic 2D model for cognitive jamming characterization, detection and classification. We also introduce the concept of disguised jamming, and point out that it can be much more harmful than the traditional strong jamming. Second, we investigate efficient anti-jamming system design for both point-to-point (one-hop) communications and multi-hop communications. For one-hop communications, we enhance jamming resistance by incorporating advanced cryptographic techniques into network-centric spectrum access control and the physical layer transceiver design. For multi-hop communications, we develop efficient and unconditionally secure cryptographic algorithms and protocols to maximize routing diversity and routing anonymity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed highly efficient anti-jamming techniques lay a solid foundation for real-time jamming detection and reliable information transmission under dynamic jamming scenarios. It can greatly improve the efficiency and reliability of high speed wireless services. This project also includes a significant education component aimed at integrating frontier research with undergraduate and graduate curricula. Research results will be presented at international conferences, meetings and published in scientific journals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1217206</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tongtong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tongli@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>renjian@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
