<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Oceanographic Instrumentation 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>28806</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James S. Holik</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A request is made by the University of Washington to fund additional and replacement instrumentation for the R/V Thompson, a 274? general purpose, global class research vessel, and R/V Barnes, a 66-foot coastal research vessel, both operated as part of the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System research fleet. These platforms provide facilities for conducting oceanographic research funded by the National Science Foundation and other federal agencies. The instrumentation they propose to acquire will provide operational flexibility to projects that are embarked upon both vessels, will address some deficiencies noted during the fall 2011 NSF vessel inspections, and will increase their capacity to do useful science and data collection during transits between funded cruises.. In order of priority, they propose to purchase the following: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Anritsu MS2821B spectrum analyzer $13,487&lt;br/&gt;2. Mystaire FE-2620 ductless fume hoods (2 each) $8,951&lt;br/&gt;3. McLane large volume in situ samplers WTS-LV04 (4 each) $129,558&lt;br/&gt;4. Oceansciences Group underway CTD $79,258&lt;br/&gt;5. SBE911plus serial uplink modifications and upgrade (3 each) $15,319&lt;br/&gt; Total $246,573&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt; The principal impact of the present proposal is under criterion two, providing infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF). The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1219436</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilcock</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wilcock@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5413</Code>
      <Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
