<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2012 Environmental Sciences: Water GRC, Plymouth, NH, June 24-29, 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>23500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Debra Reinhart</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-1222515 Tratnyek&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports the Gordon Research Conference on Environmental Sciences:&lt;br/&gt;Water to be held June 24-29, 2012. The conference will bring together 150 participants in an informal setting, for a program of plenary talks by established and emerging researchers who are doing the most innovative and significant research on diverse aspects of environmental aquatic science. The scope will span multiple disciplines (chemistry, biology, geology, engineering, health science), media (soil, groundwater, surface water, atmospheric water, drinking water, wastewater), and scales (molecular, nano, cellular, ecosystem, global). This year, the unifying theme will be the scientific "grand challenges" that form the foundations and, at the same time, the frontiers of aquatic environmental science. These grand challenges, which include topics related to free radical reactions, natural organic matter, nanoparticles, biotransformation, reactive transport and surface chemistry, will provide the general themes for each session. Overall, the program will highlight the crosscutting significance of these grand challenges through sessions that represent the depth and breadth of each grand challenge issue with speakers engaged in innovative and significant research on diverse aspects to environmental aquatic science. The conference offers a platform for graduate student and postdoctoral researchers to present their research and participate fully in the conference activities. The conference promotes broad participation from a diverse background, both through the speaker selection and through special GRC funding mechanisms that target underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1222515</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sedlak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sedlak@ce.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tratnyek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tratnyek@ohsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
