<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TWC: Small: Friendsourcing to Detect Network Manipulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nan Zhang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Traditionally, security on the Internet has been concerned with threats posed by edge nodes (hosts) to other hosts and to the middle nodes of the network (routers). However, in recent years,a rising number of instances in which hosts seek to defend themselves against the middle of the network can be seen. Examples include censorship and network neutrality violations, which fall into a general category of ?network manipulation?.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is exploring how to detect network manipulation through ?friendsourcing?, a strategy in which individuals use their social networks to get measurements from their friends. The project is developing a framework to facilitate this basic mechanism of analysis by addressing coverage, instrumentation, and co-operation. To obtain coverage, it must be possible to carry out recruitment that finds a collection of hosts in the right network locations. To deploy instrumentation, a software system capable of making the necessary measurements must be set up in such locations. To gain co-operation, it is necessary to rely on friending to get the help needed to realize the coverage and use the instrumentation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Initial studies use limited coverage based on close friending and manual instrumentation. Later studies use broader coverage with theoretical underpinnings, more modular instrumentation, weaker friending ties, and more participants. Studies use a blend of theory (of coverage), software architecture (for instrumentation) and social network binding (to assess levels of cooperation). These studies provide better foundations for understanding the capacity of social networks and friendsourcing to measure Internet behavior and address network manipulation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1223967</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gunter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cgunter@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8060</Code>
      <Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7434</Code>
      <Text>CNCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
