<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Community Computational Platforms for Developing Three-Dimensional Models of Earth Structure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1550000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leonard E. Johnson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Precise information about the structure of the solid Earth comes from seismograms recorded&lt;br/&gt;at the surface of a highly heterogeneous lithosphere. Full-3D tomography based on adjoint and&lt;br/&gt;scattering-integral methods can assimilate this information into three-dimensional models of elastic and&lt;br/&gt;anelastic structure. These methods fully account for the physics of wave excitation, propagation, and&lt;br/&gt;interaction by numerically solving the inhomogeneous equations of motion for a heterogeneous anelastic&lt;br/&gt;solid. Full-3D tomography using adjoint and scattering-integral methods requires the execution of&lt;br/&gt;complex computational procedures that challenge the most advanced high-performance computing&lt;br/&gt;(HPC) systems. Current research is petascale; future research will require exascale capabilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will establish an interoperable set of community computational platforms?vertically&lt;br/&gt;integrated systems of hardware, software, and wetware that will allow a significant community of&lt;br/&gt;investigators to employ the techniques of full-3D tomography to refine Earth structures. Two tomographic&lt;br/&gt;platforms will be built on highly scalable codes for solving the forward problem: the AWP-ODC 4th-order,&lt;br/&gt;staggered-grid, finite-difference code, which has been widely used for regional earthquake simulation and&lt;br/&gt;physics-based seismic hazard analysis, and the SPECFEM3D spectral element code, which is capable of modeling wave propagation through aspherical structures of essentially arbitrary complexity on scales ranging from local to global. A third platform, based on the Unified Community Velocity Model (UCVM) software developed by the Southern California Earthquake Center (SCEC), will provide a common framework for comparing and synthesizing Earth models and delivering model products to a wide community of geoscientists. These platforms will be deployed at the NCAR-Wyoming Supercomputing Center (NWSC).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1226343</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jordan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tjordan@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Olsen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kbolsen@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yifeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cui</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yfcui@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeroen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tromp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jtromp@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
