<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Deflecting Ingroup Members' Stereotype-Confirming Behavior: Factors that Facilitate High Performance and Positive Interracial Interactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>228814</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Breckler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Though a diverse society increases the likelihood of positive interracial interaction, it also increases the likelihood that people will apply stereotypes to group members with whom they are less familiar during such interactions. Thus, in interracial interactions, which are already characterized by subtle levels of anxiety, witnessing or interacting with racial group members who behave stereotypically (i.e., commit "stereotype-confirming" acts) may exacerbate the strain often experienced in diverse contexts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous research has shown that such experiences may increase people's motivation to behave counterstereotypically to disprove negative group stereotypes, but also may undermine performance and discourage future interracial contact. This previous work, however, leaves us at an impasse: What then contributes to people's ability to thrive in diverse settings following racial group members' stereotype-confirming behavior and how do people cope in such situations? This research sets out to answer these important questions first by investigating the factors that contribute to the divergent behavioral and social outcomes experienced by racial group members who witness the stereotype-confirming behaviors of ingroup members in interracial (vs. intraracial) interactions. It also examines the burden that racial group members may carry to represent their group positively in these interpersonal interactions and the possible psychological and social consequences of this burden. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Four experimental laboratory studies examine various conditions that may improve performance and facilitate a positive (rather than a negative) interpersonal interaction for ethnic minorities who witness racial group members behaving stereotypically in diverse settings. These studies assess the extent to which: 1) the frequency of positive interracial contact, 2) high vs. low interpersonal closeness with an interaction partner, and 3) interactions with a high vs. a low prejudice partner can improve performance and interpersonal contact in such interactions. Four experimental survey studies then build on this work to explore how majority and minority group members who strategically behave counterstereotypically following ingroup members' stereotype-confirming acts may incur social costs. Ironically, those attempting to rectify the situation may be viewed negatively by same-race members but positively by different-race members.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work has the potential to transform how we understand people's behavior in novel interracial contexts -- particularly those laden with negative group stereotypes or stereotype-confirming group members -- by providing clear strategies for improving individuals' outcomes and highlighting factors that stand to undermine these positive outcomes. Namely, when individuals of all racial and ethnic backgrounds engage in positive interracial interactions more frequently and actively cultivate cross-race friendships - even with those who may seem to lack egalitarian values - they are likely to thrive emotionally, cognitively, and socially in interracial interactions. Furthermore, these strategies may reduce the burden felt by those who are motivated to maintain positive relationships with both same-race and different-race associates when attempting to counteract racial group members' stereotype-confirming behavior. Thus, this research will assist in the larger goal of working to create and maintain positive intergroup interactions and relationships so that all individuals can thrive in diverse academic and social settings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Finally, this research meets the goals of NSF to integrate research and education and to include historically underrepresented populations in all stages of the research process. It will be conducted sprimarily at Spelman College, the nation's first historically Black women's Liberal Arts College, and will expose undergraduates to graduate-level research in social psychology. Students will be involved in the creation of the research materials and its implementation, as well as the dissemination of findings at professional conferences, on Spelman's campus, and at other institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1226930</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Valerie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taylor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vtaylor5@spelman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Spelman College</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303144399</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4042705897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>350 Spelman Lane SW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1332</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1397</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-DIRECTORATE ACTIV PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>041Z</Code>
      <Text>HBCU-Strengthening Research Capacities</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1332</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
