<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Students to Attend the 10th National Graduate Research Polymer Conference: May 21-24, 2012, Cleveland, Ohio</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL AND NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides partial travel support for graduate students to attend the National Graduate Research Polymer Conference to be held on May 21-24, 2012, at Case Western Reserve University in Cleveland.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will offer the opportunity to about 200 students, as well as professors, researchers, and industry representatives from across the country to hear the latest research in the interdisciplinary polymer science and engineering field. There will be four plenary talks by distinguished leaders in the field. Specific symposia have been organized on bio-related polymers, energy-related materials, nanostructured materials, photonics and electronics, surfaces and interfaces, self-assembling polymers, as well as on structure, characterization, theory, and processing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The major broader impact of this conference is the unique opportunity for the graduate students to stay current with the state-of-the-art research across the polymer frontiers and to promote fruitful interactions among all participants. Moreover, the conference will offer a panel discussion on career options for polymer/materials students, as well as a career fair to promote networking with company representatives.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1226122</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liming.dai@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/02/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
