<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a Stimulated Scattering Microscope for Cell Imaging</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>385374</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the proposed study is to develop a new type of nonlinear scattering microscopy based on stimulated Rayleigh/Brillouin scattering that will enable measurement of thermal and elastic properties of cells. A central part of this work is assembly of a novel laser system that will provide very rapid tuning and excellent noise properties. In this effort SRI will (1) assemble the laser system, (2) combine the laser system with its associated electronics, and (3) evaluate instrument performance and operation through imaging of cells. This work will bring a new type of nonlinear microscopy to biology and medical research that will complement existing nonlinear microscopy techniques, including multiphoton microscopy using fluorescence, second-harmonic and third harmonic generation, coherent anti-Stokes Raman (CARS) microscopy, and four-wave mixing. SRI has recently developed new advances in stimulated Rayleigh/Brillouin scattering that will enable rapid imaging of cells without causing damage to the cells. The microscope SRI proposes to develop will allow a new look at effects such as signal transduction through mechanical forces, cell motility, cell division, and other aspects involving changes in cellular viscoelastic properties.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1229808</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Faris</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gregory.faris@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SRI International</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508592651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>005E</Code>
      <Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
