<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Capture and Use of Coal Mine Ventilation Air Methane (VAM)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>487463</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project proposes to develop innovative technical solutions and products that reduce coal mine gas explosion. Methane explosion is the major cause of mining casualty and economic loss. The list of world coal mine explosion is a long and shocking one. Even today, 300 years after human?s initial mining of coal, methane explosion still kills thousands of miners each year worldwide. Developed naturally within coal seams, methane is known for explosion hazard and chemical neutrality, which makes it highly dangerous but difficult to remove. Although modern technologies have been developed to pre-release methane or to dilute it by ventilation, it is practically impossible to eliminate the threat due to frequently occurred gas bursts and accumulation. Due to economic concern, mine owners and managers hesitate to take prompt action in response to each gas alarm. Sometime, their hesitation proved to be deadly. Torrey Hills invented a technology that can effectively capture methane from ambient atmosphere and convert it to safe chemicals, and thus can reduce explosion risk and operation shutdown loss to coal mine owners. The main features of the technology are room-temperature and room-pressure operation, complementary to ventilation, attendance free, and portable.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project includes not only addition of economic value to coal mine owners and operators, but also contribution to the overall society wealth in a broader sense by reducing life loss and improving environmental protection. The world coal market is estimated to be $400-600 billion per year. According to World Coal Association, the direct economic loss caused by coal methane explosion is over $10 billion worldwide each year. Nevertheless, the broader indirect costs are difficult to measure, including loss of life, hardship on the affected families, disruption to the local business, legal burden on the companies, and associated costs to governments and the society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1230135</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Qi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lqi@torreyhillstech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>04/07/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ken</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kkuang@torreyhillstech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Torrey Hills Technologies LLC</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921212753</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585586666</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6370 Lusk Blvd Suite F-111</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
