<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Photonic and Electronic Devices Based on Self-Assembling DNA Templates</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>233000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this program is to develop reliable protocols for fabricating functional photonic and electronic nanostructures using bioinspired, molecular assembly methods. In one of the proposed tasks, seed nanoparticles will be selectively attached through molecular recognition to the ?DNA origami? template and fused to form the electrodes; a separate nanoparticle island will be separately attached forming a single-electron transistor. In the other major task, plasmonic bow-tie antennae will be assembled from nanoparticles, and the optically active nanoscale object will be attached in the hot spot. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed project stems from the convergence of recent advances in DNA-based self-assembly methods with promising preliminary results on specific surface binding of solution-assembled complexes. These nanostructures may develop into a new class of naturally biocompatible sensors that will have transformative applications in the biomedical field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are the development of alternative, cheaper (most steps are in aqueous solution) and more versatile fabrication methods for making composite bio-nano-devices. The proposal has a strongly emphasized outreach component: the PIs plan to recruit MSc students from the North Carolina Central University ? a historically black university (HBCU). The program will train the students in the unique combination of biochemical and physical methods of modern nanotechnology that are relevant for both industrial and academic careers. Disadvantaged high school students (Project SEED) will participate during the summer months to get a feel for the emerging field of nanoscience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1231888</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thom</FirstName>
      <LastName>LaBean</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thlabean@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
      <CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>103E</Code>
      <Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>108E</Code>
      <Text>Bioelectronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
