<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DMREF: GOALI - Discovery, Development, and Deployment of High Temperature Coating/Substrate Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Schlueter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL ABSTRACT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The convergence of new computational capabilities, advanced characterization techniques and the ability to generate and harness large-scale data enables new pathways for the discovery, development and deployment of advanced materials systems. This program engages a multidisciplinary team to develop a fundamental framework for design of a new class of multilayered systems for deployment in new, energy efficient power generation and propulsion systems. Novel complementary computational and experimental tools developed will be integrated with existing tools and applied to a promising new class of intermetallic-strengthened cobalt-base alloys. The unique high-temperature properties of these alloys, when combined with thermal barrier coatings, promise very substantial improvements in powerplant efficiency, motivating GE Energy and GE Global Research as partners in this DMREF-GOALI program. The program will take a systems approach, developing tools and models that permit simultaneous design of the metallic substrate and intermetallic bond coat for compatibility with the ceramic top coat, going beyond the linear, experiment-driven approach historically employed for independent development of these three critical system elements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The convergence of new computational capabilities, advanced characterization techniques and the ability to generate and harness large-scale data enables new pathways for the discovery, development and deployment of advanced materials systems. This program engages an engineering and computer science team to develop a fundamental framework for design of new multilayered materials systems for energy efficient power generation and aircraft propulsion. Novel complementary computational and experimental tools will be developed and integrated with existing tools to accelerate development of a newly discovered cobalt-base substrate material along with compatible environmental protection layers. The program will take a systems approach, developing tools and models that permit simultaneous design of the layered system, going beyond the linear, experiment-driven approach historically employed for independent development of these critical system elements.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1233704</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van der Ven</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>avdv@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tresa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pollock</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pollock@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Begley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>begley@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Petzold</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>petzold@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1712</Code>
      <Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1771</Code>
      <Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8400</Code>
      <Text>DMREF</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
