<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Planning Reliable and Resilient Transportation Networks against Correlated Infrastructure Disruptions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174586</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elise D. Miller-Hooks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This collaborative research project aims to discover a methodological framework that enhances the reliability and resilience of transportation network infrastructure systems that are exposed to multiple linked disruption risks. Such linked risks could be caused by exposure to common hazards or shared unreliable supplies. We will first establish a decomposition theory that transforms a general infrastructure system with linked facility disruption risks into one with a simpler and more explicit structure with only independent disruptions, yet ensuring that the two systems have exactly equivalent functionalities and operational behaviors. Based on this theoretical foundation, a set of advanced mathematical models will be created to address a number of pressing engineering challenges, including (i) reliable network design, (ii) critical infrastructure protection, and (iii) cascading failure mitigation. Case studies from real-world infrastructure systems (e.g., bridge networks exposed to earthquakes, electricity grids experiencing power plant disruptions) will be used to validate the proposed theory and illustrate the practical applicability of these models. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will (i) advance the knowledge base needed to address a wide range of infrastructure disruptions in many engineering contexts, (ii) provide managerial insights that hold the promise of enhancing the reliability and resilience of various infrastructure systems. This will have impacts not only on transportation and manufacturing industries but also on social communities. This project will also result in new educational practices by the integration of the research into educational materials and activities, including a new role-playing game for interactive teaching focused on infrastructure disruption mechanisms and protection strategies. Collaborations with public agencies (e.g. state Departments of Transportation) and private freight and manufacturing industries (e.g. CSX Transportation Inc. and Caterpillar Inc.) will help assure that the proposed research and educational activities are of practical relevance and importance, and that the outcomes are readily implementable.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1234936</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaopeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xiaopengli@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
      <CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1631</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>029E</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS MGT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>039E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
