<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Graphene-SiC Interface: Effect of Atomic Bonding Type on Thermal Transport</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET - 1235852 &lt;br/&gt;PI: Xinwei Wang, Iowa State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, a novel technology based on steady-state joule heating and simultaneous Raman spectroscopy will be developed to measure and distinguish the temperature between graphene and its substrate. This technology enables nanometer resolution in the out-of-plane direction for thermal mapping. Systematic knowledge will be built about thermal transport between graphene and SiC, and how this interface thermal resistance is affected by two typical interfaces: interface featuring Van der Waal force and interface with covalent bond. Atomistic modeling will be conducted to evaluate the graphene-interface thermal resistance and complement the experimental data to provide a cross-benchmarked and complemented in-depth and full-spectrum picture of the thermal transport at graphene-SiC interface. For thermal design in graphene-based devices and systems, this project will establish an important quantitative knowledge base about the interface thermal resistance sustained by Van der Waals and covalent bonds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts. The results of the research will be integrated into existing and new courses at Iowa State University. Undergraduate participation in summer research will be facilitated through the PERUSE program at ISU. Outreach to K-12 students is included, and will involve supervision of independent study projects by top students from local high schools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1235852</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xinwei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xwang3@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>150E</Code>
      <Text>Conduction/Diffusion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
