<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI-BIC: Partnerships for Innovation In Printed Devices and Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599389</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Partnerships for Innovation project from Rochester Institute of Technology entitled, "Partnerships for Innovation in Printed Devices and Materials", focuses on the use of direct-write material printing technologies and the applications made possible by their unique capabilities. Traditional microelectromechanical systems (MEMS) processing techniques are very well suited for a variety of applications. However, they are generally limited to a small set of standard materials, they are used with planar substrates, and they require clean-room environments. This project seeks to grow the universe of what is possible through the use of direct-write print technologies and a complementary photonic curing process. Direct-write deposition eliminates many of the material restrictions associated with MEMS techniques. Nano inks consisting of polymers, metals, ceramics, or composites can all be printed. The photonic curing process then enables one to cure, or fuse, high temperature printed nanomaterials without damaging surrounding low temperature materials such as polymers. The marriage of multi-material, multi-layer nano ink printing with low temperature curing opens the door to new applications using devices consisting of combinations of material types.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this research will be economic benefits for the knowledge enhancement partners as well as end users of their technologies. Nano ink formulations optimized for Aerosol Jet printing and photonic curing will be developed. Aerosol Jet process enhancements aimed at multi-material deposition will enhance the ability to produce novel MEMS-scale devices. An archive of multidisciplinary webinars as well as lab activities that are incorporated into undergraduate courses and K-12 summer camps will be maintained. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partners at the inception of the project are the Rochester Institute of Technology (RIT) and its small business partners, Optomec (Albuquerque, NM), NovaCentrix (Austin, TX), and Intrinsiq Materials (Rochester, NY). These four entities form the project's primary knowledge enhancement partners. Other large businesses supporting the knowledge-enhancement partners include Hewlett Packard, Kodak, Tyco Electronics, and Xerox.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1237761</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Collison</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cjcscha@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sawppr@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borkholder</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dabeee@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harvey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Palmer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hjpeen@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Denis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cormier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drceie@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
      <CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>123E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1662</Code>
      <Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8085</Code>
      <Text>Building Innovation Capacity</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
