<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Partial Organizational Support for the 3rd Summer Institute on Complex Plasmas. conference to be held July 30th - Aug 8, 2012 at Seton Hall in New Jersey.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9700</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven J Gitomer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant will provides partial support for American postdoctoral, graduate, and advanced undergraduate students to participate in the third Graduate Summer Institute on Complex Plasmas, an international educational workshop which will be held from July 30th to August 8th, 2012 at Seton Hall University in South Orange, New Jersey. The project objective of this summer school is the educational dissemination of the current knowledge of this new field, the advancement of the current scientific challenges, and the promotion of the potential technological opportunities afforded by complex plasmas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The third Graduate Summer Institute on Complex Plasmas will focus on dusty and strongly coupled plasmas, reactive plasmas, microplasmas, quantum plasmas, and plasmas in contact with surfaces. The summer school will provide a broad overview yet rigorous curriculum that will lead to further advancement in this emerging field by attracting young American researchers in significant numbers since they will encounter scientific challenges as well as technological opportunities upon which they can build successful academic or industrial careers. A further benefit of this program is that complex plasma applications appear to be a potentially very fertile field for small, high-tech start-up companies which will perceive this subject as a favorable innovation source for marketplace realization of new plasma technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1237413</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mehmet</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sahiner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mehmet.sahiner@shu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lopez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jose.lopez1@shu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Seton Hall University</Name>
      <CityName>South Orange</CityName>
      <ZipCode>070792646</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9732752974</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 South Orange Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
