<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI-BIC: Partnership for Interoperable Components for Parallel Engineering Simulations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599958</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Partnerships for Innovation project from Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute will advance the development and delivery of scalable simulation tools to support companies in the effective application of massively parallel computing in the design and manufacture of future products. The project will address the technology gaps that are currently preventing industry from taking advantage of the advances in cost effective massively parallel computing and the growing number of individual analysis components that execute at scale on these machines. The key technical advancement will be addressed through the development of interoperable interfaces that can effectively couple individual simulation components together to support the execution of complete massively parallel simulations as needed to reliably answer the performance questions of interest to engineers and scientists. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project will lead to new products and services of benefit to society, as well as to associated economic benefits. It will be a powerful tool for building innovation capacity. The broader impacts will follow from the new technologies that support innovation over a broad spectrum of applications ranging from the engineering of new generations of products, to the development of medical treatments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partners at the inception of the project are Knowledge-Enhancement Partners: Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute's Scientific Computation Research Center, Troy, NY; Kitware, Inc., Clifton Park, NY; Pliant Energy Systems, Brooklyn, NY; and Simmetrix, Inc., Clifton Park, NY. Other Partners: Private Sector Organization: Altair Engineering, Inc., Mountain View, CA and Clifton Park, NY;and IBM, Armonk, NY; Public Sector Organization: Division of Science, Technology and Innovation, Empire State Development, Albany, NY.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1237555</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shephard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shephard@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kolb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kolbj@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Assad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Oberai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>oberaa@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Onkar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sahni</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sahni@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
