<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CPS: Synergy: Cyber Enabled Manufacturing Systems (CeMs) for Small Lot Manufacture</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce M. Kramer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides funding for the development of Cyber Enabled Manufacturing (CeMs) process control for small lot manufacturing that incorporates a model of the process directly into the control algorithm. Such a model can be used to accommodate changes in the physical product and the manufacturing process and thus the manufacturing monitoring and control algorithm, so that changing conditions are easily accommodated without extensive additional experiments. A set of objectives of this physics and cyber-enabled manufacturing process control system are rational setting of manufacturing tolerances, real time prediction of manufacturing defects, real time control of process to eliminate defects, and real time monitoring and control for small lot manufacturing. The methodologies we propose to achieve these goals are high fidelity, physics based models including models of faults/defects, uncertainty quantification, reduced order models that run in real time, measurement, real time prediction, real time computer architecture, real time control with inverse solutions, and automating the CeMs process for generic manufacturing processes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will greatly reduce cycle time in producing new or modified products and improve the quality of manufacturing processes with accompanying reduction in waste, energy use, and cost. The development of such accurate control algorithms and their application to manufacturing processes can provide a competitive edge to US manufacturers. Perhaps more importantly, the education of engineers involved this research will supply US industry with employees who can apply this technology to many industrial processes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1239343</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beaman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbeaman@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aloysius</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mok</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mok@cs.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rmoser@ices.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Omar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghattas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>omar@ices.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jayathi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murthy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmurthy@me.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
