<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Europtrode XI Conference, Barcelona, Spain, April 1-4, 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexander Revzin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Tuan Vo-Dinh&lt;br/&gt;1239156&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project involves the organization of the conference EUROPT(R)ODE XI, which is part of&lt;br/&gt;the Europt(r)ode Conference series, which encompasses all aspects related to the research,&lt;br/&gt;development and applications of optical chemical sensors and biosensors.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The EUROPT(R)ODE XI Conference, to be held in Barcelona, Spain, April 1-4, 2012, will&lt;br/&gt;discuss the latest advances in this competitive and evolving field of optical sensors. The&lt;br/&gt;Conference is the premier worldwide forum for the presentation of innovations in optical&lt;br/&gt;sensing, showing both cutting-edge integration concepts and key emerging trends in a highly&lt;br/&gt;multi-disciplinary atmosphere. This biannual Conference presents an exceptional opportunity,&lt;br/&gt;of interest to both academic and industrial researchers, to discuss and exchange the latest&lt;br/&gt;developments in this extremely challenging field. There is no other Conference specifically&lt;br/&gt;devoted to optical (bio)sensing, thus making this meeting unique at the international level.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;The Europt(r)ode conference series has become a major scientific meeting on optical chemical&lt;br/&gt;sensors and biosensors attracting scientists and educators from across the globe. Because of the&lt;br/&gt;multidisciplinary nature of the field, Europt(r)ode has always brought together a diverse&lt;br/&gt;audience including scientists and engineers in physics, chemistry and biology all over the world.&lt;br/&gt;Their engaging discussions have stimulated interdisciplinary and international collaborations&lt;br/&gt;and helped shape scientific and academic institutions from which several generations of PhD&lt;br/&gt;students have graduated. The Conference has also fostered increasing collaborations between&lt;br/&gt;academia and industry and stimulated countless new commercial spin-offs in the field.&lt;br/&gt;Companies participate regularly not only at the level of exhibitors but though invited and oral or&lt;br/&gt;poster presentations. The Conference in 2012 will have, as a main novelty, an exclusive&lt;br/&gt;Industrial Session by invitation, where the main industrial players in the field will highlight&lt;br/&gt;scientific innovations and technological transfer in the optical sensing field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1239156</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tuan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vo-Dinh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tuan.vodinh@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
