<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STEMing the Tide: Exploring Factors Related to Minority Males Interest, Engagement and Achievement in Mathematics and Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jolene K. Jesse</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: This symposium will convene researchers in education and the social sciences with practicing STEM professionals to review, explore, and respond to research on identity factors linked to minority male success in science and mathematics. The following topics will be addressed: (1) the impact of minority male gender identity on interest and engagement in science and mathematics, with particular interest in how conceptions of manhood and masculinity are relevant; (2) gender role socialization and implications for teaching and learning of science and mathematics content for minority men and boys; (3) institutional and organizational models and programs (e.g., school design, same-sex classroom) and pathways that influence minority men and boys' interest and entry into science and math majors and careers; and (4) shared interests and goals (e.g., evidence-based initiatives), and collaboration opportunities for researchers and STEM practitioners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This symposium will serve as a catalyst for focusing on and developing a knowledge base around the educational opportunities and challenges of many minority men and boys. Manuscripts from the symposium will be distributed in a special issue of a major journal focusing on minority men and boys in math and science, as well as through an edited book with national distribution. The symposium will be a significant forum to inspire collaborations and networks among similarly interested researchers and STEM practitioners to potentially development future NSF research grant proposals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1240757</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdavis21@astro.temple.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Temple University</Name>
      <CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191405104</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2157077379</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3340 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
