<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STEM Colorado Teaching to Learn Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>799998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Keith Sverdrup</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Phase II project is designed to integrate, expand, and align teacher preparation, induction, and mastery by bringing together Noyce Teacher Teams of current and prospective teachers with different types and levels of experience. The focus of each team of veteran, novice, and prospective teachers is on conducting classroom research and the goal of this centralizing activity is the critical examination of assumptions about teaching and learning. The mechanism by which such reflection occurs is scientific inquiry into one's own practice, the practices of others, and the practices of students. Team members collaborate on four different aspects of their own professional development, preparation, or induction program: (1) discipline-based educational research in the K-12 classroom, (2) implementation of state of the art technology and research-based approaches, (3) planning of and reflection on teaching and learning, and (4) conference presentations and journal publications. The Teaching to Learn project is a collaboration of the University of Colorado Boulder, Adams Twelve 5-Star Schools, Boulder Valley, Cherry Creek, Denver Public Schools, Englewood, Jefferson County, Mapleton, and St. Vrain Valley school districts associated with former Noyce projects. The Teaching to Learn research team activities serve as mechanisms both for the professional growth of participants and as a model for how scientific inquiry into personally and professionally meaningful problems leads to knowledge generation. The project is providing scholarships and stipends to 30 preservice teachers, including undergraduates and post-baccalaureate certification students. In addition to providing extended field experiences for preservice students, the project offers an expanded professional development program for recent and more experienced Noyce graduates supported under previous grants. The expectation that Noyce Teacher Teams publish and present their work leads to a greater impact on teacher-driven professional development nationwide.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1240073</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Noah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Finkelstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>noah.finkelstein@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Valerie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Otero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Valerie.Otero@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laurie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Langdon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>laurie.langdon@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
