<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Predicting Regional Invasion Dynamic Processes (PRIDE)-Developing a Cross-scale, Functional-trait Based Modeling Framework</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>725985</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy Kratz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Invasions of exotic species pose major threats to many ecosystems and result in significant ecosystem degradation and economic loss. Research on exotic invasions has been a major topic in the last two decades and much knowledge has been gained from research done on small plots. However, current understanding of the long-term invasion process at regional to continental scales is limited, in part because long-term and large-scale empirical information is lacking. This project uses a new research framework constructed using functional traits (for example, life history information) that includes all three major invasion components: the invader, the recipient system, and the drivers that facilitate the invader, all examined across scales of both time and space. The overarching goal of this exploratory project is to establish a regional network of scientists and practitioners to develop a regional scale predictive model of invasion dynamics under this new framework. The specific aims of the project are (1) to develop an interdisciplinary team for constructing a regional to continental scale invasive modeling framework, ensuring that it is also relevant to invasion management, (2) to develop a comprehensive regional database that includes invader functional traits and current distributions, recipient system characteristics, and multi-dimensional invasion driver characteristics, and (3) to develop a new, multi-scale invasion modeling framework based on functional traits for an invader, an invasion driver, and a recipient system and use the model to explore cross-scale interactions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The outcomes of the proposed project will position the research team to develop a new generation of accurate predictive models for regional scale invasion forecasting, which will assist researchers and natural resource managers to examine what-if scenarios in the short term (5-10 years) and long term (50-100 years). The new research framework should also be easily applied to invasive species study in other regions and on other continents. In addition, the conceptual framework can be used as a mechanism to advance the field of invasion ecology by formulating new invasion theories and unifying existing hypotheses. Results of the proposed research will also have direct societal benefits. Applications to invasion management will help prevent and mitigate economic and ecological damages caused by invasive species. The project will have high impact on education as well. Two postdoctoral fellows and two PhD Fellows will be supported to conduct related research, along with six undergraduate scholars and four interns. Emphasis in recruiting will be on underrepresented and female students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1241932</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Songlin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fei</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sfei@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pijanowski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bpijanow@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qinfeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qguo@fs.fed.us</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Oswalt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>coswalt@fs.fed.us</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7959</Code>
      <Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7959</Code>
      <Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
