<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Investigating Northern Peatland Methane Dynamics by Synthesizing Measurements, Remote Sensing and Modeling from Local to Regional to Continental Scales</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1647192</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy Kratz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Wetland ecosystems are the largest natural source of methane, a potent and long lasting greenhouse gas, to the atmosphere. Wetland soils in northern latitudes are warming faster than those in temperate and tropical regions. An understanding of the influence and feedback that these northern wetland ecosystems play in the present and future climate is needed. Accomplishing this may only be done through linking newly developed technologies that measure and quantify the processes of methane emissions on a local scale with modeling efforts that scale from local studies to the region and continent. This project will collect new measurements and leverage long-term existing data on methane emissions from five well-studied research sites that span four northern climate zones. In addition, the project will use environmental and climate variables developed from remote sensing data collected by several satellites over vast areas of the far north. Using a unique scaling approach, the emissions from northern wetlands will be determined so that a global analysis can be performed. This project will implement new measurement technologies and enable more accurate representation of methane emissions on a global scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the scientific impacts of this project, it will also provide professional development opportunities for both undergraduate students and postdoctoral researchers. These postdoctoral researchers will grow, not only as interdisciplinary scientists, but also as mentors and engaged community partners. Through a series of opportunities, the postdoctoral researchers will develop research, communication, leadership and mentoring skills. A partnership with the Northern Ecosystems Research for Undergraduates program (an NSF REU site) will enable the postdoctoral researchers to mentor two undergraduates in summer research experiences, under the guidance of the program director.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1241937</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bobby</FirstName>
      <LastName>Braswell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rbraswell@appliedgeosolutions.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ruth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Varner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ruth.varner@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Changsheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>changsheng.li@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Palace</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>palace@guero.sr.unh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Hampshire</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6038622172</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
      <StateCode>NH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7959</Code>
      <Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7959</Code>
      <Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5937</Code>
      <Text>SWEDEN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
