<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Project: Capacity Building in Mobile Security Through Curriculum and Faculty Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99164</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a Collaborative Project consisting of two awards: NSF Award No. 1241651 to the University of Tennessee at Chattanooga and NSF Award No. 1241670 to Tuskegee University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The security of mobile computing is vital to the growing army of mobile device users. Educational materials and curricula focusing on mobile security are still sparse. In this project, four universities--the University of Tennessee at Chattanooga, Tuskegee University, Southern Polytechnic State University, and the University of Cincinnati--are collaboratively building research and education capacity in mobile security through curriculum development, curriculum enhancement, faculty professional development, and partnership development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators are developing a course on mobile security, including teaching materials and hands-on labs and learning exercises; developing transferable modules that cover key topics in mobile security (secure coding, cryptography, security architecture, network security, web security, and security policy and management) and contain hands-on labs; integrating the modules into existing computer science and information assurance courses such as Operating Systems and Network Security; and hosting workshops to disseminate the curriculum materials to faculty at other institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through these efforts, the project aims to build and strengthen curricula, student learning, and faculty collaboration and partnerships. The modular nature of the developed materials will aid their wide dissemination and usage, and all of the materials can be adopted in multiple disciplines, such as computer science, software engineering, information technology, and business.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1241670</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wuf@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tuskegee University</Name>
      <CityName>Tuskegee Institute</CityName>
      <ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3347278233</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 W Montgomery Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
