<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pan American Advanced Studies Institute on Spatio-temporal Modeling; Buzios, Brazil, July 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jessica H. Robin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Pan-American Advanced Studies Institutes (PASI) award, jointly supported by the NSF and the Department of Energy (DOE), will take place in July 14-25, 2014 in Búzios, State of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Organized by Dr. Peter Guttorp, a professor of Statistics, Quantitative Ecology &amp; Resource Management, and Urban Design &amp; Planning at the , University of Washington in Seattle, Washington, the institute will focus on spatial and spatio-temporal models and their statistical analysis, with lectures in theory and applications as well as practical computing exercises. The content will be linked together with advanced applications in climatology, ecology and environmental health and provide a comprehensive software archive for these methods, most of which have not been publicly available. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This PASI will introduce participants to many important techniques, including state-of-the-art methods in modeling. The activity will also foster international collaboration among researchers from the US and the Americas. The educational content of the institute and its materials will be disseminated through an integrated web site, containing presentations, software, annotated bibliography and a variety of resource links. In addition, institute participants will receive guidance in producing white papers for publication.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1241991</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guttorp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peter@stat.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>KX14</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5913</Code>
      <Text>BRAZIL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5977</Code>
      <Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7728</Code>
      <Text>PASI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
