<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pan American Advanced Studies Institute on Polymer and Composite Materials from Renewable Resources and Biorefinery: from Chemistry to Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harold Stolberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Pan American Advanced Studies Institute (PASI) on Polymer and Composite Materials from Renewable Resources and Bio-refinery: From Chemistry to Applications &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Pan-American Advanced Studies Institutes (PASI) award, jointly supported by the NSF and the Department of Energy (DOE), will take place in late 2012 or early 2013 at Centro Nacional de Alta Tecnología (CeNAT) located in San Jose, Costa Rica. Organized by Dr. Maria Auad, associate professor in the Department of Polymer and Fiber Engineering at Auburn University, the institute will focus on the dissemination of advanced scientific and engineering knowledge in the areas of green polymers and composites based on natural resources and the development of strategies for promoting collaborative opportunities for research, training and exchange in the Americas. The PASI will bring together a team of scientists and engineers to collaborate and learn from a multitude of disciplines including chemistry, characterization and fabrication of new materials such as advanced green polymers and composites, and potential applications for such materials in structural, transport, medical and others industries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PASI will help to strengthen research environments between the participating institutions, establish new partnerships across the continent, and provide interdisciplinary training for the next generation of scientists. Participants, including graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, junior faculty, and researchers, will benefit from a dual mentorship experience. Additionally, the PASI will enhance understanding of the basic chemistry and properties of these complex materials, which may lead to the creation of a new generation of multifunctional, green materials from renewable resources. The results from the PASI will be disseminated through a website where all the lectures will be available for downloading.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1242213</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Auad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>auad@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Orlando</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rojas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>orlando_rojas@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Auburn University</Name>
      <CityName>Auburn University</CityName>
      <ZipCode>368490001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 Samford Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1385</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL STUDIES AND ANALYSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5904</Code>
      <Text>COSTA RICA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5977</Code>
      <Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7728</Code>
      <Text>PASI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
