<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Iterated Homogenization Method to Study Cavitation in Soft Solids</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/20/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>67974</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eugene Gartland</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lopez-Pamies&lt;br/&gt;DMS-1009503&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Experimental evidence has shown that loading conditions with&lt;br/&gt;sufficiently large triaxialities can induce the sudden appearance&lt;br/&gt;of internal cavities within elastomeric (and other soft) solids. &lt;br/&gt;The occurrence of such instabilities, commonly referred to as&lt;br/&gt;cavitation, can be attributed to the growth of pre-existing&lt;br/&gt;defects into finite sizes. Because of its close connection with&lt;br/&gt;material failure initiation, the phenomenon of cavitation has&lt;br/&gt;received much attention from the materials and mechanics&lt;br/&gt;communities. Cavitation has also been a subject of interest in&lt;br/&gt;the mathematical community because its modeling has prompted the&lt;br/&gt;development of techniques to deal with a broad class of&lt;br/&gt;non-convex variational problems. While in recent years&lt;br/&gt;considerable progress has been made via energy minimization&lt;br/&gt;methods to establish existence results, fundamental problems&lt;br/&gt;regarding the quantitative prediction of the occurrence of&lt;br/&gt;cavitation in real material systems remain largely unresolved. &lt;br/&gt;In this project, the principal investigator develops a novel&lt;br/&gt;framework to study cavitation that: (i) is applicable to large&lt;br/&gt;classes of nonlinear elastic solids of practical interest, (ii)&lt;br/&gt;allows for 3D general loading conditions with arbitrary&lt;br/&gt;triaxiality, (iii) incorporates direct information on the initial&lt;br/&gt;shape, spatial distribution, and mechanical properties of the&lt;br/&gt;underlying defects at which cavitation can initiate, and (iv) is,&lt;br/&gt;at the same time, computationally tractable. This is&lt;br/&gt;accomplished by means of an innovative iterated homogenization&lt;br/&gt;method that allows for the construction of exact solutions for&lt;br/&gt;the mechanical response of nonlinear elastic materials containing&lt;br/&gt;random distributions of initially infinitesimal cavities (or&lt;br/&gt;defects). These include solutions for the change in size of the&lt;br/&gt;underlying cavities as a function of the applied loading&lt;br/&gt;conditions, from which the onset of cavitation can be determined. &lt;br/&gt;In spite of its generality, the analysis of the proposed&lt;br/&gt;formulation reduces to the study of tractable Hamilton-Jacobi&lt;br/&gt;equations in which the initial size of the cavities plays the&lt;br/&gt;role of time and the applied load plays the role of space. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; This project makes available a fresh methodology radically&lt;br/&gt;different from existing approaches to investigate the influence&lt;br/&gt;of defects in solids. This is a core topic in mechanics, of&lt;br/&gt;great importance for understanding and predicting the failure of&lt;br/&gt;real-world materials. More generally, the project aims to&lt;br/&gt;develop analytical techniques that link the macroscopic&lt;br/&gt;properties of soft heterogeneous materials directly to their&lt;br/&gt;microscopic properties and underlying microstructures, a central&lt;br/&gt;issue in many fields of modern science. Beyond putting forward&lt;br/&gt;fundamental understanding of how microscopic behavior influences&lt;br/&gt;macroscopic behavior, these techniques provide engineers and&lt;br/&gt;scientists with mathematical tools to characterize and predict&lt;br/&gt;the mechanical response and failure of a broad spectrum of soft&lt;br/&gt;composite materials, including elastomeric composites (e.g.,&lt;br/&gt;filled elastomers) and biological tissues (e.g., arterial walls).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1242089</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oscar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lopez-Pamies</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pamies@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
