<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integrative Tools for Underground Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>741788</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James J. Whitmore</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Assay and Acquisition of Radiopure Materials (AARM) is a collaborative effort to improve the understanding of neutron backgrounds underground. This work aids physics experiments that probe fundamental questions such as the nature of neutrinos and the dark matter in the universe. AARM, which includes experts in low-background techniques and simulations of neutron interactions underground, as well as representatives from major dark matter and double beta decay experiments and from the geology and microbiology communities, has worked together over the last three years to better understand low radioactivity environments and exploit common resources. By organizing around common goals that would benefit from structured cooperation, AARM has succeeded in creating a forum for sharing information and advancing research goals, including new technologies for particle detection, simulation techniques, and material screening. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will continue AARM's role as a central unifying force in the international underground community with these specific goals: &lt;br/&gt;1. Development of community-wide simulation tools, &lt;br/&gt;2. Confirmation of simulation physics models and cross sections relevant to underground science by comparing to data worldwide and supporting specific efforts in neutron benchmarking, &lt;br/&gt;3. Establishment of a global materials database, and &lt;br/&gt;4. Continuation of the successful integration workshops centered around simulation, material screening, and underground physics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The proposed work will create cross collaboration infrastructure support for underground physics. It directly provides training of scientists in radiation-detection technologies and low-background techniques, which supplements the country's technical intelligence base, both inside and outside physics, providing students with multidisciplinary opportunities in astro, nuclear, and particle physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1242640</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Empl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Anton.Empl@mail.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Priscilla</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cushman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>prisca@physics.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dongming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mei</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dongming.mei@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schnee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>richard.schnee@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jodi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cooley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cooley@physics.smu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7282</Code>
      <Text>Midscale Physics Projects</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7694</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGROUND R&amp;D</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
