<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Tenth East Coast Operator Algebras Symposium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>26080</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding to help defray the expenses of participants in the Tenth East Coast Operator Algebras Symposium (ECOAS), to be held at the University of Tennessee in Knoxville, Tennessee, on October 6-7, 2012. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This will be the tenth annual meeting in the East Coast Operator Algebra Symposium series. The first meeting in the series was held at Vanderbilt University in Nashville, in the fall of 2003, and since then meetings have been held each Fall. The focus of the meetings is on operator algebras and noncommutative geometry, with applications to a wide range of areas from number theory to quantum physics. In addition to facilitating interaction between researchers in the field, the East Coast Operator Algebra Symposia are forums in which young researchers, graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in the Eastern region of the United States can acquaint themselves with current issues at the forefront of research, present their own work, and interact with senior mathematicians in the field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1243411</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Remus</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nicoara</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nicoara@math.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
