<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Essential Biology of Microbial Cooperation in H2 and CH4 Production</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susanne von Bodman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;Syntrophy among microbial partners involves the exchange of metabolites, making processes possible that cannot be accomplished by either organism alone. These mutually beneficial relationships are now known to make essential contributions to the global carbon cycle. However, while syntrophic metabolism is found in nearly all anaerobic environments in nature, little is understood about the molecular, biochemical, or physiological basis of this important ecological process. The Syntrophomonas wolfei-Methanospirillum hungatei co-culture is the historical model for thermodynamically-limited syntrophic associations because both organisms are syntroph specialists that operate near the thermodynamic equilibrium, and that evolved by niche-associated interactions. This project will delineate the metabolic and regulatory systems involved in syntrophic metabolism in a well-defined model system. Syntrophic consortia are also excellent model systems to probe the mechanisms by which multispecies microbial communities interact because much about the metabolites used and the roles of each syntrophic partner is understood. Therefore, this project will serve as a paradigm for study of metabolism and gene expression in other multispecies microbial communities in key ecological habitats. The research will open up the next levels of study to decipher basic principles of this poorly understood biological process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;This project will deepen understanding of the interesting phenomenon of syntrophy, of biological contributions to the global carbon cycle, and more broadly of the underlying molecular mechanisms at play in microbial communities. It will support training of graduate and undergraduate students in laboratory research involving anaerobic microbiology, microbial physiology, enzyme analysis, and analytical chemistry. The PIs will continue to be actively involved in developing undergraduate educational materials at their respective institutions. These include web-based materials that provide access for a wider audience. Existing programs are targeted for expansion to include institutions having significant underrepresented minority enrollments and students with disadvantaged backgrounds. In addition to educating, a goal is to promote interest in and enthusiasm for microbiology. Both PIs will also assist in judging local and/or national science fairs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1244566</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gunsalus</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robg@microbio.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8011</Code>
      <Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
