<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: Doctoral Colloquium at IEEE VisWeek 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19766</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ephraim P. Glinert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is funding to support a Doctoral Colloquium (workshop) of about 12 dissertation stage doctoral students, in a variety of visualization subfields, for a day of discussions and interactions with 6 distinguished research faculty, to be held in conjunction with this year's IEEE VisWeek meeting, which will take place during the week of October 14-19, 2012, in Seattle. Visualization, or the use of interactive graphics to support data analysis and understanding, has become an integral part and critical component of many application areas. IEEE VisWeek is the premier forum for visualization advances in science and engineering for academia, government, and industry, now bringing together about 900 researchers and practitioners from around the world with a shared interest in techniques, tools, and technology. VisWeek consists this year of the 23rd annual IEEE Scientific Visualization Conference (SciVis), the 18th annual IEEE Information Visualization Conference (InfoVis), and the 7th annual IEEE Visual Analytics Science and Technology Symposium (VAST). Co-located symposia this year include the IEEE Symposium on Large-Scale Data Analysis and Visualization (LDAV), the IEEE Symposium on Biological Data Visualization (BioVis), and the International Symposium on Visualization for Cyber Security (VisSec). The papers published in the special conference issue of IEEE Transactions of Visualization and Computer Graphics are rigorously refereed and widely cited. More information is available online at http://www.visweek.org. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Doctoral Colloquium at IEEE VisWeek is a research-focused meeting which has taken place annually at the Visualization conference since 2006, and has helped launch the careers of a number of outstanding young researchers. In 2012 the workshop will convene on Sunday, October 14 or on Monday, October 15, with follow-up events during the VisWeek technical program. A primary goal of the Doctoral Colloquium is to allow students to discuss their research directions in a supportive atmosphere with a panel of distinguished leaders and with their peers, who will provide helpful feedback and fresh perspectives. The workshop supports community building, by connecting beginning and advanced researchers, one of the objectives being to build a cohort group of new researchers who will then have a network of colleagues across the world. Student research will be disseminated via posters during the VisWeek technical program, and via publication in the VisWeek Extended Abstracts. Feedback about the Doctoral Colloquium will be provided to future conference committees. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The VisWeek Doctoral Colloquium brings together the best of the next generation of visualization researchers and allows them to create a social network both among themselves and with senior researchers, which plays a major role in their enculturation into the profession. Since the students and faculty are a diverse group on several dimensions (nationality, scientific discipline, research specialization), the students' horizons are broadened at a critical stage in their professional development. The PI has affirmed that in managing this event the organizers, while trying to identify and include the broadest possible group of highly qualified participants, will also make an effort to encourage participation by women, racial/ethnic minorities, and persons with disabilities. They will furthermore ensure that NSF funds are used chiefly to support participation by students enrolled in graduate programs in the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1244831</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leland</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilkinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leland.wilkinson@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Niklas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elmqvist</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>elm@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Healey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>healey@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
