<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CC-NIE Network Infrastructure: Implementation of a Science DMZ at San Diego State University to Facilitate High-Performance Data Transfer for Scientific Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>498597</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The CC-NIE Network Infrastructure project at San Diego State University&lt;br/&gt;(SDSU) is constructing and deploying a Science DMZ to support data&lt;br/&gt;intensive science and accommodate specific end-to-end dataflow scenarios&lt;br/&gt;between SDSU and other universities and national laboratories. The&lt;br/&gt;design of the Science DMZ follows the vision and architecture laid out&lt;br/&gt;by the Energy Sciences Network (ESnet). Cisco Nexus 7000 and 2000&lt;br/&gt;series switches are deployed, along with a 10Gbps connection to the&lt;br/&gt;CalREN-HP network with exclusive use by the Science DMZ. Researchers at&lt;br/&gt;SDSU are hosting delay-sensitive applications and datasets on Lustre&lt;br/&gt;parallel file systems directly attached to the Nexus switches. These&lt;br/&gt;applications and datasets support research projects in the numerical&lt;br/&gt;simulation of earthquake rupture and wave propagation, coastal ocean&lt;br/&gt;modeling, pulse detonation engines, vortex rings in Bose-Einstein&lt;br/&gt;condensates, and large-scale data for proteomics, gene promoter&lt;br/&gt;bioinformatics, and microbial metagenomics. The project will directly&lt;br/&gt;impact the faculty and students who encompass the Computational Science&lt;br/&gt;Research Center which draws participation from all science and&lt;br/&gt;engineering departments at SDSU. The Science DMZ provides researchers&lt;br/&gt;with the capability to rapidly exchange large datasets and deploy&lt;br/&gt;Web-based science applications that are accessible through a dedicated&lt;br/&gt;network that is separate from, and therefore not impacted by, general&lt;br/&gt;Internet traffic generated by the campus population. The DMZ will&lt;br/&gt;promote remote usage of computing resources at SDSU, cultivate&lt;br/&gt;development of collaborative tools for sharing data with the broader&lt;br/&gt;scientific community, establish new research partnerships, and foster&lt;br/&gt;new mentorship opportunities between faculty and students engaged in&lt;br/&gt;computational science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1245312</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Castillo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jcastillo@sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rich</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pickett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rich.pickett@sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paolini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paolini@engineering.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
