<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Printed Photonic Crystal-Based Tandem Polymer Solar Cell</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>110000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Currently, a major issue limiting the solar energy conversion efficiency of polymer solar cells (PSC) is the inefficiency in harvesting the entire solar spectrum. This is mainly due to two reasons: incomplete light absorption and small bandgap of the active polymer materials used. The objective of this proposal is to address these issues by developing a PSC capable of efficiently harvesting solar energy over a wide spectral range by employing (1) light trapping printed photonic crystal architecture, and (2) plasmonic field assisted energy upconversion. Accomplishing light trapping and upconversion simultaneously in a tandem PSC will be a transformative approach. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The proposed research is the first example of combining photonic crystal and plasmon assisted light upconverting structures in a tandem PSC. The device developed will be capable of harvesting a broad solar absorption spectrum. A systematic study on the dependence of photonic crystal architecture and the energy conversion efficiency will be performed based on modeling. The success of the proposed printing technology will open up new avenues for developing plasmon assisted upconverting tandem PSC.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The subject of this proposal involves nanotechnology, optics and material science and therefore the graduate students involved in this research will be exposed to cutting edge research projects in the state-of-the-art laboratories. PI desires to integrate the subject of the proposal into the graduate curriculum currently offered in The College of Optics and Photonics at the University of Central Florida. This will be beneficial to develop a workforce in the energy conversion realm.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1247838</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jayan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thomas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jayan.Thomas@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>101E</Code>
      <Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7423</Code>
      <Text>Energy collection &amp; storage</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
