<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RCN-UBE - GCAT-SEEK: The Genome Consortium for Active Undergraduate Research and Teaching Using Next-Generation Sequencing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>445039</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher Meyer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The focus of this RCN-UBE project is to support and expand participation in the newly formed Genome Consortium for Active Teaching using Next-generation Sequencing (GCAT-SEEK). Genomics and bioinformatics are dynamic fields well-suited for capturing the imagination of undergraduates in both research laboratories and classrooms. However, high costs, demanding technical skills, and high rates of change inhibit integration of next-generation sequencing approaches into the undergraduate curriculum. GCAT-SEEK aims to generate and use massively parallel sequencing data associated with the research interests of network members as the catalyst for producing innovative and broadly disseminated educational modules that offer authentic research experiences to students. The goals of this project are to increase network participation, produce and disseminate educational modules that are assessed for student learning gains, foster a sense of community among network faculty and students, and support network communications. Hands-on faculty/student workshops centered on participant research projects are the key implementation strategy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Anticipated outcomes include improved faculty expertise, increased authentic student research experiences for undergraduates, and production of innovative, effective educational modules that improve student preparation for graduate, technical and research careers. We anticipate impacting thousands of students via this project. Workshops will be moved around the country to include three minority serving host institutions to bolster participation by groups under-represented in STEM disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts towards support of Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1248096</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Trun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>trun@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vincent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buonaccorsi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>buonaccorsi@juniata.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tammy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tobin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tobinjan@susqu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Newman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>newman@lycoming.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grove</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dsg4@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Juniata College</Name>
      <CityName>Huntingdon</CityName>
      <ZipCode>166522119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8146413000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Moore Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7513</Code>
      <Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7972</Code>
      <Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1664</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
