<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Tissue Engineered Sustainable Leather</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149994</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will investigate the application of a novel tissue engineering approach to the fabrication of animal products, in particular leather. The approach relies on the automated deposition of conveniently prepared multicellular units into a three dimensional arrangement. Biological structure formation takes place post deposition of the discrete units through the mobilization of shape-forming, morphogenetic processes akin to those in embryonic development, such as tissue fusion and cell sorting. A distinguishing feature of the technology is that it is fully biological; it uses only cells and cell-secreted substances. It has successfully been used for applications in regenerative medicine. This project takes the technology beyond regenerative medicine to produce animal products in an environmentally sustainable, resource-conscious and ethically acceptable way without slaughtering animals. The end product of this proof of concept Phase I project will be an engineered leather sample of about 10 cm by 10 cm and 0.5-1 mm thickness. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project has far-reaching implications for the public and society broadly. It represents a fundamental innovation in agriculturally-related manufacturing. The approach is a safe, economical, environmentally conscious and ethically acceptable alternative to present industrial leather production practices. It does not require the slaughtering of animals or their unethical treatment, as it uses cells harvested via biopsy. It enables reduction in livestock raised specifically for leather or meat (leather being a byproduct) and consequently in demand for resources. As the technology eliminates a number of leather production steps (e.g. de-hairing, de-fleshing, splitting, curing, bating), it also eliminates many of the most toxic stages thereby reducing environmental pollution. Since it allows for better control of composition and shape, it enables dramatic reduction in waste. Production can be largely local with all phases under the same roof, leading to savings in transportation, fuel, etc. The commercial applications of the proposed technology are broad with leather being an initial product and with other materials to follow. Given the unprecedented control over every processing step, the final products can be optimized in an application-dependent way.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1248497</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karoly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jakab</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kjakab@modernmeadow.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Modern Meadow, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Columbia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5737380080</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1601 S Providence Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
