<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC) 2013. To Be Held in Budapest, Hungary, June 9-13,2013.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15570</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhi Tian</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 2013 IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC) will be held in Budapest, Hungary from June 9 to June 13, 2013. This preeminent technical conference is the flagship conference of the IEEE Communications Society, and the primary venue for presenting new research results in the area of communications. It is widely attended by researchers and practitioners in the field. Attending conferences such as ICC is of paramount importance for the development of graduate students. Participants have the opportunity to present their work, attend panel and keynote sessions, and interact with hundreds of others performing leading-edge research in the field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This proposal provides travel support for approximately fifteen graduate students in the United States to attend this premiere conference, which will be held for the first time to Eastern Europe in 2013. The travel awards will target graduate students, in particular, women and under-represented minority students, since attending conferences is an important part of their educational experience, and they often have limited travel funds. The research community and the Engineering workforce benefit from the improvement of students in the pipeline, and the introduction of new researcher perspectives.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1250316</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tommaso</FirstName>
      <LastName>Melodia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>t.melodia@northeastern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
      <CityName>Amherst</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
