<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multidomain and Integrative Capabilities for Large-Scale Systems Simulations with High-Order Methods</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>264720</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this grant is to develop new algorithms for scientific computations that involve integration of multiple computational modules and are accurate, efficient, robust, and scalable on thousands of processors. Integration of multiple computational modules within a single framework becomes increasingly important with the rise in complexity of modern computations that tend to involve large-scale and/or multi-scale systems. This project will concentrate on developing multi-domain capabilities within the high-order spectral-element fluid dynamics and heat transfer solver and ensuring high-order global accuracy and stability of the coupled algorithm. The multi-domain capabilities will include overlapping and moving grid systems and can be applied to many important problems of multi-scale and multi-physics nature. The algorithmic and computational developments will be systematically validated versus known analytical solutions and existing experimental data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this effort will produce an accurate and scalable computational tool equipped with integrative capabilities to enable scientific computing in the 21st century, available as open source software under a public license. The new tool will allow for efficient computational analysis of important problems of multidisciplinary nature. One such problem is the performance of rotating wind turbines subject to complex atmospheric inflow, which can be more accurately predicted and optimized with the availability of the developed methods. Modern computing advances and capabilities as well as their importance in solving realistic engineering problems will be a central theme for multiple outreach and educational activities, including participation of women in science trough Girls in Engineering Program at ASU, working with K-12 students and teachers in the Kyrene School District in Tempe, and organizing on-campus visits of national lab collaborators to expose students to the most recent advances in the field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1250124</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yulia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peet</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ypeet@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8084</Code>
      <Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8021</Code>
      <Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
