<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAR-PF: Integrating Field Deposit, Remote Sensing, and Numerical Modeling Perspectives on the Injection and Fallout of Hazardous Volcanic Ash</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Alexa Van Eaton has been awarded an NSF Earth Sciences Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a research and education plan at the U.S. Geological Survey and Arizona State University. This project aims to improve our ability to predict and respond to the hazards of explosive volcanic eruptions. Dispersal of fine volcanic particles injected into the atmosphere during these events pose wide-reaching threats to infrastructure and the environment. Given the strong national and international reliance on numerical predictions of volcanic cloud movement, this project focuses on introducing new, field-based observations of eruption dynamics into existing methods of ash dispersal modeling. Two key questions motivate this approach: (1) how does the nature of particle aggregation evolve with respect to measurable properties of volcanic clouds?; and (2) what is the role of eruption column instability and surface water interaction in controlling the vertical distribution of mass in the atmosphere? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The initial stage of the project targets assimilation of field data from volcaniclastic deposits and remote sensing archives from the well-documented eruptions of Redoubt, Alaska (2009) and Mount St. Helens, Washington (18 May 1980). These observations will be used to characterize the spatiotemporal impact of atmospheric feedbacks accompanying volcanic ash dispersal, and provide inputs for 3d simulations of eruption column development using a cutting-edge microphysical model known as ATHAM. Results will guide the design and deployment of a new generation ash dispersal model that can account for the impacts of ash aggregation and column instability in a fast-running, operational setting. In addition, Dr. Van Eaton will partner with the Cascades Volcano Observatory (USGS, Vancouver) and School of Earth and Space Exploration (Arizona State University) to develop tabletop exercises educating undergraduate students, K-12 geoscience teachers and TV broadcasters about responding to volcanic ash hazards in the event of an eruption.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1250029</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van Eaton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Van_Eaton Alexa R</Name>
      <CityName>Wellington</CityName>
      <ZipCode/>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>New Zealand</CountryName>
      <StateName/>
      <StateCode/>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1573</Code>
      <Text>PETROLOGY AND GEOCHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1575</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
