<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Impacts of Tropical Storm Debby in Apalachee Bay</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49971</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Candace O. Major</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Tropical Storm Debby (June 24-26, 2012) was a 1 in 15 year event for Bald Point, a coastal barrier in Apalachee Bay, FL. With as much as 1.8 m of surge and 0.5 m of rainfall during the storm, significant impacts on the landscape due to flooding and overwash are likely. This Rapid Response project will characterize the geomorphic and sedimentological signature of TS Debby at Bald Point, leveraging substantial work already conducted in this area by the principal investigator, a scientist at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution. LiDAR collected before the storm will be compared to post-storm total station surveys to quantify net erosion/accretion. Sediment samples from washover surfaces and shallow, backbarrier cores will be collected for textural and microfossil analyses. This work will help to calibrate and verify previously generated records of tropical storm frequency based on Bald Point's backbarrier stratigraphy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will lead to a better understanding of the impacts and historical frequency of severe storms in the northeastern Gulf Coast region. A post-doctoral researcher and an undergraduate student from WHOI's REU program will be supported. Results of the project will be communicated to coastal management groups and the general public. Data will be made broadly available through the WHOI Coastal Systems Group website.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1250506</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Donnelly</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdonnelly@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
