<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: A GENERALIZED APPROACH TO THE CHARACTERIZATION OF NATIVE RNA WITHIN THE CELLULAR MILIEU-AN INTEGRATED EDUCATION AND RESEARCH STUDY</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>316922</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1253691 - Santangelo&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall focus of the research and education components of this work is on the integration of cell biology and molecular engineering. Within the research component, integration of these disciplines will be utilized in the development of a generalized approach for the sensing and characterization of RNA molecules in the cellular milieu, based on previously published single RNA sensitive imaging probes. This approach will then be applied to the study of megakaryocytes, which recently were discovered to sort RNAs to sites of platelet formation. In the education portion of this proposal, the goal is to create education modules, utilizing active learning experiences, at both the undergraduate and secondary school level, that facilitate the ability of students to integrate engineering principles and biology, and new assessment strategies will be employed in order to gauge their utility. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is targeted to have broad impact at both the scientific level and within society. From a scientific perspective, given the role of RNA in almost every biological problem, new tools that allow for its thorough characterization will impact the science of many researchers. On a societal level, by improving the ability of students to integrate engineering approaches with cellular biology, we?ll be able to improve their general ability to think critically and solve problems using all the tools they have been exposed to during their education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1253691</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Santangelo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>philip.santangelo@bme.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>142E</Code>
      <Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
