<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Additive Manufacture of Copper Cellular Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven R. Schmid</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The primary research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) project is to test the hypothesis that copper cellular materials can be realized via three-dimensional printing (3DP) of copper oxide powders followed by a reduction/sintering post-process to convert it to metallic copper. The secondary research objective is to test the hypothesis that jetted nanosuspension binder (i) will fill interstitial voids in the part bed, thus increasing part density and (ii) will effectively bond neighboring powder particles during sintering to provide continuous bonding strength, thus enhancing final part properties. The primary educational goal of this program is to prepare a new generation of engineers for the design and fabrication of complex systems via additive manufacturing (AM). This will be achieved by providing learning experiences with AM technologies across a broad educational spectrum, including (i) an undergraduate/graduate AM course, (ii) a "3D Printing Vending Machine" that provides students open access to AM, and (iii) AM summer workshops for K-12 STEM teachers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will result in a manufacturing process capable of fabricating copper cellular materials and an understanding of how 3DP of nanosuspension binders affect the process and its resultant parts. Components resulting from the proposed manufacturing process could be useful for thermal management of many mechanical and electrical products. An understanding of how nanosuspension binder affects 3DP will provide a basis for addressing material constraints of this, and other, AM processes. This program's integrated manufacturing and engineering education research activities will result in inquiry-based learning interventions targeted at educating future engineers in designing systems with AM. A combination of qualitative and quantitative engineering education research methods will provide an understanding of how the proposed interventions affect teacher/student perceptions of manufacturing. The proposed summer workshop will provide 15 teachers with 3D printers as well as AM instructional modules for their classrooms, which will be shared on a dedicated Wiki website. Changes in teacher and student perceptions of engineering and manufacturing will be explored via the High School High School Students' Attitude to Mathematics, Science and Engineering Survey and the Deloitte and the Manufacturing Institute's Manufacturing Attitude Survey. The design of the "3D Printing Vending Machine" will be openly shared for other universities and public spaces (e.g., museums, libraries, etc.) to leverage. Assessment, in the form of in-line usage statistics and surveys, semi-structured interviews, and the Engineering Design Self Efficacy Instrument will provide opportunity to explore how students engage in technology-infused informal learning settings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1254287</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbwill@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING &amp; CONST MACH EQP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
