<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Monodisperse Metal Alloy Nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>650000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Amala Dass from the University of Mississippi is supported in a CAREER award jointly funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry (MSN) program of the Division of Chemistry and the Office of the Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR). Professor Dass and his students study gold-metal (Cu, Ag, Pd) alloy nanomolecules, which are ultra-small gold alloy nanoparticles (&lt; 3 nm, &lt; 500 atoms) of molecular definition with specific numbers of metal atoms and protecting ligands. Their chemical and physical properties are unique and different than in bulk materials due to quantum-size effects. Alloy Nanomolecules of the following composition: Au38 Metal38-x (SR)24, Au144 Metal144-x (SR)60 and Au324 Metal324-x (SR)92 will be synthesized using wet co-reduction methods. The compositional assignment will be performed using matrix assisted laser desorption ionization (MALDI) and electrospray ionization (ESI) mass spectrometry. The nanoalloys will be further characterized using optical spectroscopy, electrochemistry and X-ray diffraction methods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will facilitate the understanding of these alloys in this size regime where quantum effects play important roles. These have potential applications in catalysis, plasmonics, solar cells and medical diagnostics. As part of this CAREER educational program, Professor Dass and his students will develop a K-12 outreach program to North Panola high schools and involve high school and undergraduate students in the proposed research. These programs will encourage the participation of younger and under-represented students in science careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1255519</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amala</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dass</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amal@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Mississippi</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>386771848</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6629157482</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 BARR HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1948</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7234</Code>
      <Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
