<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: GENETICS OF LIFE CYCLE EVOLUTION AND THE EFFECTS ON TEMPORAL ISOLATION AND GENE FLOW</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>347578</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George W. Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The long-term goal of the research is to understand the process of speciation, in which one species splits into two, often through the evolution of multiple forms of reproductive isolation. The project focuses on reproductive isolation that occurs because of differences in the timing of major life cycle events, a widespread and potentially major impetus for speciation when differences in time of reproduction restrict gene flow. In a multi-pronged approach that applies high-throughput DNA sequencing, genetic mapping, population genomic analysis, metabolic profiling and field experiments the research will examine the genetic basis of life cycle variation and temporal reproductive isolation in the European corn borer moth (Ostrinia nubilalis), and evaluate the consequence of these differences in preventing gene flow between populations in nature. These experiments will provide a rare glimpse into the role of temporal isolation in origin of new species. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although a superb model for speciation, the European corn borer is also a major pest of corn and other crops, costing the United States ~$1B each year. By leveraging the moth as an organism of both scientific and economic interest, the research builds community partnerships to simultaneously promote basic scientific discovery, public understanding of the relevance of evolution in daily life, and sustainable agriculture.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1256688</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Searle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbs295@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harrison</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rgh4@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/05/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/03/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
