<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Future Internet Architecture Investigator Meeting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports a Future Internet Architecture (FIA) principal investigator meeting in October 2012. The goal of this meeting is to allow a technical assessment and critique of the projects. The meeting is organized to give each of the projects feedback on their designs, and to inform each of the projects about the work being done by the others. Periodic investigator meetings are critical to overall success of the FIA program and the goal of the FIA program is not just the funding of distinct architecture projects, but also the generation and sharing of design insights and architectural concepts among the various teams.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The feedback and assessment of each project is intended to allow each project to improve its technical approach, and to build upon the work of other projects as appropriate. As such, the technical merit of this proposal is the enhancement of the work being done as part of the NSF-funded FIA projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader goal of the NSF FIA program is enhancing the relevance and impact of the NSF program of network research, intellectual enrichment of the network research community, and the contribution of new concepts and thought leadership to the future of the Internet. The results of this workshop, which will be posted on the FIA website for public dissemination, will be a contribution to this broader goal.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1258691</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddc@csail.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
