<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: Polyploidy in Phlox and its effects on diversity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>352250</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A team of three scientists from Kansas State University, Michigan State University and the Desert Botanical Garden will investigate polyploidy (the condition of having more than one set of chromosomes) and diversity in the plant genus Phlox (Polemoniaceae). The Phlox species P. amabilis, P. nana and P. woodhousei all exhibit variation in ploidy level and occur as diploid (two sets of chromosomes, 2X), tetraploid (4X) and hexaploid (6X) populations in the southwestern United States. Geographic patterns of ploidy level variation will be documented for these groups using flow cytometry and chromosome count data. By combining phylogenetic, population genetic, morphological, and ecological analyses the researchers will infer relationships among populations, reconstruct their origins, estimate patterns of gene flow, investigate the effect of polyploidy on phenotypes, and identify whether particular ploidy types are more commonly associated with different ecological niches. Data from these approaches will also be used to revise the taxonomy of the group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While polyploidy is considered to play an important role in plant evolution, our current knowledge of ploidy level variation relative to diversity is limited. This project investigates questions of general interest on polyploidy and diversity and integrates findings to advance a broader understanding of the role of polyploidy in the diversification of plants. Educational modules relating incorporating this research will be developed for public school and botanical garden audiences, and participants from the undergraduate to postdoctoral level will benefit from training and collaboration.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1258167</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ferguson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ferg@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kansas State University</Name>
      <CityName>MANHATTAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>665061103</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7855326804</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2 FAIRCHILD HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
