<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Javelina Engineers STEM Scholarships: Building the Pathway for Baccalaureate to Masters Degrees</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>609025</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Lee</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Javelina Engineers STEM Scholarship (JESS) program provides scholarships to academically talented and financially needy students to complete baccalaureate and master's degrees in engineering, computer science, or industrial management and technology at Texas A&amp;M University-Kingsville (TAMUK), a Hispanic-Serving Institution. The JESS program objectives are to: recruit at least 20 academically promising students with diverse socio-economic backgrounds and high levels of financial need, with an emphasis on recruiting students from underrepresented groups; retain 80% of these students through completion of a baccalaureate degree and 40% through enrollment into a master's program; and integrate student support infrastructure across the TAMUK campus to improve access to services for all engineering students. Additionally, JESS partners with Del Mar College, an HSI community college in the same service region, to recruit and retain high-quality community college transfer students to TAMUK College of Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The JESS program provides comprehensive support for both bachelor's and master's degrees. Student support services include tutoring, social activities, one-on-one advising from JESS project team members, undergraduate research and/or internship placement, and a lecture series to promote graduate school preparation and awareness. Scholarships are awarded to Javelina Scholars early in their undergraduate careers with the expectation that they pursue a master's program immediately following attainment of the baccalaureate degree. At least 20 scholarships are provided annually for students studying architectural, chemical, civil, electrical, environmental, or mechanical engineering; industrial management and technology; or computer science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1259029</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rajab</FirstName>
      <LastName>Challoo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>r-challoo@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Selahattin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ozcelik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sozcelik@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Breanna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bailey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>breanna.bailey@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Farzin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heidari</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>farzin.heidari@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dolores</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guerrero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kfdg000@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M University-Kingsville</Name>
      <CityName>Kingsville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>783638202</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3615933344</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Campus Box 201</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
