<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Biology Scholars: Literature, Laboratory, and Leadership Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>606528</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The overall goal of the program is to increase biology graduation rates in selected rural communities by providing scholarships and support to academically talented biology students with limited financial means. The project supports 18 total students, six students in each of three cohorts with funding for up to four years per student. From 2003-2007, freshmen biology majors from the selected rural communities graduated in lower rates in biology (39.1%) compared to freshman biology majors from all counties (45.5% graduation rate). These academically talented students are being retained and becoming graduates of the Saint Vincent biology program through two objectives: 1) increasing (or maintaining) their enthusiasm for the field of biology and 2) strengthening their biology foundation. The program is focussing on three general activities: engagement in the biological literature through Journal Clubs; research through Sophomore Laboratory Rotations; and leadership experiences including mentoring underclassmen, presenting at conferences, and participation in academic, social, and community service activities. The program is providing the skills and resources necessary for Scholars to properly attain employment or graduate school acceptance depending on the individual desires and abilities of the Scholar. Preliminary and final reports are being presented at Biology and STEM conferences and are being written for publication. A recruitment presentation is also being made. An S-STEM Scholars website includes an overview of the program, application materials, updates on the Scholars, and preliminary data to increase dissemination of the program and results. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Within the last several years, there has been a movement to increase student engagement and become more student-centered in the classroom to increase student retention in Biology and other STEM fields (Seymour and Hewitt, 2000; Vision and Change, 2009; A New Biology, 2009). The activities the Saint Vincent S-STEM Scholars participate in are increasing critical thinking, reasoning skills, communication and collaboration, and are exposing the students to external research and biological careers, and leadership opportunities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This successful program allows continual engagement of academically talented students from rural communities. In addition, the overall graduation rate with students from these areas has been low so the success of this program is encouraging expansion to other majors to increase graduation rates. There are many college students from similar rural counties throughout the United States that will benefit from the extra engagement the Saint Vincent program is demonstrating leads to student success in biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1259904</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jodis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stephen.jodis@email.stvincent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koehl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jennifer.koehl@email.stvincent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Albert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gahr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>albert.gahr@email.stvincent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kellam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james.kellam@email.stvincent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Saint Vincent College</Name>
      <CityName>Latrobe</CityName>
      <ZipCode>156502690</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7248052271</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 Fraser Purchase Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
