<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Michigan STEM Academy Scholars</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>621708</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Lee</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of Michigan is developing an integrated, holistic curricular and co-curricular support system for students with high ability and potential in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) but who for reasons associated with socioeconomic class, first generation college status, race, gender, or rigor of high school background might not experience their full potential for success at a highly competitive research university. The University of Michigan STEM (M-STEM) Academy provides transitional academic and social support for a selected cohort of approximately 50-60 students during their first and second years in the College of Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The M-STEM Academy is grounded in well-documented success strategies, developed by the Meyerhoff Scholars Program at the University of Maryland Baltimore-County, for the retention and academic success of diverse students. It expands upon the Meyerhoff model by transferring the components to a large university setting and working with students who, although-well qualified, have often struggled and not reached their full potential in this environment. It partners closely with other University of Michigan STEM education pipeline efforts such as the Center for Engineering Diversity and Outreach, the Michigan Louis Strokes Alliance for Minority Participation (MI-LSAMP) Program, and the Michigan Alliances for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (MI-AGEP) Program to provide a seamless continuum of STEM education and support services from grade school to graduate school and the workplace. The M-STEM Academy is fully supported by the University Central and College administrations in a continual effort to increase the number and success of STEM students, with an emphasis on diverse students. The assessment of the Academy by faculty in the Center for the Study of Higher and Post-Secondary Education provides continual feedback for needed modifications to the program as it is implemented.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1259395</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Holloway</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james.paul.holloway@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>03/05/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cinda-Sue</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>csdavis@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
