<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Enhancing Academic Achievement and Career Preparation for Scholars in Computer Science, Mathematics, and Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>627010</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ron Buckmire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The five-year S-STEM program at Shepherd University provides support for 30 students majoring in Computer Sciences, Mathematics and Engineering (CME) and has four objectives: (1) increase enrollment of first-year and transfer students in CME, (2) increase retention of S-STEM scholars, (3) increase the four-year graduation rate of S-STEM scholars, and (4) increase the proportion of graduating S-STEM scholars who continue graduate studies or find employment in their field within six months of graduation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The program provides financial, academic, social, and career support to a diverse cohort of students, particularly first generation (a large percentage of the student body), female, and transfer students, and assesses the effect of these supports on their retention and graduation rates. Student learning, engagement, and career preparation are enhanced through tutoring, faculty and peer mentoring, learning communities, CME student clubs, close interaction with industry and government agencies, and research, internship, and networking opportunities. The focus on first generation, transfer, and female students--the latter highly underrepresented in CME fields--demonstrates which recruitment and support activities are most effective at encouraging these populations to continue to baccalaureate-level studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The program strengthens and applies student support systems to the educational success of a diverse community of CME scholars. In particular, it eliminates barriers and seeks to improve retention of first generation, transfer, and female students in STEM fields. Entering students from small towns and rural areas and transfer students from community colleges are supported and encouraged to complete their education at least to the baccalaureate level. The program strengthens student education, undergraduate research, and career counseling infrastructure; enhances Shepherd's regional alliance with business, industry, and government agencies; and improves connections with local high schools and community colleges.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1259713</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qwang@shepherd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhijun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zwang@shepherd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Shepherd College</Name>
      <CityName>Shepherdstown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>254435000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3048765358</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 5000</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
