<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Cascade Topology Seminar</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29212</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Cascade Topology Seminar will hold its 49th meeting the weekend of December 1-2, 2012 in Eugene, Oregon within the University of Oregon's Fenton Hall. The basic goals of the Cascade Topology Seminar are to provide for frequent contacts between workers in similar fields, to facilitate local mathematician's keep abreast of recent developments in Topology, Geometry and related fields by bringing in speakers from outside the region, to enable graduate students and early career topologists in the Pacific Northwest and Southwestern Canada to hear, consult, and possibly collaborate with the outside speakers and members of other institutions, and to provide an opportunity for local people to lecture on their own work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the CTS is designed in part to keep its participants abreast of recent developments in their own and related fields, no attempt is made to limit the topics covered in the lectures. However, the interests of the various organizers tend to be mirrored by the interests of the speakers, thus, the lectures usually concern algebraic, geometric, or low dimensional topology, differential or algebraic geometry, or combinatorial group theory. The Seminar also coordinates its activities with the Pacific Northwest Geometry Seminar and the Western States Geometric Topology Workshop with whom joint meetings have occasionally been held.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;General information on the Cascade Topology Seminar can be found at http://www.pdx.edu/math/cascade-topology-seminar&lt;br/&gt;Specific information on the Dec1-2, 2012 meeting can be found at http://pages.uoregon.edu/sadofsky/cascade12f.html</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1260906</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bleiler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bleilers@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Portland State University</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
