<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Upgrade of the Earth &amp; Environmental Science Electron Microprobe Laboratory at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>54558</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is to upgrade the Earth &amp; Environmental Science's Electron Microprobe Laboratory (EMPL) housing a Cameca SX-100 Electron Probe Microanalyzer at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI). The upgrade involves the installation of a new computer workstation running Probe for EPMA and Probe Image interfaced with the instrument. This upgrade was justified on the basis of three main criteria: First, examples were provided of major limitations imposed by the current vendor-supplied software package (Cameca's Peak Sight) that may be overcome using software available from Probe Software, Inc including (1) new algorithms to improve minimum detection limits, precision, and accuracy; (2) superior time-dependent intensity corrections; and (3) improved X-ray mapping capabilities. Second, a description was presented of ongoing and future projects that have compelling scientific merit and require characterization using a state-of-the-art electron microprobe. Third, this facility has had an excellent track record of high quality science with current instrumentation, a successful and sustainable maintenance and administration plan, numerous collaborative research efforts, and a highly diverse user base. An upgraded Electron Microprobe Laboratory at RPI will benefit both the larger Rensselaer Community and the broader Upstate New York/New England Region by enhancing current capabilities as a regional facility. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The EMPL has been and will continue to be open to the public along with undergraduates, graduate students, post-docs, research faculty, and professors at Rensselaer and elsewhere. In addition to providing analyses free of charge to undergraduates completing various projects, this facility participates annually in the ExxonMobil Bernard Harris Summer Science Camp, a free two-week program for fifty middle school students (grades 6-8) from the New York Capital Region designed to instill a life-long interest in math and science. This upgrade will greatly enhance the learning experiences of students, visitors, and new users alike thanks to the fully-integrated, user-friendly nature of Probe for EPMA which visually emphasizes important considerations (background models, time-dependent intensity corrections, wave scans, etc.).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1262252</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spear</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spearf@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruscitto</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ruscid2@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/28/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
