<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Chemistry of Materials for Renewable Energy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>277335</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry at the National Science Foundation supports a Research Experiences for Undergraduate (REU) Site led by Professors Andrew Greenberg and Robert Hamers, both at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. The REU Site entitled "Chemistry of Materials for Renewable Energy" (CMRE REU) will fund 11 to 12 undergraduate students for a 10 week summer research experiences. Students will conduct individual research projects focused on chemical research applied to problems in renewable energy. The CMRE REU program will help students to strengthen their written and oral communication skills through proposal presentations, mid-experience report writing, and poster presentations. A novel aspect of the CMRE REU program is the encouragement of students to participate in an outreach experience with the Institute for Chemical Education's (ICE) "Fun with Chemistry Camp" to teach 5th-8th students about solar energy. To ensure proper mentoring and development of CMRE REU students, this project includes a mentoring workshop for graduate students, post-doctoral fellows, and faculty working directly with the REU Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of the award involves young scientists who will be exposed to modern research methods and tools as part of their training. This REU site aims to provide cutting-edge research training in the chemical sciences to these students who might not otherwise have this opportunity. The research projects in chemistry will have an impact in the areas of energy and sustainability. The diverse student cohort participating in research at this site will be well-prepared for graduate school, and eventual employment as part of the country's technical workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1262750</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hamers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjhamers@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Greenberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aegreenb@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
