<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The executive science network: University trustees and the organization of university industry exchanges</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399053</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maryann Feldman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This study explores how the external interests of university trustees and senior university officers influence innovation between academe and industry. Previous research has noted a difference in the composition and function of the trustees of private and public universities belonging to the American Association of Universities (AAU). Trustees of private universities are often heads of science-based corporations and simultaneously members of boards of directors of other corporation(s). Over time trustee research interests and those of the universities of which they are stewards become more similar with regard to areas in which they patent and broad fields of science in which their universities are funded. The trustees and senior university management of private AAU universities form a dense network, in which one member is not more than half a step away from any other, constituting an executive science network that creates channels for innovation between academe and industry. Trustees of public AAU universities are not part of this network. This study gathers additional data extending the temporal coverage of the earlier research while broadening the scope to include trustees of public university foundations (arms-length organizations) because pilot research suggests that these trustees may be part of the network and create channels of innovation between public universities and industry rather than public university trustees who are political appointments. The data are analyzed using network analysis and regression analysis to understand how the network functions (i.e., whether trustees? firms? position in biotechnology networks or sub networks or computer science sub networks predicts success in university research funding; whether trustees? firms are likely to patent with or have partnerships with the universities of which they are stewards). These quantitative data are augmented by interviews with 60 trustees at 4 universities to gain in-depth understanding of trustees? corporate exchanges with the universities they govern and how these contribute to technology development and economic innovation. However, if trustees and senior university officers are managing their universities as firms and establishing exchanges with their corporate firms (whether as CEO or member of a board of directors) the possibility of institutional conflict of interest arises. While trustees firms? and universities may both benefit by these exchanges, there is a possibility that pursuit of technology development may harm university science (i.e., by emphasizing some types of science over others). Thus, the interviews focus not only on trustee-university exchange with regard to technology development, but also on how trustees and senior management handle institutional conflict of interest. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this project are several. First, this project advances our understanding of the part research university trustees play in bringing innovative science to the market place, enhancing U.S. ability to compete internationally. Second, the research compares public and private university trustee channels between academe and industry, identifying trustee characteristics that promote innovation. Third, the project examines how trustees involved in exchanges with the universities they govern manage institutional conflict of interest, suggesting best practices for other research universities. All three of these broader impacts will be helpful in developing policy to enable research universities to better participate in technology development and economic innovation that will lead to economic growth.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1262522</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sheila</FirstName>
      <LastName>Slaughter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slaughtr@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barrett</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taylor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Barrett.Taylor@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
