<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SYNTHESIS OF P-CHIRAL ORGANOPHOSPHORUS COMPOUNDS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>260000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Scott Rychnovsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Synthesis Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Jean-Luc Montchamp of the Department of Chemistry at Texas Christian University will explore the development of methods for the formation of compounds that are chiral at the phosphorus atom (P-chiral organophosphorus compounds). Access to P-chiral compounds remains a major synthetic challenge, and chemists largely still rely on rare commercially available but expensive compounds for the development of their various catalytic methodologies. This proposal aims at the general and practical preparation of P-chiral phosphorus compounds. Although a variety of methods exists, to date every single method suffers from significant limitations such as high cost, limited scope and scalability, extended time-investment, or complicated experimental conditions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Practical routes to P-chiral compounds could have a major impact on enantioselective catalysis, as chiral phosphines are ubiquitous in enantioselective catalysis. More effective enantioselective catalysis will have an impact in all areas of chemistry where the synthesis of chiral molecules is needed such as the pharmaceutical, agricultural, and chemical industries. Additionally, this project will provide excellent training of coworkers, from undergraduate research participants to post-doctoral, including those from groups historically underrepresented in the physical sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1262254</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jean-Luc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Montchamp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>j.montchamp@tcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas Christian University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Worth</CityName>
      <ZipCode>761290001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8172577516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2800 South University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6878</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1948</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
