<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Convergence Ecology - Research Experience for Undergraduates in Ecological Diversity across Systems and Disciplines</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>344744</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site award has been made to Southern Illinois University (SIU) that will provide research training for 10 students for 10 weeks each summer during the summers of 2013- 2015. The program has a goal to provide students with hands-on training with a diversity of tools used to conduct ecological research across a spectrum of research areas (to include soil, plants, animals, and multiple ecosystems) and processes (ecological pattern and variability, ecological response to environmental degradation, ecological response to restoration, and conservation and management) through the diverse research programs of 12 faculty members affiliated with SIU?s Center for Ecology. The program will immerse students in research and educational activities aimed to foster (1) hands-on scientific inquiry (from observation through conclusion) by conducting a research project, (2) development of a diverse ecological skills-set through guided quantitative field and laboratory methods, (3) comprehension of and confidence in communicating science through weekly reading and discussion, (4) a broad awareness of ecological science through weekly seminars, and (5) a better understanding of biodiversity (to include human culture) through educational field trips to local natural and cultural areas. Students also will be trained in ethics, responsible conduct of research, and proper animal care and use. The program will culminate with The Colloquium of Undergraduate Research in Ecology ('The CURE'), a symposium of oral presentations delivered by REU students and other undergraduate researchers at SIU. The program's multi-phase recruitment effort consists of both traditional "hard copy" formats as well as digital-based advertising. Students are selected based on academic record, prior research performance, and potential for outstanding research in ecology. Students are tracked to determine their continued interest in their academic field of study, their career paths, and the lasting influences of the research experience. Information about the program will be assessed by various means, including use of an REU common assessment tool. More information is available by visiting http://www.ecology.siu.edu, or by contacting the PI (Dr. Clay Nielsen at kezo92@siu.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Sara Baer at sgbaer@siu.edu).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1263050</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sgbaer@siu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Clayton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nielsen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kezo92@siu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Illinois University at Carbondale</Name>
      <CityName>Carbondale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>629014308</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6184534540</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Ofc. of Sponsored Projects Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
