<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Combining Integrative Biosciences and Bioinformatics for Undergraduate Research Experiences (IBS REU)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>355800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Sites award has been made to Tuskegee University that will provide research training for 10 students, for 10 weeks during the summers of 2013- 2015. The Tuskegee University IBS-REU site offers undergraduates (in the STEM majors, but particularly in Biology, Chemistry, Animal Sciences, Plant and Soil Sciences, Agricultural Economics, and other bioscience majors) a novel approach to conduct research by integrating multiple areas in the biosciences with an emphasis on bioinformatics. We define "integrative biosciences" research as any research where the continued integration of two or more science disciplines is requisite, for example, determining the consequences of genetically-modified sweet potato (Plant Genomics, Plant Sciences) on soil microbial biodiversity (Soil Science, Soil Microbiology, Genetics). Over 30 university faculty will serve as mentors, offering a wide range of interesting and exciting projects for participants. Students are expected to do full-time lab research as well as participate in seminars and career development workshops, such as the ethics and responsible conduct in research, professional communication skills, career opportunities in industry, government and academia, preparing for the GRE and the graduate school application process. REU students have access to a rich array of individual mentor's facilities as well as many labs and centers with core facilities across the Tuskegee University campus. The program's multi-phase recruitment effort consists of both traditional "hard copy" formats as well as digital-based advertising. Students are selected based on academic record, research performance, and potential for outstanding research in integrative biosciences with an emphasis in bioinformatics. Students are tracked to determine their continued interest in their academic field of study, their career paths, and the lasting influences of the research experience. Information about the program will be assessed by various means, including use of an REU common assessment tool available to BIO-funded REU PIs. More information is available by visiting http://www.onemedicine.tuskegee.edu/IBS/project/IBS_REU.htm , or by contacting the PI (Dr. Olga Bolden-Tiller at obtiller@mytu.tuskegee.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Deloris Alexander at dalexander@mytu.tuskegee.edu).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1263207</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deloris</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alexander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dalexander@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Olga</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bolden-Tiller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>obtiller@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tuskegee University</Name>
      <CityName>Tuskegee Institute</CityName>
      <ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3347278233</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 W Montgomery Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
