<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research in Political Science: Participation in Loyalist Protest Activities in Northern Ireland</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>22400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Erik Herron</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objectives: Cultural protest actions are used by political actors around the world to achieve political objectives, but existing political science theories cannot fully explain their dynamics. In particular, the current literature does not account for why individuals participate in actions that have significant political consequences but that do not offer material inducements for participants or social punishments for non-participants. The aim of this dissertation is understand who chooses to participate in politically-relevant protest actions and why.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Theory: To address the inadequate treatment of the characteristics of cultural protest actions in the political science literature, this project draws on two key findings from the literature. First, cultural actions are not "merely symbolic," but provide meaningful benefits to participants; and second, they carry multiple and ambiguous meanings. Briefly, the argument is that individuals choose to participate in cultural actions that provide them with meaningful and enjoyable benefits that are intrinsic to the act of participation. This contrasts with prevailing theories of collective action and collective identity that focus on the beneficial outcomes for participants, and ignore the content of identities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Methods: This project uses original quantitative and qualitative data collected during extensive fieldwork in Northern Ireland, where traditional protest actions by Protestants carry enormous political weight. In fact, these controversial actions are one of the greatest sources of sectarian tension and violence today. The quantitative data will come from a two-wave survey of randomly selected protest participants and non-participants, where each respondent will be interviewed before and after the largest protests of 2013. The qualitative data will come from in-depth interviews and careful observation of protests. These data collection efforts build upon research conducted over three months of recent fieldwork. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The proposed research synthesizes previously disparate strands of research in sociology and political science to advance a novel theory about the relationship between political collective action and collective identity. Students of politics tend to study identities as a static collection of individuals or a set of beliefs, but collective identities are a richer phenomenon and can affect politics through other channels. This dissertation will identify how and why one of these other aspects of collective identity--cultural protest actions--matter politically. The focus on such actions will also illuminate understudied dynamics of political collective action, such as roles of emotional processes, symbols, and collective identities in motivating participation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: Anticipated research findings have the potential to improve the management of divisive political conflicts. Evidence of cultural protest actions being used to polarize groups can be found in divided societies throughout the world, but the creation of effective policy solutions is hindered by a lack of understanding about their dynamics. The findings of this research will be distributed to members of civil society organizations in Northern Ireland, many of whom have already expressed enthusiasm and interest in the project. The hope is that providing community leaders and activists with comprehensive and rigorous results will help them develop strategies that minimize the harmful effects of protest while still allowing groups the right to cultural expression that is inherent in, and necessary for, a robust democratic society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1263772</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Snyder</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jls6@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blake</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jsb2177@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
