<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GARDE: FEASIBILITY AND USABILITY ASSESSMENT OF AN INTRAORAL INCONSPICUOUS CONTROL SURFACE</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>269435</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michele Grimm</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Ghovanloo &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1264624&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI and his team have developed a wireless tongue-operated assistive technology (AT), known as the Tongue Drive System (TDS). Clinical trials on participants with tetraplegia using an external version of the TDS (eTDS), which resembles a wireless headphone, have well established the functionality, ease of use, and acceptability of the eTDS over traditional devices, such as Sip-n-puff. However, mechanical stability of the eTDS is insufficient, and affects its reliability and usability in uncontrolled daily life conditions. While it is possible to firmly secure the eTDS on the user's head with stretchable traps and buckles, the result may reduce the comfort level in long term usage and negatively impact its appearance. An alternative solution is a highly miniaturized intraoral version of the TDS (iTDS) in the form of a dental retainer, which can be customized based on the user's oral anatomy and clasp onto the user's teeth similar to an orthodontic brace. However, very little is known about the feasibility, level of comfort, and usability of an intraoral appliance to be used as a wireless tongue-operated control surface.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The main objectives of the proposed research are: (A) Design and development of a fully functional proof-of-concept iTDS prototype that can be used in human subject trials, while solving key technical challenges. (B) Qualitatively compare the eTDS and iTDS in terms of acceptability, level of comfort, and potential interference with other activities such as speech and ingestion using mockup oral appliances and headsets, interviews, and focus groups involving potential end users with severe physical disabilities. (c) Detailed quantitative assessment of the pros and cons of the intraoral approach in comparison with the eTDS approach based on widely accepted performance measures in the field of human-computer interfacing as well as reliability and robustness against external interfering factors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The number of people with disabilities is increasing among all age groups, particularly the elderly who currently comprise 12% of the U.S. population. Individuals severely disabled as a result of various causes from spinal cord injuries to stroke, cerebral palsy, and ALS find it extremely difficult to carry out everyday tasks without continuous help. We intend to transform the lives of the most severely disabled individuals by helping them live active, self-supportive, and productive lives. Paralysis is considered one of the most expensive disabilities. Solutions such as the iTDS could help reduce healthcare and assisted-living costs and increase the employability of people with severe disabilities, allowing them to participate more fully in the society, while relieving their family members or dedicated caregivers. iTDS can even be used by able-bodied individuals, where motion of the limbs is hindered.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1264624</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maysam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghovanloo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mghovan@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Young Mi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Choi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>christina.choi@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5342</Code>
      <Text>Gen &amp; Age Rel Disabilities Eng</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>010E</Code>
      <Text>DISABILITY RES &amp; HOMECARE TECH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
