<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multimode Smartphone Biosensor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1264377&lt;br/&gt;Cunningham&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The smartphone biosensor will utilize the internal camera as a spectrometer, and the internal LED as a broadband light source. Demonstrated applications will include detection of biomarker proteins that are used to indicate the nutritional status of children, detection of a toxic chemical that can contaminate harvested corn, detection of mRNA sequences used to identify a bacterial pathogen, and detection of an HIV viral antibody. The wide availability of a low-cost, robust, and multimode biosensor detection capability will spur accelerated development of sensing applications in myriad settings where laboratory capabilities are lacking, or where current ?closed? platforms are aimed at only a very specific commercial market. Smartphone-based detection systems are expected to find applications in situations where laboratory facilities are not available such as point-of-care analysis in the home, clinic, farm, or remote locations. The data-sharing capabilities of smartphone-based sensors will enable distributed networks of sensors to be deployed across large physical areas, but with cloud-based systems that can collate and map data. Such systems can aid in the interpretation of sensor data, or make data readily available to clinicians who are not at the same location as the patient.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1264377</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lumetta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lumetta@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bcunning@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7236</Code>
      <Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>005E</Code>
      <Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
