<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: New Techniques for Solid-State NMR Studies of Pharmaceuticals</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/18/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11257</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Eric Munson of the University of Kansas and co-PI John Heinrich of Revolution NMR, LLC, are supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry (with co-funding from the GOALI program in the Engineering Directorate) to develop new techniques for solid-state Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (SSNMR) spectroscopy, and to apply those techniques to substances of pharmaceutical interest. They are collaborating with researchers from GlaxoSmithKline, who can provide insight into significant problems in the pharmaceutical industry and can help provide interesting compounds for study. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research aims for significant increases in sensitivity and throughput that will broaden the application of SSNMR in almost all fields of chemistry. Industrial collaborations will add value by promoting the rapid dissemination and application of technologies and information. They will also promote the rapid development of safe and efficacious drugs and drug formulations by increasing the number of drugs which can be analyzed, as well as identifying potential problems with proposed drug formulations. Finally, the interdisciplinary collaborative nature of the work will enhance the education of graduate students and postdoctoral associates performing and presenting this research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1265397</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Munson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eric.munson@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1974</Code>
      <Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
