<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Functionalization of Metals by Hierarchical Surface Patterning</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>231311</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research is about understanding and controlling the functional properties (wetting, corrosion, and adhesion) of metals by surface patterning. The approach of this research will be to utilize viscous softening of amorphous metals to impart controlled topography (micro, nano, and hierarchical) for desirable functionality in metal components. The scientific objectives of this research are to 1) decouple the contribution of surface topography and chemistry and 2) to understand the effect of atomic structure (amorphous vs crystalline) on surface properties of metals. For objective 1, effect of systematic variation in topography on properties will be characterized without altering the surface chemistry of a metallic alloy. Objective 2 will involve fabrication of comparable surface topography from a metallic alloy in its amorphous and crystalline state. This will be achieved by crystallizing the patterned amorphous metal without significantly changing the surface pattern. The outcomes of these objectives will quantify the effect of topography, composition, and crystal structure on the functional properties of metallic alloys. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the benefits of this research will include a new avenue for surface engineering of metals by patterning, which has been historically limited to polymers and semiconductors due to their advanced fabrication techniques. By integrating surface pattering and net-shaping, complex metals parts with desirable properties can be fabricated without additional functionalization steps. The multi-disciplinary research will provide a stimulating learning environment for the undergraduate and graduate students involved. Outreach activities will include demonstration of correlation between surface properties (hydrophobicity and adhesion) and topography (structure of lotus leaf and fibrillar adhesives) to promote K12 students? interest in the field engineering and science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1266277</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Golden</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>golden.kumar@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
      <CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
      <ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1633</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1444</Code>
      <Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8021</Code>
      <Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
