<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pathways for Alternative Energy Automotive Technicians</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>587687</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Abiodun Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There is a growing need for well-educated highly skilled technicians with practical knowledge of alternative energy automotive systems. The Columbus State Community College (CSCC) "Pathways for Alternative Energy Automotive Technicians" project addresses local workforce needs for technicians that are knowledgeable about such systems. Given innovations in the automotive alternative energy industry and the increased computerization of automotive systems, the traditional training of automotive technicians must be updated to equip them for today's industry needs. Areas of need include conventional hybrid, plug-in hybrid, all-electric vehicle technologies as well as biodiesel, propane, ethanol, compressed natural gas, liquefied natural gas, and fuel-cell vehicles. This project will also address an impending workforce shortage among automotive dealers in central Ohio who have a need for new 21st Century technicians to meet an upcoming wave of retirement among today's mid-career mechanics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the project, CSCC will be developing a new career pathway and new curricula in Alternative Energy Automotive Technology with the help of a dedicated industry-based leadership team. The rigorous curriculum will include key topics from the sciences, automotive technology, engineering and mathematics, all essential for the preparation of the future technical workforce. As technicians must have strong hands-on diagnostic skills, project-based learning will be employed liberally throughout the curriculum. In addition to the new curricula at the college level, pre-college faculty will be exposed to emerging trends in alternative energy automotive technology to aid the recruitment of high school graduates. Additionally, from a safety perspective, first responders will be trained to deal with hazardous aspects of hybrid and alternative fuel technology. CSCC will be working in collaboration with several partners in the region including Clean Fuels Ohio, the Center for Automotive Research at The Ohio State University, local high school districts and technical centers and industry partners. The project will build upon the results of previously funded NSF project at the Center for Aviation and Automotive Technical Education using Virtual E-School (CA2VES) at Clemson University and the South Carolina Advanced Technological Education, National&lt;br/&gt;Center (SCATE).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1600689</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
      <LastName>Levin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slevin@cscc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Foor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dfoor3@cscc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mitchell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmitchel@cscc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbus State Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432151722</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6142872639</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>550 East Spring Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
