<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Creating Learning Opportunities for Undergraduates in Developing Technologies (CLOUDTech)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>432117</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>stephanie august</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The significance of the Creating Learning Opportunities for Undergraduates in Developing Technologies (CLOUDTech) project is its development of an innovative educational pathway in Cloud Computing Technology to address a critical industry need. Because of the emerging nature of cloud technology, institutions of higher education have not yet widely created curriculum and supporting labs to effectively train technicians in this rapidly growing field. This project will advance knowledge and learning by providing a new emphasis in the traditional Network Systems Management program. The newly developed courses will strengthen knowledge in cloud technologies, including virtualization, storage, networking and cybersecurity. Both the courses and labs resulting from CLOUDTech will be broadly disseminated for use by other institutions across the country. These curricular additions will expand educational and career pathways, prepare students for highly 足skilled and highly 足demanded occupations in this particular region's burgeoning information technology sector, and will promote the development of STEM education nationwide.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of CLOUDTech is curriculum and lab development for a series of virtualization and cloud computing courses that will lead to a certificate with stackable credentials toward an associates degree. This goal will be met through four objectives: 1) Development of a rigorous curriculum that will foster an environment of learning and success through hands 足on experience with Cloud Technologies including virtualization, storage, Linux and Windows network operating systems, and network cybersecurity; 2) Development and sharing of curriculum and NETLAB focused hands足 on exercises with Regional ATEs such as ACE, CSSIA, Cyberwatch, and CSEC; 3) Providing professional development for faculty; and 4) Strengthening industry partnerships through collaboration in developing and reviewing cloud technology curriculum, laboratories and student learning objectives. Broad dissemination of the curriculum, labs, and other materials developed by the project, including a User's Guide to facilitate adaptation, have the potential to impact technical education at post-secondary institutions on a national scale.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1601166</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schupbach</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dane.schupbach@tridenttech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trident Technical College</Name>
      <CityName>Charleston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>294238067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8435746195</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O Box 118067</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
