<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Early Career: Acquisition of Ground Penetrating Radar</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>79131</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1602192&lt;br/&gt;Shepherd&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Division of Earth Science Instrumentation and Facilities Program grant supports acquisition of a Ground Penetrating Radar (GPR) system with multiple antennas in a range of frequencies to support non-invasive imaging investigations of the structure and properties of the near subsurface. The instrument will support research and research training in the Department of Geosciences at Auburn. The lead PI is an early career, female geoscientist with plans to engage underrepresented middle school students in rural Alabama in locally relevant environmental research using the requested GPR. This support is congruent with NSFs mission of promoting the progress of science and advancing the national health, prosperity and welfare given the importance of training the next generation scientific workforce in modern techniques of geophysical remote sensing and the societal importance of understanding the impacts of river restoration programs and extent of historical seismic hazards in the central U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;GPR permits non-invasive investigation of the dielectric properties of near surface sediments and can yield insights into near surface stratigraphic relationships and materials properties. The GPR will support studies of Quaternary fluvial processes and landscape evolution, investigation of flood plain restoration strategies in watersheds that impact Mobile Bay Estuary, and paleoseismic investigations of earthquake induced liquefaction from historic earthquakes in the New Madrid mid-continent seismic zone.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1602192</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shepherd</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slshepherd@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lorraine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wolf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wolflor@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Auburn University</Name>
      <CityName>Auburn University</CityName>
      <ZipCode>368490001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 Samford Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
