<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Interfacing Nanotubes and Graphene into Ordered Crystallographic Orientations Through Substrate-Induced Strain</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>137610</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Strachan, Douglas R. &lt;br/&gt;#: 1603152&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As future devices are reduced to the smallest nanometer sizes, material interfaces are expected to play an ever-greater role in determining their behaviors. At these ultra-small sizes, the precise ordering of the atoms at the interfaces is of critical importance for determining these nanoscale properties. A promising approach for controlling these precisely-ordered interfaces is to connect together the nanoscale materials the same way that lego toys are connected; i.e., with their periodic lattices snapped together. To make these nanoscale ?lego-snapped? interfaces of use requires that they be reproducibly and controllably achievable between technologically-relevant materials. Achieving this goal, however, requires a fundamental understanding and control of the relevant interactions at the interfaces of nanomaterials. As an important step in the long-term goal of understanding and controlling the relevant interactions at such interfaces, lego-snapping will be investigated between two of the most promising and important nanomaterials ? these being graphene and carbon nanotubes. The investigation of lego-snapping between these nanomaterials will be achieved in an innovative method that tunes the interactions between the graphene and the carbon nanotubes through the use of a third adjacent material. This innovative investigation should provide fundamental insight into the mechanisms of forming lego-snapped interfaces that could be of use in engineering nanoscale alignments with mass-scale reproducibility and specificity ? results that would be of tremendous technological use in the fabrication and synthesis of future nanoscale technologies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As nanoscale systems are reduced in size, the relative crystallographic orientations of materials? lattices should become increasingly important to their interfacial properties. Utilizing nanoscale components that consist of well-ordered lattice-matched nanomaterials is a novel and promising avenue for achieving these highly crystalline interfaces. Atomically-thin nanomaterial components, like carbon nanotubes and graphene that consist of the same lattice back-bone are ideal for achieving such lattice-matched interfaces. Moreover, the fact that these materials are atomically-thin permits a new innovative method for probing their interfaces via the use of additional adjacent ?substrate? materials. These adjacent ?substrate? materials will provide a route to control the localized strain of the nanotube-graphene system and, thus, provide a method to modify, probe, and enhance the lattice matching of their interface. Through the use of this external strain control, a fundamental understanding of the relevant interactions at the interfaces of these atomically-thin nanomaterial systems will be obtained.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1603152</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strachan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>doug.strachan@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1179</Code>
      <Text>Enviro Health &amp; Safety of Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
