<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Understanding how interaction of single-walled carbon nanotubes with biological interfaces in the gastrointestinal system may alter chemical bioavailability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Bisesi, Joseph H.&lt;br/&gt;# 1605119&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Single-walled carbon nanotubes are small man-made materials that are currently being used in a number of consumer industries. With this increased use, there is increased likelihood that these materials will make their way into aquatic environments. The materials have properties which make them highly likely to be consumed by aquatic organisms such as fish where they may interact with the fish intestinal system. The overall objective of this project is to understand how single-walled carbon nanotubes influence the intestinal environment by making fish more susceptible to chemicals (i.e. pollutants) that are already present in our environment and are associated with health concerns. To achieve this objective the PI will examine how single-walled carbon nanotubes may change the normal structure and function of the intestines of exposed fish and determine whether these changes contribute to increasing their susceptibility to other chemicals that are already present in our aquatic environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Single-walled nanotubes are lipophilic in nature and are likely to sorb other aquatic contaminants already present in our environment as well as alter the intestinal tract of fish through dietary exposure routes. The objective of this research is to better understand the specific interactions of single-walled carbon nanotubes with fish intestines by probing their interaction with lipids in the gastrointestinal system which may result in structural and functional changes in the intestinal lipidome. The PI will also examine whether such changes in gastrointestinal lipid profiles result in release of chemicals that may be adsorbed to single-walled carbon nanotubes, increasing bioaccumulation of these contaminants. The PI will accomplish these objectives by examining gastrointestinal lipid profiles during single-walled carbon nanotube dietary exposure, determining the effects of lipids on sorption of chemicals to these materials, and examining the effects of nano-lipid interactions on chemical bioaccumulation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Activities performed in this project are expected to have far reaching impacts on an international, national, and regional scale. Results from the nano-bio interaction studies will contribute to the design of next generation nanomaterials that take advantage of, or avoid, identified downstream behavior. In this way the PI can continue to utilize the amazing properties of nanomaterials without detrimental consequences. On a local level, the research team plans to include students from underrepresented groups in this project as well as increasing public knowledge on the benefits of nanomaterials through the use of videos. The scientific community will be involved in this project on a national scale through teaching of short courses at regional meetings as well as leading sessions at national meetings. Finally, the research team will expand education by integrating information about nanomaterial uses for combating health issues in resource poor countries through existing teaching programs in international communities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1605119</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sabo-Attwood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sabo@phhp.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bisesi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbisesi@phhp.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1179</Code>
      <Text>Enviro Health &amp; Safety of Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
