<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Advanced Membrane Technology Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Escobar, Isabel C.&lt;br/&gt;Proposal: 1607899 &lt;br/&gt;This proposal requests $49,000 to partially defray conference costs for up to 30 graduate&lt;br/&gt;and post-doctoral students to participate in the Engineering Conferences International Meeting&lt;br/&gt;on Advanced Membrane Technology VII in September 2016. The meeting will have 13-14 technical&lt;br/&gt;sessions covering recent advances in membrane research, development and applications. Some &lt;br/&gt;examples include the nexus of nanotechnology, biotechnology and membrane separations, as well&lt;br/&gt;as wastewater reclamation, gas and liquid separations and purifications, and energy issues.&lt;br/&gt;A poster session is also an integral part of the meeting. Supported students will be asked&lt;br/&gt;to present at the poster session. The meeting will feature a number of internationally renowned&lt;br/&gt;and up and coming researchers. The anticipated attendance for the meeting is 100 membrane&lt;br/&gt;researchers from all parts of the world representing industry, government and academic facilities.&lt;br/&gt;Membrane technology is an important part of the separation technology. Topics were selected&lt;br/&gt;based on providing an update from the previous meeting, marking specific areas for special&lt;br/&gt;attention, and showcasing recent advancements related to water production, the environment&lt;br/&gt;and special needs. The conference will highlight the following four topics:&lt;br/&gt;(1) Environmental engineering through sessions that will highlight the use of membranes to&lt;br/&gt;remove emerging contaminants, such as endocrine disruptors and algal toxins (e.g. microcystin,&lt;br/&gt;as the issues facing Lake Erie and numerous world countries). Another session will have presentations&lt;br/&gt;on lowering membrane fouling.&lt;br/&gt;(2) Sustainability through two sessions that will discuss sustainable water treatment, such&lt;br/&gt;as water reclamation and recycling; and will discuss membranes for energy applications, such&lt;br/&gt;saline water gradient.&lt;br/&gt;(3) Advances in nanotechnology for membranes, which will highlight the use of metal nanoparticles,&lt;br/&gt;carbon nanotubes, graphene and other nanomaterials for the improvement of membrane operation.&lt;br/&gt;(4) Scalable nanomanufacturing of membranes, which will highlight the mechanisms that can&lt;br/&gt;lead to failure during the scale up of nanocomposite membranes.&lt;br/&gt;Given the scope of this meeting, its more intimate meeting structure and diverse internationally&lt;br/&gt;renowned attendees, the ECI Advanced Membrane Technology VII Conference provides an exceptional&lt;br/&gt;intellectual training opportunity for graduate students and young faculty.&lt;br/&gt;The potential to improve advanced membrane technology rests on our continuing ability to harness&lt;br/&gt;results from basic science and engineering, of the kind supported by</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1607899</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Isabel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Escobar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>isabel.escobar@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hestekin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhesteki@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Engineering Conferences International, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100041644</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2125146760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>32 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1179</Code>
      <Text>Enviro Health &amp; Safety of Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1440</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
