<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RET Site: Optics Research Experience for Teachers in Native American Schools (O-RETinas)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499038</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) in Engineering and Computer Science Site, entitled Optics Research Experience for Teachers in Native American Schools (O-RETinas), at the University of Arizona (UA), Engineering Research Center (ERC) for Integrated Access Networks (CIAN), will expose K-14 STEM teachers and community college faculty, serving Native American communities and students nationwide, to cutting-edge research on photonic materials and devices for optical communication which will replace current electronic technology. Keeping the U.S. in an information technology leadership position will require developing dense, integrated optoelectronic systems that extend the capabilities of the current fiber network core, while retaining the same cost as today's electronic access network. The interdisciplinary nature of optics and photonics, coupled with real-world industry experiences applied within the context of Native American values will transform K-14 classrooms and provide fertile ground for developing creative problem-based course modules in math, physics, electrical engineering, optical engineering, and technology that align with state and national standards, motivating students toward pursuit of STEM degrees. CIAN will partner with the nationally acclaimed Teachers in Industry (TII) program of UA's College of Education and local STEM companies in this program. The program addresses identified barriers for precollege Native American students who lag significantly behind other minority groups in college matriculation, retention and graduation, particularly in engineering. The industry exposure O-RETinas teachers will gain as a result of their participation will provide tools to improve STEM curriculum and encourage the pursuit of STEM education among Native American students, thus creating the potential for local economic growth and a diverse engineering workforce. This program has the potential to exhibit to the indigenous communities nationwide that academic and industry stakeholders in communities are addressing the need for more Native American students in higher education, which ultimately may benefit their communities. Through the partnership with TII, RET participants will learn transformative teaching techniques to transfer engineering and industry knowledge to their students. The O-RETinas program is also addressing the issue of retention of teachers in rural districts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over a three-year period this RET Site will offer an intensive summer research program to a total of 30 STEM precollege teachers and community college faculty who will join research teams performing hands on research on topics including improved fiber optics, waveguide materials, short-pulsed lasers, micro-fabrication, and silicon photonics and have opportunities to apply research and lab techniques in industry settings. The research experience will also include: an industry practicum; earning graduate professional development credits through TII; attending Native American focused workshops that discuss integrating optical sciences into Native American culture; and receiving training in best practices for curriculum development with the expertise of business and research communities, and applying these experiences and knowledge in the context of Native American values to create lesson plans, hands-on activities, and course units for their classrooms. Dissemination of the results of RET participants' research projects, through poster sessions and national conferences such as AISES and NSTA, will broadly disseminate innovative lesson plans and course units.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1608843</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Norwood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rnorwood@optics.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huff MacPherson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>allison@optics.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1359</Code>
      <Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>115E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
