<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SusChEM: Understanding Microwave Interactions to Control Magnetic Nanocrystal Growth from a Single Source Precursor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Langell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Sustainable and cost-effective nanomaterial production requires synthesis methods that demand small amounts of energy, rapid reaction rates, and recyclable components. For industrial applications, these synthesis methods must also be scalable and reproducible. Microwave (MW) chemistry methods may achieve these performance demands. Dr. Geoffrey Strouse is investigating microwave chemistry to develop new methods for the synthesis of magnetic alloys with very small dimensions (nanoparticles). He is particularly interested in determining the effects of MW frequency, power, and optical properties on the rate of thermal decomposition of molecular clusters based upon the Prussian blue molecule. Prussian blue molecules have are two different transition metals which, when decomposed by MW heating to form a metal alloy, create a nanoparticle with extremely strong magnetic properties. These magnetic properties may be useful in many technological applications. By judiciously choosing the MW variables, Dr. Strouse is able to control the composition and size of the nanoscale magnet, carefully tailoring its magnetic properties to the task at hand. The research uncovers knowledge that is broadly useful in bimetallic nanoparticle synthesis and establishes new synthetic routes for nano-metal systems that are sustainable and can be scaled to industrial applications. The MW methodology developed in this research impacts not only the fields of magnetism and magnet technology, but may offer routes to new catalysts as well. Dr. Strouse's research has significant broader impacts, since it is attractive to students at many levels. He is actively involved in training students underrepresented in the STEM fields. He interacts with high school and middle school scientists by providing learning experiences for them with hands on scientific activities. Dr. Strouse maintains up-to-date details on MW methodolgy, microwave effects, and structural properties of the new materials on his publically-accessible website at Florida State University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Supported by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry (MSN) Program of the Chemistry Division at NSF, Dr. Geoffrey Strouse of Florida State University employs microwave (MW) chemistry to develop new synthesis methodologies for nano-scaled bi-metallic magnet alloys. His MW synthesis uses recyclable supercritical CO2 solvent and a shelf-stable single-source precursor, (M'[M(CN)6])n, where M', M are transition metals chosen for their magnetic properties in the metal alloy form. By careful selection of microwave power, frequency, and molecular design, Dr. Strouse is able to control the rate of the reaction by selectively coupling to electric and magnetic dipoles in the precursor. In conjunction with computational studies, dielectric spectroscopy and magnetic measurements, instrumental design, and materials characterization of the nanosized bi-metallic alloys are used to fabricate a series of advanced magnetic materials and to investigate MW-induced reaction mechanisms. The research has significant broader impact on industrial magnetic and catalytic applications, since the methodology is scalable and may be translated to new materials and larger quantity applications. Dr. Strouse involves young students, science teachers, undergraduate and graduate students in his research, and serves as a mentor of students underrepresented in STEM fields. He is actively engaged in outreach to high school and middle school students, and provides learning experiences for these students with hands-on science activities. He actively maintains a website for dissemination of data, experimental methodology, and detailed MW analysis, accessible to the general public through Florid State University web pages.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1608364</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Geoffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strouse</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>strouse@chem.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8060</Code>
      <Text>SEES Unsolicited</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8248</Code>
      <Text>SusChEM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8650</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
