<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Future Internet Architecture Fall 2015 Investigator Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>31760</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports a Future Internet Architecture Next-Phase (FIA-NP) investigator meeting in November, 2015. This meeting focused on lessons learned and open issues, including metrics for evaluation and availability, a presentation of network requirements by DARPA, and status reports on environments where the FIA-NP architectures are being deployed, experimented upon, and tested.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The range of topics discussed represent important aspects of the FIA-NP program. The discussions are intended to bring out implications of the design decisions within each of the funded network designs. Cross-fertilization of the projects is an important aspect of the overall program, and these workshops are a critical means to do so.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The broader goal of the NSF FIA-NP program is enhancing the relevance and impact of the NSF program of network research, intellectual enrichment of the network research community, and the contribution of new concepts and thought leadership to the future of the Internet. The program, and the workshops in particular, are a means to train a cohort of academic network researchers in the practice of long-range architectural thinking. The program has the potential to contribute to a future Internet that is materially more secure, robust, economically viable, and fit for the needs of society than the Internet of today. The summary of this workshop, which is posted on the FIA website http://www.nets-fia.net/ for public dissemination, will be a contribution to this broader goal.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1608691</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddc@csail.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
