<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Research Within Communities of Practice</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>298949</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Opportunities to conduct authentic research not only improve students' understanding of science but also promote their self-identification as scientists. This project will explore the potential to positively transform undergraduate science education through student research seminars that are specifically structured to produce peer-reviewed journal articles based on students' research within the confines of a single semester. At the outset of their college careers, students participating in this model will form student-managed teams within a supportive scientific "community of practice." The seminars will teach the students how science really works through projects that they themselves plan and manage. By conducting and publishing scientific research, the students will become -- both technically and sociologically -- real scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For the past decade, Cuesta College, a community college in San Luis Obispo, California, has offered an astronomy research seminar with the format described above. Over 150 students have completed the seminar as coauthors of published papers, primarily reporting observations of visual double stars. Recently, the seminar has also been offered by nearby California Polytechnic State University, a public institution, as well as by Concordia University, a private institution in Irvine, California. This project will expand the seminar model to other areas of observational astronomy beyond double stars (but still within the small-telescope community of practice), such as observations of exoplanet transits, binary star eclipses, and pulsating stars. The investigators will also expand the model into environmental science, featuring three types of atmospheric measurement: (1) the size, distribution, and morphology of small atmospheric particles; (2) infrared and Raman spectroscopy of particulate matter that settles from the atmosphere; and (3) atmospheric gas samples analyzed with infrared spectroscopy, gas chromatography, and mass spectrometry. Results will be correlated with local weather conditions, road traffic data, sample location, and special climatic events such as forest fires and Santa Ana winds. Through the Council on Undergraduate Research (a partner in the project), the investigators will assess opportunities for applying the seminar's community-of-practice approach to other sciences beyond astronomy and environmental science and will organize a focus group of national education and policy experts, who will consider how to expand nationally and scaffold the research seminar's paradigm of students as scientists within a community of practice. One of the project's contributions to STEM education research will be to examine the impact of the seminar's malleable factors, moderators, and mediators on such student outcomes as motivation to become a scientist, critical thinking (enhanced by having research papers reviewed by other students, instructors, and external experts), improved project planning and management skills, writing skills, and preparing and giving presentations on research projects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1610350</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dwight</FirstName>
      <LastName>Collins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>decollins21@comcast.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Genet</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>russmgenet@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kenney</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.kenney@cui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ambos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eambos@cur.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Polytechnic State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Luis Obispo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>934070830</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8057562982</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Grand Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1998</Code>
      <Text>IUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8209</Code>
      <Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
