<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fifteenth Extotic Beam Summer School</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Allena Opper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support for students to participate in the Fifteenth Summer School on Exotic Beam (EBSS) Physics at the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory, July 17 - 24, 2016. The school is designed for graduate students, senior undergraduate students who are actively involved in research and postdocs (within 2 years of their degree). The school will consist of morning lectures and hands-on activities in the afternoons. Students will also have an opportunity to present their research. The aim of the summer school is to educate the next generation of scientists that will drive the research at the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams (FRIB) when it comes online and other existing rare isotope facilities. In years to come, substantial progress in low-energy nuclear physics will have a broad impact on society, ranging from our understanding of the origin of the elements to the enhancement of national security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous sessions of these summer schools have had broad participation of under-represented minorities, with slightly more than 40% of the participants of the Fourteenth EBSS being female. The organizers of the Fifteenth EBSS will continue the use of accepted best practices to increase diversity and have an inclusive summer school.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1612624</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hironori</FirstName>
      <LastName>Iwasaki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>iwasaki@nscl.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/02/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1233</Code>
      <Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
