<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Meeting: High-throughput Plant Phenotyping and Data Analysis, A Series of Workshops at the Plant and Animal Genome Conference XXIV, January 9-13, 2016 San Diego, CA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>48033</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne Sylvester</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An interdisciplinary group of researchers will meet to discuss and identify key challenges in plant biology and applied breeding at the Plant and Animal Genome Conference in San Diego, CA, January 10-11, 2016. Three workshops will focus on developing data standards for the use of so-called "high through-put phenotyping" tools, such as remote sensing, rover/robot field assistance, deployment of unmanned aerial device and other recent developments. These emerging technologies are powerful tools capable of generating large scale datasets that researchers and breeders can use to understand plant growth and responses to the environment. However, to make use of the data effectively, researchers must establish standards of data acquisition and develop best practices for managing and sharing the massive datasets these technologies produce. The goals of these workshops are to identify gaps in technology and develop a roadmap for managing and sharing data. On the first day, 8-12 invited speakers will deliver presentations at two workshop sessions on the broad topics of phenotyping, data collection and information management to catalyze broad discussion. A panel discussion will engage the audience in open dialogue to establish best practices and develop research trajectories. The second day will include a brainstorming session aimed at refining topics raised during the prior workshops and culminating in the development of a whitepaper, or roadmap, designed to guide research over the coming years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshops will encourage interdisciplinary discussions to develop data standards and recommend key priorities for strategic Federal and International investment. The workshop will include participation from researchers using both reductionist (controlled environment) and holistic (field-based) approaches, as well as the data scientists who enable broad access to research outcomes via information resources. Participants will be from across disciplines such as plant biology, genomics, genetics, plant breeding, systems biology, computer science and the data sciences. Scholars will also participate from diverse career stages, institutional types, geographical locations, gender, and ethnic backgrounds. As an outcome of the workshops, a whitepaper will be prepared that identifies gaps in knowledge, infrastructure, participation, and educational opportunities. The whitepaper will further identify potential research directions, propose solutions to fill the identified gaps and emphasize strategies for training the next generation of plant breeders. Both short- and long-term goals for integrating plant sciences, agriculture, and the data sciences will be articulated. The whitepaper will serve as a community gold standard to be widely disseminated through publication, meeting presentation and made available through web portals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1613452</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lawrence-Dill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>triffid@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
