<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Observations, Theory, and Simulations of the Sun-Earth System International Symposium; Golden Sands, Varna, Bulgaria; September 12-16, 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29060</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Meriwether</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provide support for an international workshop, the International Symposium on Recent Observations and Simulations of the Sun-Earth System III (ISROSES-III). This activity is intended to be a forum for scientists from all heliophysics communities to present and discuss recent advances in theory, modeling and observations of the Sun-Earth System (SES) and to form research collaborations. This workshop would be the third one following similarly-focused workshops held in 2006 and in 2011. The budget covers travel expenses and registration expenses for three people (PI and two Co-PI). Registration expenses for 20 invited speakers would be supported from this award. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The uniqueness of this Symposium is in that it will bring together cross-disciplinary scientists from around the globe to have focused discussions on fundamental problems related to the Sun-Earth System and space weather. The main emphasis will be put on the integration of these studies - ranging from observations to related interpretation, theory and numerical modeling across different temporal and spatial scales of this system. It will thus provide training for new researchers in geospace system science. Young postdoctoral and early career researchers are expected to come away from the Symposium with a better appreciation of the benefits of interdisciplinary approaches to understanding the dynamic near-Earth space environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1614840</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borovsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jborovsky@spacescience.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Denton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdenton@spacescience.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vania</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jordanova</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vania@lanl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SPACE SCIENCE INSTITUTE</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803012532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7209745888</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4750 Walnut Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1523</Code>
      <Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
