<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Magnetic Filaments at the Center of our Milky Way Galaxy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>308564</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glen Langston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Radio astronomers have discovered remarkable magnetic field structures near the center of our Milky Way galaxy. These structures, called filaments, are much more complicated than simple hot clouds of gas. These filaments are many light years in length. The filaments are thought to be visible to radio telescopes because high-energy particles are orbiting along very long magnetic fields. The investigators will study the detailed physical characteristics of these filamentary structures using the NSF Very Large Array (VLA) radio telescope. Museum and public events will be developed at both the University of Iowa and the University of California at Los Angeles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will study non-thermal filamentary structures observed in the radio images of the Galactic Center. This study will exploit the new capabilities of the VLA, an NSF radio telescope in New Mexico, to obtain detailed physical information of these structures, including polarization analysis. The outcomes of this project have important implications in other fields of astronomy, in particular the study of the active galactic nuclei in other galaxies, and the role of magnetic fields in the environments of accreting black holes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At University of Iowa, the investigator will work with an undergraduate to develop a museum exhibit. The investigators will also participate in the museum activities and lecture series. At the University of California at Los Angles, another investigator will participate in public education events, as well as in training undergraduate students from underrepresented backgrounds.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1615375</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cornelia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cornelia-lang@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Iowa</Name>
      <CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1216</Code>
      <Text>GALACTIC ASTRONOMY PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1206</Code>
      <Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
