<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AF: Small: A-Hypergeometric Solutions of Linear Differential Equations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>449999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jack Snoeyink</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Many scientific laws are captured as differential equations --&lt;br/&gt;formulas that relates a quantity (such as position) to its derivatives&lt;br/&gt;(velocity and acceleration). Differential equations are common in&lt;br/&gt;science, mathematics and engineering. They can be solved numerically,&lt;br/&gt;but may also have a closed-form solution -- an exact solution written&lt;br/&gt;in terms of familiar functions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Except for small equations, closed-form solutions were thought to be&lt;br/&gt;rare. Algorithms for second-order equations, which were developed by&lt;br/&gt;the PI and his students, have demonstrated that closed form solutions &lt;br/&gt;of linear differential equations with polynomial coefficients&lt;br/&gt;are actually common; solutions can often be written in terms of&lt;br/&gt;Gauss's hypergeometric function, a familiar function in differential&lt;br/&gt;equations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to find out if closed form solutions are also common&lt;br/&gt;for higher order equations. The PI will work with two graduate&lt;br/&gt;students to develop algorithms to search for solutions in terms of&lt;br/&gt;A-hypergeometric functions, which were introduced by Gel'fand,&lt;br/&gt;Kapranov and Zelevinski.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a wide variety of A-hypergeometric functions, which&lt;br/&gt;correspond to polytopes. A-hypergeometric functions can be&lt;br/&gt;multivariate, so several tools that currently only exist for&lt;br/&gt;univariate equations need to be generalized. A key motivating&lt;br/&gt;question is if convergent integer-series solutions can always be&lt;br/&gt;written in terms of A-hypergeometric functions. If true, then&lt;br/&gt;A-hypergeometric solutions would be common in areas of mathematics and&lt;br/&gt;science that involve combinatorial structures or integrals, such as the Ising model&lt;br/&gt;or Feynman diagrams in physics. This question leads to several others&lt;br/&gt;on A-hypergeometric functions, some of which can be settled by the&lt;br/&gt;algorithms to be developed in this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1618657</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>van Hoeij</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hoeij@math.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7796</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7933</Code>
      <Text>NUM, SYMBOL, &amp; ALGEBRA COMPUT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
