<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI: Small: Lensless Cameras --- Enabling Novel Imaging Capabilities with Programmable Masks and Computational Imaging</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project develops fundamentally new types of cameras that are extremely thin and flexible. Today, the primary technology for imaging and photography is by using a lens to focus light onto a planar sensor. However, this design requires a certain minimum distance - often, several millimeters - to focus the light from the scene to produce a high-resolution image. In addition, lenses are fundamentally incompatible for imaging on non-planar surfaces. By removing lenses from the imaging system, this project designs cameras that have thicknesses in the order of 100s of micrometers. This enables novel applications in mobile photography, endoscopy, microscopy, and the internet-of-things where there are stringent requirements on the thickness of the camera. Further, by exploiting advances in flexible electronics, the project is building novel camera designs for imaging on flexible and curved surfaces. The research in lens-less imaging is also incorporated into outreach activities in middle and high schools in the Greater Pittsburgh area, where workshops on camera building introduce students to basics concepts in optics and engineering while inspiring them to pursue a STEM career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research focuses on designs for imaging at thin form factors and on curved and flexible surfaces. This is achieved by placing a carefully-designed mask in close proximity to the sensor. By analyzing the fundamental capabilities and limitations of mask-based imaging, highly optimized masks and associated reconstruction algorithms are designed to resolve scenes at high resolutions. Specifically, masks are optimized to deliver high light-throughput while providing invertible scene-to-sensor transfer functions. Programmable mask designs are also explored for enabling a richer space of transfer functions that are capable of acquiring not just images and videos, but also light fields. The research makes it possible to characterize the fundamental limits of thin form-factor imaging and the associated imaging architectures that achieve them.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1618823</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aswin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sankaranarayanan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>saswin@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
