<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AF: Small: Quantitative and Algorithmic Aspects of Semi-algebraic Sets and Partitions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399640</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jack Snoeyink</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"Divide and conquer," a time-honored technique in computer science and&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, partitions a problem into smaller pieces to make it&lt;br/&gt;easier to solve. This project deepens the study of partitioning in two&lt;br/&gt;directions, both in the context of semi-algebraic geometry -- which is&lt;br/&gt;the study of geometric and topological properties of sets defined by&lt;br/&gt;real polynomial equalities and inequalities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first direction is to systematize polynomial partitioning, which&lt;br/&gt;has recently become a powerful tool capable of tackling many&lt;br/&gt;long-standing open questions in the area of incidence geometry. In&lt;br/&gt;computational geometry, the space or sets being partitioned are often&lt;br/&gt;complex but partitioning is by simple objects: splitting by planes or&lt;br/&gt;cutting into trapezoids. Polynomial partitioning allows high degree&lt;br/&gt;cutting polynomials, necessitating more precise degree-based upper&lt;br/&gt;bounds on the topology of semi-algebraic sets and real varieties than&lt;br/&gt;the ones known before, and leading to a very fruitful interaction&lt;br/&gt;between the fields of real algebraic geometry and discrete geometry.&lt;br/&gt;The PI will develop new techniques in semi-algebraic geometry to meet&lt;br/&gt;the new demands imposed on the field by the developments in discrete&lt;br/&gt;geometry, and develop a new theory of polynomial partitioning that can&lt;br/&gt;systematize their study and lead to new applications as well.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second is to generalize quantitative and algorithmic&lt;br/&gt;semi-algebraic geometry to a much more general and geometric setting&lt;br/&gt;-- the category of constructible sheaves. Constructible sheaves come&lt;br/&gt;with an underlying semi-algebraic partition (on whose elements the&lt;br/&gt;stalks of the sheaf are locally constant). Kashiwara and Schapira&lt;br/&gt;proved a fundamental theorem on the stability of this category under&lt;br/&gt;the six standard sheaf operations (analogous to Tarski-Seidenberg&lt;br/&gt;principle for semi-algebraic sets). The PI will study the quantitative&lt;br/&gt;and algorithmic questions related to constructible sheaves. The&lt;br/&gt;complexity upper bounds and algorithmic results would have wide&lt;br/&gt;applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will have impact in several areas of mathematics and&lt;br/&gt;computation -- including quantitative and algorithmic semi-algebraic&lt;br/&gt;geometry, discrete and computational geometry, computational&lt;br/&gt;complexity theory and quantitative study of the solutions to linear&lt;br/&gt;systems of partial differential equations. The project will train a&lt;br/&gt;graduate student and a postdoctoral researcher in quantitative and&lt;br/&gt;algorithmic real algebraic geometry and its modern applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1618981</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Saugata</FirstName>
      <LastName>Basu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbasu@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7796</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7933</Code>
      <Text>NUM, SYMBOL, &amp; ALGEBRA COMPUT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
