<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Uplift and Seismic Structure of the Greater Caucasus</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>44700</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Luciana Astiz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project uses the Greater Caucasus Mountains in southern Asia as a natural laboratory to study the early stages of mountain building. Using data from over 106 new seismic stations in Azerbaijan, Armenia, Russia, and Georgia, the researchers gain a better understanding of the recent uplift of the Greater Caucasus and the nature of earthquake related deformation in the region. This research helps gain better understanding of the processes that lead to the formation of mountain belts on Earth and the sub surface processes that lead to large earthquakes and volcanoes in a continental collision. This project includes improving seismic hazard assessment in continental deformation belts where thousands of lives and billions of dollars are at risk from recurrent devastating earthquakes including some of the world's largest energy producers. The aim is to improve the scientific community's understanding of earthquake hazards and the forces that are actively deforming the earth in a very young mountain belt. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Caucasus region is a logistically and politically challenging region to collect seismic data; however, we have managed to establish collaborative agreement with all of the countries involved in this project to share the data with one another. Due to a lack of quality data, the region has largely been unexplored in terms of the detailed uppermost mantle and crustal seismic structure thus this work is nearly guaranteed to find first order information concerning deep structure beneath the Greater Caucasus. This seismic experiment has two components: (1) a grid of stations spanning the Greater Caucasus and (2) a seismic transect consisting of passive stations spaced at distances of less 5 km that crosses the Greater Caucasus. In addition to the temporary stations, this research integrates data from the national networks to produce high resolution images of the seismic structure. The primary scientific question that this project intends to resolve with the images of the deep subsurface structure is the uplift mechanisms for the Greater Caucasus and how these relate to the uplift mechanisms for mountain belts in general.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1620613</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nabelek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nabelek@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1572</Code>
      <Text>TECTONICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
