<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Implementation Project: Hinds Community College- Utica Campus Phase II- Establishing a Cohesive Community College STEM Institutional Transformation Academy - STEM-UP Academy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>748639</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Implementation Projects provide support to Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) to design, implement, study, and assess comprehensive institutional efforts to increase the number of students receiving undergraduate degrees in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) and enhance the quality of their preparation by strengthening STEM education and research. The project at Hinds Community College-Utica seeks to build on previous successful efforts to facilitate students' transition from high school to community college to four year institutions and to increase their success rate in STEM disciplines. The goal is to assist students in navigating their educational path and to increase retention and graduation rates of students with STEM associate degrees. The project aims to specifically increase the placement of community college students into four-year institutions through academic partnerships with Jackson State University and Alcorn State University. The project is expected to create a pathway model for student matriculation from community colleges to four-year degree granting institutions which can be adapted and scaled by other institutions of higher education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The following activities and strategies are designed to meet the project's goals: development of the Summer STEM Academic Integrated Learning Program for high schools students in Copiah, Claiborne, Hinds, and Vicksburg-Warren counties; a College Success Camp for entering freshmen; development of a support and mentoring program to assist students with transfer and enrollment in a four-year university of their choice while providing them with summer research experiences at the Hinds Community College-Utica campus or at participating universities; establishment of faculty professional development programs to assist faculty in restructuring the learning environment and in building new collaborations. A cyber-mentoring component will be established to continue providing support to graduates of the program once they transfer to a four-year program. The project strategies supporting these objectives are evidence-based and will be monitored and evaluated for effectiveness.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623282</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mitchell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shears</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Mitchell.Shears@hindscc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Debra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mays-Jackson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Debra.Mays-Jackson@hindscc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hinds Community College-Utica</Name>
      <CityName>Raymond</CityName>
      <ZipCode>391541100</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6018573200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>501 East Main Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
