<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: MAKER: Deployable Makerspace: Mobility, Additive Manufacturing, and Curricular Spectacle</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299780</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>erick jones</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project leverages Making to develop and test its role in improving the effectiveness of informal learning pathways for increasing retention and broadening participation in Science, Technology, Engineering, Art, and Mathematics or STEAM through the context of a deployable makerspace with a particular emphasis on additive manufacturing (AM). Mobile makerspaces have been shown to excite local communities and this research investigates how this initial fascination can impact learning and engagement with STEAM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates how deployable makerspace provides a more comprehensive spectrum of concepts related to material extrusion additive manufacturing called a "material-to-form" model with particular depth in design and material science important to making. Also, the impact on broadening participation through the experiential component of making by adapting makerspaces will be explored.The question of whether interaction with a deployable makerspace will improve participants knowledge of Additive Manufacturing and the material and design considerations associated with it. This research brings together important technological innovations that are transforming how we conceptualize STEAM education: digital fabrication, makerspace culture, and mobility. Finally this research will explore what possibilities for engagement and curriculum development when the Makerspace goes to the student. This project is a part of NSF's Maker Dear Colleague Letter (DCL) portfolio (NSF 15-086), a collaborative investment of Directorates for Computer &amp; Information Science &amp; Engineering (CISE), Education and Human Resources (EHR) and Engineering (ENG).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623494</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meisel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nam20@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Knochel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>adk176@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lauerman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tal16@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1998</Code>
      <Text>IUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
