<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improved cyberinfrastructure to support data driven research in a model social-ecological system</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>184233</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter H. McCartney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The telecommunications revolution is enabling scholarly innovation and discoveries not otherwise possible: in particular, high speed data networks utilizing submarine fiber-optic cables now link even remote research sites to mainland (cloud-based) resources. Field scientists can thus access high performance computing systems, advanced instruments, data storage systems, visualization environments, and data repositories. They can also maintain academic interactions with colleagues and students on their home campus, increasing productivity and allowing more time in the field. The improved cyberinfrastructure provided by this project will help the University of California's Gump South Pacific Research Station (http://moorea.berkeley.edu) on the island of Moorea to support a transition to technology intensive, data driven field research and to develop innovative cyber-learning programs. Among other benefits, it will help advance the scientific understanding of coral reefs by supporting programs such as the NSF Moorea Coral Reef Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) site. Hotspots for global biological diversity, coral reefs are sources of societal significance and economic value. Local and global processes, including climate change and ocean acidification, however, increasingly threaten the continued health of these exceptional natural systems. New research on the population dynamics, ecosystem processes, biodiversity and resilience of coral reefs is critical to their successful management, conservation, and restoration. In addition to the benefits for research, the cyberinfrastructure upgrade will also promote advanced training in field science at the graduate and undergraduate level, benefiting students from universities and colleges from California, Hawaii and across the United States. Located in French Polynesia, the project will have the added benefit of providing international and multi-cultural experience for American scientists and students. The Gump Station has a strong outreach program through collaborations brokered by its partner local community organization: Association Te Pu Atitia. The upgrade will strengthen scientific research and education enabling the Gump Station and Te Pu Atitia to communicate these findings to communities in Moorea, Hawaii, California and elsewhere - particularly K-12 schools - working with partners to develop programs that reach out to historically underrepresented groups in science (including Polynesians and other Pacific Islanders).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Strategic facilities planning activities in 2014-2015 found that all current research and educational programs at the Gump Station had an urgent need for improved cyberinfrastructure to support their increasingly data-intensive science. The upgrade will improve overall cyberinfrastructure and particularly Internet access capacity, developing a comprehensive network that serves the entire campus. Fiber optic cabling will be installed to the Station's core research areas and its educational public outreach facility (the Atitia Cultural Center). The Gump Station will transition from multiple residential-style ADSL connections to a single Internet connection that will provide much better capacity to support using the Internet for collaborations and to upload data and video in real or near real time. The improvements will follow a typical design for a small campus network with a small border router to connect to the local Internet Service Provider and global Research and Education Networks, and a core router to move traffic between the various VLANs and buildings. The new network will be a traditional hub and spoke model using fiber to serve each of the core research and outreach sites. In addition, improvements to the wireless network will provide better and more reliable coverage across the Station.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1624860</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davies</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ndavies@moorea.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7593</Code>
      <Text>FIELD STATIONS AND MARINE LABS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
