<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SensorSpace: A Cutting-edge Facility for Environmental Sensor Design, Production, and Deployment for Research and Education at Flathead Lake Biological Station</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>413065</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter H. McCartney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Environmental scientists need access to sensitive and affordable environmental sensors in order study dynamic environments in lakes, streams, forests, grasslands, and other habitats. In the past, scientists have needed to rely on expensive commercial instruments or to settle for lower-quality sensors that they fabricate themselves. However, in recent years a "maker movement" has transformed access to sophisticated design and fabrication capabilities, leading to innovation in a variety of sectors. This grant will fund the creation of a ?maker space? for sensors at the University of Montana's Flathead Lake Biological Station that will serve as a regional and indeed national resource for environmental scientists and engineers to use to develop, fabricate, and test sophisticated instruments for their research and monitoring projects. The FLBS "Sensor Space" will also be a resource for members of the local and regional community (including tribal members) to use, empowering "citizen science" and inspiring students at various levels (K-12, college) to continue studies in science and engineering fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant will fund the creation of a sophisticated "maker space" for environmental sensor design, fabrication, and testing at the Flathead Lake Biological Station (FLBS) of the University of Montana, a world-renowned research and education center whose mission focus is limnology, the study of inland waters (http://flbs.umt.edu/). The proposed facility, which we call the "FLBS SensorSpace", will advance a variety of cutting-edge research areas, such as: novel networked sensors for high-resolution physiochemical monitoring; eDNA detection with automated in situ genomic analyzers; stream turbulence and bedload monitoring with acoustic profilers; single-cell genomics with microfluidic devices; high resolution ground-truthing of passive optical sensors; and in situ stream metabolism assessment from continuous physical-chemical profiling, to name a few. Four core technology zones will define the proposed FLBS SensorSpace: Manufacturing, Optics, Microfluidics, and Embedded Systems. In addition to these four core capacities, the facility will include a meeting space where researchers can work/teach/collaborate in a flexible manner, a computer terminal bench, a teaching/reading area, and a technology showcase display. This facility will advance ongoing and anticipated research at FLBS and help make the station a regional magnet for scientists and students interested in developing and field-testing customized sensor systems suited to their needs, ranging from the most basic to the most advanced capabilities currently available. The SensorSpace will also advance education, public appreciation of science, and commercial applications. This will occur via integration of the SensorSpace into the curricula of our summer course offerings and development of a new course, "Environmental Sensor Design and Production"; via collaboration with Salish Kootenai College; via programs for high school students; via efforts to establish a freestanding Citizen Science program at FLBS; and via use of the SensorSpace to attract environmental scientists, students, entrepreneurs, and businesses interested in developing sensors and other instrumentation as part of their research and development portfolio, leading to economic benefits and intellectual property.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1624837</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jim.elser@umontana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Montana</Name>
      <CityName>Missoula</CityName>
      <ZipCode>598120001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4062436670</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>32 CAMPUS DRIVE MAIN HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1104</Code>
      <Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1108</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
