<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo (ICME) 2016: Doctoral Symposium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant supports U.S. Ph.D. students to participate in the Student Program in IEEE ICME (International Conference on Multimedia and Expo) 2016 in Seattle. The support enables more graduate students to directly interact with senior researchers as well as their peers from diverse research institutions. This will provide important help to the graduate students at a critical stage of their development and advance the state of the art in multimedia technologies. The ICME 2016 Student Program provides an opportunity for Ph.D. students whose dissertations are on topics related to multimedia, to present their research and receive feedback from an invited committee of faculty and industry researchers and from other students working in the related area. It is aimed to provide students valuable exposure to outside perspectives on their work, a setting to discuss and fine-tune their career objectives, and to identify development needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since 2000, ICME has been the flagship multimedia conference sponsored by the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), serving as a forum to promote the exchange of the latest advances in multimedia technologies, systems, and applications from both the research and the development perspectives of four IEEE societies: Circuits and Systems, Communications, Computer, and Signal Processing. The topics of the conference span interdisciplinary areas including content analysis, activity and event understanding, search and retrieval, location-based media, social, user-generated and cloud-based media, immersion and VR/AR (Virtual Reality/Augmented Reality), security and forensics, multimodal interaction, networking and communication, signal processing, and systems and applications. With about 700 submissions and 500 participants each year, ICME has a highly selective acceptance rate: 15% for oral presentations and the next 15% for posters. Further information on the ICME 2016 Student Program can be found on the ICME 2016 web site (http://www.icme2016.org).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1624118</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ming-Ting</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sun@ee.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/02/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
