<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I/UCRC for Broadband Wireless Access and Applications Center Site at the Catholic University of America</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dmitri Perkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will support creating a new I/UCRC Site of Broadband Wireless Access and Applications Center (BWAC) at the Catholic University of America (CUA). The CUA Site will complement existing BWAC Center strengths to develop novel technologies in the wireless domain. The new site, in combination with the existing center, addresses a critical area of American economy, and has potential to increase the societal ability to access broadband wireless services and to support development of broadband wireless as a platform for innovation. The I/UCRC Site will help recruit diverse and promising students into the electrical engineering and computer science programs at CUA. Research related to wireless realm will be seamlessly integrated with education. By involving undergraduate and graduate students directly in the projects of actual interest to industry, the center will better prepare the students in their career development, and enhance the intellectual capacity of the engineering and science workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CUA Site will address the technical challenges of broadband wireless access and applications with an integrative approach, and conduct research in the areas of software defined wireless networks, mobile edge cloud, cognitive radio networks, dynamic spectrum sharing, millimeter wave antennas and networking systems, Internet of Things, and wireless and mobile applications. The cooperative research efforts at the CUA Site will potentially make impactful contributions to advance wireless technologies and applications, software and hardware components, and wireless standards.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1624485</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nader</FirstName>
      <LastName>Namazi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>namazi@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lin-Ching</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>changl@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liuh@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ozlem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kilic</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kilic@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Catholic University of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200640001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026355000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>620 Michigan Ave.N.E.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
