<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Gulf Coast Research Laboratory (GCRL) Museum Improvements and Modernization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>218726</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter H. McCartney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Natural history research collections provide vital references and resources for taxonomic, phylogenetic, ecological, natural disaster, invasive species, developmental, genetic and biodiversity research on an extraordinary diversity of animals, plants and other natural objects. Those collections allow researchers to examine a broader range of material, both geographically and temporally, at a substantially lower cost than would be possible if samples had to be obtained independently by the scientist. Such collections also contribute to the training of the next generation of graduate and undergraduate students, providing them with hands-on research experience and an understanding of current museum practices, and expose members of the public, K-12 students and their teachers to this type of research via tours, workshops and presentations. To best serve the scientific community, however, such collections must have carefully maintained, environmentally-controlled housing and must remain updated with the potential for expansion to meet the ongoing research needs of the community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Southern Mississippi's Gulf Coast Research Laboratory (GCRL; http://gcrl.usm.edu) is home to the GCRL Museum, which houses extensive ichthyological and invertebrate collections dating back to 1958. More than 36,500 lots of fish specimens, representing 3,400 species from 270 families, are catalogued within the Museum, as are 6,536 lots of invertebrate specimens. The facility serves as the primary repository for specimens obtained during ongoing local, national, and international research programs conducted at GCRL and at other institutions and provides support for regional and federal programs such as NOAA's SouthEast Area Monitoring and Assessment Program (SEAMAP). Current infrastructure and equipment for the Museum are outdated and do not support efficient maintenance or utilization of this vast collection. Improvements to the Museum will include renovation of current facilities: (a) to accommodate modern, space-efficient compactorized shelving units and (b) to integrate upgraded safety and containment systems. Renovated Museum facilities and associated storage efficiency will allow for a completely centralized collection of fish and invertebrate specimens that will aid in better internal management of the collection and foster increased use of the collection for academic and research purposes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1624688</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph (Read)</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hendon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Read.Hendon@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern Mississippi</Name>
      <CityName>Hattiesburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>394015876</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6012664119</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2609 WEST 4TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1104</Code>
      <Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
