<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Single-Crystal Diffractometer for Chemistry and Materials Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>268193</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) Program, the Chemistry Research Instrumentation (CRIF) Program as well as the Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR), Professor Sean Parkin from the University of Kentucky and colleagues John Anthony, Susan Odom, Edith Glazer and Oleg Tsodikov have acquired a microsource single crystal X-ray diffractometer equipped with a complementary metal oxide sensor (CMOS). X-ray diffraction is a powerful tool to investigate the atomic structure of solid materials. This tool is able to probe beneath the surface of compounds and materials. The knowledge of the underlying atomic structure of materials is fundamental to understanding their properties and developing improvements. Consequently, modern developments in the development of X-ray sources, detectors and computer technology have made X-ray diffractometers important for chemical and materials research. The applications of microscopic structural knowledge ranges across fields from chemistry to biology, materials and medicine, to applications such as developing better agrochemicals, electronic devices or pharmaceuticals and many others. This state-of-the-art system is used for teaching in a laboratory-based crystallography course, for class assignments in undergraduate inorganic chemistry teaching laboratories, as well as in ad-hoc training of Faculty, post-docs, students, visiting scholars, summer students, high-school senior interns, and students from UK's high-school STEAM academy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The acquisition of this diffractometer will advance research, especially in areas at the University of Kentucky such as (a) studies of organic electronic materials, (b) investigations of light-activated agents for gene regulation and cancer treatment, (c) design of energy storage materials and (d) analysis of biologically relevant natural products. It will also be used broadly in other varied research groups in departments of Chemistry, Physics, Biochemistry, Pharmacy, the Center for Advanced Materials (CAM), and the Center for Applied Energy Research (CAER) at the University as well as at other institutions in the region and out-of-state.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1625732</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Anthony</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anthony@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Parkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spark2@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edith</FirstName>
      <LastName>Glazer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ec.glazer@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Odom</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>susan.odom@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oleg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tsodikov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>oleg.tsodikov@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8396</Code>
      <Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8399</Code>
      <Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
