<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Accessible STEM Instruction with Deaf Students: Supporting Faculty in Pedagogical Exploration and Innovation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>156755</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lidia C. Yoshida</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project, developed by Rochester Institute of Technology (RIT), collaborating with the University of Texas at Austin, will explore existing strategies for effective access and inclusion in their courses with mixed groups of hearing and deaf and hard of hearing (DHH) students, and develop new strategies of effective, accessible and inclusive instruction. A significant aspect of this project is the development of an Accessibility ToolKit, a set of inclusive instructional materials, strategies, and discussions. Such tools and strategies will be beneficial to diverse groups of learners, not only for DHH students. This project will serve the national interest of effective and inclusive education of DHH students in STEM fields, leading to successful degree attainment, and an increase in the diversity of STEM graduates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project goals are: (1) to increase access, engagement and academic success of DHH students taking postsecondary courses at RIT via the creation, implementation, and evaluation of an Accessibility ToolKit for evidence-based educational approaches in STEM disciplines; (2) to create training environments where faculty experiment with and innovate new resources and strategies for accessible and inclusive pedagogy, through collaborative professional development and assessment of evidence-based strategies; and (3) to document and disseminate the ToolKit and processes so that they may be applied to other populations of postsecondary students with disabilities. Results will examine best practices that promote faculty adoption of these instructional strategies to maximize learning for students with other diverse learning needs, and the impact of such adaptations on inclusive teaching and student engagement. This project will broaden the scope and use of accessible and inclusive strategies to increase DHH student engagement and to address communication and learning needs in STEM classrooms.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1625846</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cawthon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stephanie.cawthon@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1998</Code>
      <Text>IUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8209</Code>
      <Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
