<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectrometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>527275</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) and support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Program (CRIF), Professor Michael Doyle from the University of Texas San Antonio (UTSA) has acquired a 500 MHz NMR spectrometer equipped with a broadband probe. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as the study of biologically-relevant species. In general, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists to determine the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the changing interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. The results from these NMR studies have an impact in synthetic organic/inorganic chemistry, materials chemistry and biochemistry. This instrument is located a general user facility managed by highly qualified scientists and is an integral part of research, research training and teaching in the Departments of Chemistry and Biochemistry at this institution. The spectrometer helps in the overall university mission by providing students in South Texas with NMR knowledge and enabling their success in the chemical/engineering workforce. Several other regional universities: Texas Lutheran University, St. Mary's University, TAMU Kingsville and the University of Incarnate Word also use the instrument through collaborations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels, especially in: (a) synthesizing heterocyclic compounds enantioselectively; (b) exploring new catalytic approaches to the highly stereoselective syntheses of structurally complex organic compounds; (c) characterizing the dynamic conformational changes of proteins; (d) exploring bioinorganic chemical catalysis, and (e) synthesizing and biophysically understanding biomaterials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1625963</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Doyle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael.doyle@UTSA.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
      <CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782499113</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
