<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a Cloud Based Instrument for Heterogeneous Biomedical Body Sensor Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399898</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project, developing a cloud-based instrument, aims to aggregate data driven from an array of body sensors. The instrument can be used in a wide range of wearable sensor-based medical applications. The proponents investigate research challenges focused on Biomedical Body Sensor Data Acquisition, Transmission, and Analysis. Recent advances in cloud computing and sensor technologies have made feasible to develop a software instrument that is able to integrate all aspects of heterogeneous biomedical body sensor systems, from sensor data preprocessing, transmission, and critical event detection at sensor side, to data reliability evaluation and enhancement, data analysis, sensor control at data aggregator (usually a smart phone or PC), and finally data storage, retrieval, and further extensive analysis at the cloud server. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Build jointly with UT-Dallas, the instrument development includes: 1. Android developing; 2. Mobile cloud computing; 3. Cloud infrastructure and set up; 4. Cloud API and Sensor side APUI; 5. Reliability Enhancement, and 6. Event detection. Its major components include: 1. A cloud cluster to support data storage/indexing analysis; 2. APIs for sensor side data preprocessing, critical event detection, and transmission strategies based on open source platform TinyOS; 3. Mobile App development ; and 4. API for sensor data access and analysis algorithms evaluation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1626586</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mingli@csufresno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State University-Fresno Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Fresno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>937261852</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5592780840</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4910 N. Chestnut Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
