<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a sputtering deposition system to expand science and engineering research at Utah State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>144918</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Chengshan Xiao</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Thin films of various metallic and insulating materials of a few-nanometer thick are widely used in devices and sensors. At present, Utah State University (USU), a land-grant university of more than 28,000 students, has no thin film deposition system that can perform a uniform thin-film deposition across a 4-in wafer. The fact that the existing small evaporator can only deposit low-melting point metals, such as aluminum and gold, severely limits the research capability at Utah State University. This proposal is to acquire an advanced sputtering deposition system which will provide crucial improvements include: (1) substrate holder for a 4-in wafer, (2) substrate heater up to 800 °C, (3) sufficient power to sputter high-melting point metals, magnetic materials, and dielectric materials, and (4) a load-lock to improve through-put and film quality. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed sputtering deposition system will enable a broad range of funded transformative research at USU including: (1) carbon-nanotube-based radiometer for unprecedented accuracy on measuring radiation for monitoring global warming and calibrate laser power. (2) Depositing catalytic nano-particles on patterned carbon-nanotube sidewalls for CO2 capture to help mitigate climate changes and conversion to useful chemicals such as methanol. (3) Depositing dielectrics and growing graphene patterns for the fabrication of intelligent antennas for next generation of cognitive wireless communication. (4) Fabricating titanium oxide nano-structures to investigate cell behavior affected by nanotopography. (5) Depositing thin film of cobalt and phosphorous to enhance electrocatalytic water splitting for high-energy-density chemical fuels. (6) Depositing nickel and alumina thin films to investigate nanoparticles self-assembled by solid-liquid interface instability for optoelectronics and magnetic data storage. (7) Depositing various oxide and carbide thin films to investigate electrical charging, deposition and electron transport in multi-layered samples to mitigate electrostatic discharge damage to spacecraft and power grid. More innovative research will be supported since the tool is only limited by the targets available from suppliers around the globe. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this tool should be assessed by the synergy with other tools at NDL as a whole. The proposed sputter coater will be integrated into NDL which has been serving the research needs of faculty from at least 5 departments in Colleges of Engineering and Science. Approximate 30 graduate and undergraduate students from the 6 profiled major research groups are expected to be trained and using this tool with other tools at NDL for their research. This tool is also planned to be involved in the capstone and senior research projects (~20 students/yr) in 4 engineering classes and a laboratory module for two microfabrication classes (~30 student/yr). In addition to offering advanced training for university students, NDL participates in many activities organized by various units of USU for disseminating new science and technology to the general public. The expanded research capability brought by the proposed tool will also help academia-industry partnership such as the existing SBIR and STTR programs with Box Elder Innovations, LAM Research, Ball aerospace, and Orbital Sciences, among others.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1626344</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tsung-Cheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tc.shen@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anhong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Anhong.Zhou@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bedri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cetiner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bedri.cetiner@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas A.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roberts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nick.roberts@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yujie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yujie.sun@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Utah State University</Name>
      <CityName>Logan</CityName>
      <ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
