<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2016 Biomedical Engineering Society Annual Meeting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michele Grimm</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1628291-Hart &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF has made an award to support travel costs and registration fees for undergraduate students (17), graduate students (5), postdoctoral fellows (2) and early career faculty members (2) who will be attending the 2016 Annual Meeting of the Biomedical Engineering Society (BMES) that will be held in Minneapolis, MN, October 5-8, 2016. The meeting will feature 19 Program Tracks with the theme "Transforming Discovery into Technology for Human Health." Approximately 800 oral presentations, 1600 poster presentations and over 4,000 participants are anticipated. The BMES Annual Meeting serves as a primary vehicle for scientific sharing and dissemination of the latest advances in biomedical engineering, as well as a facilitator of important cross-fertilizations between the life sciences and engineering technologies, which foster a multi-disciplinary approach in the practice of Biomedical Engineering. The travel awards will afford the opportunity for young investigators and investigators from underrepresented groups to attend the Annual Meeting, be informed on the latest scientific and technological advances in Biomedical Engineering, and help support BMES members involved in research and training focused on health disparities and minority health.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1628291</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hart.322@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Biomedical Engineering Society</Name>
      <CityName>Landover</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207852224</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014591999</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8201 Corporate Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
