<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Conference on Music Perception and Cognition</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8793</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Betty H. Tuller</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Conference on Music Perception and Cognition (ICMPC) is an interdisciplinary conference devoted to the dissemination of new, unpublished research relating to the neuroscientific, psychological, and computational bases of music perception and cognition. Founded in 1989, ICMPC is an international collective made up of research societies from different parts of the world, including the Society for Music Perception and Cognition in North America, the European Society for the Cognitive Sciences of Music, and the Asia-Pacific Society for the Cognitive Sciences of Music.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will provide support for a number of graduate students to attend the International Conference on Music Perception and Cognition (ICMPC), to be held July 5-9, 2016 at the University of California San Francisco (UCSF). Awardees will be enrolled in a Ph.D. program at a U.S. institution and will present their work at the ICMPC. Awardees will be selected to enrich the diversity of the conference in terms of geographical, cultural, and ethnic backgrounds and gender balance. ICMPC will host a lunch for all award recipients to meet and network with the keynote speakers and other award recipients.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1632014</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zanto</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Theodore.Zanto@ucsf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Francisco</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941034249</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4154762977</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1855 Folsom St Ste 425</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7252</Code>
      <Text>PERCEPTION, ACTION &amp; COGNITION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7252</Code>
      <Text>Perception, Action and Cognition</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
