<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RII Track-2 FEC: Probing and Understanding the Brain: Micro and Macro Dynamics of Seizure and Memory Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01060100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>robert coyne</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-technical Description&lt;br/&gt;Twelve researchers across three institutions in three states (Louisiana, Arkansas, and Alabama) will collaborate on this brain research, and develop a foundation for the region as a hub for interdisciplinary, collaborative research activity in the neurosciences. This work will focus on understanding the initiation of epileptic brain seizures and longer-term impacts on brain function such as memory. Epileptic seizures directly impact roughly 1% of humans, and have indirect impacts on loved ones and caregivers as well as economic impacts on society. Epilepsy has been called a ?window to brain function? because the condition impairs different brain functions depending on the location of the seizure in the brain and the impacted network of neurons, and because it provides a unique opportunity to study an impaired brain?s function over time and space. The project will develop minimally invasive implantable sensors that can be used for monitoring before, during, and for several months following seizure events. Researchers will relate changes occurring during seizure events with those observed in the intervals between events. The project includes hiring four new faculty, design and purchase of equipment, development of new undergraduate and graduate courses, recruitment and training of a diverse student population to better reflect the regional community, and new student research and workforce opportunities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description &lt;br/&gt;The activities of the team across three institutions (Louisiana Tech University, the University of Arkansas, and the University of Alabama) are organized under four thrust areas that focus on recording and analysis of electrical activity, magnetic activity, neurochemical and optical signals, and memory function of the brain. A series of coordinated and synergistic investigations will be conducted using innovative methods and tools designed to probe brain function at the molecular, cellular, and macro levels in epileptic rats and human subjects. Patients with focal epilepsy, during their presurgical evaluation, will undergo implantation of intracranial electroencephalographic (iEEG) electrodes for subsequent long-term (days) recording and monitoring of their spontaneous seizures. Non-invasive magnetoencephalographic (MEG) imaging is also used to provide important complementary information on the electromagnetic activity of the brain. This collaboration will advance research and also result in the creation of unique databases of human and animal data from the participating institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1632891</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>DeCoster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>decoster@latech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tmurray@latech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonidas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Iasemidis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leonidas@latech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jerzy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Szaflarski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>szaflaj@uab.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>L. John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Greenfield</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>LJGreenfield@uams.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/16/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Larson-Prior</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>LJLarsonPrior@uams.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana Tech University</Name>
      <CityName>Ruston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>712723178</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3182575075</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O BOX 3168 TECH STATION</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7217</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
