<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Investigator Travel Awards for OHBM 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>27077</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alumit Ishai</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Organization for Human Brain Mapping (OHBM) is the primary international organization dedicated to non-invasive neuroimaging research and the functional organization of the human brain. The Annual Meeting of OHBM is regarded as the premier venue for the integration of innovative brain imaging methods and cognitive neuroscience, and has emerged to address the need of the brain-mapping scientific community for a forum to disseminate findings and enable interactions among scientists investigating the functional organization of the brain with emerging imaging-based methods. Since 1994, the OHBM has sponsored twenty-one highly successful meetings, where attendees are exposed to cutting-edge neuroimaging data acquisition methods, emerging approaches to large-scale neuroimaging data analysis, the visualization of results, and their applications in health and disease. This award will fund travel awards for deserving students and trainees to attend the 2016 Annual Meeting to be held in Geneva, Switzerland. Travel awards will be given to the 25 students with the highest-ranked abstracts. Of these at least 15 travel awards will be awarded to the students with the top-ranked abstracts among 3 targeted groups (women, minorities, disabled). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Annual Meeting provides a means for students of neuroimaging to attend educational courses, hear lectures from leading brain researchers, form new collaborations, and to present their original research. Historically, female representation in the mathematical and computational sciences has been low. In contrast, in both neuroscience and psychology it has been relatively very high. Hence, the ability to work in the cross-section of statistics, computer-science, psychology, and neuroscience promises to provide computational training to a diverse audience and help bridge the gender gaps in the STEM fields. In addition, improved understanding of the organization of the human brain is directly relevant to treating neurological and psychiatric disease, and the use of non-invasive imaging methods is increasingly important to translational investigation and training in clinical neuroscience. As neuroimaging is used in a wide-range of scientific disciplines, we would expect benefits for society in areas ranging from economic and social policies to medical, educational and psychological interventions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1633160</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lindquist</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mal@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1699</Code>
      <Text>COGNEURO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1699</Code>
      <Text>COGNEURO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
