<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: An Investigation of Factors that Influence African Americans' Entrepreneurship in STEM Fields</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20112</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maryann Feldman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Minority business entrepreneurship, specifically in the areas of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) provides multiple opportunities for innovation, job creation, high earning potential, and for increasing the diversity of the U.S. workforce to reflect current population demographics. The purpose of this dissertation research is to understand the factors of STEM programs that influence STEM-educated African American graduates to pursue high tech entrepreneurship. Currently, there is evidence that while the U. S. has experienced growth in the number of African American entrepreneurs, this growth has not occurred in STEM fields, which are highly linked to high tech firms. Knowledge about African American STEM entrepreneurship is limited, as current data sets captures minimal information on the background or education of entrepreneurs. This research aims to fill that gap by analyzing administrative and survey data collected from STEM program alliances (collaborations between multiple colleges/universities) across the country. A greater understanding of which factors in education influence African Americans to pursue entrepreneurship can provide empirical data to guide policies and programs that encourage and support African Americans in STEM, allow for the modification or re-evaluation of existing programs, and promote the linking of entrepreneurial activities with STEM-support programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research identifies what educational experiences predict African American entrepreneurship in STEM fields by reviewing existing STEM-support programs. The review of these programs and their components such as social networking, mentoring, role models, and financial support, allows identification of bridging factors which encourage entrepreneurship, as well as to what degree knowledge about entrepreneurship is provided. The results of a quantitative analysis of survey data from undergraduate and graduate STEM-support programs as well as business owner characteristics aims to reveal the relationship between these factors and entrepreneurship in STEM fields. These results can be used to determine which factors are more likely to cultivate entrepreneurship among African Americans.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1633305</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Colleen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Casey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>colleenc@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zoranna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zoranna.jones@mavs.uta.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7009</Code>
      <Text>SciSIP-DDRIG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8050</Code>
      <Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
