<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Rail Infrastructure and the Emergence of National Identity and the Nation-State</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Holly Hapke</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This doctoral dissertation research project will analyze the role of rail infrastructure in the formation of territory at the scale of the nation. The research will address how the structures of rail stations and carriages, along with the practices and behaviors of travelers and personnel, contribute to the production of national spaces and national communities and are used by the State as a means of political unification. Railways have served to bind nations together for more than a century and have contributed to the development of nationalism in many countries. This was true for the United States in the past and continues to be true for other developing states. This research project will contribute to basic understanding of the nation, nation-building, and nationalism by incorporating the role of material infrastructure like rail into conceptualizations of the nation. Rail infrastructure is thus one important means through which the nation becomes imaginable through the people and places it connects. The specific process by which this is takes place and the implications for national identity and state-making are the focus of this research project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The historical prominence of rail travel in China, combined with the system's significant expansion in recent decades, makes China an ideal location to examine the impact of rail on society. The increasing salience of nationalism in China also makes this research timely. This research is driven by questions such as: 1) How is the Chinese rail network constituted and reproduced through both its material infrastructure and everyday practices of passengers and railway personnel? 2) How have planners and users conceptualized the Chinese rail network over time? How do these concepts manifest as representations materially embedded in the rail spaces? 3) How do rail spaces contribute to materializing the Chinese nation? The project will adopt a two-pronged approach coupling 'top-down' geographic information systems (GIS) analysis of spatial integration and population circulation, with a 'bottom-up' traveling ethnography of rail spaces (trains and stations) and the people within them. This will allow the investigators to identify the concrete mechanisms through which rail exerts a nation-building force on territory and society without losing sight of rail as a single coherent system. Geo-spatial analysis will show where and how the network has served to integrate China's vast territory at the national scale, while also identifying points of shear where some areas become relatively isolated. The ethnography, which treats the whole rail system as a single dispersed, infrastructural 'field site,' will show how rail spaces are designed, structured, and maintained in standardized ways across the country, and also investigate the myriad ways they are put into use by savvy rail travelers. This research will produce a multi-scalar account of the impacts of rail infrastructure on material processes of territory-making and nation-building in today's China, which will contribute broadly to the theorization of nation and infrastructure and methodologies for studying human/infrastructural assemblages. Understanding the roots of contemporary Chinese nationalism may also inform U.S. international policy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1634029</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dylan P</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brady</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbrady@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buck</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>danielb@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
