<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Enhancements to the OOI Cabled Array at Axial Seamount</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>178060</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Deborah Smith</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Part of the Ocean Observatories Initiative (OOI) is a cabled observatory in the northeast Pacific Ocean that extends offshore to Axial Seamount, an active submarine volcano that has frequent eruptions, hydrothermal vent fields, and unique deep-sea ecosystems. Because it is so active and accessible, Axial Seamount has been a long-term study site and monitoring has revealed a cycle of volcano inflation and deflation that has been used to forecast eruptions with increasing accuracy. This project will enhance the OOI Cabled Array at Axial Seamount by adding instruments with the capability to detect changes in hydrothermal output in the summit caldera, and to ground movements at the volcano, which will in turn improve eruption forecasts. These enhancements to the monitoring effort at Axial Seamount will help to increase our understanding of magma storage systems at active volcanoes, the processes that lead to and trigger eruptions, and the impacts of submarine eruptions on hydrothermal systems and the deep-sea ecosystems they sustain. A teacher will participate on the research cruise to deploy the instruments, and the teacher will interact with classrooms before, during, and after the research cruise. Public lectures at the Hatfield Marine Science Visitor Center in Newport, OR will include results from this project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2015 eruption at Axial Seamount was the first detected in real time by the OOI Cabled Array. Although it captured the event in unprecedented detail, it also showed that there are some key observations missing from the instrument network that limited understanding of the eruption and its consequences. This project will make the following targeted and timely additions to the cabled observatory: (1) one new seafloor CTD (Conductivity, Temperature, Depth) instrument to add critical salinity measurements, which are currently lacking but are needed to test the hypothesis that hydrothermal brine is released from the crust during seafloor eruptions, and (2) one bottom pressure/tilt instrument that has already been built and paid for. In addition, four autonomous (non-cabled) miniature pressure recorders will be built and an acoustic release transducer will be purchased to be used on an existing autonomous bottom pressure recording mooring. These instruments will enhance the spatial and temporal monitoring of volcanic deformation of the seafloor and the modeling of its causes in the subsurface.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1634150</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chadwick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bill.chadwick@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7398</Code>
      <Text>OCEAN OBSERVATORY SCI &amp; TECH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
