<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Metabolic Engineering 11 Conference, June 26-30, 2016; Kobe, Japan</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Theresa Good</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1634294 &lt;br/&gt;Gill, Ryan T. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal seeks support for the 11th International Conference on Metabolic Engineering (ME11) to be held at the Awaji Yumebutai International Conference Center in Kobe, Japan. The Metabolic Engineering Conference is a leading conference for sharing the state-of-the-art developments and achievements made in the field of metabolic engineering over the last two years. The theme of this year's conference is Design, Synthesis and System Integration for Metabolic Engineering. The Conference is one of the first among several conference series related to biotechnology that started 20 years ago as an Engineering Foundation conference with focus on recombinant DNA technology. It has been the first conference with explicit focus on the application of recombinant DNA technology to the engineering of microorganisms for industrial processes. This metabolic engineering relies now on the tools commonly referred to as synthetic biology and systems biology. This conference has been instrumental in addressing issues contemporary to technological advancements, engineering research and to education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scope of this international conference is to bring together influential established researchers, young investigators, industrial researchers and practitioners, and graduate students to assess the contributions and future opportunities of metabolic engineering with focus on biological design and synthesis. The support will enable attendance by graduate students, postdocs, academic scientists and engineers and industrial researchers that will benefit from interactions with the international community of biotechnology researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Due to the interdisciplinary nature of the Conference, the award by the Biotechnology and Biochemical Engineering Program of the CBET Division is co-funded by the Systems and Synthetic Biology Program of the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1634294</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rtg@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gabriel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Levesque-Tremblay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gabrl@aiche.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Institute of Chemical Engineers</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100054020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6464951350</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>120 Wall Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1491</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8011</Code>
      <Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>144E</Code>
      <Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
