<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Advance of the Algorithmic Frontier and the Evolution of Work: A Workshop to Explore Public Policy Implications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49011</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maryann Feldman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop advances the science of science and innovation policy by linking basic research in an array of disciplines to urgent public policy questions related to the changing nature of work. The workshop advances the development of the research community focused on understanding more fully the nature of production of societal value. The workshop introduces new data and research-based insights into policy debates about the future of work. The workshop nurtures a new data and structure rich analysis that have the potential to improve science and innovation policy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The production algorithm refers to the processes for turning ideas into goods and services. A culinary recipe is an example: it is a means for turning ingredients into a meal. The advance of the algorithmic frontier refers to improvements in production algorithms that occur over time. This workshop brings together a multi-disciplinary team of researchers involved with the relationship between the advance of the algorithmic frontier, the changing nature of human work and the potential for inclusive opportunity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1636453</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Auerswald</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pauerswa@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/11/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Mason University</Name>
      <CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7626</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
