<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Graduate Student Participation in National Workshops to Encourage Women's Engagement in Mathematics Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49962</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports graduate student participation at four workshops presented by the Association for Women in Mathematics (AWM) during major US mathematics meetings in 2016-2018. These meetings are the annual meeting of the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics in 2016 (held in Boston, MA) and 2017 (held in Pittsburgh, PA), and the Joint Mathematics Meetings in 2017 (held in Atlanta, GA) and 2018 (held in San Diego, CA). These Meetings Workshops will bring the rising women stars and current mathematical leaders together with graduate students and recent graduates from a variety of fields in pure and applied mathematics. By creating a rich intellectual community centered on shared research interests, the activities promise to generate new mentoring relations, new research collaborations, and increased activity in the associated research areas. Such relationships can lead to a lifetime of professional success. Moreover, these events at highly visible national meetings benefit the entire mathematical community by showcasing the excellent mathematical work done by women.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each Meetings Workshop has a research focus derived from a prior AWM Research Collaboration Workshop, a week-long event where participants work together on open research problems. At the Meetings Workshops, leaders in each research field will introduce younger mathematicians to a deeper understanding of the field and its connections with their own work. Graduate students will, in turn, share their research during poster sessions and small group interactions. The research topics that will be highlighted in the next four workshops include Dynamical Systems with applications to Medical Problems; Number Theory; Numerical Partial Differential Equations; and Noncommutative Algebra. These topics span a broad spectrum of current mathematical problems, and will correspondingly enhance the future careers of many young women mathematicians. For more information on the first two conferences, please see https://sites.google.com/site/awmmath/programs/workshops/SIAM-workshop and https://sites.google.com/site/awmmath/programs/workshops/jmm-workshop. This award is jointly funded by the Infrastructure, Algebra and Number Theory, Mathematical Biology, and Computational Mathematics Programs within the NSF Division of Mathematical Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1636610</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leonard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kathryn.leonard@csuci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ami</FirstName>
      <LastName>Radunskaya</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aer04747@pomona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Magnhild</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lien</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>magnhild.lien@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Association For Women in Mathematics</Name>
      <CityName>Fairfax</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220306078</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039340163</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11240 Waples Mill Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7334</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
