<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BD Spokes: SPOKE: MIDWEST: Collaborative: Advanced Computational Neuroscience Network (ACNN)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>164912</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Fen Zhao</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Novel neuroscience tools and techniques are necessary to enable insight into the building blocks of neural circuits, the interactions between these circuits that underpin the functions of the human brain, and modulation of these circuits that affect our behavior. To leverage rapid technological development in sensing, imaging, and data analysis new ground breaking advances in neuroscience are necessary to facilitate knowledge discovery using data science methods. To address this societal grand challenge, the project will foster new interdisciplinary collaborations across computing, biological, mathematical, and behavioral science disciplines together with partnerships in academia, industry, and government at multiple levels. The Big Data Neuroscience Spoke titled Midwest: Advanced Computational Neuroscience Network (ACNN) is strongly aligned with the national priority area of neuroscience and brings together a diverse set of committed regional partners to enable the Midwest region to realize the promise of Big Data for neuroscience. The ACNN Spoke will build broad consensus on the core requirements, infrastructure, and components needed to develop a new generation of sustainable interdisciplinary Neuroscience Big Data research. ACNN will leverage the strengths and resources in the Midwest region to increase innovation and collaboration for the understanding of the structure, physiology, and function of the human brain through partnerships and services in education, tools, and best practices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ACNN will design, pilot and support powerful neuroscientific computational resources for high-throughput, collaborative, and service-oriented data aggregation, processing and open-reproducible science. The ACNN Spoke framework will address three specific problems related to neuroscience Big Data: (1) data capture, organization, and management involving multiple centers and research groups, (2) quality assurance, preprocessing and analysis that incorporates contextual metadata, and (3) data communication to software and hardware computational resources that can scale with the volume, velocity, and variety of neuroscience datasets. The ACNN will build a sustainable ecosystem of neuroscience community partners in both academia and industry using existing technologies for collaboration and virtual meeting together with face-to-face group meetings. The planned activities of the ACNN Spoke will also allow the Midwest Big Data Hub to disseminate additional Big Data technologies resources to the neuroscience community, including access to supercomputing facilities, best practices, and platforms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award received co-funding from CISE Divisions of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (ACI) and Information and Intelligent Systems (IIS).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1636850</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Satya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sahoo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>satya.sahoo@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>024Y</Code>
      <Text>BD Spokes -Big Data Regional I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>028Z</Code>
      <Text>BD Spokes Full Awards</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8083</Code>
      <Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8089</Code>
      <Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
