<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Environmental Education Workshop for Wisconsin Institutions of Higher Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>134400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julia Clark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will advance efforts of the Innovative Technology Experiences for Students and Teachers (ITEST) program to better understand and promote practices that increase students' motivations and capacities to pursue careers in fields of science, technology, engineering, or mathematics (STEM) by engaging in hands-on field experience, laboratory/project-based entrepreneurship tasks and mentorship experiences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Wisconsin-Oshkosh aims to conduct an Environmental Education Workshop for Wisconsin Institutions of Higher Education to support the improvement of environmental education instruction for preservice students in the state's public and private teacher education programs. The objectives are to (1) develop a shared vision for what environmental education should be for all teacher preparation programs in Wisconsin; (2) produce 20 environmental education instructional activities for middle and high school preservice teachers that integrate traditionally separate disciplines; and 3) bring the strengths and expertise of faculty from different institutions together to collaboratively offer new learning opportunities about environmental education for students now and in the future. The project offers a 3-day, Environmental Education workshop to faculty from all 33 public and private teacher preparation programs in Wisconsin. Two individuals in different licensure program or content areas from each institution will be invited to participate (66 participants total). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The three- day workshop that will help determine a shared vision for how to include environmental education in teacher preparation programs (a legal requirement within the state) and produce deliverables (20 environmental education instructional activities) that may be used in programs for middle and high school preservice teachers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1638420</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beeth</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>beeth@uwosh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Oshkosh</Name>
      <CityName>Oshkosh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>549013551</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9204241415</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 Algoma Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7227</Code>
      <Text>ITEST</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
