<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR: Exhibiting Intuitive Touch Feedback for Virtual Reality</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will be seen across a broad number of applications. These applications include virtual reality and video games, as well as, physically interacting with computer-aided design (CAD) or medical models; creating interactive chemistry models; experiencing physics simulations; bringing engineering curriculum for STEM (Science Technology Engineering Math) training to life; and better connecting a surgeon to a medical procedure during minimally invasive surgery. Imagine if instead of interacting with a CAD or molecular model with a computer mouse, it was inexpensive enough that you could use the developed haptic device to grab the model within a 3D environment and pull on it to feel the strength of fasteners or molecular bonds. While these interactions can already be portrayed with desktop interfaces like Novint?s Falcon force feedback device, our technology could do this at a much lower price point and could also be used in large workspace applications like playing video games or exploring in VR a home living room. This project will also contribute to the understanding of the human perception of touch. This project relates to the technology area of ?Human Assistive Technologies and Bio-related Robotics? and the consumer electronics market segment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to meet the market demand for intuitive, immersive, and inexpensive haptic technologies. This demand has been fueled by the renewed interest in virtual reality (VR) with the availability of inexpensive 3-dimentional (3D) head-mounted displays (HMDs). Current haptic interfaces are either too expensive and have limited workspaces or are too crude to portray force/torque interactions. The company hypothesizes that it can create an ungrounded haptic motion controller that can emulate force feedback at a price that will be viable for consumer virtual reality. This research will utilize tactile shear feedback within the handle of a game controller interface. Actuators within the controller will apply friction and shear forces to the user?s hand, which will in turn be driven based on simulated interaction forces from a VR physics engine. This will create an integrated haptic experience that will connect the user to the virtual environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1638511</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Provancher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>AOR@tacticalhaptics.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tactical Haptics</Name>
      <CityName>Fremont</CityName>
      <ZipCode>945553638</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5105161494</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>34531 Heathrow Ter</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1385</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL STUDIES AND ANALYSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6840</Code>
      <Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8035</Code>
      <Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9139</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
