<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Group Travel to the XXXIV SCAR Open Science Conference, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>84987</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julie Palais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Wilson/1639838&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports attendance for up to 45 U.S. scientists at the 34th SCAR Open Science Conference (OSC) to enable them to present their scientific findings, develop new collaborations with international scientists and become involved in SCAR-related activities and SCAR specialists groups. In previous symposia, U.S. scientists have made important and significant contributions to the success of the SCAR Open Science Conferences. The SCAR-OSC provides a key platform for generating or augmenting international collaborations not generally available for graduate students and early-career researchers. The 34th SCAR-OSC meeting, Antarctica in the Global Earth System: From the Poles to the Tropics, will be held 22-26 August 2016 in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scientific program for the SCAR Open Science Conference emphasizes interdisciplinary research that places Antarctica and the Southern Ocean in a global context, providing essential perspective for students and early-career researchers. In addition to the five multi-disciplinary mini symposia there are 41 sessions that include research about the Antarctic and Southern Ocean climate evolution, ice-sheet, glacial and subglacial dynamics, diversity and evolution of life and its unique ecosystems, atmospheric, astrophysical and astronomical observations, surface processes and landscapes, observations of the cryosphere and biota responses to global weather and climate changes, among others. This support will allow a more diverse group of researchers to participate in defining the future direction of international Antarctic research and will encourage global collaboration and cooperation. It will augment the training and development of graduate students and young investigators as they benefit from the opportunity to interact with the international community of Antarctic researchers. Individuals at all levels (students to senior researchers) interested in engaging in international collaborative activities and, potentially, assuming active leadership roles in SCAR groups, will be targeted for support. The Association of Polar Early Career Scientists (APECS), an international organization that aims to facilitate interdisciplinary research collaborations and develop future leaders in polar research, education and outreach, will have a one-day career development workshop available for early-career researchers at the 34th SCAR Open Science Conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1639838</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cristina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Millan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>millan.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>twilson@mps.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1647</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC INSTRUM &amp; SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5111</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC ORGANISMS &amp; ECOSYST</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5112</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC EARTH SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5113</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5115</Code>
      <Text>Antarctic Astrophys&amp;Geosp Sci</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5116</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC GLACIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5292</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC INTEGRATED SYS SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
