<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT: Development of a Portable Sensor for Rapid Detection of Crop Infections</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Accelerating Innovation Research Technology Translation project focuses on translating a novel biosensor technology into a proof-of-concept for an early stage prototype for direct screening of vegetative crop diseases. The innovation addresses an important and unmet need in the agricultural industry, as there is no early crop disease detection tool presently available in the market. The technology focuses on the development of an enzyme based electro-chemical biosensor for highly selective, ultra-low level detection of volatile markers released by plants during pathogen infections. Currently used methods for disease detection in agricultural crops are time consuming, destructive, demand skilled analysts, and do not offer real time monitoring or on-field deployment possibilities. A rapid, real-time, non-destructive, ex-situ method for early detection of infections will help crop producers to locate and contain the infection, prevent the spread of disease, spray chemicals selectively and timely and hence avoid colossal crop damage. The proposed technology could fundamentally transform the approach towards disease management and precision agriculture. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gap(s) as it translates from fundamental discovery to a proof-of-concept an early stage prototype: (1) Development of paper based sensor strips using ink-jet printing with multilayered biosensor platform. (2) Testing and evaluating paper based sensor strips using real volatile organic compounds released by diseased plants. In addition, the project will provide entrepreneurship and technology transition training to a post-doctoral research assistant.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1640608</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ramaraja</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ramasamy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rama@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
