<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: 2016 Ciliate Molecular Biology Conference to be held at the Orlando World Center Marriott in Orlando, FL on July 13-17, 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen C. Cone</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will support attendance by early career researchers at the Ciliate Molecular Biology Conference to be held in conjunction with The Allied Genetics Conference (TAGC) at the Orlando World Center Marriott in Orlando, FL on July 13-17, 2016. The format of the meeting is a combination of talks and posters, which will promote scientific exchange in both formal and informal settings. A number of activities are aimed at professional development and mentoring for early career scientists. There will be ample opportunity for sharing latest research results and for exploring STEM career possibilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research on ciliates has led to key discoveries and established new biological paradigms such as self-splicing RNAs, telomeres and telomerase, and the role of histone modifications in gene expression. More recent studies have provided novel insights into the role of RNA interference related pathways and non-coding RNAs in the epigenetic regulation of the programmed chromosome rearrangements and the function of post-translational tubulin modification. The unusual biology of ciliated protozoa (e.g., the presence of two functionally distinct nuclei in each cell, complex cytoskeleton and abundant cilia) and innovative research approaches provide researchers unique opportunities to gain mechanistic understanding of major biological processes. Cutting-edge and late-breaking research will be highlighted in short talks chosen from the abstracts and in posters. Being part of TAGC will offer the ciliate community to reach out to other model organism communities to educate them about ciliates and to establish new connections and potential educational and research collaborations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1640853</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Winey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>winey@beagle.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
