<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT: High Efficiency Ultraviolet Light Emitting Diodes Based on Tunneling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating highly efficient ultraviolet light emitters into compact, ultraviolet (UV) light emitting diodes (LEDs). There is a strong market and societal need for efficient UV LEDs for air and water purification, food sterilization, and biomedical and security applications that require compact ultra-violet sources, both in the developed and developing world. These UV LEDs can enable compact, low-cost, and environmentally safe water and air disinfection systems for a variety of applications. This project will result in a prototype of a highly efficient ultraviolet LED with a unique feature, tunneling injected diode structure, that enables significantly higher efficiency, higher power, and lower cost, when compared to leading competitors in this market space. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gap(s) as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application. The main challenges to realizing highly efficient tunneling injected ultraviolet light emitters are the low internal quantum efficiency and the low light extraction efficiency. The project will address both of these. Firstly, investigators will study optimization of the light emitters through rigorous experiments studies to improve internal quantum efficiency. Secondly, a careful study of methods to improve the light extraction efficiency will be carried out. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, personnel involved in this project, graduate and undergraduate students, will receive innovation and technology translation experiences through their work in developing the high efficiency prototype, and being involved in patenting of intellectual property.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1640700</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Luo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>luo.571@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Siddharth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rajan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rajan@ece.osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
