<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: N2Women Student Travel Support for the 2016 SIGCOMM Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6250</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is for conference travel support and proposes to provide travel support for under-represented graduate students to attend the Networking for Networking Women (N2Women) event and SIGCOMM 2016. SIGCOMM is the flagship conference for networking, and participation in the conference provides a great opportunity for graduate students. Attending SIGCOMM not only exposes students to leading-edge research in the field, but also provides an opportunity to interact with senior researchers. Active participation can be challenging for students who are first-time attendees and know few people within the SIGCOMM community, which is especially common for under-represented students since there are few other minority participants at the conference. The N2Women event, co-located with the conference, aims to make it easier for the students to fully participate in the conference. Active participation in SIGCOMM is an effective way to expose students to new ideas and inspire students to address the tough problems in their respective fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The requested travel funds will allow more under-represented students to attend N2Women events, participate in a high-quality technical conference, and interact with senior researchers. This requested travel funds will help foster the under-represented minority community at SIGCOMM and promote a friendly environment for minority students to develop their career. It is expected that the impact to the students careers from attending the N2Women event and the SIGCOMM conference to be substantial.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1641677</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aruna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Balasubramanian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>arunab@cs.stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
