<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for the 2016 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (IEEE Big Data 2016)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 2016 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (IEEE Big Data 2016) provides a leading forum for disseminating the latest research and education in Big Data research, development, and applications. The scientific program will cover synergistic themes on Big Data Science and Foundations, Big Data Infrastructure, Big Data Management, Big Data Search and Mining, Big Data Security &amp; Privacy, and Big Data Applications. The IEEE Big Data 2016 will have great world-renowned scientists as keynote speakers and invited speakers, contributed talks at a highly competitive acceptance rate, special issue publications in top scientific journals such as IEEE Transactions on Big Data as well as the broad participation of the research community serving on the Program Committee and the organizing committees for workshops, tutorials and posters. As an effort to engage young researchers, the IEEE Big Data 2016 has involved them in the meeting organization and has included mentoring activities in the conference program. This conference aims to provide the crucial funding needed to support the participation of early career researchers and graduate students, especially those from underrepresented groups, as a training opportunity for the next generation of scientists and engineers, thereby, broadening the scientific impact of this international conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1643224</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaohua (Tony)</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xh29@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8083</Code>
      <Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
