<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Wireless Hands-Free Mobile Wheelchair Control Kit</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project focuses on allowing a greater number of people with varying abilities to independently operate a power wheelchair. The kit developed with this project can also provide more independence by freeing up the hands from operating the wheelchair and allowing for the wheelchair to be operated within a specified range - even if the user is not seated in it. This wireless control technology can be used to control other devices such as robots, travel scooters and adaptive sport devices. Using sensors that are already part of smart phones, and the software application including in the kit, a control device that is user friendly and cost effective is created. Expanding the concept of how humans control machines beyond a typical joystick can change the way society views wheelchairs and other mobile devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will explore the commercialization of a hands free wheelchair control kit that can be used by power wheelchair users, including those with a spinal cord injury, multiple sclerosis, muscular dystrophy or poly trauma injuries. The device is designed to allow power wheelchair users the ability to operate their wheelchair without the need to manipulate a joystick with their hands. A smartphone and its accelerometer sensors becomes the joystick by sending the control signals via Bluetooth to the controller of the wheelchair or any mobile device. The smartphone can be attached to the user's arm, head, chest, or remotely, to control the wheelchair. The kit is also designed to toggle between the wheelchair's original joystick controller and the customized smartphone controller using a switch. A wiring harness is used to connect the custom controller to the original controller of most wheelchair manufacturers for easy installation and operation. Preliminary work by the team has shown its capabilities as a successful control alternative to a joystick opening up wheelchair manipulation to a wider group of users.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1648682</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scarey3@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
