<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 24th IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ICNP 2016, the 24th annual edition of the IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols, is a conference covering all aspects of network protocols, including design, analysis, specification,, verification, implementation, and performance. This award partially covers the travel costs of approximately 15 graduate students enrolled in United States academic institutions to attend the conference. ICNP 2016 will be held in Singapore from November 8th to 11th, 2016. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This award serves to broaden participation at ICNP by lowering the financial barrier of attendance for graduate students attending institutions in the Unites States. Allowing exposure to a high quality conference at an early stage of a researcher's academic life is an important investment in the future of the field. Providing opportunities for attendance to underrepresented students in particular will result in a greater diversity of ideas discussed or sparked during the conference. Disseminating the latest results around network protocols as well as furthering the knowledge in this area requires maximizing the number of participants at well-established relevant conferences such as ICNP and targeting a wide variety of researchers. The goal of this award is to assist in both efforts by increasing the number of attendees at ICNP and encouraging women and minorities to participate in such a high quality research event. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Research in network protocols is advanced by the interactions of participants at conferences such as ICNP. The requested travel support will have a significant impact in at least three ways. First, graduate students that would have been unable otherwise to attend ICNP will be benefited by following the speaker's talks and participating in resulting discussions. Second, ICNP participants in general will indirectly benefit by the presence of the grant recipients. Since the award committee will make an effort to select a diverse group of students, the demographics of the conference will become more diverse as well. Finally, the research community as a whole will be positively impacted by the continuing success of the ICNP. The participation of scholars at early stages of their careers, some of which are coming from underrepresented groups, will advance training and the quality of the next generation of research leaders in the field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1651071</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Despoina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Perouli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>despoina.perouli@marquette.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Marquette University</Name>
      <CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4142887200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 1881</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
