<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Genetic Effects of Plant Defense on Above- and Below-ground Ecological Interactions and Natural Selection</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20641</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Scheiner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Using a plant species native to the Rocky Mountains in the mustard family, Boechera stricta, the investigators will test how differences in mechanisms of natural selection across environments influences the maintenance of variation of natural plant chemical defenses. In natural populations, the persistence of variation of traits among individuals allows for adaptation to occur. Despite the central role of variation in the process of adaptation, it is poorly understood how and why variation persists in the face of natural selection eliminating less fit varieties. Chemical defense strategies (various types and concentrations of mustard oils) are highly variable across natural populations of the study species. These defensive compounds have known ecological effects, both as deterrents of insect feeding on leaves (above-ground effects) and as drivers of microbial community composition in the soil (below-ground effects). The researchers will test how plant growth and reproduction are influenced by the above- and below-ground effects of different chemical defense strategies on plant-insect and plant-microbe interactions. The project provides opportunity for undergraduate training. Planned outreach activities will target middle and high school students, and also the general public during the Crested Butte Wildflower Festival.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The pleiotropic effects of plant defensive chemicals and the genes that underlie them are well documented. In addition to influencing fitness by mediating herbivory in aboveground environments, defensive chemicals can affect microbial communities in the soil immediately surrounding root tissue. It is likely that interactions between above- and belowground selective pressures influence overall patterns of natural selection on plant chemistry. The investigators will test for pleiotropic above- and belowground effects of a chemical defense gene utilizing near-isogenic lines of the ecological model species, Boechera stricta (Brassicaceae), that vary in a gene controlling mustard oil biosynthesis to. They will first characterize the effects of defensive chemical profiles on microbial community assembly in the rhizosphere. Second, they will assess how rhizosphere selection affects plant fitness. Finally, they will test how the belowground context may modify aboveground effects of mustard oils as anti-herbivore defenses, and how interactions between the above- and belowground fitness effects of mustard oils result in the maintenance of genetic and trait diversity over space and time.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1701790</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mitchell-Olds</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tmo1@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/17/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lnc14@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/17/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
