<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>JUNO 2016 PI Meeting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>31740</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports hosting the final Japanese-US Network Opportunity (JUNO) PI meeting to be held at the George Washington University on Dec. 8, 2016, in Washington DC. This meeting continues a research collaboration between US and Japanese networking researchers jointly funded by the NSF/NeTS program and the Japanese National Institute of Information and Communications Technology (NICT).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In 2013, NSF issued a solicitation for proposals titled Networking Technology and Systems (NeTS: JUNO), Japan-US Network Opportunity: R&amp;D for "Beyond Trillions of Objects." This "Beyond Trillions of Objects" Japan-US joint research and development program has addressed a critical subset of the issues that arise when environments with trillions of device and information objects are network-connected, as is expected to be the case by the year 2020. Seven collaborative research projects have addressed novel approaches for network design and modeling, new technologies for network management and control in support of object mobility, and flexible optical networks with the speed, capacity and environmental characteristics needed to accommodate communications among objects in the emerging world. The first program PI meeting was held at the University of California, Davis, in June 2014, and the second PI meeting was held in Tokyo in October 2015. This final PI meeting will bring together the PIs from the US and Japan, as well a selection of US student participants in the JUNO projects. The meeting will provide the opportunity for all project participants to learn about the progress to date on all of the JUNO projects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1712583</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suresh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Subramaniam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>suresh@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200522000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2029946255</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2121 Eye Street NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
