<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Women's Intellectual Networking Research Symposium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4300</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Women's Intellectual Network Research Symposium: A Meeting of Mathematical Minds is a one-day symposium that will be held at Brown University on Saturday, March 4th, 2017. The goal of this symposium is to bring together undergraduate and graduate students, as well as post-doctoral fellows and faculty from New England, in order to engage in research discussions and exchange ideas. This symposium particularly seeks to connect women and other underrepresented minorities in similar fields of mathematics or statistics from universities in the New England area, as well as to promote collaboration and share strategies for addressing issues facing these groups. However, the symposium is more broadly inclusive, and hopes to benefit a larger community. The symposium is open to everyone, regardless of gender identity. The symposium will feature two plenary talks, in applied dynamical systems and geometric group theory, three tutorials, including one on public key cryptography, and one in data science, short talks by students (graduate and undergraduate), post-doctoral fellows and faculty, a poster session, and a panel on effective mentoring. A meeting of members of AWM (Association for Women in Mathematics) Student Chapters will also be convened during the symposium. The symposium seeks to have a broad representation from pure, applied and industrial math, and encourages participation from researchers in all areas of mathematics, applied mathematics and statistics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This pan-New England symposium will serve to build bridges between universities and connect researchers, particularly upcoming and younger researchers, women and underrepresented minorities, in similar mathematical fields. The geographic proximity of these universities makes it more likely that networks formed at the conference can be sustained and strengthened, which in turn should increase the probability that these researchers stay in the field and become highly productive members of the community. The symposium lays a strong emphasis on vertical integration, namely having representation at all levels, from undergraduate students to faculty, as we believe this is particularly beneficial to achieve the objectives of the symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium website is: http://www.dam.brown.edu/people/aah/WINRS/index.html</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1727318</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kavita</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ramanan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Kavita_Ramanan@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1263</Code>
      <Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
