<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on Multiscale Modeling with Partial Differential Equations in Computational Science and Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10590</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in a regional conference on the topic of multiscale modeling. The conference is organized by the Great Lakes Section of the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) and will take place at Grand Valley State University in Grand Rapids, MI on May 2, 2015. Multiscale modeling from atomistic to macro scales, which is at the core of computational science and engineering (CSE), has affected almost every modern industry and all disciplines of basic science, engineering, as well as social sciences. To bridge gaps in communication among mathematics, statistics, computer science, environmental science, basic science, engineering, and industry, the 2015 Annual Conference of the Great Lakes Section of SIAM (GLS-SIAM) brings together researchers in CSE to foster advanced discovery and understanding of multiscale modeling, while promoting training in CSE. The conference features a series of keynote talks by world-leading researchers in CSE that address current challenges and opportunities in advanced multiscale simulations. The conference has significant impact for the establishment of CSE-related research activities and training in the Great Lakes area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In recent years, modeling and simulation of multiscale phenomena have attracted enormous attention from the mathematical and scientific research communities, with profound positive impact on transcendent technologies and future product development in both academia and industry. These modeling problems are characterized by having multiple scales of length and time, interactions among multiple phenomena or components, generation of truly big data, and unknown levels of uncertainty. They require innovative approaches to be able to formulate accurate, reliable models to bridge the macro-nano-molecular-atomic scales by capturing the complex dynamic interactions that are vital to the simulation of any real device and to the optimization of design-cycle times. However, this systematic multiscale framework presents central mathematical and scientific challenges both in theory and computation required for successfully combining models or coupling algorithms across various scales. This conference shall provide a forum for scientists to communicate their new findings in multiscale modeling, and furthermore, to develop new collaboration in research and student training. The conference website is http://www.gvsu.edu/siamgls2015/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1500067</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yupaul@gvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Salim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haidar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haidars@gvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Grand Valley State University</Name>
      <CityName>Allendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>494019401</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6163316840</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 Campus Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8396</Code>
      <Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8609</Code>
      <Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
