<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>p-adic Methods in Number Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support for participation in the conference "p-adic Methods in Number Theory" held at the University of California, Berkeley on May 26-30, 2015. Since their conception by Kurt Hensel around 1900, p-adic numbers have played a central role in number theory; for example, they are used in a crucial way in the proof of Fermat's Last Theorem. To a number theorist, p-adic numbers are just as "real" -- and just as important -- as real numbers. Both are ways of "filling in the gaps" left by considering just rational numbers. In their book "Number Theory I: Fermat's Dream," Kato, Kurokawa, and Saito write poetically, "In the long history of mathematics a number meant a real number, and it is only relatively recently that we realized that there is a world of p-adic numbers. It is as if those who had seen the sky only during the day are marveling at the night sky. [ ] Just as we can see space objects better at night, we begin to see the profound mathematical universe through the p-adic numbers." This conference will bring together experts in the many different facets of p-adic numbers and their applications, will promote a cross-fertilization of ideas between number theorists of all stripes, will expose graduate students and postdocs to state-of-the-art techniques and results, and will promote participation by underrepresented minorities and women in high-level number theory research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A conference on p-adic methods in number theory is timely and important, as many spectacular recent number-theoretic advances have made use of deep p-adic methods. We mention, for example, recent work establishing special cases of the p-adic local Langlands correspondence; the proof that most hyperelliptic curves of odd degree have just one rational point; developments on non-abelian Coleman integration and integral points on curves; work on the fundamental curve of p-adic Hodge theory; and recent results on perfectoid spaces. More Information can be found at https://sites.google.com/site/padicmethods2015/.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1500868</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbaker@math.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
