<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Conference in Homological Algebra</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>22000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Conference in Homological Algebra will be held July 22-24, 2015, at the University of Kentucky, Lexington KY. The focus will be on Homological Algebra and its applications. It will provide an overview of recent results and developments of homological methods, as well as their applications. The conference will attract some of the world's leading researchers who will present their latest work. There will be a mixture of talks given by world class scientists with talks by junior faculty, post docs and graduate students. Perhaps the greatest impact will be on young researchers (assistant professors, post-doctoral fellows, and PhD students) who will see new connections and hopefully new directions for their research. It will also be a great networking opportunity for junior faculty and for graduate students. The funds will be used to support the main speakers, as well as some of the participants (priority will be given to graduate students and post doctoral researchers). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The topic of the conference is Homological Algebra which is currently both an active field of research and a very useful tool for many areas of mathematics, including Algebraic Geometry, Commutative and Non-Commutative Algebra, Model Category Theory, and Relative Homological Algebra. The aim of the conference is to present various aspects of recent applications and developments of homological methods in the specific areas listed above. The meeting is timed to follow immediately after the one semester long program that the Centre de Recerca Matematica (Barcelona, Spain) will host between January and June 2015. This program will introduce (to post-doctoral fellows and to graduate students) some of the research topics that are planned for the conference. Some of the main speakers (and their students) will participate in the Barcelona program. It is planned to disseminate broadly the results by publishing the proceedings of the conference. The conference will include a day honoring Dr. Edgar Enochs' career. Dr. Enochs (University of Kentucky) will soon retire after teaching for more than 50 years and advising more than 50 PhD students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1501160</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sergio</FirstName>
      <LastName>Estrada</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sestrada@um.es</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Iacob</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aiacob@georgiasouthern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheatham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cheatham@mtsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Southern University Research and Service Foundation, Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Statesboro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>304588005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9124785465</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>261 Forest Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
