<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Investigating the genomic structure of speciation: a comparative approach using wagtails (Aves: Motacilla)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>16380</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George W. Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Investigating geographically variable traits can reveal the processes driving evolution. Widespread species are useful systems for exploring differences in physical traits and their underlying genetic basis, because they offer comparisons among populations at different stages of the speciation continuum. The identification of common features may provide insight into the fundamental principles guiding the speciation process, as well as the relationship between genotype and phenotype. To facilitate this research, the PIs have developed an international network of collaborators in Sweden, China, Russia, and the USA. This project also supports outreach and the public communication of science through Natural History Museums. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; In birds, feather color and pattern can play an important role in mating preference. Because of this, plumage differences can arise rapidly and be detected before changes to the genome have time to catch up. This project investigates how plumage diversity emerges using Eurasian wagtails, a group of birds with large difference in plumage color and pattern, but with very little genetic differentiation. The drastic color pattern differences in wagtails are thought to be a result of sexual selection, in which case the differences in phenotypes could be the result of changes to a small number of genes. This project will use whole-genome sequencing to identify regions of high genetic differentiation from throughout the genome. Sequencing these specific regions of differentiation from wagtails collected across Eurasia will add to the relatively small body of literature on the genetics of plumage pattern. Beyond plumage, our data will allow us to investigate the historical events that likely shaped the evolution of this group in Europe, Asia, and Africa.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1501131</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leache</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leache@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harris</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rbharris@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
