<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Supply Chain Management and Manufacturing Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199992</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The U.S. Department of Labor reports that within the next ten years, the number of logistics technician jobs will double, requiring even more sophisticated technical training and experience. Recent development of the International Inland Port of Dallas has created a critical local need that mirrors the national demand for skilled technicians in all areas of supply chain manufacturing. The rapidly growing regional companies, including FedEx, Wal-Mart, BMW Distribution, Kohls, LOreal, CVS, and others, have dramatically changed production methods by implementing the newest technology, thus creating new jobs and careers for the communities in southern Dallas County. To address this critical demand for highly trained technicians in emerging supply chain logistics technologies who have industry recognized certifications and college degrees, Cedar Valley College, of the Dallas County Community College District, will develop and implement a Supply Chain Management/Manufacturing Program that is designed to produce technicians for the emerging high-tech manufacturing industries. The program will provide a coherent sequence of courses that lead to multiple recognized logistics certificates, culminating in an associate degree in Manufacturing/Logistics that will prepare individuals for employment in the new logistics technology industries and/or transfer to a four year college or university. This project will impact the economy of southern Dallas County, formerly an area of slow economic growth through development of a much needed highly skilled technical workforce that will help alleviate the local and national shortage of logistics technicians. By pursuing a curriculum that leads to high tech careers with a living wage, southern Dallas residents will improve their standard of living, and the college will help advance economic development. The project will foster diversity in the workplaces as it targets community college students and dual credit high school students, with a focus on minorities, women, and veterans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Because the movement to higher technology will continue to decrease opportunities for unskilled workers while simultaneously creating a demand for trained workers with skills in modern technology, this new manufacturing logistics technician program will prepare workers to enter careers in modern supply chain industries. It will provide curriculum that leads to Level 1 and Level 2 industry recognized certificates and ultimately to an associate degree. Students will gain advanced critical thinking and problem solving skills, high level communication ability, and applied mathematics expertise gained through college participation. Project activities will include the development of curriculum and course content, along with marketing, faculty development, and partnerships. The college will also strengthen partnerships with existing nationally recognized educational programs, which will enhance the reputation of the college as a hub for technological learning. This project will offer dual credit college courses to high school juniors and seniors and recruit these and other students to the Supply Chain Management/Manufacturing Program at Cedar Valley College. Strong partnerships with area companies will provide industry internships and potential employment upon completion. A comprehensive evaluation will identify best practices in logistics education and the impact of this project on providing highly educated technicians to employers and increasing the diversity of the workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1501105</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ruben</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjohnson@dcccd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Dallas County Community College Dist Cedar Valley College</Name>
      <CityName>Lancaster</CityName>
      <ZipCode>751343705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9728602916</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3030 North Dallas Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
