<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pilot Project to Increase Applications to Ocean Science REU Programs from Underrepresented Minority Students through Representation and Participation at LSAMP Meetings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29907</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An analysis of the graduation rates of undergraduates and graduate students with degrees in the ocean sciences reveals that very few students of color pursue these degrees, and the low participation rate is not improving. For example, while the overall percentage of minority-earned doctoral degrees has increased significantly in the past ten years, the number of doctoral degrees awarded to minorities in Ocean Sciences has remained level. The PIs propose a pilot project with the goal of increasing the participation of under represented students in the field of ocean sciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Students who participate in a research experience, and particularly in an REU program that has a strong mentorship component, are more likely to attend graduate school. Threfore, the PI's will work to increase the rate at which under represented students apply to OCE-funded Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) programs. The PI's will recruit students at a series of Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) conferences, providing information about the REU programs, encouraging students to apply to these programs and supporting students in the application process. The PI's will engage students who express an interest in marine sciences in virtual workshops and webinars via the Institute for Broadening Participation (IBP) and will help these students connect with OCE REU program directors. They will also provide networking opportunities to connect LSAMP faculty with OCE REU faculty to encourage student applications to the REU programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1506040</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gilligan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gilliganm@savannahstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Siegfried</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dsiegfried@ibparticipation.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Institute for Broadening Participation</Name>
      <CityName>Damariscotta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>045430607</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2075635929</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 607</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maine</StateName>
      <StateCode>ME</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1690</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
