<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>17th IMS New Researchers Conference (IMS-NRC)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>23000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 17th Meeting of New Researchers in Statistics and Probability, a conference series sponsored by the Institute of Mathematical Statistics (IMS), is organized by and held for junior researchers. The primary objective is to provide a much needed venue for interaction among new researchers. The meeting will take place over three days, August 6-8, 2015, at the University of Washington, in Seattle, WA. The meeting will be held immediately preceding the Joint Statistical Meetings (JSM) in downtown Seattle. Participants will be statisticians and probabilists who have received their Ph.D. within the past five years or are expecting to receive their degree within the same year. Each participant will present a talk or poster. Topics will cover a variety of areas in statistics and probability, from theory and methods to applications. Senior speakers will give plenary talks for inspiration and other senior researchers will take part in discussion panels covering topics of importance for young people embarking on an academic/research career, such as teaching, mentoring, publishing and funding.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference series is explicitly aimed at training the future leaders and workers in statistics and probability. In helping to create networks of new researchers, it lays the groundwork for future collaboration and the informal exchange of ideas and knowledge. It is also critical for professional cohesion, which is particularly important as research fields become more and more specialized. Meeting people outside of one's research specialty area, and learning about their research, favors a more comprehensive view of research, which is important when taking editor positions and other professional service activities. The conference also attracts participants with different backgrounds and nationalities, and underrepresented groups --- women, minorities and people with disabilities --- are explicitly encouraged to attend.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1506255</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Noah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Simon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nrsimon@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shojaie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ashojaie@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
