<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: A New Multi-DOF Reduced-Gravity Simulation Technology for Aerospace and Healthcare Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Astronauts must go through extensive training of their space-walk tasks in a simulated micro- or reduced-gravity environment before they can perform the tasks in space. The currently used technologies for such training are either extremely expensive (e.g., the neutral buoyancy and parabolic flight technologies) or of low simulation fidelity (e.g., the cable-based suspension technology). Therefore, new reduced-gravity technologies of low-cost, high fidelity, and safe operation are needed in space industry to meet the future manned space exploration missions. Additionally, millions of patients who have lost mobility capabilities due to injury, stroke or other diseases also need reduced-gravity simulation technology (as body-weight offloading devices) to support their rehabilitation for restoring locomotion and mobility functions. Currently used devices for such a purpose are either very expensive (such as the robotics-based rehabilitation devices) or of constraining too much mobility (e.g., cable-based suspension devices). Therefore, low-cost and dexterous body-weight offloading devices are needed for better rehabilitation in healthcare industry. This project aims at speeding up the process of commercializing a new, passive and dexterous reduced-gravity physical simulation technology and its prototype device.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Developed based on a spring-based passive balancing technique, the proposed reduced-gravity simulation technology and device can compensate its own weight and any desired percentile (from 0% to 100%) of the weight of a person attached to the device, such that the person, while walking or doing some other physical exercises, will biomechanically feel like he or she were in a microgravity or reduced-gravity environment such as in an orbiting spacecraft or on the Moon, Mars or another planet. The design of the mechanism takes into account of the natural multi-directional mobility of human limbs and joints so that a person attached to the device will feel unrestricted and comfortable. Further, since the device is passive in operation (i.e., not powered or actuated), it is intrinsically safe, inexpensive and easy to maintain. These are appealing advantages for the users of the device. At the end of the proposed project, the I-Corps team will have a clear understanding of the market-specific needs, new design requirements for addressing the market/customer needs, and an implementable plan of how to transit the new technology into real products.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1506335</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ou</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>oma@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kramer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Winingham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jkramer@ad.nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
      <CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
      <ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
