<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A One Millimeter Wavelength Focal Plane Array Receiver for the LMT</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1047567</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project seeks to construct a 16-element array receiver system called OMAR (One Millimeter-wave Array Receiver) at the 50 m Large Millimeter Telescope (LMT) located in Tonantzintla, Puebla, Mexico. OMAR will be installed as a common-user facility instrument, available for American astronomers. LMT is a joint project of the University of Massachusetts and the Instituto Nacional de Astrofisica, Optica, y Electronica (INAOE). OMAR is designed to operate in the 210 - 280 GHz (~1 mm wavelength) atmospheric window, and will be equipped with state-of-the-art receivers. OMAR will build on the proven experience and the heritage of success of the UMass instrumentation group in building state-of-the-art focal plane arrays. OMAR will provide an unprecedented combination of sensitivity, mapping speed, spectral coverage, spatial and spectral resolution in the 1 mm band, that will enable a wide variety of scientific projects covering the gamut of distant galaxies to comet flybys in our own solar system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;OMAR will be the first heterodyne array receiver at millimeter wavelengths that is equipped with sideband-separation super-conducting receivers. In each pixel, 8 GHz of effective bandwidth per sideband (16 GHz total) will be available without the use of mechanical tuners. OMAR will be deployed as a 16 element dual polarization array which will be arranged in a 2x4 (8 beams) format. OMAR will be used with on-the-fly (OTF) mapping mode to provide an unprecedented combination of sensitivity, mapping speed, spectral coverage, spatial and spectral resolution in the 1 mm band. OMAR is a technically innovative instrument that will define the state-of-the-art for SIS heterodyne array receivers. As a purely technical advance, this project will implement a high level of integration of mixer, amplifier, local oscillator injection components in a innovative sideband separation system that will have a significant impact in the field of heterodyne focal-plane arrays.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1507267</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Min</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>myun@astro.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stella</FirstName>
      <LastName>Offner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>offner@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Erickson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>neal@astro.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gopal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Narayanan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gopal@astro.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>F. Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schloerb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schloerb@astro.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1218</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1218</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7697</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
