<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Supramolecular Chemistry of Amyloidogenic Peptides</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>465000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David A. Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Division of Chemistry is funding Professor James Nowick of the University of California-Irvine to utilize chemical synthesis to create model systems that assemble in the same fashion as the more complex biomolecules, and thereby serve as model systems for the aggregation of proteins. Molecular assemblies known as amyloid assemblies formed by peptides and proteins have been implicated in a variety of diseases, such as Alzheimer's disease, frontotemporal dementias, Parkinson's disease, and type 2 diabetes. This project seeks to learn more about the structures of these amyloid oligomers. The chemical model systems being generated have the advantage that they can form crystals, allowing the structures of the oligomers to be determined with exquisite precision by X-ray crystallography. By determining the structures of these chemical model systems, the researchers will gain insights into the molecular assemblies formed by associated peptides and proteins. This project will achieve broader impact through the knowledge gained in the research, the training of students at the graduate and undergraduate level, K-12 educational outreach, and contributions to STEM education. Graduate students and undergraduates who assist in the project will receive training value cross-disciplinary training. A large number K-12 students are being targeted through the UCI Chemistry Outreach Program. The PI will continue to contribute to STEM education on the US and global level through UCI's OpenChem Initiative, by teaching and creating video content for the public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Nowick research group has developed a new strategy to elucidate the structures of oligomers formed by amyloidogenic peptides: incorporating the peptides into macrocycles and using a single N-methyl group to prevent uncontrolled aggregation to fibrils. The resulting macrocyclic beta-sheet peptides assemble to form well-defined oligomers, and a sizeable fraction of the peptides form crystals suitable for X-ray crystallography. This approach will be used to elucidate the structures of oligomers from amyloidogenic peptides derived from the protein tau, the protein alpha-synuclein, and the islet amyloid polypeptide (IAPP, amylin). The structures of the oligomers that form will be determined at atomic resolution by X-ray crystallography, and the crystallographic structures of the oligomers will be correlated with the oligomerization state in solution by size-exclusion chromatography and other techniques such as NMR spectroscopy. The relationship between the biological properties of these oligomers and those of natural amyloidogenic peptides and proteins will be assessed by dot-blot assays. These studies aim to provide a better understanding of the relationship between oligomer sequence and three dimensional structure, and the implications of these upon stability and biological properties.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1507840</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nowick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jsnowick@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498244768</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5171 California Avenue, Ste 150</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6883</Code>
      <Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
