<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Exploring lateral photo-Dember effect in two dimensional atomic layer crystals for terahertz generation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The efficient generation of long wavelength radiation at the 0.1~10 terahertz region remains a key challenge for the development and deployment of terahertz technology for high speed communication, spectroscopy, and imaging applications. This research project explores a unique lateral photo-Dember effect in 2-dimensional nanomaterials for terahertz generation. The proposed project will open a door to developing new type of compact terahertz sources with a broad range of applications. In addition, the knowledge and techniques acquired through the proposed research can readily be extended to study ultrafast optical physics of other type of 1-dimensional and 2-dimensional nanomaterials. More broadly, the proposed project is highly interdisciplinary and should advance science and technology in areas of nanomaterials, optical science, nanoelectronics, nanophotonics, and device physics. The project also includes an outreach and education program promoting awareness of and interest in nanoscience and nanotechnology among K-12 and undergraduate students. The knowledge and research findings resulting from this project will be integrated into a number of new nanotechnology courses currently under development that are related to carbon nanotechnology, optical science, and nanophotonics. This project will be further enhanced by proactively recruiting underrepresented students, which can improve the diversity of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics disciplines and workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project aim to understand the fundamental lateral photo-Dember effect in 2-dimensional atomic layer crystals including graphene and few layer transition metal dichalcogenides, and to pioneer new terahertz sources based on these 2-dimensional nanomaterials. The project tasks are: (1) to perform fundamental study to thoroughly understand the ultrafast photo-carrier dynamics in graphene and transition metal dichalcogenides; (2) to fabricate and characterize the terahertz emission from metal/2-dimensional nanomaterial junctions; (3) to design new terahertz emitter arrays based on 2-dimensional nanomaterials and test their performance. A combination of advanced optoelectronic characterization techniques for 2-dimensional nanomaterials will be developed and utilized in this project, including scanning photocurrent measurement, ultrafast pump-probe photocurrent measurement, and terahertz time-domain spectroscopy techniques. The success of the project will generate fundamental and detailed understanding of light-matter interaction and ultrafast carrier dynamics in low dimensional nanomaterials. In addition, the finding of the project will truly showcase the advantages of 2-dimensional nanomaterials for unique optoelectronic applications which are not possible in bulk semiconductors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1509354</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhaohui</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zzhong@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
      <LastName>Norris</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tnorris@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>091E</Code>
      <Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
