<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>UNS: Coupled Flow-Chemistry Modeling of Thrombogensis in Human Ventricles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>290005</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1511200(Mittal)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal is focused on the understanding of the flow of blood in the human heart using computations. When blood flow in the heart is disturbed by myocardial infraction, it is possible to create conditions that lead to blood clotting. The novelty of the proposed work is in the use of computational models that account not only for the flow, but also for the detailed biochemistry of clot formation. Hundreds of thousands of Americans each year are found to suffer from myocardial infraction and could potentially benefit from the results of this research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite many decades of research, the complex interplay between the ventricular fluid dynamics and the chemistry of coagulation is not well understood. It is proposed to take advantage of recent developments in medical imaging and computational fluid dynamics to simulate blood flow in realistic models of the heart, and to investigate the coupling between the flow and the chemistry associated with left ventricle (LV) thrombogenesis. It is proposed to use medical imaging to create a model of the LV to simulate blood flow. The resulting flow field data will be used to model the convection, diffusion and reaction of species known to be important in the coagulation cascade as well as platelet dynamics and adhesion. The specific objectives of the project are: (1) develop coupled flow-chemistry computational models of LV thrombus formation; (2) validate computational hemodynamic results against in-vivo data; (3) investigate the mechanisms of flow-mediated thrombogenesis; and (4) use simulations to examine alternate coagulation pathways and the effectiveness of anticoagulant therapies. This project will break new ground in flow-chemistry coupling, imaging-to-model construction, hybrid (CPU-GPU) high performance computing models, dual-time-stepping procedures for stiff coupled systems, and new protocols for validating CFD results from in-vivo data. The coupled flow-chemical modeling approach that will be developed is expected to advance the state-of-the-art in this arena that has been limited to simple, stationary vessel geometries and laminar flows.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1511200</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rajat</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mittal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mittal@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7334</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7454</Code>
      <Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>059E</Code>
      <Text>Complex fluids</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
