<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Network Detection and Analysis Through Semi-Parametric Odds Ratio Model</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gabor J. Szekely</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to develop innovative statistical methods for tackling the challenging problems in the analysis of massive data generated in the studies of complex systems, such as biological systems, financial systems, and social networks. This project addresses the lack of flexible statistical models and methods for the analysis of high-dimensional network data with mixed categorical and continuous measurements. The methodology and software under development increase the accuracy of the network detection, estimation, and interpretation, which have widespread applications. One such application is to genomic research that holds great promise for better disease prevention, diagnosis, and treatment. The project's approach to network analysis can reveal more accurate structures of causal pathway and system functionalities, which in turn can lead to better understand of the underlying biological mechanisms. The project also provides training opportunities for the next generation statisticians doing research on high-dimensional data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, this project studies a flexible alternative to the traditional Gaussian model in the analysis of multivariate data. Such data may be biasedly sampled and may also include many discrete variables, which makes the data inherently non-Gaussianly distributed. The semiparametric odds ratio model under study in this project unifies and extends the Gaussian models for continuous data and the log-linear model for categorical data. This approach not only models complex associations with highly interpretable model parameters, it also naturally address the problem of biased sampling designs frequently encountered in biomedical data collection. The penalized likelihood approach can consistently detect sparse associations among mixed continuous and discrete variables (i.e., sparse association networks with mixed nodes). Novel theory for consistent sparse network detection and algorithms for implementing the methods will be developed. In comparison to the traditional Gaussian model for association network detection, the methods under study have the advantages of detecting sparse association between groups of variables without modeling the association within the groups of variables in high-dimensional settings. The research results can substantially improve the information extraction from high-dimensional data and the interpretation of such information.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1512930</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hua Yun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hychen@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/06/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
