<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Models for Trait-Mediated Dispersal in Ecology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>507778</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Ann Horn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The dispersal of organisms strongly influences their interactions with their environment and with populations of other organisms. The ecological effects of dispersal in turn influence the fitness of individuals, and hence influence natural selection, which drives evolution. Thus, the effects of dispersal can feed back to influence the attributes and behaviors of organisms, including those that affect dispersal and its consequences. Such attributes and behaviors are known as traits. They include tendencies to seek resources, avoid predators, or migrate seasonally, which can be viewed as dispersal strategies, but they also include the ways that organisms use information about their environment to decide how to move or how they communicate such information with other members of their species. This project will use mathematical models to gain insight into the connections between the structure and variability of the environment and the dispersal traits that can be expected to evolve and persist. Mathematical models are necessary to gain such insight because the effects of dispersal and the feedbacks involved in its evolution are too subtle and complex to capture with verbal descriptions. In past research, the investigators have gained a good understanding of which fixed dispersal traits are most favorable in the context of a single population in an environment that varies in space but not in time. One aspect of this project is to address similar issues in the context of environments that are also changing in time. Another is to study more deeply how dispersal influences species interactions, especially when it interacts with variations in timing of life history events. Both of those research directions are motivated in part by ecological problems related to global change. Other aspects of the project focus on understanding behavioral traits related to dispersal; some of those may be relevant to conservation/restoration efforts and to understanding the movement of disease vectors. Some parts of the project will be conducted in collaboration with postdoctoral fellows and thus should contribute to enhancing the scientific workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The dispersal of organisms affects their fitness by determining their spatial distribution and interactions with other populations, which then creates selective pressure on traits related to dispersal. This leads to complex feedbacks between the effects and evolution of dispersal traits that can only be understood by using mathematical or computational models. Traditional models of dispersal typically assume it is a fixed behavior, independent of environmental conditions, such as simple diffusion. However, organisms seek resources, avoid enemies, and engage in behaviors such as migration that require the use and transmission of information. These conditional dispersal behaviors are traits, which can be shaped by evolution and can be viewed as strategies from the viewpoint of adaptive dynamics. In previous work, the investigators used pairwise invasibility analysis of various models, including reaction-advection-diffusion equations, discrete diffusion systems, and their nonlocal integro-differential analogues, to show that for a single unstructured population in a spatially varying but temporally constant environment the evolutionarily stable strategies are those that produce an ideal free distribution. The research team will use similar methods to gain understanding of the evolution of dispersal traits in the more realistic contexts of populations in environments that vary in both space and time, populations that are structured by stage or internal state, and systems of interacting populations. To do that, the investigators will use additional types of models including integro-difference models as well as those used before. It is expected that the detailed conclusions in those cases will often be different from those for an unstructured population in a temporally constant environment. Some numerical experiments may be needed to suggest what the conclusions should be. Hybrid models that include both dispersal and phenology will also be studied, as well as models for organisms with multiple dispersal modes. The first of those is relevant to understanding how phenology shifts caused by global change could interact with spatial effects. For example, how are the effects of isolation in time similar to those of isolation in space, and how do they differ? The second is relevant to understanding the movement patterns of various organisms, including female mosquitoes that switch between seeking blood meals and seeking oviposition sites. More broadly, understanding dispersal traits is relevant to conservation and pest management and to predicting the effects of global change on natural and agricultural ecosystems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1514752</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cosner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gcc@math.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cantrell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rsc@math.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami</Name>
      <CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7334</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7454</Code>
      <Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
