<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Optimization and Investigation of MRI Contrast Phenomena</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is one of the most powerful tools available for biomedical imaging today. This is especially true when paired with contrast enhancement agents. Although current FDA approved contrast enhancement agents are sufficient, they are far from optimal. This project will focus on identifying the key variables contributing to contrast enhancement and exploiting this information to develop highly efficient, completely optimized MRI contrast agents. Optimizing such materials will reduce agent dosage and increase accuracy of MRI scans. This work will be done in collaboration with Dr. Tim St. Pierre, a leading authority in the field of biomagnetics, at the University of Western Australia in Perth Australia. Dr. St. Pierre's lab is one of two places in the world that possess such a diverse set of magnetic instrumentation, this will allow for the full characterization and investigation of the contrast enhancement materials in question. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Investigations in contrast enhancement physics will be done using an MRI active nanoparticle complex that can be accurately varied in size and composition. This investigation will determine optimal parameters for novel contrast agents effectively lowering dose and toxicity while increasing contrast. Once ideal parameters are attained, core shell particles that combine both longitudinal and transverse relaxation agents (T1 and T2 respectively) will be synthesized in accordance with optimization data. The dual mode agents will allow for the reduction in noise and misinterpretation due to artifacts appearing in weighted scans, as well as reducing the amount of contrast required for a normal procedure. The bimodal nature of the particles will allow the subtraction of such artifacts seen by a single weighted scan using the combined contrast to determine artifact enhancement and eliminate it. The dual contrast complex will also enhance the understanding of the contrast mechanism, and how changes in local field influence the relaxation times measured in MRI. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Australian Academy of Science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1515112</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fellows</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fellows Benjamin D</Name>
      <CityName>Clemson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
