<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transcriptional Silencing and Enhancing Mechanisms in Maize</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William B. Eggleston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Modifications (called epigenetic marks) of DNA or of the proteins associated with DNA can cause certain genes to be turned on or off (gene regulation) at different stages of growth and development. This project will define a mode of epigenetic-based gene regulation that is poorly understood in all organisms using as a model system maize (corn), which is an important agricultural product for human and animal consumption and for bioenergy production in the US. Since these epigenetic marks are heritable and can be used to turn on genes with desired traits, this project may uncover novel approaches for engineering new strains of corn for agricultural purposes. This project will engage high school students in summer research programs, and offer research experiences and training to graduate and undergraduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proteins will be isolated by sequential chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) from a known epigenetic regulatory sequence in maize. They will be compared from ChIP samples of DNA in transcriptionally active and silenced states, along with specific deletions of the known regulatory sequence. Collectively, this will be used to elucidate the specific protein-DNA interactions associated with transcriptional silencing and activation. Because the regulatory sequence participates in allelic communication, proteins involved with epigenetic regulation associated with allelic communication will also be identified. Analysis of these interactions will provide insight into mechanisms of transcriptional silencing, enhancers, and paramutation in eukaryotes and address the complexity of combinatorial epigenetic regulation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1517536</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>McGinnis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcginnis@bio.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
