<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RCN: Arabidopsis Research and Training for the 21st century (ART-21)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>189447</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen C. Cone</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Research Coordination Network will support a suite of enabling research and training activities for the Arabidopsis and broader plant science communities. The research goals of the network are to enable fundamental discovery research and development of emerging technologies in Arabidopsis for translation to research in crop plants. The training goals are to educate plant biologists at the intersections of quantitative and computational biology for careers both inside and outside academia. Linking the research and training efforts will be activities aimed at increasing the visibility and participation of under-represented groups in plant research. Outcomes will include development of summary analyses and recommendations to define needs, challenges, and possible new directions for Arabidopsis research and training in the 21st century. Information and resources developed through network activities will be disseminated through a dedicated webpage hosted by the North American Arabidopsis Steering Committee. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using the next five International Conferences on Arabidopsis Research as organizing venues, the coordinators and steering committee of this RCN will address three objectives: 1) to identify emerging technologies where using Arabidopsis as a model organism will provide fundamental discoveries and enable translational research in crop species, as recommended in the recently published decadal vision for plant science, "Unleashing a Decade of Innovation in Plant Science;" 2) to enhance interdisciplinary training of scientists for academia and extra-academic careers; and 3) to increase diversity of Arabidopsis research scientists using targeted mechanisms. To achieve the goals, a set of interconnected activities will emphasize network building through surveys and follow-up focus group meetings, community workshops, and publication of white papers to disseminate findings. Strategic incorporation of leadership roles for minority and early-career scientists in the network activities will promote and increase diversity in the Arabidopsis community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1518280</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Siobhan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brady</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbrady@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joanna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Friesner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdfriesner@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1664</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
