<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Understanding Inequalities in Response to Disaster Recovery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This dissertation uses qualitative methods to investigate how inequalities based on race, class, gender and age are constituted in long-term recovery from tornadoes that occurred in Joplin, Missouri and Tuscaloosa, Alabama in 2011. This research has implications for disaster mitigation, making cities more resilient after disaster, and the creation of better social policies. First, since disasters are increasing globally this research will provide disaster practitioners with information about long-term recovery and how recovery varies by social groups. Second, because Joplin and Tuscaloosa responded to their tornadoes in different ways, this dissertation compares how varying local governmental responses influences long-term recovery. Third, based on our findings, the investigators will recommend future policy directions for disaster mitigation, prevention and resilience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The dissertation project is a multi-sited qualitative study utilizing participant observation, interviews and archival work. The investigators ask the following research questions: 1) How have spaces inside Joplin and Tuscaloosa been constructed in classed, gendered, and racialized ways, creating particular privileges and vulnerabilities in processes of long-term recovery? 2a) What resources were available to people in Joplin and Tuscaloosa after the tornadoes? 2b) How does this vary by location and what factors contribute to this variation? Findings from this research can assist governmental and non-profit disaster organizations providing aid and resources in long-term recovery in ways that are sensitive to inequalities and cultural and geographic difference</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1518862</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ashleigh</FirstName>
      <LastName>McKinzie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amcKinzi@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Richards</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>plr333@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
