<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Chemistry of Atmospheric Aerosols at Pacifichem 2015 Congress Conference in Honolulu, Hawaii; December 15-20, 2015</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20300</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports a symposium entitled "Chemistry of Atmospheric Aerosols" at the 2015 International Chemical Congress of Pacific Basin Societies (Pacifichem). The symposium will include a diverse group of presentations in the form of invited, contributed, and poster presentations. This will be the second time a symposium devoted to atmospheric aerosols is part of the Pacifichem program and it will provide a unique opportunity for scientists from different countries to gather in one place and discuss the cutting edge advances in the cross-disciplinary areas of aerosol research. The broader impacts of this project will be the sharing of knowledge about current research on atmospheric aerosols related to air quality. Air pollution issues in western Pacific Rim countries are the most apparent examples of the environmental impacts of atmospheric aerosols.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The American Chemical Society, the Canadian Society for Chemistry, the Chemical Society of Japan, the New Zealand Institute of Chemistry, the Royal Australian Chemical Institute, the Korean Chemical Society, and the Chinese Chemical Society are sponsoring the conference. The American Chemical Society is the host society for the 2015 Congress. Pacifichem 2015 will be the seventh in the series of successful cosponsored scientific conferences of Pacific Basin Chemical Societies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Chemistry of Atmospheric Aerosols will consist of five half-day oral sessions, two evening sessions, and one poster session. The session topics chosen by the organizing committee are: (1) Chemical composition of atmospheric aerosols, fog and cloud water; (2) Multiphase reactions of aerosols and environmental surfaces; (3) Optical properties of atmospheric aerosols; (4) Impact of aerosols on cloud formation; (5) Frontiers in modeling studies of aerosols; and (6) Frontiers in aerosol analytical chemistry and spectroscopy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1519142</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sergey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nizkorodov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nizkorod@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498244768</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5171 California Avenue, Ste 150</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1440</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
