<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Microfluidics-Enabled Interfacial Capacitive Sensing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Schwerdtfeger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project includes the development of novel microfluidic-enabled interfacial capacitive sensing solutions for a wide range of existing and emerging applications, including medical devices, robotics or consumer electronics. Upon successful completion of this SBIR Phase I project, the interfacial capacitive sensors could offer a transformative solution to various medical and industrial applications, where high sensitivity, flexibility and miniature footprints are required. By translating the early-stage laboratory discoveries into commercial pressure sensing products, the initial applications target two clinical challenges in cardiovascular medicine, fraction flow reserve measurement for patients with coronary artery stenosis and interface pressure monitoring for patients with chronic venous disease. The sensors proposed here offer unique advantages and features over the existing medical products on the market. For embedded FFR-measurement pressure sensors, these advantages include reducing the surgical time, complications, and therefore, risks during coronary cauterization. For interface pressure monitoring of compression therapy, the advantages include provides patients with more affordable, accurate, accessible, easy-to-use and comfortable-to-wear pressure sensing solution for better therapeutic outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims at developing the pressure sensors based on microfluidic-enabled interfacial capacitive sensing for cardiovascular applications. These include a miniature pressure sensor embedded in a coronary guide wire for fraction flow reserve evaluation, and a wearable pressure sensor with wireless transmission for interface pressure measurement in compression therapy. The proposed sensor integrated with the guide wire, once developed, allows significant reduction in electrical wiring complexity and easy procedure for surgical operations, in addition to improved structural integrity by replacing hollow wires with solid constructs. For the application of the interface pressure measurement, the interfacial capacitive sensor, upon its successful translation, would become a viable solution capable of simultaneously measuring interface pressure at multiple compression positions as well as providing real-time measurement data to both patients and clinicians. Research will be conducted on system design and manufacturing scalability of the sensors, electrical and mechanical characterizations of the sensor performance, and proof-of-concept demonstrations of potential medical sensing applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1520481</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Baoqing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bnie@tacsense.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>TacSense, LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Woodland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>957764617</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307970008</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 N East Street, Suite 108</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>093E</Code>
      <Text>System fab/packaging &amp; assembly</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8034</Code>
      <Text>Hardware Components</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
