<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EXP: Understanding Computational Thinking Process and Practices in Open-Ended Programming Environments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>608024</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Russell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Cyberlearning and Future Learning Technologies Program funds efforts that will help envision the next generation of learning technologies and advance what we know about how people learn in technology-rich environments. Cyberlearning Exploration (EXP) Projects explore the viability of new kinds of learning technologies by designing and building new kinds of learning technologies and studying their possibilities for fostering learning and challenges to using them effectively. This project brings together two approaches to help K-12 students learn programming and computer science: open-ended learning environments, and computer-based learning analytics, to help create a setting where youth can get help and scaffolding tailored to what they know about programming without having to take tests or participate in rigid textbook exercises for the system to know what they know. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project proposes to use techniques from educational data mining and learning analytics to process student data in the Alice programming environment. Building on the assessment design model of Evidence-Centered Design, student log data will be used to construct a model of individual students' computational thinking practices, aligned with emerging standards including NGSS and research on assessment of computational thinking. Initially, the system will be developed based on an existing corpus of pair-programming log data from approximately 600 students, triangulating with manually-coded performance assessments of programming through game design exercises. In the second phase of the work, curricula and professional development will be created to allow the system to be tested with underrepresented girls at Stanford's CS summer workshops and with students from diverse high schools implementing the Exploring Computer Science curriculum. Direct observation and interviews will be used to improve the model. Research will address how learners enact computational thinking practices in building computational artifacts, what patters of behavior serve as evidence of learning CT practices, and how to better design constructionist programming environments so that personalized learner scaffolding can be provided. By aligning with a popular programming environment (Alice) and a widely-used computer science curriculum (Exploring Computer Science), the project can have broad impact on computer science education; software developed will be released under a BSD-style license so others can build on it.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1522990</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shuchi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grover</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shuchi.grover@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bienkowski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marie.bienkowski@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stamper</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jstamper@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SRI International</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508592651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>005Y</Code>
      <Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7980</Code>
      <Text>Core R&amp;D Programs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8020</Code>
      <Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5905</Code>
      <Text>ISRAEL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8045</Code>
      <Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8244</Code>
      <Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8841</Code>
      <Text>Exploration Projects</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
