<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Organizing the 22nd GENI Engineering Conference (GEC-SC2015) Networking Event</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200449</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports the four-day and 22nd edition of the GENI Engineering Conference (GEC), including organizing and hosting the demo session, to be held March 23-26, 2015, at the George Washington University and at a nearby conference hotel. The Global Environment for Network Innovations (GENI) is a virtual instrument that is rapidly becoming operational across the United States and that is designed to address three issues:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) Science Issues: We cannot currently understand or predict the behavior of complex, large-scale networks.&lt;br/&gt;2) Society Issues: We increasingly rely on the Internet but are unsure we can trust its security, privacy or resilience.&lt;br/&gt;3) Innovation Issues: Pre-GENI, substantial barriers existed to at-scale experimentation with new Internet architectures, services, and technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;GENI addresses these issues via scale (from federation) and support for two kinds of experiments: 1) controlled and repeatable experiments, which will greatly help improve our scientific understanding of complex, large-scale networks; and 2) long-running trials of experimental services that engage large numbers of human participants. In addition to the original motivation for GENI, an understanding has grown that virtualized, federated software-defined infrastructures, of which GENI is a first example, are a key technology for building the next generation of the Internet. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GEC meetings and demo sessions have long provided graduate students with both an opportunity to demonstrate and explain their work to the GENI community prior to formal publication. GEC 22 will provide an opportunity to reach out to a larger community to show and explain the possibilities of GENI and the technology it enables, both for computer science experimentation and for public-benefit applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The four-day conference will be held in Arlington, Virginia. The demo night event will be held at the George Washington University's Science and Engineering Hall (Foggy Bottom Campus).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1523380</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>DuRousseau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddurousseau@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200522000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2029946255</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2121 Eye Street NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
