<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AGS-PRF Impacts of Large-Scale Dynamics on Regional Climate Sensitivity: Model-Paleodata Comparisons in Three Mid-Latitude Regions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>172000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020108</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David J. Verardo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This AGS PostDoctoral Research Fellow (PRF) award supports the comparison of simulations of last glacial maximum (LGM) and present-day climates from general circulation models to paleoclimatic proxy data to investigate dynamical mechanisms that affect regional climates. This analysis will help to determine the dominant large-scale mechanisms affecting the regional climates at LGM of three mid-latitude regions, as well as clarify the ability of regional paleodata to elucidate large-scale paleoclimatic phenomena. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Climate models that are used to predict future climate changes will be benchmarked against paleodata that serve as proxies for past climate parameters thereby testing the ability of these models to correctly simulate past climate states and helping to ensure that dynamical processes involved in generating regional responses are well represented and properly simulated. This, in turn, will help assess the regional capabilities of models under climates different than the current, informing future improvements and development of these models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Of principal interest is the influence of planetary-scale dynamics on regional-scale changes in temperature and the hydrological cycle. The Fellow will examine the effects of such phenomena as mid-latitudinal stationary waves and monsoon dynamics on atmospheric and surface temperatures and precipitation in three regions including the Chinese Loess Plateau, the southwestern United States, and the midwestern United States with the aim of quantifying the regional sensitivities in the models. Output from Paleoclimate Modelling Intercomparison Project (PMIP) simulation model runs will be compared to published datasets that serve as proxies for temperatures and the hydrological cycle in these three regions. The Fellow will further investigate identified dynamical mechanisms, including their sensitivities to boundary and forcing uncertainties by use of the Laboratoire de Météorologie Dynamique (LMDZ) model. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project helps to improve understanding surrounding regional response to climate variability across temporal scales and significant outreach activities. Outreach activities to be conducted at Markham Middle School, whose students are predominantly Hispanic and Afro-Caribbean, are intended for improving science communication and education to minorities. Also, one of the undergraduates who will work with the Fellow over the next year is also from an underrepresented minority in the sciences. As an additional broadening participation exercise, the Fellow will give a science talk about the proposed research at the UCLA chapter of the Society for the Advancement of Chicanos and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS), and will furthermore recruit an undergraduate student from the SACNAS chapter to be involved in the research and outreach activities during the second year of the fellowship.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1524866</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lora</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lora Juan M</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857189537</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1530</Code>
      <Text>PALEOCLIMATE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1530</Code>
      <Text>PALEOCLIMATE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
