<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 400 MHz NMR Spectrometer for Research and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>289000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) and support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Program (CRIF), Vassar College will acquire a 400 MHz NMR spectrometer. The instrument will allow research in different areas including the synthesis of materials of potential commercial interest such as of carbon nanotubes, fullerenes and small molecules which are potential precursors to pharmaceuticals. Areas of biochemical interest such as the biosynthesis of lipids will be investigated. In general, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. This instrument will be an integral part of teaching as well as research performed by students at Vassar College, Marist College, SUNY New Platz and other undergraduate institutions in the area. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal is aimed at enhancing research especially in areas such as (a) characterizing glycerophospholipid structures; (b) investigating titanium-mediated asymmetric imine alkylation; (c) charactering pyrrolidine substituted fullerenes; (d) developing biodegradable polyanhydride materials; and (e) studying C-Shaped diastereomers containing cofacial thiophene-substituted quinoxaline rings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1526982</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tanski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jotanski@vassar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garrett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tegarrett@vassar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vassar College</Name>
      <CityName>Poughkeepsie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>126040657</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8454377092</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>124 Raymond Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8650</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
