<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 400 MHz NMR Spectrometer to Support Undergraduate Research and Chemical Education at Florida Gulf Coast University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>274466</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) and support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Program (CRIF), Florida Gulf Coast University will acquire a 400 MHz NMR spectrometer. The instrument will allow research in different areas including organic synthesis and materials, peptide, forensic and inorganic chemistry and enhance the teaching program at the University. The research will impact areas of biological and environmental interest including DNA stability, anti-viral peptides, precursors to novel drugs and gas adsorption materials. In general, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. This instrument will be an integral part of teaching as well as research performed by undergraduate students at Florida Gulf Coast University. The NMR will also increase the chemistry department's capability to collaborate with local law enforcement institutions on drug identification as well as with local bio-tech companies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels, especially in areas such as synthesizing (a) bio-inspired ionic liquids; (b) medicinally relevant natural products; (c) bioactive molecules; (d) studying structure and function of membrane disruptive anti-viral peptides; (e) studying forensic applications of NMR with concentration in long-term structural and chemical stability of DNA; and (f) studying metal-organic materials from pillared discrete structures.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1530959</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paull</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dpaull@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Michael</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smichael@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arsalan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mirjafari</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amirjafari@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sulekha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coticone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scoticon@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boyce</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gboyce@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Gulf Coast University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort MYERS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>339656565</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2395907022</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10501 FGCU Blvd. South</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8819</Code>
      <Text>Forensic Science</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
