<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Kirigami solar cell development for commercial applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lydia Mcclure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Solar tracking is a mature technology that substantially increases the power output of a given photovoltaic (PV) module. Conventional tracking systems such as single and dual axis trackers have the potential to improve the overall efficiency of PV modules and thereby lower costs, but have not been widely implemented due to system complexity, high installation costs and the need for cumbersome structural components to support system weight and wind loading. Moreover, such tracking systems cannot be deployed in space-limited locations. This team has developed a new paradigm for lightweight and compact solar tracking based on the ancient art of Kirigami. This team's proposed technology has the potential to reduce the cost of photovoltaic modules and can be deployed in locations that are not accessible via the use of existing tracking technology such as mobile and residential (pitched) rooftops on account of its low-profile, compact nature. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Kirigami tracking modules consist of a simple kirigami-cut pattern integrated with thin-film solar cells, whereby pulling on the device results in a change in angle of the solar cells embedded on the substrate. By leveraging the unique geometric properties of the kirigami substrate itself, and the excellent electrical and mechanical properties of the thin-film solar cells, these devices can be used to efficiently track the sun. Due to the low-profile nature of kirigami tracking systems, there is no wind loading and, thus, no need for additional structural components to support such forces. Furthermore, kirigami tracking is lightweight in design, allowing one to eliminate much of the foundation and supporting structures that, in fact, make up much of the cost of conventional tracking systems. Due to the continuous nature of the kirigami substrate and the ability of all cells to be actuated simultaneously (unlike conventional tracking systems, where additional components are needed to connect each panel), system scaling is also relatively straightforward. Finally, by eliminating many of the components needed for conventional tracking and drastically reducing module size, this team believes that kirigami tracking will help open new market segments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1533829</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Max</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shtein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mshtein@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
