<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>XPS: EXPL: CCA: Verification and Optimization Tools for Heterogeneous Memory Consistency Models</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tao Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Over the past decade, the deceleration of Moore's Law and Dennard Scaling has required computing to make a dramatic shift towards on-chip parallelism in order to achieve computer performance scaling at acceptable power budgets. In further response, the use of diverse processing elements and specialized accelerators has also increased; many smartphone processors or systems-on-chip (SoCs) include 4-6 different instruction set architectures (ISAs) and memory consistency models (MCMs). In the face of this increasing heterogeneity, this project's research aims to tame the architecture, verification, and software implications of this fast-growing complexity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ensuring that computations occur on the right data at the right time is fundamental to computing system reliability, and MCMs are intended to guarantee this in multi-threaded systems, but better verification and translation support is needed. In particular, this work is developing a toolkit with elements including: (i) Grammars for specifying MCMs and hardware implementations, as well as tools to derive these specifications from existing design descriptions, appropriately annotated if needed. (ii) Modules for enumerating and checking implementation-level (i.e. microarchitecture-level) Happens-Before-Graphs to generate verifiers for arbitrary MCMs and implementations. (iii) Modules for automatically translating from one MCM to another. (iv) Tools that compose the above modules to automatically generate litmus tests, to do binary translation including MCM translation, and other useful examples. (v) A pedagogical tool (an MCM animator and illustrator) for teaching students in computer architecture and parallel programming classes. To facilitate broad use of this work, basic modules and composed tools will be distributed as free software.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1533837</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martonosi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>martonosi@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8283</Code>
      <Text>Exploiting Parallel&amp;Scalabilty</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
