<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: Bilateral Photonics Workshop of the National Science Foundation (NSF) and Ministry of Science and Technology (MOST), Taiwan, May 29-June 1, 2015</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Year 2015 is designated as the "International Year of Light and Light-based Technologies" by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO). This bilateral workshop brings together leading researchers in the science of light (optics and photonics), from US and Taiwan. Via talks, discussions and planned lab visits, the event provides a platform for scientists from both sides to share latest research results, to have face-to-face discussions and to instigate collaboration. The event is organized by the US National Science Foundation (NSF) and the Ministry of Science and Technology (MOST) of Taiwan. The workshop takes place in Taipei, Taiwan from May 31 to June 1. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Optics and photonics is one of the most active and fast developing fields in engineering and science. Technological advances in optics and photonics have significantly advanced a broad range of areas from communication, medicine, aerospace to advanced manufacturing. Both US and Taiwan governments and industry have invested significantly in optics and photonics research. In particular, with the world largest foundries like Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Corporation (TSMC), Taiwan is a powerhouse of semiconductor industry, which has long been the engine of optics and photonics research. As technological breakthroughs continues to be achieved and new topics of optics and photonics, such as silicon photonics, plasmonics, new lasers and 2D materials, continue to emerge, multilateral collaborations between nations are becoming more and more important to the development and dissemination of research. This workshop and event will stimulate bilateral collaboration in photonics research between researchers in Taiwan and United States. Through face to face discussion and laboratory tours, information of the latest development in photonics research, research infrastructures and facility will be exchanged. Potential bilateral outreach possibility will also be discussed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1536097</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>moli@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>091E</Code>
      <Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
