<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Students to attend the ICS-NSF Vouchering the Stratigraphic Record Workshop and the Second International Congress on Stratigraphy Graz, Austria</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Judith Ellen Skog</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Travel Support for Students to attend the ICS-NSF Vouchering the Stratigraphic Record Workshop and the Second International Congress on Stratigraphy&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dena Smith, Geological Society of America&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will provide partial support for the international travel of 10 US graduate and post-doc, stratigraphers to attend the Second International Congress on Stratigraphy (STRATI 2015) and the ICS-NSF Workshop - Vouchering the Stratigraphic Record (VSR) in Graz, Austria from 19-25 July 2015. It is expected that more than 800 stratigraphers and sedimentologists from around the globe will attend STRATI 2015. The ICS-NSF Vouchering the Stratigraphic Record Workshop will bring together a group of international researchers and students to work on ways to synthesize and make available stratigraphic data from around the world. Those selected to receive travel support will be chosen from across the stratigraphic sciences, ensuring that a diverse group of graduate students and early professionals have the opportunity to attend and present their research results. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stratigraphy is a vibrant discipline that includes such currently relevant topics as geochronology, cyclostratigraphy, lithostratigraphy, sequence stratigraphy, tectono-stratigraphy, astronomical tuning, natural resource exploration and development, etc., all of which are needed to develop a detailed understanding of the history of the earth, its sedimentary crust, life, paleoenvironments, and anthropogenic impact. The STEPPE coordinating office, in collaboration with the American Geosciences Institute (AGI), Geological Society of America (GSA), the Society for Sedimentary Geology (SEPM), and the Paleontological Society (PS) will read and evaluate applications, ensuring that there is equal representation from across the disciplines and that there is balance in terms of gender and participation by those from underrepresented groups. Such participation in the 2nd International Congress on Stratigraphy and the ICS-NSF Vouchering the Stratigraphic Record workshop will uniquely contribute to the earth sciences because it will bring together a cross section of stratigraphers and sedimentary geologists from around the world, of all career stages, to share their research methods, findings and experiences in the field. This will lead to new opportunities for collaboration and the creation of novel approaches to studying our world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1539850</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dena@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Geological Society of America Today</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803011806</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3033571000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3300 PENROSE PL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7459</Code>
      <Text>SEDIMENTARY GEO &amp; PALEOBIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5955</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
