<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CyberSEES: Type 1: Enabling Sustainable Water Supplies Through Self-Powered Sensor-Based Monitoring</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>396011</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The worldwide demand for freshwater is increasing rapidly while water resources are becoming increasingly scarce. Exacerbating this imbalance is the deteriorated state of the water distribution infrastructure, which is afflicted with leakages of 15-25% of the total water supply. Consequently, the severe deterioration of this infrastructure poses a serious challenge to water sustainability. Leakage detection is an essential, but challenging, aspect of water supply management. Real-time monitoring schemes based on the changes in the vibration characteristics of the water pipelines have potential to detect leaks in a timely manner. Embedded wireless sensor networks are essential for such monitoring schemes; however, model designs and architectures of currently available wireless sensing networks remain severely constrained by the small energy reserves of environmentally-harmful batteries that last only for a limited period of time. This CyberSEES project is exploring possible hardware and software schemes for embedded wireless sensing systems, powered by locally harvested energy, to detect leakages in water distribution systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Leveraging a real-size, experimental pipeline set-up, this project explores (1) the energy harvesting potential in the water distribution system environment for use in sustainable powering of smart embedded sensing networks; (2) the use of vibration sensing-based methods to detect and locate pipeline leaks in water distribution systems; and (3) energy-efficient sensing and communication schemes suitable for use in constrained and variable energy environments. With advancements on several fronts, the research outcomes will make it possible to build smarter and adaptable water supply infrastructures for a more sustainable future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By adopting the developed sustainable monitoring set-up, water utilities will be equipped to prevent leakage of treated fresh water, conserve energy, and potentially prevent catastrophic failures in water distribution systems through early-detection of defects. The developed wireless sensing-based monitoring scheme can be easily adapted to other harsh, dynamic and energy-constrained environments for defect detection. The impact of this project on research infrastructure, especially the expansion of the pipeline test bed on the Clemson University campus, is significant as it offers several follow-up research and educational opportunities. This project also offers research opportunities for undergraduates and underrepresented students in addition to graduate student mentoring.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1539536</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sorber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jsorber@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kalyan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Piratla</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kpiratl@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sez</FirstName>
      <LastName>Atamturktur Russcher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sez@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abdul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abdkhan@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clemson University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8211</Code>
      <Text>CyberSEES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8207</Code>
      <Text>CyberSEES Type 1</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8231</Code>
      <Text>CyberSEES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
