<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Participant Support for Attendants to the 11th International Conference on Objective Bayes Methodology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gabor J. Szekely</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Workshop on Objective Bayes Methodology, O-Bayes15, will be held in Valencia, Spain, June 1-4, 2015. This will be the 11th meeting of one of the longest running and preeminent meetings in Bayesian statistics, following earlier meetings held in West Lafayette, IN, USA, 1996; Valencia, Spain, 1998; Ixtapa, Mexico, 2000; Granada, Spain, 2002; Aussois, France, 2003; Branson, MO, USA, 2005; Roma, Italy, 2007; Philadelphia, PA, USA, 2009; Shanghai, China, 2011; and Durham, NC, USA 2013. The principal objectives of O-Bayes15 will be to facilitate the exchange of recent research developments in objective Bayes theory and methodology, and related topics, to provide opportunities for new researchers, and to establish new collaborations that will channel efforts into pending problems and open new directions for investigation. O-Bayes15 will feature 21 invited talks and discussions, 3 tutorials and a poster session, all centering on major recent developments in objective Bayesian theory, methodology and application. The organization of the meeting is designed to facilitate interactions, with at most 7 talks per day and extensive discussion built in. The tutorials and evening poster sessions enhance the conference experience for graduate students and new researchers. Funding primarily supports graduate students and new researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;O-Bayes15 will bring together leading researchers in Bayesian analysis from around the world. The last decade has seen an explosion of interest in Bayesian statistical methodology across engineering, medicine and science, and this meeting provides a timely forum for the exchange of recent research developments, provides opportunities for new researchers and underrepresented groups, and establishes new collaborations that will channel efforts into pending problems and open new directions for investigation. In particular, the past two years have seen remarkable advances in the subjects of the conference; an event to disseminate these advances and spark new developments and collaborations is thus very timely. The scientific topics that will be considered include foundations of objective Bayesian analysis; objective priors in high dimensions; model uncertainty with huge model spaces; nonparametric analysis; massive multiple testing and subgroup analysis; and objective Bayesian methods for the interface of statistics and computational modeling of processes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1540663</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>George</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>edgeorge@wharton.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
