<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Meeting: 19th International Congress on Nitrogen Fixation to be held in Pacific Grove, California from October 4-9, 2015</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>C. Eduardo Vallejos</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 19th International Congress on Nitrogen Fixation (ICNF-19) that will be held at the Asilomar Conference in Pacific Grove, California from October 4-9, 2015 is a scientific meeting that provides outstanding opportunities for graduate students and postdoctoral scientists to interact with scientists from academia and industry on a global scale. The meeting actively emphasizes and supports the training of students and postdocs in developing their communication and interpersonal skills. Detailed efforts are planned to broaden the participation of women and members of groups under-represented in the sciences. The funding provided by NSF will broaden participation and help defray the costs of participation of students, postdoctoral associates and early-career investigators from the U.S. scientific community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since 1974, the ICNF has brought together previously insular research communities to stimulate international dialogue on the critical issues relating to biological nitrogen fixation. The conference presents perspectives on the state of knowledge and covers diverse topics on nitrogen fixation. The 2015 conference will have an outstanding program consisting of five plenary speakers: Peter Vitousek (Stanford University), Dennis Dean (Virginia Tech), Claire Gough (INRA, France), Jens Stougaard (Aarhus University, Denmark) and Mariangela Hungria (EMBRAPA, Brazil) along with closing remarks by Hauke Hennecke (ETH, Zurich). The core program includes poster sessions as well as 12 sessions consisting of oral talks on the Biochemistry of Nitrogen Fixation, the Chemistry &amp; Theory of Nitrogen, Technology &amp; Business Aspects, Regulation &amp; Physiology, Molecular Genetics &amp; Genomics of Legume Symbioses, Nodule Development &amp; Physiology, Global Aspects, the Evolution, &amp; Ecology, Genetics &amp; Genomics of Legume Symbiosis, Real World &amp; Food Security Issues, Microbiology &amp; Synthetic Biology, and Non-Legume Systems. The content of the meeting will be disseminated by providing access to abstracts through the conference web site. In addition, like many previous ICNF meetings, the plan is to publish a book volume summarizing the presentations for ICNF-19.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1541289</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cramer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spjcramer@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8011</Code>
      <Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9109</Code>
      <Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
