<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Holocene Deglaciation of the Western Ross Embayment: Constraints from East Antarctic Outlet Glaciers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>335196</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julie Palais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Reconstructions of past changes in thickness and extent of the Antarctic ice sheet are important for evaluating past and present sea-level change, and for validating numerical models necessary to make realistic predictions of changes under future climate and ocean conditions. Models estimate that the Ross Sea sector was one of the largest contributors to sea-level rise from Antarctica as the ice sheet adjusted during the past ten thousand years from the glacial period to the Holocene. In this sector, ice flow into the embayment comes through West Antarctic ice streams and through East Antarctic outlet glaciers that flow through the Transantarctic Mountains. Observational data constrain the last glacial maximum and the Holocene retreat, but models are necessary to understand the environmental conditions needed for outlet glaciers to reach observed high stands, to fit the observed patterns of retreat, and to understand how the contribution of ice from West Antarctica and from East Antarctica changed over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will use available geological and geophysical data in combination with forward ice-flow models and inverse models to investigate the evolution of the four Transantarctic outlet glaciers where sufficient data exist. The objectives of this new modeling are to constrain the glaciological conditions necessary for these glaciers to thicken during the last glacial, thin during the Holocene, and reach their present-day state. By testing specific hypotheses this work contributes to an interdisciplinary effort to understand Holocene deglaciation of the Ross Sea Embayment. In addition, the modeling will address the resolving power of the available data to answer key questions for each target glacier. Broader impacts include mentoring a graduate student, public outreach, incorporation of research into high-school and university classes, and support of an early-career investigator.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1542756</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koutnik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkoutnik@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Conway</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hcon@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bsmith@apl.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5116</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC GLACIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8013</Code>
      <Text>High Risk/Reward Innovative Research</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
