<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Mapping, Measuring and Modeling Geomorphology and Ice Change in Dronning Maud Land, Antarctica</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36928</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julie Palais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Reconstructing and predicting the response of the Antarctic Ice Sheet to climate change is a major challenge facing the Earth Science community. Computer models of ice sheet behavior are central to addressing this challenge. In this project we will test and improve ice sheet models by comparing model predictions of past ice extent to the geologic record in Dronning Maud Land, Antarctica. This innovative project will collect key geologic data from mountains called nunataks that extend above current and former ice levels that can be used as "dipsticks" to reconstruct changes in ice elevation that will be used to improve the models. The end result will be both much better knowledge of past three-dimensional changes of the Antarctic Ice Sheet, and improved models that allow for more accurate simulations of potential future changes in the ice sheet. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will fill critical gaps in the geologic record of the pattern and timing of vertical changes in the East Antarctic Ice Sheet in western Dronning Maud Land, by focusing on areas that are critical for differentiating between possible models of past ice sheet configuration. Reconstruction of ice-sheet surface changes will involve mapping and cosmogenic nuclide dating of glacially sculpted bedrock, ice-marginal moraines, and erratic boulders at different elevations on nunataks. Patterns of 10Be, 26Al, 14C, and 21Ne concentrations and ratios will enable inferences about the timing and magnitude of changes in maximum ice surface elevations and periods of burial by non-erosive (cold-based) ice. Results will be integrated with data from other areas to provide insight into changes across the entire Antarctic Ice Sheet, and into the role of large ice sheets in climate evolution and global sea level changes. The field-based results will provide constraints against which predictive ice sheet models will be tested and improved, contributing to glaciology, climate and Quaternary science. Broader impacts of this study will also advance the development of the next generation of STEM students and polar scientists. While gaining experience in international collaboration, field and laboratory methods, data analysis, and modeling, two graduate students will work with teachers to develop, implement, and disseminate standards-based lesson plans for student activities linking this research to learning objectives for middle school science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1542930</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lifton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nlifton@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harbor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jharbor@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5116</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC GLACIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
