<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PARTIAL SUPPORT OF THE CONDENSED MATTER AND MATERIALS RESEARCH COMMITTEE</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Sokol</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This award provides partial support for the activities of the Condensed Matter and Materials Research Committee (CMMRC). The CMMRC is a sub-committee of the National Academy of Science Board on Physics and Astronomy and is tasked with serving as a conduit for interactions between the condensed matter and materials research communities and the federal government, including the agencies that support this research, and with monitoring the health of and identifying important new developments in these fields. The members of the CMMRC are leading scientists from across all the subfields encompassed by condensed matter and materials research. The CMMRC carries out its mission using regular meetings to discuss emerging research areas, working with sponsoring agencies to organize topical workshops, interacting with professional societies, and developing resources for the general public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This project provides partial support for the National Research Council's (NRC) Condensed Matter and Materials Research Committee (CMMRC). The CMMRC is a multidisciplinary group with membership drawn from universities, industry, and government laboratories. The areas of expertise represented on the committee are intended to cover the breadth of the condensed matter and materials research fields. Nominees for committee membership have been and will continue to be selected on the basis of demonstrated intellectual leadership in these areas and thoughtful consideration of cross-cutting issues. The operating guidelines of CMMRC include the following objectives: (1) to respond to requests for technical information and assistance, both from within the National Academies and from outside federal research agencies; (2) to initiate and oversee ad hoc studies in these fields and their multidisciplinary connections to other fields of science and technology; (3) to serve as long-term stewards for studies initiated under CMMRC's direction; (4) to act as an educational resource for the condensed matter and materials research communities and the agencies that support them; and (5) to provide a forum for discussion among condensed matter and materials scientists and Washington D.C. policymakers. To carry out those objectives, CMMRC meets on an annual basis and between those meetings, conducts its business through telephone conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1542084</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlancaster@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1710</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
