<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-CORPS Team: Cocoon Cam, a Wearless Smart Baby Monitor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lydia Mcclure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Despite the availability of baby monitors, parents continue to check on their baby at regular intervals. Conventional video or audio based baby monitors are not able to detect vitals or identify if the baby is unwell. Parents like existing video based monitors to confirm that the baby is safe and well when awake, but the lack of body movement while the baby is sleeping leads to anxiety and repeated check on the baby. This problem recently led to the development of wearable baby monitors that can detect vitals. However, wearables are perceived detrimental to the baby's health due to radio frequency effects and possible skin allergies. The technology developed by this team involves integration of software and hardware enabling concurrent non-contact measurement of heart and respiratory rate, and temperature from a single device, day and night.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps team will build a portable non-contact device to detect vital signs and eliminate the need for hardware to be attached or in extremely close proximity to the baby. The proposed solution is Cocoon Cam, a wearless network-connected system that consists of hardware and software sensors and provides video, audio, and vitals on a dashboard to check on those at day or night. Parents can view the dashboard on a smartphone and set personalized alerts for any of the monitored features. Parents perceive that a dependable device that could help monitor vitals is beneficial and gives peace of mind that their babies are healthy and comfortable.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1542255</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nadir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weibel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weibel@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
