<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2015 Campus Cyberinfrastructure Program PI Workshop: CC-NIE, CC-IIE and CC-DNI</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>70000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This workshop builds upon the success of the 2014 CC-NIE Campus Cyberinfrastructure Workshop, providing an opportunity for NSF Campus Cyberinfrastructure award recipients to meet in-person, exchange project findings, interact with national cyberinfrastructure experts and collaborate across project areas and project regions. The proposed workshop will be co-located with two other community meetings, the ESnet Site Coordinators Committee (ESCC) meeting and The Quilt Fall Member meeting. The workshop will promote dialogue across a range of important and timely topics in campus networking including the larger context of campus cyberinfrastructure. Joint programming with the Quilt and ESCC on Day 2 of the workshop will provide an opportunity to develop stronger ties between campus cyberinfrastructure, science driven applications and regional networks as technical and cyberinfrastructure resources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is the exchange project findings, interaction between national cyberinfrastructure experts, collaboration across project areas and project regions that will lead to new ideas, relationships and collaborations associated with an in person workshop. The broader impact includes the dissemination of workshop information, including the workshop presentations along with a final workshop report to Campus Cyberinfrastructure award participants as well as to the campus and research community in general.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1544340</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gwendolyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huntoon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>huntoon@kinber.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leasure</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jen@thequilt.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Keystone Initiative for Network Based Education and Research</Name>
      <CityName>Harrisburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>171124051</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7179637490</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5775 Allentown Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
