<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference Grant: Student Travel Awards for IEEE RFID-TA 2015, Tokyo, 16-18 September 2015</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6750</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Hao Ling</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Conference Grant: Student Travel Awards for IEEE RFID-TA 2015, Tokyo, 16-18 September 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IEEE International Conference on Radio-Frequency Identification Technology and Applications (IEEE RFID-TA) is a premier conference for multidisciplinary research encompassing RFID, wireless sensor networks, energy-harvesting, localization, and low-energy wireless communications. With the conference site in Tokyo, Japan in 2015, it is expected to draw researchers from Japan, Korea, mainland China, Hong Kong, Taiwan, and other Asian countries, many of whom do not regularly attend the North American IEEE RFID conference. Approximately 150 attendees with 30 paper presentations are expected. The NSF funds will provide partial travel support for graduate students or post-doctoral researchers who are US citizens or permanent residents to attend IEEE RFID-TA 2015 and present their work at the conference. The IEEE Counsel on RFID has already provided some base funding for a travel grants program for student attendees. The NSF-sponsored travel grants program will be used as a topping grant, to be awarded competitively to US citizens or permanent residents that meet the existing travel grants program requirements. The NSF grant will provide numerous benefits to early-career US researchers, who may not otherwise be able to attend, by providing them with international networking opportunity and brightening their future prospects. Moreover, this conference has strong industry attendance, and will allow early-career researchers the opportunity to explore collaborations with industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1545862</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Durgin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>durgin@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>105E</Code>
      <Text>RF/Microwave &amp; mm-wave tech</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
