<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Creating a Global Network of Mountain Observatories: A workshop to be held in September 2015 in Crested Butte, CO</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter H. McCartney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this workshop is to plan a global network of mountain observatories by linking and aligning existing mountain observatories. Mountains are high-value features within the Earth system. Mountain regions are currently experiencing profound environmental changes, which translate into serious challenges to society. Bringing science to bear on these challenges requires more comprehensive, long term data on mountain systems around the world. A global network of observatories on mountain social ecological systems is a key step toward obtaining these data and promoting comparative analyses. Observatories of various types exist already in mountains around the world; the key is to bring them into communication with each other and to move toward congruent observing methodologies that reveal the complexity of these social ecological systems. Such a network of observatories accelerates innovation and aligns methodologies. A network promotes exchange on questions and methods by promoting transparency and breaking barriers between disciplines and cultures. A network can also develop data analysis and management policies and procedure to support collaboration. Members within the network build stronger contacts, see different solutions, and learn whom they can work with to find help with their challenges. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will convent an international panel of representatives from research, government, and education to address the motivating science questions, the structure of the network, the key variables now and for the future, the management of data, and communication. It will define objectives to bring together data from many different sites, modeling approaches that could help extend observations and best practices with respect to the engagement of stakeholders and the co-production of knowledge. Many of the environmental issues facing mountain regions have serious social implications. The participant list includes stakeholders that can make the network more effective at informing decision making and policy. Observatories can serve as active sites where researchers can engage with and learn from advocates, business, and elected officials. Such a network will also encourage active engagement with local stakeholders, K-12 education, governmental and non-governmental organizations, and institutions of higher learning.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1547475</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Sagehen@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
