<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: The Role of Engineered Systems in Adaptation of Staphylococcus aureus</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>71388</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1547080&lt;br/&gt;Brion&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Several common bacteria are beneficial in the human system; however, mutations in these bacteria can result in strains that cause infectious disease. In recent years, deaths attributable to bacterial infections from these strains exceeded those from HIV/AIDS. In preliminary work the PI has detected high concentrations of infectious bacterial strains in wastewater treatment plants, and she plans to investigate whether these facilities are hot spots for the processes that foster the mutations that create harmful bacteria. The PI will investigate the prevalence of a particular harmful bacterium across two wastewater treatment plants, one connected to multiple hospitals and the other collecting primarily suburban sewage. The results of this project may guide new methods for wastewater treatment that will reduce concentrations of harmful bacteria and avoid the infectious diseases caused by these bacteria.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent findings of Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) in wastewater suggest that our sewage collection and treatment systems may serve as reservoirs and adaptive hot-spots for community acquired MRSA. It is possible that wastewater systems promote conditions that facilitate horizontal gene transfer of mobile genetic elements between Staphylococcus aureus strains and other bacteria. An example is the conjugative plasmid for vancomycin-resistant enterococci that has resulted in the emergence of vancomycin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus. Preliminary data from 10 pairs of influent samples at the plants have documented the prevalence of both Staphylococcus aureus and MRSA to be greater in the hospital-fed system. To date, no studies have compared the prevalence of MRSA in hospital sewer systems to that of domestic sewage without hospital waste. The results of this research will expand our knowledge of how engineered systems may create conditions conducive to evolution of more virulent and environmentally robust strains of non-enteric pathogens, spurring a rethinking of the primary purpose of sewage treatment and the control systems engineers put into place to protect health and the environment. Results may change the way we view and design sewage collection, treatment, and distribution systems, track adaptation of microbes, and prevent disease transmission. In this exploratory research the PI will apply recent advances in clinical and ecological research to understand the potential risks associated with engineered systems with respect to evolving pathogenic microbiota.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1547080</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brion</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gbrion@engr.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1440</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>021E</Code>
      <Text>Water management</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
