<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Planning Grant for a STEM Broadening Participation Research Center Initiative</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200096</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities - Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) provides support to undertake an institutional self-analysis in preparation for a Broadening Participation Research Center. Broadening Participation Research Centers are expected to serve as a national hub for the rigorous study and broad dissemination of the critical pedagogies and culturally sensitive interventions that contribute to the success of HBCUs in educating African American STEM undergraduates. The project at Morehouse College seeks to plan the essential research questions, experimental designs and programmatic activities for creating a large-scale STEM broadening participation research innovation center designed to research "how HBCUs can best understand and activate the particular brand of genius within a given student."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to employ this asset-based approach in partnership with HBCUs, industry, and nonprofit organizations to plan a research center that will in part utilize STEM innovation as a tool for student empowerment. Activities of the project include: networking with other HBCUs and forming partnerships with Morehouse College; soliciting involvement from innovation centers, industry and non-profit organizations; developing well defined research questions and experiments; planning a dissemination program to include a comprehensive web portal, workshops, faculty sabbaticals, summer internships for students and faculty, conferences and possibly a journal. The project will be guided by an external advisory committee.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1548523</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lycurgus</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muldrow</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lmuldrow@morehouse.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Garikai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Campbell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>doreen.stevens@morehouse.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Morehouse College</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4046812800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>830 Westview Drive S W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
