<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Environmental Assessment of the McMurdo Dry Valleys: Witness to the Past and Guide to the Future; Colorado State University, May 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>92935</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Cutler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Through the unique global partnership that is the Antarctic Treaty system, the entire continent is formally designated as a natural reserve, devoted to peace and science. To visit, and operate in, an environment like this comes with a responsibility to do so carefully and with as minimal an impact as possible. It is thus imperative that scientists, tour operators, contractors and managers operating in Antarctica convene regularly to assess the state of the environment and delineate requirements for the future that will maintain the pristine nature of the continent. A region of Antarctica that is particularly vulnerable to human impact is the McMurdo Dry Valleys (MDV). This area is the largest ice-free expanse on the continent (ice free area = 4,500 km2) and encompasses a total area of 22,700 km2. The landscape is a mosaic of glaciers, mountain ranges, permanently ice covered lakes, ephemeral streams and novel soil ecosystems. The global uniqueness of this environment has led to increased levels of scientific research and tourism over the past decade. Given the increase in human presence, it is important to assess routinely the impact of these activities for both ethical and scientific reasons. It has been 17 years since environmental stewardship of the McMurdo Dry Valleys (MDV) has been formally addressed. During these 17 years, research activities in the valleys have increased exponentially and major research campaigns have been established in the Taylor, Wright, Miers, Garwood, Beacon and Victoria Valleys. This 17-year period has seen the implementation of a Dry Valleys Specially Managed Area (ASMA) and several new Specially Protected Areas (ASPAs) in the region. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the relatively long hiatus since the last environmental assessment of the MDV, in concert with exponential increases in research activity, this award will partially fund a fourth workshop to assess the environmental integrity of the region, discuss the success of present management strategies, and develop an international plan with which to move forward. The workshop will include more than 40 scientists, contractors and environmental mangers to discuss environmental stewardship and scientific site integrity of the MDV. Workshop participants have been carefully chosen to ensure gender balance and representation from all career levels. The early career scientists will have a chance to change the way they will work in Antarctica, allowing them to conduct research in an environment that they have had a hand in shaping. Individuals from five countries will participate, providing a global balance to the workshop. A report will be produced by this workshop that will set the stage for environmental stewardship in the MDV for the next decade.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1548256</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Priscu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpriscu@montana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Montana State University</Name>
      <CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5292</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC INTEGRATED SYS SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
