<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty, Unsupported Educational Pathways and Stagnant Social Mobility via Mobile Apps</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glenn H. Larsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I project is targeted to support two end users; one being, first-generation college students who do not have the resources or college knowledge to get them through degree completion; and two, college advisors/counselors whose caseloads have reached insurmountable proportions making it impossible to provide quality attention to students with numbers spiking at rates not seen before since before the 2008 recession. Using technology that supports both users and research suggesting a need for innovative methods will find that this project can positively impact both. In the form of a mobile app, students are connected to their college advisor 24/7 and can send questions or concerns. Through this technology, students receive responses, notifications, and weekly guidance directly on their smart device, laptop or desktop. Implementing this app system not only teaches students and breaks down college policies and procedures, it also supports college advisors/counselors with reports and real-time data that enhances their role to perform efficiently through digital advising. Compared to the traditional methods currently being used today, significant differences can be found in the number of times and ways apps can provide service in just a matter of minutes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The product and platform during Phase I consists of 29 different native, web-based, mobile applications to be accessed through the Google Play Store, App Store and used on any Internet-based smart device and/or computer by post-secondary students. The curriculum has been created from a psycho-cultural perspective - meaning considered the beliefs, behavior, and emotions of historically underrepresented first generation students and used that data in developing the app curriculum. This system also serves college advisors/counselors to generate a number of reports including number of advisor to student connections (up to 48 times per semester), student engagement as well as periodic and strategic grade checks. The apps are a stand-alone product with no need to integrate into any existing system and takes 15 minutes to learn. This app system is designed to supplement student support services via their college advisor/counselor and overall goal is to increase student retention, persistence, and graduation efforts. To measure usability and feasibility, research team will use system data reports and surveys completed by students and college advisors/counselors to interpret and summarize results to provide a solid foundation for Phase II R/R&amp;D.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1549290</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Renee</FirstName>
      <LastName>Romero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>RRomero@CyclusBreak.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/27/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CyclusBreak</Name>
      <CityName>Denver</CityName>
      <ZipCode>802052751</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3032043665</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3222 Champa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>118E</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8031</Code>
      <Text>Education Products</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8032</Code>
      <Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8039</Code>
      <Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
