<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for the Doctoral Consortium Program at IEEE International Conference on Health Informatics (ICHI) 2015</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports twelve US matriculated students to participate in IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics (ICHI) Doctoral Consortium Program. Students who are selected will receive funding to cover their expenditures on registration, travel, and lodging. Students will be scheduled for a rapid-fire talk, with auto-advancing slides, to present a synopsis of their work. These rapid overviews will be followed by a poster session where participants and mentors can discuss research in greater detail. Selected participants may also be invited to give a longer oral presentation. The consortium will close with a panel discussion discussing topics relevant to doctoral students (e.g., dissertation proposal, dissertation execution, job search, and grant seeking). Awardee students will also benefit from vis-a-vis meeting with leading researchers and receive valuable guidance on direction of their dissertation, specific issues in health informatics, as well as career development. This award promotes the training and development of the future generation of leaders and workforce, as well as enhances the participation of women and minority students in in this critical field. The student award application procedure and results will be announced at the ICHI 2015 conference website (http://cs.utdallas.edu/ichi2015/).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics (ICHI) is the premier community forum concerned with the application of computer science principles, information science principles, information technology, and communication technology to address problems in healthcare, public health, and everyday wellness. The conference highlights the most novel technical contributions in computing-oriented health informatics and the related social and ethical implications. The conference aims to (i) fertilize interdisciplinary education among healthcare informatics students, researchers, and practitioners; (ii) promote research design and methodology development in the emerging fields; and (iii) coalesce knowledge translation between academia and industry/government. Issues addressed by ICHI become increasingly important in the marketplace with availability of numerous consumer and clinician systems and services. The conference has been held four times: 2010 (IHI 2010, Washington DC, USA), 2012 (IHI 2012, Miami, Florida, USA), 2013 (ICHI 2013, Philadelphia, PA, USA), and 2014 (ICHI 2014, Verona, Italy). ICHI 2015 will be held in Dallas, Texas USA on October 21-23, 2015. The IEEE ICHI 2015 proceedings are published by IEEE.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1549949</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mingli@csufresno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State University-Fresno Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Fresno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>937261852</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5592780840</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4910 N. Chestnut Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
