<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Exploratory Research to Demonstrate the Feasibility of "Tactile Internet" Islands</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299396</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The vision of this exploratory project is to support the research needed to examine the hardware-software techniques that would be needed to enable a Tactile Internet. The Tactile Internet is a wireless based internet framework for steering and control of remote objects and has the potential for breakthrough technologies much in the same way the cellular telephony was enabled by the wireless technologies during the past few decades. It could have wide ranging applications with broad social impact in areas such as education, traffic control, remote surgery, sports, entertainment, gaming, smart grid etc. Thus, the broader societal impact of the project would be in the long run, but is likely to be far reaching. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop novel algorithms and the hardware-software co-design methods to address the issues of ultra-low latency and resilience that would be required of the Tactile Internets of the future. The project will undertake building a prototype at the International Institute of Computer Science (ICSI) at Berkeley, California. It is expected that while the technical risks in this project are significant, the potential gains far exceed the risks, and if successful, this exploratory project can lead to new research more suitable for consideration by several federal and industrial sponsors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1550143</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerhard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fettweis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Gerhard.Fettweis@vodafone-chair.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>International Computer Science Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947044115</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106662900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1947 CENTER ST STE 600</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7945</Code>
      <Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
