<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Role Of Resource Control In The Development Of Social Complexity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240867</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Mitch Hendrickson, at the University of Illinois at Chicago, and his international collaborative team, is undertaking research on the role of iron production in the expansion of medieval states, with specific focus on the Angkorian Khmer Empire in Cambodia. Iron has long been viewed as an important catalyst for societal development yet few studies have effectively demonstrated evidence of changes in the scale of production or the impact that sudden access to high quality sources had on agricultural, architectural and military activities. Archaeology offers critical new insight into the way that iron was made, distributed and consumed over time as well as identifying the type of political-economic relationships between the state and local stake holders who lived around major resources. Fundamental to this investigation is how and why do major sources suddenly become a critical part of state development? New technologies and increased access are two important factors enabling control over resources that were often known but left untouched for hundreds of years. Parallel processes are witnessed today within the oil and gas industry and the expansion of China?s global resource interests across Asia and Africa.&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Hendrickson?s team will investigate whether intensification and control of industrial activities were responsible for vast and sudden imperial expansion in the past. The geographic focus of the project is the Phnom Dek region in central Cambodia, the largest iron ore source available to the Angkorian Khmer Empire. The research team comprising archaeologists, archaeometallurgists, paleobotanists, and geologists will record the spatial and temporal history of industrial production and the relationship between the state consumers and local producers over a period of five hundred years. Excavation and intensive survey of smelting sites will identify critical changes in production technology and corresponding shifts in the quantity and quality of iron used for tools and weapons. The impact of this industrial history will be examined on two levels. First, what type of control did the state exert over the groups responsible for producing iron? Second, is there a direct correlation between increased production and major architectural building episodes and military campaigns undertaken by the Khmer Empire? The results will provide a dynamic history of resource management and political process that will become a benchmark for understanding the successes and failures of states and their impact on manufacturing communities. In addition to providing new opportunities for education and student training this project will generate important regional databases on metallurgical technology, the archaeomagnetic intensity curve of the earth, and industrial forest management that will be generally available and have broad, immediate scientific significance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1550850</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mitch</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hendrickson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjhend@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
