<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Descent, rational points, and the geometry of moduli spaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>246759</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Diophantine geometry is the study of integer solutions of polynomial equations, seen through the prism of the geometry of their solutions over the complex numbers. Structural characteristics of the integer solutions are sometimes governed by subtle geometric phenomena. We rely on results on the geometry of complex surfaces, especially those defined by equations of small degree. Examples include equations of degree three or four in three variables. Our hope is to discern larger patterns governing the behavior of large classes of problems sharing common characteristics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses problems at the interface of algebraic and Diophantine geometry arising from fundamental questions about the behavior of rational points on algebraic varieties. In the simplest situations, these touch on beautiful constructions from classical algebraic geometry. Beyond these, one quickly encounters deep geometric problems not accessible through classical techniques. Specific research questions will include: How to interpret moduli spaces of K3 surfaces with level structure geometrically? To what extent can these be organized using notions of derived equivalence for K3 surfaces and their twisted analogs? Can these techniques be used to evaluate Brauer-Manin obstructions explicitly? Given two derived-equivalent K3 surfaces, how are their Diophantine properties related, especially over local fields? For del Pezzo fibrations over curves, how are spaces of rational curves governed by cohomological invariants? As the numerical invariants of the fibrations vary, what inductive structures are shown by the spaces of rational curves? These will be addressed using deformation-theoretic properties of rational curves, structural descriptions of cones of effective curves arising from Bridgeland stability conditions, and classifications of degenerate fibers of K3 fibrations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1551514</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brendan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hassett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bhassett@math.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
