<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CyberGIS Curriculum Workshop for Synthesizing Education Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49987</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sushil Prasad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CyberGIS, defined as geographic information science and systems (GIS) based on advanced cyberinfrastructure, has emerged during the past several years as a interdisciplinary field to improve research productivity and enable scientific breakthroughs. CyberGIS represents a new-generation GIS in the era of big compute and data for advancing data-intensive knowledge discovery, visualization and visual analytics, and collaborative problem solving and decision-making. While cyberGIS research is making advancements in a number of domains, it has become increasingly important to understand broad education and workforce development needs for cyberGIS across various communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate curriculum aspects of cyberGIS and engage domain experts and stakeholder representatives to develop a roadmap leading to curriculum guidelines and resulting in recommendations for adoption in undergraduate and graduate core courses in the U.S. and internationally. This workshop effort will employ a community-driven approach to understanding how to synthesize interdisciplinary education materials revolving around cyberGIS and cyberinfrastructure. Therefore, the workshop will build on previous community efforts and focus on community engagement, particularly in assessing new models of curriculum development and adoption. The project intends to engage interests from industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1551492</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shaowen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shaowen@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7361</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND WORKFORCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9254</Code>
      <Text>CURRICULUM DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
