<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>APS DPF Participant Travel Support - 68th Annual DFD Meeting in Boston, MA, November 22-24, 2015</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1551170 (Cole)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal seeks funds to partially cover travel expenses of graduate students, post-doctoral researchers, and junior faculty members from institutions in the United States to participate in the conference entitled, "American Physical Society, Division of Fluid Dynamics, 68th Annual DFD Meeting 2015" in Boson, MA, November 22-24, 2015. This is the largest international annual meeting of fluid dynamicists in the world, with 2,500 anticipated attendees. The meeting has been successfully run for over sixty five years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The chief intellectual merit of this conference lies in the exchange of scientific ideas, presentations of cutting edge research, and exposure to a richly diverse array of topics in virtually every sub-discipline of fluid dynamics. The conference will be attended by both prominent and young scientists in fluid dynamics from around the world, who will be discussing present and future directions of research and research challenges. The conference will foster cross-fertilization of ideas among researchers in cutting edge areas of fluid dynamics and will address challenges involved in advancing the field in the near future. The broader impact will be to increase participation of students and young scientists who would not otherwise be able to afford to travel to the meeting and pay associated costs. Preference is given: (i) to those presenting talks at the meeting, (ii) to students, (iii) to those who have not received such an award in the past, and (iv) to no more than one applicant from a given research adviser. The application and selection process is under the auspices of the DFD External Affairs Committee, chaired by Prof. Beverley McKeon of the California Institute of Technology with Vice Chair Prof. Kenneth Christensen of Notre Dame, serving as the process coordinator. Each member of the External Affairs Committee reads each of the applications and ranks them according to the priorities of the travel grant program (emphasis is given to students, young scientists, and, in general, scientists from under-represented groups). NSF support will fund individuals from the US only.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1551170</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ken</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cole</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cole@aps.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Physical Society</Name>
      <CityName>College Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207403841</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3012093220</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Physics Ellipse</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>058E</Code>
      <Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>059E</Code>
      <Text>Complex fluids</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
