<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: The Size of the Global Dust Cycle and its Radiative Impact on Climate</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>601670</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anjuli S. Bamzai</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>At any given time, the Earth's atmosphere contains tens of millions of metric tons of desert dust. Surprisingly, many basic questions regarding the effects of these vast quantities of dust on climate remain poorly known. How much dust is actually in the atmosphere? Does desert dust warm or cool our planet? Will future climate-induced changes in dust storms oppose or enhance man-made climate changes? This project will address these fundamental questions by leveraging satellite observations, experimental measurements of atmospheric dust and its properties, and climate model simulations of desert dust climate impacts. In addition, this project will integrate educational and research activities at UCLA's department of Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences through the establishment of a Research-Enhanced Learning Assistant program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will lead to improved understanding of desert dust's prevalence and its climate impacts as well as enhance forecasts of regional and global climate changes, thereby helping to inform policies to adapt to or mitigate future climate changes. Furthermore, the project results will facilitate improved understanding of dust impacts on weather, the biosphere, air quality, and human health. Finally, the Research-Enhanced Learning Assistant program will improve learning, recruitment, and retention of geosciences students, and especially of under-represented minorities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1552519</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jasper</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kok</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jfkok@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5740</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
