<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: BIGDATA: SMART Data - Academic Success Made Affordable, Rapid, and Timely through Integrated Data Analytics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cherniavsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Academic Success Made Affordable, Rapid, and Timely through Integrated Data Analytics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Data science techniques have revolutionized many academic fields and led to terrific gains in the commercial sector. They have to date been underutilized in solving critical problems in the US educational system, particularly in understanding Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) learning and learning environments, broadening participation in STEM, and increasing retention for students traditionally underserved in STEM. The goals of the Directorate for Education and Human Resources through the Critical Techniques and Technologies for Advancing Foundations and Applications of Big Data Science &amp; Engineering (BIGDATA) program are to advance fundamental research aimed at understanding and solving these critical problems, and to catalyze the use of data science in Education Research. This Early Concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) will seek to understand the background and backbone of systems of data processing and analytics that can provide insights using standard types of data that colleges and universities already have (for example, from their Learning Management Systems, administrative data systems, and advising systems) to provide predictions and recommendations to students and instructors to increase the percentage of students who succeed in college and graduate on time. This has terrific potential to increase graduation rates at two- and four-year institutions, which can lower college costs for families and students. In addition, it has terrific potential to increase the attraction and retention of underrepresented minorities in STEM fields, as it will identify barriers for all students to graduating successfully and on time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team vision is to eventually build a data platform that integrates key data sources and provides tools that leverage important insights from these sources. The types of data sources are: 1) longitudinal data from undergraduate students on their academic trajectories in STEM majors; 2) Learning management system (LMS) records of student activity, and 3) text data from a variety of sources, such as advisors. The tools will include a 1) GUI for students, teachers and administrators to see student academic pathways and 2) a portal for communication between students, faculty and advisors. This system will help students, teachers and admistrators engage in Data Driven Decision Making (D3M) around academic pathways to successful and on time graduation from college. This Early Concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) will solve many challenges that must be undertaken to achieve this vision and provide the solutions to those challenges to relevant communities in a variety of ways. The team has four goals for this early concept project. The first is to examine existing data and predictive models for understanding student success and retention and build a catalog of applications and data types available for decision making around pathways to these outcomes. The second goal is to describe design specifications, including data types, algorithms, and machine learning techniques that are needed to build the data platform. The third is to pilot research on critical elements of a D3M training program for undergraduate students, instructors and administrators. The final goal is to develop a design framework that builds ethics, privacy and security in from the ground up. All products will be made available as publications, curricula, or software shared openly on common forums such as GitHub.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1552288</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ohland</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ohland@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heidi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Diefes-Dux</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hdiefes@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Krishna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Madhavan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cm@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mihaela</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vorvoreanu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mihaela@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zentner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mzentner@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8083</Code>
      <Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
