<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Production of an affordable synthetic colostrum replacer in edible green algae</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>712550</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruth M. Shuman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will be to produce colostrum proteins in edible green algae that have the potential to reduce the use and dependence on antibiotics in livestock animals. Colostrum proteins have both beneficial health and growth properties that may drastically decrease the dependence on antibiotics. Unfortunately, there is a limited supply of colostrum. Algae provide an affordable and scalable system for the production of the valuable proteins found in colostrum. Recently, it was demonstrated that the use of antibiotics in livestock animals caused the formation of antibiotic resistant bacteria. Colostrum proteins naturally stimulate the animal's immune system and allows them to improve their own ability to fight off infections and ultimately increase their rate of weight gain. The production of colostrum proteins at a large scale in an untapped market that has the potential to gain market share from the multi-billion dollar antibiotic industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase II project proposes to demonstrate the feasibility of producing colostrum proteins in algae using biomanufacturing. Some of the problems associated with having the animal livestock industry adapt a new product is demonstrating cost and feasibility. To accomplish the goal of decreasing antibiotic use, this project will first focus on optimizing the production process to drive the cost of producing colostrum proteins in algae down. Next, work will be done on developing optimal formulations of colostrum proteins and testing them in mice models before moving to larger livestock animals. Once an optimal formulation is established, trials will be done in pig models. In the pig models, colostrum proteins produced in algae will be tested to determine their ability to assist animals in fighting off infections and also their ability to improve the animal's rate of weight gain. Finally, this project will strive to demonstrate that colostrum proteins produced in algae can give the same positive outcomes in animals when compared to animals given antibiotics. By accomplishing these goals, algae colostrum proteins can drastically decrease the dependence on antibiotics and their negative side effects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1555951</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Miller</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tran</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>miller@tritonai.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Triton Animal Products</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921032110</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173208743</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>302 Washington St #150-2995</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8032</Code>
      <Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
