<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Catalytic C-C Bond Formation and Cleavage at Cobalt: Mechanism, Origins and Application</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>626635</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this CAREER award funded by the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Wesley Bernskoetter from Brown University is investigating the mechanistic pathways and origins of selective two-electron, carbon-carbon bond transformations at earth abundant metals. In particular, strong field cobalt complexes that mediate carbon-carbon bond reductive elimination and oxidative addition reactions necessary for catalytic applications are being targeted. These fundamental studies examine factors such as ligand field strength, spin state interconversion, and coordination geometry, which may influence the rate and selectivity of these transformations. This research will further the utilization of base-metals as surrogates for platinum group metal catalysis in reactions ranging from cross-coupling to carbocyanation. In concert with the research endeavors, this project is enhancing the training of undergraduate students through peer mentoring and tutorials as well as through a discovery-based introduction to physical sciences for pre-college students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A variety of manufacturing industries rely on metal-based catalysis to produce chemicals and materials in an energy efficient and cost-effective manner. The past decades have witnessed a significant growth in the number of important new catalytic reactions promoted by metal catalysts; however, the metals employed in these discoveries have largely come from a group of expensive, rare, and toxic metals. This research project seeks to develop routes to accomplish some of the same important catalytic reactions using metals that are much more abundant, less expensive, and potentially less toxic. Future impacts of the work could include the development of more economical and sustainable manufacturing technologies. This project will also include professional training for the next generation of research scientists and opportunities for pre-college students to discover the important place of science in society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1556093</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wesley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bernskoetter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Wesley_Bernskoetter@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8650</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8676</Code>
      <Text>Critical Elements</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
