<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Origins of Hawaiian Reef Fishes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>591550</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David L. Garrison</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Hawaiian Islands are the product of a volcanic hot spot in the middle of the North Pacific. Hence every living thing on this isolated archipelago has origins elsewhere. This project will investigate the origins of Hawaiian reef fishes, which are important both as a food source and a cultural touchstone in native Hawaiian communities. Two prominent hypotheses maintain that marine fish originally arrived from the south (Line Islands and Johnston Atoll) or from the west (Japan). To test these hypotheses, this research will augment existing specimens from Hawaii with expeditions to Johnston Atoll (closest shallow habitat to the south), the northern Line Islands (Palmyra), southern Line Islands (Christmas Island), and Ryukyu Islands and Ogasawara Islands in Japan. Advanced genetic techniques will be used to resolve the closest relatives to the Hawaiian fish species and the pathways by which reef species colonize Hawaii and help establish patterns of biodiversity. In cases where Hawaiian species are closely related to widespread sister species, this project will detect hotspots of genetic divergence. Because this research will reveal the sources of Hawaiian marine biodiversity, results can be used to help define priorities for reef protection. The project will support two graduate students and train at least two more in all aspects of the project from rebreather diving, specimen collection and curation, information management, and advanced genetic techniques. There will be outreach efforts to schools through existing programs, and expedition teams will include a videographer to provide footage for the award-winning Voice of the Sea program, broadcast locally. Expeditions will also include an outreach specialist to handle media reports and promote awareness and concern for reefs in the communities surrounding study sites. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will sample a suite of 20 reef fishes at locations to the south (Johnston and Line Islands) and west (Ogasawara and Ryukyu Islands) of Hawaii to resolve the origins of Hawaiian biodiversity. The investigators will employ both population genetics (shifts in genotype frequencies) and phylogenetics (DNA sequence divergence) for more ancient separations to test their hypotheses. Restriction-digest associated DNA sequencing (RAD-seq) will be employed for the phylogeography, phylogenetics, and population biology studies because it provides high coverage of homologous portions of the genome from multiple individuals for comparatively low cost and effort.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1558852</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bowen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbowen@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1650</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1097</Code>
      <Text>DIVERSITY: ROLE IN ECOSYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1174</Code>
      <Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8556</Code>
      <Text>Coral Reefs</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9117</Code>
      <Text>MARINE BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
