<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: REU Site: Security Printing and Anti-Counterfeiting Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>91939</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The South Dakota School of Mines and Technology, along with its partner organizations, the University of South Dakota and South Dakota State University, will offer an innovative Research Experiences for Undergraduate (REU) Site focused on interdisciplinary research dedicated to Security Printing and Anti-Counterfeiting Technology (SPACT), for a diverse group of undergraduate students, targeting Tribal Colleges and other institutions with limited STEM research opportunities. The SPACT research theme is of great societal importance. Counterfeiting is a growing issue in the U.S., posing serious economic, safety and national security concerns and impacting a wide variety of industries (e.g. pharmaceutics, semiconductors). In this REU Site students will conduct research on transformative anti-counterfeiting technology. SPACT is a field which demands development in four key areas: advanced materials, advanced manufacturing/patterning technologies, detection and encryption technology, and software and database infrastructure. The SPACT REU will implement a unique undergraduate research program to curb the economic losses and health and safety risks associated with counterfeiting. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The key objectives of this 10-week summer REU Site are to: 1) conduct transformative research in a collaborative, interdisciplinary environment, and 2) provide STEM professional development opportunities to a diverse group of 10 undergraduate students, each year for three years. A team of faculty mentors from the three partner institutions, all with demonstrated experience in mentoring undergraduate researchers, will implement a program in SPACT by applying research methods from various fields of science and engineering. Participants will develop collaborative research skills via carefully designed research projects and training seminars. Students will participate in a highly integrated professional development and technical communications program. The faculty, alongside industry leaders, will deliver training seminars to broaden the student's existing academic training in the necessary SPACT areas. The long-term goal of this REU Site is to provide a diverse group of STEM researchers with the training and skills needed to pursue graduate studies at the highest levels and to advance the developing field of SPACT.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1559958</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Logue</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brian.logue@sdstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>South Dakota State University</Name>
      <CityName>Brookings</CityName>
      <ZipCode>570070001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6056886696</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Administration Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
