<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IRES: US-UK: Enabling Ultra-Dense Future Cellular Networks (5G)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249394</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Graham M. Harrison</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This IRES project at The University of Oklahoma will support international research experiences for US engineering students to work at the globally recognized 5th Generation Cellular Systems Innovation Centre (5GIC) at the University of Surrey, U.K. In each of its three years, the twelve-week program supported by this project will provide five (2 graduate, and 3 undergraduate) students an opportunity to work closely with an internationally renowned research group in three focused research areas within the domain of next generation ultra-dense wireless cellular networks namely: Interference Mitigation, Energy Efficiency and Mobility Management. This project will also provide participants an opportunity for a hands on research experience using a one of a kind, outdoor, large scale 5G test-bed for wireless cellular system innovation that has recently been established at the University of Surrey as part of 5GIC. Ultra-dense deployment of cellular systems is inevitable in near future to meet mounting capacity demands. Interference, energy and mobility are emerging as key constrains in realization of ultra-dense networks. This project focuses on building complementary international cooperative efforts to address these challenges. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will enable US students and PIs to establish long-term collaborative links with globally recognized academia and international industrial partners in cellular domain. The project will introduce students to the European perspective on research and development in cellular domain. The extensive field research experiences planned in this project for undergraduates will help to increase the success of these students in graduate programs in engineering fields. For the graduate students participants, the opportunity to do validation of their ideas on a real network (5G test-bed) will help to transform and enhance their understanding of their research and promote the ability of US engineers to advance and contribute to leadership on state of the art mobile broadband wireless networks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1559483</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
      <LastName>Imran</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ali.imran@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hazem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Refai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hazem@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pramode</FirstName>
      <LastName>Verma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pverma@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
      <CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7727</Code>
      <Text>IRES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5980</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5914</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7727</Code>
      <Text>IRES/DDEP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
