<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Multi-physics of Active Systems and Structures II</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>378014</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This three year renewal of the Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site program will enhance the educational experience of undergraduate engineering students by actively engaging them in advanced research activities within the Florida A&amp;M University (FAMU)-Florida State University (FSU) College of Engineering (CoE). The program will be a collective effort from a diverse group of engineering faculty engaging topics such as micro air vehicles, multi-modal robots, active flow control, sensors and actuators, and smart materials. The multidisciplinary nature of these projects will engage students in learning cross-cutting technologies through their specific research and group activities. The REU site program has at its overarching goal to motivate more U.S. students, in particular underrepresented minorities and women, to pursue advanced engineering degrees or enter research-oriented careers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over a three year period, this REU Site program will engage undergraduate students in a 10-week intensive, summer research experience focused on the common theme of "Multi-physics of Active Systems and Structures II (MASS-II)" which covers interdisciplinary topics such as Micro Air Vehicles (MAV), active flow control, multi-modal robotic systems, smart materials, sensors, and actuators, and autonomous control. The students will work on individualized projects and participate in group activities such as seminars, lab/industry tours, outreach and a group design project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1560337</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chiang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shih</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shih@eng.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/27/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7680</Code>
      <Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
