<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: New Political Parties, Societal Linkages and Developing Stable Ties with Voters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>23530</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Brian D. Humes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>General Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project offers a new explanation of how voters become partisans. The PI examines the different trajectories of new parties and asks why some are able to take root in society, establish stable ties with voters quickly, and successfully compete in elections over time, while others fail to do so. Most prior research focuses on parties' direct appeals to voters. This research also explains success in terms of different types of direct appeals to groups that organize around social cleavages. Stable ties between a party and societal organizations may also attach organization members to that party and socialize them into identifying with it. The PI argues that organizational linkages can yield more stable voter-party ties and support bases. The PI test his argument using a multi-method strategy. This research contributes to our understanding of how traditionally marginalized groups are incorporated into the electoral arena through parties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project examines the different trajectories of new parties and asks why some are able to take root in society, establish stable ties with voters quickly, and successfully compete in elections over time, while others fail to do so. Most prior research focuses on parties' direct appeals to voters. This research also explains success in terms of different types of direct appeals to groups that organize around social cleavages. Stable ties between a party and societal organizations may also attach organization members to that party and socialize them into identifying with it. The PI argues that organizational linkages can yield more stable voter-party ties and support bases. The PI test his argument using a multi-method strategy, integrating conjoint experiments on the microfoundations of party support, comparative case studies of new parties in Bolivia, Ecuador, and Mexico, statistical analysis of survey data; and ecological inference leveraging a new data set. This project advances our understanding of new parties and contributes to efforts to promote sustained representation that is accountable to broad population segments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1560656</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mathias</FirstName>
      <LastName>Poertner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mathias.poertner@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunning</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Thad.dunning@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>009Y</Code>
      <Text>Political Science DDRIG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
