<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Influence of Intertidal Sandbar Welding on Dune Growth</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>385241</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Justin Lawrence</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This coastal geomorphology project is relevant to the large coastal populations that rely on dunes for protection during storms and it could provide useful information for coastal planners and engineers. The project aims to advance understanding of the recovery and building of coastal dunes with a focus on the welding of intertidal sandbars to the shoreline. The investigators will develop novel approaches to measure the effects of waves and wind on the movement of sand. They will communicate findings to coastal management agencies and will train one PhD student and two undergraduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal is to improve understanding of beach-dune dynamics by testing the hypothesis that sediment supply to the backshore beach and dunes is dominated by the welding of intertidal sandbars to the shoreline. While this mechanism has long been proposed as critical, only limited quantitative data exists. The investigators propose a comprehensive field experiment (SEDEX2, the Sandbar-aEolian-Dune Exchange EXperiment) in which measurements of waves and wind, subaqueous and aeolian sediment transport, and subsequent morphological changes will be collected synoptically during an intertidal bar welding event along a highly progradational beach. The findings will inform conceptual and numerical models of beach-dune interaction and help to improve management of vital backshore resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1561847</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruggiero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ruggierp@geo.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7458</Code>
      <Text>GEOMORPHOLOGY &amp; LAND USE DYNAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7458</Code>
      <Text>GEOMORPHOLOGY &amp; LAND USE DYNAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
