<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Atomic Layer Deposition for Large-Area Sub-10 Nanometer Patterning for Super Absorbing Optical Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nanomanufacturing is an important driving force for many applications, including nanomaterials, nanoelectronics, and nanophotonics. In the past decades, we have witnessed significant advances in nanomanufacturing capabilities. Different pre-designed patterns down to nanometer scale can be fabricated using various top-down and bottom-up methods. However, it is still a great challenge to manufacture nanostructures with sub-10 nanometer features over large areas using conventional fabrication techniques. Such small-scale structures are needed for the development of new applications. Using nano-scale antenna structures, localized optical field enhancements or 'hot-spots' are possible. Smaller gaps between the metallic nanopatterns will result in stronger 'hot spots'. Therefore, an affordable manufacturing method for large-area nanopatterning with sub-10 nanometer features is highly desirable. This award will employ the atomic layer deposition process to develop an inexpensive nanomanufacturing method to fabricate surface nanopatterns with accurately controlled gaps that can efficiently concentrate light field down to sub-10 nanometer scales over large areas. This interdisciplinary effort will link nanomanufacturing, computational electromagnetics, optoelectronics and optical sensing, and will provide a great opportunity for students to develop skills, values, and broad perspectives necessary for success in the global marketplace and for leadership in complex, multidisciplinary projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Building on recent successes in light management using nanostructures, this award will explore the potential to use this new nanomanufacturing method to fabricate super absorbing metamaterial surface structures or metasurfaces with controllable, ultra-narrow (sub-10nm) gaps. Specifically, this award will explore affordable fabrication processes to produce metallic nanopatterns with controllable separation distances defined by atomic layer deposited (ALD) dielectric films with the thickness accuracy of ~0.1nm. Such a capability will result in revolutionary advances in light-matter interactions at extremely deep subwavelength scales. Combined with pre-designed metamaterial cavity structures, incident light can be trapped within the nanogaps efficiently, resulting in a strongly enhanced localized field. By controlling the geometric parameters of nanopatterns, especially the gap dimension, the ultimate limit for plasmonic enhancement may be approached and be characterized conveniently over large areas. In this project, ALD-defined films will be combined with periodic and random nanopatterns to manufacture large area super absorbing metasurfaces, which will enable the development of novel on-chip energy collection, conversion and biosensing applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1562057</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qiaoqiang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qqgan@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cartwright</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anc@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
      <CityName>Amherst</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
