<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Perdigao--The Stable Boundary Layer over Complex Terrain</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>120772</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020105</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nicholas F. Anderson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The lowest part of the atmosphere, known as the boundary layer, changes character from being well-mixed with frequent air movement during the day to a nocturnal state of stability and stratification. However, despite the overall stability of the nocturnal boundary layer, there is still intermittent turbulent air movement. This study will leverage a large field campaign effort in Portugal, known as Perdigao, to study the stable boundary layer in complex topography. Better understanding of turbulence and wind flow in complex terrain will improve numerical weather models and support critical applications such as air quality, aviation, wind energy, transportation, and climate modeling. The project will also contribute to the education and training of the next generation of scientists and the researchers will contribute to public literacy of science through various outreach efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Perdigao field experiment is part of a large European campaign to improve the efficiency of wind energy production. This award will bring in a basic research component with a focus on studying the mechanisms controlling turbulence intermittency in stable boundary layers in complex terrain. This will be a combined observational and modeling effort, with additional observational data provided by the Univ. of Colorado at Boulder's Tethered Lifting System (TLS) and three profiling Lidars. The modeling component will make use of the WRF model with an immersed boundary method (IBM) implemented in order to enable simulation over steep terrain surfaces, and the model simulations will be able to nest down to 5m in the horizontal and 0.5m in the vertical. The researchers plan to address the following questions: (i) What is the structure of turbulence budgets, especially turbulence dissipation rate, within and above the valley? How does it change with the evolution of stability, particularly under stable conditions? (ii) What mechanisms generate intermittency of the turbulence? How is the intermittent turbulence within and above the valley represented in large-eddy simulations? (iii) How are coherent structures affected by the wind turbine wake? How does this influence intermittency? (iv) What physical parameterizations and numerical techniques are needed to appropriately integrate mesoscale and microscale models in complex terrain?</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1565483</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fotini</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chow</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tinakc@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1525</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
