<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>New Concepts for Multifunctional Asymmetric Catalysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Scott Rychnovsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division supports the research of Professor Daniel Seidel. Professor Seidel is a member of the Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology at Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey. This project aims to advance the field of asymmetric catalysis on a fundamental level through exploration of conceptually new and underdeveloped methods of substrate activation. Asymmetric catalysis is the development of small molecules that can achieve high selectivity in chemical reactions - producing a specific product in high prurity. Chiral molecules have a right-handed and left-handed version. These two mirror image molecules are described as enantiomers. A major goal of this resesarch is the development of reactions that produce enantiomerically enriched products through intervention of chiral ion pairs. Novel Brønsted acids and hydrogen bond donor catalysts are used to facilitate unprecedented enantioselective processes and address challenging problems. Multifunctional catalysts are being used as a means to achieve enzyme-like catalysis under mild reaction conditions. The research provides an excellent training ground for undergraduate and graduate students and preparing them for future careers in industry or academia. There is a strong commitment to engage a diverse group of students carrying out this research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ability to prepare complex chiral molecules in the most cost-effective way possible is directly dependent on the availability of sustainable synthetic methodologies. The new synthetic methods that are emerging from this work provide enhanced access to biologically significant, chiral nitrogen containing compounds such as amines, amides, lactams, amino acids and indole containing substances that, in turn, help advance the chemical industry. Furthermore, this project provides an ideal training ground to prepare the next generation of researchers in the chemical sciences. Students working on this project gain expertise in modern synthetic methods and laboratory techniques while being exposed to an intellectually stimulating and challenging environment that will prepare them for future careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1565599</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seidel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>seidel@rutchem.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8037</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8396</Code>
      <Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8398</Code>
      <Text>Hydrocarbon Conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
