<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-CORPS: Scalable Production of Polymeric Nanoparticles Encapsulating Hydrophobic Compounds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this NSF I-Corps activity is to systematically study technology transition and establish the commercial viability of the technology of scalable production of polymeric nanoparticles encapsulating hydrophobic compounds. One of the greatest advantages of polymeric nanoparticles is that they can carry hydrophobic compounds at much higher concentrations than the solubility of these compounds in aqueous solutions and yet, the encapsulation keeps the compounds from being exposed to physiological conditions until they reach their targets. However, it is challenging to generate large-scale polymeric nanoparticles with well-controlled physical, chemical, and pharmaceutical properties for biomedical applications. The product being proposed is a continuous, scalable process for generating polymeric nanoparticles by integrating flash nanoprecipitation with drying processes. The resulting nanoparticles can have high drug loading, high drug encapsulation efficiency, and narrw particle size distribution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team will reach the goal of this I-Corps study through assessing product possibilities, potential markets, economics and business models. If successful, the technology of commercial scale production of polymeric nanoparticles with controlled properties will initiate a paradigm shift in the biopharmaceutical industry with realized potential for health benefits for society at large. Low dose and dose frequency, and reduced side effects of the hydrophobic compounds can be achieved by increasing drug bioavailability. Drug compounds demonstrated to have in vitro or ex vivo therapeutic efficacy but undeliverable or difficult to administer can be formulated and available for clinical applications of treating complex diseases. Reproducibly generating nanoparticles with controlled propertied can serve as a platform to study drug pharmacokinetics,functionality, and efficacy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1566113</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ying</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liuying@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
