<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CRII: SaTC: Hardware based Authentication and Trusted Platform Module functions (HAT) for IoTs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>175000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Crucial and critical needs of security and trust requirements are growing in all classes of applications such as in automobiles and for wearable devices. Traditional cryptographic primitives are computation-intensive and rely on secrecy of shared or session keys, applicable on large systems like servers and secure databases. This is unsuitable for embedded devices with fewer resources for realizing sufficiently strong security. This research addresses new hardware-oriented capabilities and mechanisms for protecting Internet of Things (IoT) devices. This research has the potential to significantly enhance the security capability of today and emerging applications, particularly those that can benefit from reliable authentication using hardware features. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project concerns a hardware-based authentication framework using strong physical unclonable functions (PUFs) for enhanced security for Internet of Things (IOT) devices. It focuses on new authentication techniques, incorporating lightweight cryptographic primitives with PUFs, and novel pre-boot authentication and storage encryption functions for trusted platform modules (TPM). The project will evaluate the proposed techniques against a threat model, including model-building, replay, and probing attacks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1566530</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fareena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Saqib</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fsaqib@fit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>MELBOURNE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>329016975</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3216748000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>150 W UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>026Y</Code>
      <Text>CRII CISE Research Initiation</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>025Z</Code>
      <Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8228</Code>
      <Text>CISE Resrch Initiatn Initiatve</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
