<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Tailoring the Colorimetric and Luminescence Response of Supported Platinum(II) Salts for Aqueous Ion Sensing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamic &amp; Mechanism B Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor William B. Connick of the Department of Chemistry at the University of Cincinnati is preparing a new class of materials containing salts of transition metal complexes that undergo a distinct color change (and change in phosphorescence) upon exposure to certain ions in water. These materials are of interest for the development of a new generation of sensors to monitor toxic pollutants in flowing natural water, underground plumes, industrial effluent, and drinking water. The project lies at the interface of molecular inorganic chemistry and materials science, and is therefore well suited to the education and preparation of young scientists who will contribute to solving scientific challenges in the 21st century. The project also provides scientific education and training for students from traditionally underrepresented groups. Outreach activities engage local 8th grade students in hands-on, inquiry-based laboratory learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Linear-chain salts composed of stacked square planar platinum (II) ions are attractive candidates for the development of highly specific ion detection systems. This project focuses on determining the factors that govern the colorimetric and luminescence-based responses of supported platinum (II) salts to aqueous anions and cations. The objective is to establish how synthetic parameters can be used to tailor the properties of these materials. In addition, this research provides fundamental insight into the influence of micro- and nanoenvironments on structure and electronic properties of the incorporated platinum salts. The research helps to delineate the role of the metal salt solubility and water evaporation in the kinetics and thermodynamics of ion transport and the resulting spectroscopy. The research is accomplished by exploring a series of synthetic strategies and employing a battery of physical methods for materials characterization and investigations of ion exchange. Ultimately, these studies are expected to provide the fundamental understanding needed to develop rational strategies for designing aqueous anion sensing devices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1566438</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Connick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bill.connick@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
      <ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7234</Code>
      <Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8990</Code>
      <Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
