<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Electromagnetic Peening Assisted Laser Micromachining (EPALM) - A Hybrid Micromachining Process with Enhanced Mechanical Properties</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhijian Pei</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this collaborative research project is to investigate a novel electromagnetic peening-assisted laser micromachining process. The research objectives of the project are to understand responses of a workpiece under the simultaneous action of laser beam radiation and compressive forces generated by electromagnetic induction during machining, and to test the hypothesis that, during the electromagnetic peening-assisted laser micromachining process, the application of electromagnetic forces can generate a beneficial peening effect, enhancing the mechanical properties of the workpiece. A physics-based model will be developed based on continuum mechanics and Maxwell's electromagnetic field theory, which can predict and help understand the process mechanism. The model will be tested by comparing with experiments that include both in-situ observations of the electromagnetic peening-assisted laser micromachining process and the characterization of the processed workpieces. The machining rate, microstructures and residual stresses will be characterized using an optical surface profilometer, scanning and transmission electron microscopes and X-ray diffraction respectively. The fatigue properties of machined samples will also be tested. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will provide an improved understanding of material response under laser radiation and electromechanical forces. The electromagnetic peening effect is expected to enhance the mechanical properties of laser-machined workpieces, with a potential to improve product quality. This technology is environmentally friendly as it does not involve harmful chemicals. Better product quality and longer lifetime decrease the need for re-manufacturing and hence imply less energy and material consumption and less waste generation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1000226</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gjcheng@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
