<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>p-adic local Langlands and Iwasawa theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200388</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Over the last decade, the Iwasawa theory of non-ordinary modular forms of weight 2 has seen a surge of results which has brought the theory more on par with the well-established ordinary case. However, in weights greater than 2, little is known in the non-ordinary case about even the most fundamental questions on Selmer groups and L-values.&lt;br/&gt;The most serious obstacles to progress along these lines are (1) the wild behavior of non-ordinary p-adic L-functions, and (2) the complicated nature of the local conditions at p which arise. To circumvent the first of these obstacles, Pollack seeks to make a systematic study of the Iwasawa theory of non-ordinary modular forms at each finite level of the cyclotomic Zp-extension. To deal with the local obstacle, he aims to use the p-adic local Langlands correspondence to control the local structures which arise, and to then formulate an algebraic theory of theta-elements which is the analogue of the analytically defined Mazur-Tate elements. Pollack aims to prove a series of theorems which show that these algebraically defined elements control the size and structure of Selmer groups, and to show that the main conjecture is equivalent to the equality of these elements with Mazur-Tate elements. One particular goal of this program is to combine results of Kato and the theory of algebraic theta-elements to prove a conjecture of Mazur and Tate which asserts that their analytic theta-element lies in the Fitting ideal of a certain dual Selmer group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The motivation for the study of this project comes from the theory of elliptic curves which are certain mathematical objects whose points have the shape of a doughnut. Elliptic curves, once the focus of study of only pure mathematicians, have now become ubiquitous in both the theory and practice of cryptography. Further, as a result of the breakthrough proof of Fermat's Last Theorem by Andrew Wiles in the mid 90s, we now know that elliptic curves are intimately connected to modular forms which are functions of a complex variable with many many symmetries. Wiles' theorem essentially states that one can make a precise dictionary between elliptic curves over the rational numbers (which are geometric objects) and certain modular forms of weight 2 (which are calculus-type objects). This project pushes out beyond the case of weight 2 modular forms, and seeks to make a systematic study of certain properties of arbitrary weight modular forms. It remains to be seen if these higher weight modular forms (which can be thought of as generalized elliptic curves) are also highly important from a cryptographic viewpoint.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1001768</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pollack</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rpollack@math.bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
