<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Resonant Nano Electro Mechanical Systems adapted for Sensing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;Objectives: In this proposal we will provide the enabling science and technical underpinnings that will move sensing with N/MEMS beyond the realm of a scientific curiosity. We will investigate the dissipation of diverse resonant N/MEMS operating in air, leading to optimized performance in air, the carrier gas from which analytes will be sensed. We will also enable and demonstrate sensing of volatile organics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit rests on our three pronged approach: 1. To reduce radiated sound energy that damps the motion of resonators in air, making the resonant frequency shift a more sensitive transduction mechanism. 2. To investigate tensile stress to increase the Q in polysilicon and other low loss materials and also expose the origin of the enhancement of Q by stress. 3. To explore stress-based sensing where an analyte in the air induces a change in stress in a functionalizing coating on a surface &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts for the proposed research extend to high Q systems under investigation for quantum computation as mechanical qubits (the Q providing a high fidelity). Our research will enable diverse sensing functions for security and threat recognition from chemical and biological agents. Other benefits will flow from our planned REU and K-12 initiatives. The integration of undergraduates in aspects of the research and links to applications will benefit a broad spectrum of junior scientists, and equip them with practical problem-solving knowledge that extends beyond the classroom or laboratory environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1001742</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harold</FirstName>
      <LastName>Craighead</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hgc1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeevak</FirstName>
      <LastName>Parpia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmp9@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bojan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ilic</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rob@cnf.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
