<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Planning Grant for a National Center for Nuclear Energy Education and Training (NCNEET)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>69964</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Duncan E. McBride</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The increased interest in nuclear energy combined with a nuclear workforce that is close to retirement has created a timely and critical need to educate a 21st century nuclear energy workforce at all employment levels. Specifically, over the next two decades a need is projected for more than 41,000 trained technicians in the nuclear industry. Current educational programs are not scaled to meet the forecast need. &lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this planning project is to develop the infrastructure for a National Center for Nuclear Energy Education and Training (NCNEET). The goal of the NCNEET is to make sure the demand for skilled nuclear technicians is met in a unified, systematic way. The main goals of the planning project are: &lt;br/&gt;1. Identify and enlist faculty and representatives from businesses, the nuclear energy industry, nuclear agencies, and organizations to provide intellectual leadership for the center's various activities. &lt;br/&gt;2. Study the specific technician needs of the nuclear power industry in the different regions of the country and establish educational strategies, priorities and timelines. &lt;br/&gt;3. Build a coalition of colleges with established nuclear technician education facilities, infrastructure, and faculties. &lt;br/&gt;4. Identify the specific discipline of focus for each partner college and their needs in the effort to scale up to become a center for education. &lt;br/&gt;5. Develop a comprehensive plan showing an understanding of the workforce needs and the ability and readiness of NCNEET to meet these needs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT &lt;br/&gt;NCNEET is directed by Indian River State College in conjunction with Miami Dade College, Linn State Technical College, and Salem Community College. These institutions have been involved in nuclear technician education for almost 30 years and have been recognized nationally for their excellent programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACT &lt;br/&gt;By building a network of dynamic educational programs capable of scaling up to meet the energy industry's workforce needs, the NCNEET reduces the risk associated with serious shortages of technicians. In addition, the existence of the NCNEET can accelerate the implementation of new nuclear facilities. The project encourages participation by members of groups under-represented in the nuclear industry, especially women and members of ethnic minorities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1002817</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Farinos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jfarinos@ircc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chrys</FirstName>
      <LastName>Panayiotou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cpanayio@irsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/02/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cooper</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kcooper@irsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/02/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cooper</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kcooper@irsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/02/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indian River State College</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Pierce</CityName>
      <ZipCode>349815541</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7724624703</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3209 Virginia Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
