<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Rural Energy and Manufacturing Education Project (REMTEP)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Herbert H. Richtol</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This institution along with its high school and industry partners provide a technician education pathway for lower achieving students that boosts high school student math and science proficiency while generating interest in manufacturing and energy careers. The project is feasible for small, rural high schools with enrollments of fewer than 350 students and limited resources. Many manufacturing and energy companies struggle to hire entry-level employees with the necessary math, science and basic technical skills. Area high schools offer no manufacturing or energy related courses and students have little knowledge of those expanding career sectors. Additionally, over sixty percent of partner high school students score below state math and science proficiency standards. With industry-education collaboration, this project improves math and science proficiency by inserting industry-based contextual learning modules into grades 9 and 10 algebra, geometry and physical science courses. Industry technicians and college faculty assist teachers with curriculum and instruction and present special hands-on industry related workshops for students. High school juniors and seniors enroll in a dual-credit Technological Studies Certificate program offered through the college and are awarded a technical certificate upon completion. Enrolled students acquire foundational knowledge for entry-level manufacturing and energy jobs or prepare for 2 and 4-year technical majors. Students are able to connect math and science success with high demand careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1003532</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pat.wilber@minnesota.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Drummond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>don.drummond@minnesota.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Drange</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paul.drange@minnesota.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Minnesota State Community &amp; Techncial College</Name>
      <CityName>Moorhead</CityName>
      <ZipCode>565604899</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2187794861</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1900 28th Ave S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
