<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Assessment and Outlook for Undergraduate Physics Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>293403</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports an effort by the National Research Council, Board on Physics and Astronomy, to conduct an assessment and outlook for undergraduate physics education. An expert committee will identify the grand challenges facing undergraduate physics education and examine issues underpinning the field with two main foci. First, to assist in identifying those challenges and issues, the committee will assess the current status of physics education including a summary of what is now known about learning, teaching, and assessment in physics, drawing on findings from physics education research. Second, they will use that assessment to address the future of undergraduate physics education with particular emphasis on recruiting and preparing the next generation of physics researchers, providing strong physics foundations for students pursuing other science and engineering professions, and preparing K-12 teachers of physics and physical sciences. This includes describing the current landscape of undergraduate physics education and identifying best practices in undergraduate physics education. The committee will identify and prioritize areas for improving undergraduate physics education as well as future studies in physics education research. Recommendations will address best practices for instruction, strategies for academic institutions, priorities for physics education research, and education policy. This award is funded by the Division of Physics in the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences and by the Division of Undergraduate Education in the Directorate for Education and Human Resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1003414</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlancaster@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7492</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
