<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Socials Aspects of Hurricanes: Preparation, Response and Recovery with Vulnerable Populations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>309633</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Fahmida N. Chowdhury</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project summary: With a recurring six-month hurricane season, projections of intense hurricane activity for the next two decades, and the experience of seven major hurricanes between 2004 and 2005, Florida is an ideal location for hurricane-related research. The University of South Florida will continue its summer REU to research the social aspects of hurricanes , i.e., how individuals, communities and institutions prepare for, experience and recover from hurricanes. Particular attention will be given to vulnerable populations including children, older adults, and those of lower socio-economic standing. Drawing faculty and mentors from anthropology, sociology, education, geography, psychology, public health and social work, the program is designed to achieve these objectives: 1) to provide an intensive, mentored interdisciplinary research experience for undergraduate students; 2) to train students in qualitative and quantitative methods appropriate to social science research; 3) to provide experiential learning opportunities to increase student knowledge of systems and networks integral to research within the context of disaster preparedness and response; 4) to increase student knowledge of ethical issues in research, including cultural competency and certification in IRB human subject protection. Each component of the REU is designed to enhance critical thinking skills of the student with regard to the social aspects of hurricanes and other disasters, with a focus on decreasing loss of life and building resilience in recovery. This foundation of knowledge and skills will prepare students for both basic and applied graduate research. The USF Office of Undergraduate Research and the Honors College have committed significant resources to ensure the success of this program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: The need for effective hurricane preparation, response and recovery has been recognized nationally; the USF REU's focus on researching this important societal need from an interdisciplinary perspective will advance knowledge and understanding, bringing students together with nationally-recognized hurricane researchers, as well as first-responders. Severe weather events such as hurricanes carve a path of death and destruction throughout vulnerable communities, requiring a broader knowledge base to successfully prevent or mitigate these costly outcomes. Recently, research aimed at understanding the social dimensions of hurricanes has taken on increased importance, particularly investigations of vulnerable populations (such as children, older adults and low income individuals or families), communities with limited resources, and institutions charged with providing necessary services for health and safety. Research stemming from the REU has and will result in culturally and socially responsive evidence-based approaches to build protective factors and enhance resiliency of individuals, communities and institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: The program is designed to prepare the next generation of graduate students and researchers through a structured program including mentored group research projects, seminars, ethics training, disaster management and response training, on-site experiential trainings and directed readings. A long-term evaluation procedure will track participants' subsequent application to and participation in graduate programs in relevant disciplines and areas. The REU's innovative incorporation of training in social dynamics and populations at risk as a component of hurricane-related group's impact will also be assessed. The REU will broaden participation of under-represented groups by recruiting students from FAMU and Alcorn State, two Historically Black Institutions which have committed to working with the REU team, from McNair programs at other institutions and from geographic regions impacted by hurricanes and other disasters. Both the students and the faculty will contribute to the dissemination of knowledge and broader societal impact. Research projects will explore a range of issues, including but not limited to: evacuation and transportation concerns; impacts of hurricane-related displacement on children, the elderly and vulnerable populations; and mobilization and utilization of community assets, particularly within distressed or resource-poor neighborhoods. Each project will have the potential to directly benefit both USF's west central Florida community, other hurricane-affected areas, and any disaster-vulnerable community, through a better understanding of potential impacts and successful practices. Students will present their research locally within the greater Tampa Bay area and at their home institutions, at the Florida Governor's Hurricane conference or an equivalent state-level venue, and at relevant disciplinary professional conferences. USF's Hurricane REU Site will become a model for community-serving research by undergraduates both through dissemination of results and presentations by REU faculty at conferences such as AAC&amp;U and the Gulf-Coast Summit.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1004980</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ersing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rersing@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/04/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/28/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ersing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rersing@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Naomi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yavneh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yavneh@honors.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/04/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/28/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
