<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Photovoltaic Properties of Two-Dimensional Conjugated Macromolecules</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is aimed at developing conceptually new two-dimensional semiconducting macromolecules to investigate photovoltaic effect. The proposed two-dimensional macromolecules include discotic liquid crystal (LC) and narrow bad gap oligomer arms. The strong tendency in discotic LC materials to form self assemblies will be used to enhance pi-pi interaction, which will lead to higher charge carriers' mobility. The resulting assembly will possess void spaces that allow the insertion of fulleride derivatives (PCBM) to form interpenetrating networks without interrupting the pi-pi stacking. It is an ideal morphology that will facilitate charge separation and charge transport and benefit the enhancement of the performances of resulting solar cells. New conjugated oligomers with low bandgap and suitable functional groups will be synthesized for further coupling with planar core compounds. Detailed synthesis and characterization of these new macromolecules are proposed. Extensive structural, spectroscopic and morphological characterizations will be carried out on these macromolecules and their corresponding assemblies. Systematic studies on solar cell performances will be carried out in different compositions and processing conditions. The results will provide insightful information on structure/property relationship and new materials for highly efficient solar cells.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is aimed at developing conceptually new two-dimensional semiconducting macromolecules for solar cell applications. Fundamental research on synthesis and characterization of these new macromolecules is proposed. The results will provide insightful information on structure/property relationship and new materials for highly efficient solar cells. The proposed materials will push the power conversion efficiency of organic solar cells to 10% and make these devices viable for commercial products. &lt;br/&gt;This research activity can have an impact on the national and global effort in developing new and sustainable energy strategy and technologies, thus having an impact on our nation's economy and improving environmental quality by reducing the use of fossil fuels. This research project offers the students involved the opportunity to experience interdisciplinary training and learn the skills to face future scientific challenges. The proposed materials will attract interest from industrial partners and international collaborators. This project provides platforms to allow students to establish collaborations with industrial and international research groups and appreciate the importance of renewable energy research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1004195</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lupingyu@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
