<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: The Appalachian Chemistry Research Experience in Energy and the Environment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>257106</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry (CHE) supports a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site led by Nicole Bennett and Claudia Cartaya-Marin at Appalachian State University for three summers, commencing in 2010. The site will support ten students per summer in a ten week program. The majority of research projects focus on topics in chemistry of relevance to energy or the environment. Sample projects include: (1) the non-microbial production of fuel ethanol from renewable resources; (2) the study of the prevalence and concentration of anthropogenic endocrine disruptors in the environment; (3) the synthesis of biodiesel using recyclable catalysts; (4) the development of catalysts for the production of fuels (5) the development of sensors for the detection of pesticides and chemical warfare agents ; (6) the development of new materials for use in proton exchange membranes; (7) the development of more-easily recyclable polymer materials; and (8) the study of the radiative forcing in the southern Appalachians by atmospheric aerosols. In addition to conducting research during the summer, the students participating in this program will participate in a number of professional development activities, including workshops on ethics, proposal writing, graduate school preparation, and special topics in instrumentation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Young scientists need exposure to modern research methods and tools as part of their training. This REU site aims to provide cutting-edge research training in chemical problems of relevance to issues of energy and the environment. Students will be recruited primarily from rural Appalachia, thus providing opportunities for research to a significant number of students who might not otherwise be reached. Recruiting partnerships will also be developed with regional minority-serving institutions. The diverse student cohort participating in research at this site will be well-prepared for graduate school, and eventual employment as part of the country's technical workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1004896</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Claudia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cartaya-Marin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cartayacp@appstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicole</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bennett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bennettns@appstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>05/10/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Libby</FirstName>
      <LastName>Puckett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>puckettlg@appstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Appalachian State University</Name>
      <CityName>Boone</CityName>
      <ZipCode>286082174</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8282627459</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 32174</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1309</Code>
      <Text>GLOBAL TROPOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5560</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY CONVERSION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7243</Code>
      <Text>FUND RES TO ENHANCE NATIONAL SEC (FRENS)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9189</Code>
      <Text>WATER RESOURCES/COASTAL &amp; MARINE ENVIRON</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
