<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S. Egypt Cooperative Research: Surface Modification and Size Dependence of Magnetic Nanoparticles for Biomedical Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lara Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal is to investigate effects of size, shape and surface modification of magnetic nanoparticles (MNPs), which have been used in biomedical applications such as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), tissue engineering, hyperthermia, and gene and drug delivery. The US PI will be collaborating with Dr. Emad Girgis at the National Research Centre (NRC) in Egypt.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: In this project, the PIs will synthesize MNPs of different sizes and shapes and surface modification for in-vivo applications. The particle diameter and structure will be investigated using FESEM, TEM, and XRD analyses. The magnetic properties of the MNPs will be measured at room temperature using vibrating samples magnetometer. MNPs with a mean size of 5-10 nm will be prepared under inert atmosphere, with support of natural polymeric starch, by using chemical colloidal method. The surface of MNPs will be treated with a coordinatable agent for higher dispersion ability in water and retaining the superparamagnetic property. The prepared magnetic nanoparticles will be coated with starch, dextran, PEG, MPEG or polymerizable liposomes to extend their application potential in various fields of nano biomedicine. Before using the magnetic nanoparticles in biomedicine applications, we will investigate the genotoxicity of the MNPs to optimize the surface modification processes. Finding non- or minimal genotoxic MNPs is the final goal of this project. The results from this project will not only transform our understanding on the relationship between the genotoxicity and the surface modification on MNPs, but also provide pivotal guidelines in designing a new class of nanoparticles and coating materials for numerous biotechnology and biomedical applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: A postdoctoral student will be actively engaged in project and will have an opportunity to travel to Egypt during the project for an international research experience. The PI intends to collaborate with industrial researchers and to publish research results will be published on his website (http://wilhelmy.lci.kent.edu) for broad access. The proposed research will be integrated in educational and outreach programs. At the graduate level, the US PI will accommodate the research methods and results in a new course offering at KSU. In this course, graduate students will gain a broad exposure to soft matter and biomaterials and will have ample opportunities to gain teaching experience in lab demonstrations. Outcomes resulting from this collaborative effort between the Egyptian and US teams may be useful for magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), gene and drug delivery applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is funded under the US-Egypt Joint Fund Program, which provides grants to scientists and engineers in both countries to undertake cooperative research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1004228</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chanjoong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ckim9@kent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kent State University</Name>
      <CityName>KENT</CityName>
      <ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3306722070</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF THE COMPTROLLER</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
