<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site for Electrical and Computer Engineering at The University of Minnesota</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Esther Bolding</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This renewal three-year REU Site program in Electrical and Computer Engineering at the University of Minnesota is focused on encouraging a culturally diverse group of students to pursue successful careers in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) beyond the undergraduate level. Eight undergraduate students each year will participant in a ten-week summer research experience in which they will be paired with electrical and computer engineering faculty and work within their faculty mentor's research group. This REU Site program will provide participants with an integrated research and educational experience. Participants will have access to state-of-the-art research facilities while working with faculty who are actively involved in relevant academic research and have extensive experience mentoring undergraduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the research activities, the REU participants will be involved in complementary educational activities that will provide them with knowledge on career choices and graduate studies options, procedures, and funding. These complementary educational activities include a weekly seminar focusing on their research, workshops on career options, ethics, graduate school, and opportunities for exploring the teaching and outreach aspects of academia, and company visits. As a capstone to their REU experience, students will prepare final written reports and give presentations at a departmental poster session and an all-campus summer research program symposium. Social interaction between students will be enhanced through organized social events/outings, with additional student-student interaction provided by a community living environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU Site program will provide undergraduate women, underrepresented minorities, and students from non-research institutions with a challenging and rewarding introduction to research in electrical and computer engineering. By specifically targeting women, underrepresented minorities, and students from institutions without significant research opportunities, this program will strive to increase participation of these groups in the U.S. research and development enterprise by encouraging them to attend graduate school and pursue careers in STEM areas. Results from participant?s research activities will be widely disseminated through the programs website, conference presentations, and journal articles.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1005006</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ernie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ernie@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ted</FirstName>
      <LastName>Higman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>higman@ece.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
