<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Summer Research for Undergraduates in Atmospheric Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>196100</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site at the Geophysical Institute associated with the University of Alaska at Fairbanks. Organized around the theme "From the Center of the Earth - to the Center of the Sun", the institute attracts Arctic researchers from the U.S. and abroad and their research is advancing knowledge across the major fields of geosciences and geophysical research. This research-intensive environment provides an opportunity to expose students to a broad range of topics and cutting-edge research techniques. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program targets students majoring in the physical or chemical sciences and provides six students per year with an opportunity to work in an interdisciplinary team setting. Each year students will be organized into two three-member teams to work on projects related to various fields within atmospheric sciences, such as atmospheric chemistry, atmospheric radiation, climate, cloud and aerosol physics, turbulence physics, physics of the planetary boundary layer and numerical modeling. The team members will each be assigned a well-defined research project within a theme that the group can successfully handle and finish as a team within ten weeks. Teams will be supervised by a mentor who will introduce students to the specific details of the research project. While the teams will be responsible for the research and encouraged to follow their initiative, the research project leaders, the team mentor, and the mentor's graduate students will be available for help and support for the entire ten-week period. Thus, each REU student will experience how research and research teams work in the real world. Students will participate in regular research group meetings and have an opportunity to interact with graduate students and post-doctoral researchers. A weekly seminar series will expose the interns to fields of research beyond the scope of their own project themes. Through their research interactions with faculty, graduate students, and research staff, and through seminars and group discussions, the REU students will gain perspectives on graduate-student life as well as research experience. At the end of the summer each research team will write a project report and make an oral presentation to their peers. This experience should appeal to students who are interested in interdisciplinary work and obtaining a broad geophysical perspective. Preference will be given to students expressing a strong interest in physics and chemistry especially with respect to the atmosphere, calculus, statistical and computational work, and numerical simulations. Individuals from a variety of backgrounds bring a diversity of perspective to the scientific process, thus contributing to project success. Thus women and minorities, including Native Alaskans and Native Americans, are particularly encouraged to apply.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1005265</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerhard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kramm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kramm@gi.alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
