<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Physics REU at AAMU</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>258000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports the continuation of the summer REU program in the Department of Physics at Alabama A&amp;M University. Opportunities will be offered to 30 students to be actively engaged in cutting-edge research under the direction of senior faculty mentors for three consecutive summers. The projects available to participants include forefront physics research in Space Science, Nonlinear Optics, and Materials Science. Participating students will experience the excitement of frontline research in Nanotechnology, Pyroelectricity, Triboluminescent Materials, Optical Hole Burning, Fiber Bragg Gratings Sensors, Electroporation, Surface Enhanced Raman Scattering, Chemical Sensors, Electric Redshift, Solar Cells, Corona Mass Ejections, and Coronal Loops and get acquainted with ethical issues in Physics. Individual guidance and mentoring promotes participating students' intellectual development. Each participant will be making unique advancements in the understanding of technology-based devices and/or their utilization, as well as engaging in hands on research and exposure to a professional career in STEM disciplines through their personal and shared experiences with their research team members. The participants will gain experience in technical writing, presenting their research work to a variety of audiences, including dissemination of their results in local, regional, and national scientific conferences focused on undergraduate research. This award is funded by the Division of Physics in the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences and by the Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) in the Directorate for Education and Human Resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1005174</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Padmaja</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guggilla</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>padmaja.guggilla@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mostafa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dokhanian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mostafa.dokhanian@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Alabama A&amp;M University</Name>
      <CityName>Normal</CityName>
      <ZipCode>357620285</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2563728186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O BOX 411</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
