<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Copolymers and Plasticized Polymers at Interfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>354000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL ABSTRACT &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is focused on determining the behavior of copolymers and plasticized polymers adsorbed on the surfaces of particles and on the development of nanocomposites where the interaction of the polymer with the particles is critical to their use in different applications. Polymers adsorbed at interfaces have properties that are altered compared to those in bulk. Their characterization is often difficult and sometimes impossible to determine with many techniques, as most of the interfacial polymer systems are opaque. A variety of techniques, including, nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy (NMR), and also modulated differential scanning calorimetry (MDSC), and Fourier-transform infra-red spectroscopy (FTIR) will be used to understand the behavior of these important interfacial systems. The intellectual merit of this project lies in the understanding of the behavior of copolymers and plasticized polymers at interfaces and the role of polymers in nanocomposite systems. Copolymers are often used in surface systems because the presence of a single monomer alone does not always have the preferred properties for a specific application. Given the different characteristics of monomers, copolymers at interfaces will have differences in structure and dynamics compared to their behavior in bulk. Plasticizers may also behave differently in surface polymers than in bulk. With the synthesis of specially labeled plasticizers, it should be possible to understand how the plasticizer behaves in surface adsorbed polymers. In situations where the plasticizer is not effective in the adsorbed polymers, it should be possible to determine if the polymer excludes the plasticizer or effectively entraps it in the constrained polymer configuration at the surface. This work will also help in understanding the role of polymers in nanocomposites for different applications, e.g. electronic and catalytic applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is focused on providing fundamental scientific understanding of the behavior of polymeric materials at interfaces and the role of polymers in nanocomposite systems. The broader impact of the work lies in the application of this knowledge to the design of new systems where polymers are used in conjunction with solid fibers and fillers. Structural, electronic and other devices can be improved by an understanding of the interfacial layers of polymers. In addition, devices such as memory and catalysis sensors can be more readily developed based on information gained through research on nanocomposite materials. The integrated training provided to students, at all levels, will be another significant benefit of this work. They will receive a broad-based education in the polymer/materials area with specific expertise in polymer synthesis, polymer characterization, physical and electronic properties of polymers. The PI has been very active throughout his career in educational and outreach activities and will continue to do so through this award.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1005606</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fblum@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
      <CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
      <ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
