<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Rational Design of Novel Collagen-Based Biomaterials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials Research to University of California-Irvine is to synthesize collagen-like polymers and their mimics utilizing a novel "bottom-up" strategy using recombinant yeast system that was developed by the investigators for this project. This approach is expected to allow unprecedented flexibility in the range of independent biological and material properties that can be incorporated in the engineered biopolymers. The ability to create new artificial scaffolds that can direct the activity of cells is a critical component of furthering a number of areas such as regenerative medicine, therapies for disease, and mechanistic cell studies. Since collagen is the most abundant protein in the extracellular matrix and it dynamically interacts with cells, a collagen-based polymer could potentially mimic natural characteristics that are better than purely synthetic systems. As part of this project, investigators will introduce non-native cysteine cross-linking sites and matrix metalloproteinase proteolytic domains, and will examine their effects on collagen architecture, mechanical properties, molecular transport characteristics, and cell-based responses. The project will serve as an ideal platform to train both undergraduate and graduate students in science and engineering. Students participating in this interdisciplinary collaboration will gain an integrated perspective of the important synergies between traditionally diverse fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The capability to create novel materials which can mimic biological matrices and exhibit a broad range of new properties is especially critical in advancing health-related research such as regenerative medicine and therapies for disease. Collagen is an abundant, natural protein which dynamically interacts with its surrounding cells. By fabricating mimics of natural collagen, the investigators will examine the scope and applicability of new mechanical, structural, and biologically-responsive biomaterials. This can lead to a better understanding of how such materials can be used in disease treatment. The project will serve as an ideal platform to train both undergraduate and graduate students in science and engineering. Due to the interdisciplinary nature of this collaboration, students participating in this research will gain an integrated perspective of the important synergies among traditionally diverse fields that are now needed for a state-of-the-art research. In addition to hands-on training for students, the results from this proposed work will also be incorporated into graduate courses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1006999</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Szu-Wen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wangsw@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Da Silva</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ndasilva@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7623</Code>
      <Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
