<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Parallel Plasmonics and Raman In-Situ Study of Au Nanoparticle: Metal Oxide Interfacial Catalytic Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>439241</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: Within the past decade, much has been learned about the nanoscale properties of metal/metal oxide nanocomposite materials, but much is still left to be discovered regarding the interrelationship between environmental conditions and nanoscale properties and their resulting effects on the nanocomposite's catalytic and/or sensing properties. Specifically, the unique catalytic properties of Au nanoparticles or their clusters are strongly affected by their size, shape (platelets, rods, etc.) and the metal oxide host material. While supported nanoparticles have been shown to be unstable and generally form spheres at elevated temperatures, embedded nanoparticles have been shown to retain their unique shapes at elevated temperatures. Thus they show great promise for enabling unique catalytic reactions at elevated temperatures. In this project, they will systematically study catalytic reactions at the interface of the metal/metal oxide nanocomposite to determine how the size and shape of the metal nanoparticle as well as the ceramic?s chemistry affect the reaction. The project will provide educational opportunities for graduate, undergraduate and high school students through an outreach program which will enable both research and education focused outcomes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS: They will develop an all-optical localized surface plasmon resonance/micro surface enhanced Raman spectroscopy (LSPR/uSERS) analytical method for the study of gold nanoparticle (AuNP)- metal oxide nanocomposite films with precise grain size and shape control. The unique catalytic properties of Au nanoparticles or their clusters are strongly affected by their size, shape (platelets, rods, etc.) and metal oxide host material. However, supported particles are thermally unstable at elevated temperatures and tend to grow and or become spherical and thus their unique catalytic properties are not amenable for a broad range of thermal environments. Embedded particles have been shown to be more stable and will be deposited using electron beam lithography and aerosol-assisted chemical vapor deposition and these will be studied for their thermal stability as well as for their unique optical and catalytic activity. As catalytic reactions typically involve a number of charge transfer events, plasmonic studies will be used to determine the total charge on the catalytically active nanoparticle in parallel with uSERS for probing both the surface chemistry as well as the metal oxide host. This project will enable the development and study of novel catalytically active materials, new plasmonic sensing array paradigms as well as an educational outreach program for graduate, undergraduate and high school students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1006399</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carpenter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcarpenter@sunypoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hartley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhartley1@albany.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
      <CityName>Albany</CityName>
      <ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5184374550</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
