<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Flexible Statistical Modeling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gabor J. Szekely</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project studies methods for analyzing large datasets using L1 and&lt;br/&gt;related regularization. Coordinate descent algorithms are developed to&lt;br/&gt;provide entire families of solutions for L1 and more aggressive&lt;br/&gt;concave penalized regression problems. Applications include&lt;br/&gt;generalized linear regression models for very wide datasets, and&lt;br/&gt;structure-finding algorithms for undirected graphical models. L1&lt;br/&gt;regularization is used as well to develop efficient convex algorithms&lt;br/&gt;for finding low-rank approximations (SVDs) to extremely large,&lt;br/&gt;sparsely populated matrices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project develops tools with a wide variety of applications,&lt;br/&gt;illustrated here in medicine and merchandising. Modern technologies in&lt;br/&gt;genomics produce measurements of half a million or more&lt;br/&gt;genotypes at particular locations (SNPs) along an individual's genome&lt;br/&gt;in a few hours. Armed with such measurements on a few thousand&lt;br/&gt;individuals, some sick and some healthy, this project develops&lt;br/&gt;powerful statistical tools for identifying groups of SNPs associated&lt;br/&gt;with diseases such as Alzheimer's or breast cancer. Online movie&lt;br/&gt;renters or book buyers are often asked to rate their&lt;br/&gt;purchases. Although each individual sees a minuscule fraction of the&lt;br/&gt;selections available, the investigators are able to develop&lt;br/&gt;recommender systems that exploit the overlap to learn genres of&lt;br/&gt;movies, and assign viewers to like-minded cliques, and which allow&lt;br/&gt;them to make recommendations for products not yet seen.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1007719</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Trevor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hastie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hastie@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
