<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Space-Time Statistics for Wind Power Forecasting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gabor J. Szekely</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The technology to harvest electricity from wind energy&lt;br/&gt;is now sufficiently advanced to make entire cities powered&lt;br/&gt;by wind a reality. High-quality, short-term forecasts of&lt;br/&gt;wind speed are vital for making this a more reliable energy&lt;br/&gt;source. The investigator proposes to study two topics in&lt;br/&gt;wind power forecasting, develop relevant methodologies and&lt;br/&gt;analyze their corresponding properties and performances both&lt;br/&gt;theoretically and through Monte Carlo simulations studies.&lt;br/&gt;The new methods will be applied to a first-of-a-kind testbed&lt;br/&gt;wind dataset from northeastern US. The first topic concerns&lt;br/&gt;shrinkage and selection of space-time variables in various&lt;br/&gt;models for wind power forecasting. The investigator proposes&lt;br/&gt;to combine techniques such as partial least squares and the&lt;br/&gt;adaptive lasso with space-time correlation information that&lt;br/&gt;naturally arises among the predictor variables in the wind&lt;br/&gt;forecasting models. The second topic concerns realistic&lt;br/&gt;forecast evaluations in the context of wind power forecasting.&lt;br/&gt;The investigator proposes to develop new loss functions that&lt;br/&gt;are economically relevant for wind power and study their&lt;br/&gt;properties and their use in building and evaluating forecasting&lt;br/&gt;models in the wind energy arena.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary impact of this project is that the new methods&lt;br/&gt;for wind power forecasting will provide valuable tools to&lt;br/&gt;applied practitioners in wind farming. There is an obvious&lt;br/&gt;need for statisticians to be involved in such important&lt;br/&gt;problems related to renewable and clean energies for the&lt;br/&gt;well-being of our society. In particular, the research &lt;br/&gt;topics address crucial and major challenges for advancing &lt;br/&gt;the use of energy from wind.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1007504</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>YANYUAN</FirstName>
      <LastName>MA</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yanyuanma@stat.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Genton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>genton@stat.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/19/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
