<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission 50th Anniversary</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>82200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI has requested funding to publish a special issue of Oceanography magazine in September 2010 (Volume 23, Number 3) titled: "A Celebration of the 50th Anniversary of the Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission: IOC Leadership in the Evolution of International Ocean Science." The idea for this special issue emerged from discussions within the U.S. National Committee for the Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission (IOC) (reporting to the State Department and the U.S. Representative to the IOC) pertaining to U.S involvement in the 50th anniversary. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This volume, proposed as part of the U.S.-supported contributions to ?the 50th? celebrations of the IOC, will highlight important international science that has been implemented as a result of the strong partnership between the United States and IOC, show U.S. appreciation of the important international efforts the IOC has supported in this partnership, and educate younger scientists about the role of the IOC in fostering international research cooperation in partnership with the United States.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The United States has been an active Member State of the Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission (IOC) since its establishment at the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) in 1960. Of particular interest to the United States is the key role played by the IOC in facilitating and coordinating the collection and distribution of ocean data. The United States (NOAA, NSF, US State Department) contributes about US$1.5 million per year to the IOC in direct and indirect funds. IOC is important as the intergovernmental mechanism for coordinating access to exclusive economic zones for purposes of ocean data collection. It serves as a forum for addressing issues such as ocean data exchange policies and internationally agreed standards and strategies for long-term ocean observing activities. The capacity building mission of the IOC helps developing countries through the combined efforts of all Member States. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF has been providing its contribution to IOC for at least 25 years. It seems fitting that NSF fund a TOS special issue commemorating the 50 years of IOC contributions to ocean science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed chapters for this special issue cover a wide array of topics and current directions in oceanography, ranging from basic approaches and methodologies needed to address contemporary topics in oceanography, including ocean circulation, C cycling, living marine resources, harmful algal blooms and problems. Relevant time and space scales for addressing these topics will be discussed and approaches to synthesis of data in order to make it meaningful to the scientific and management communities as well as decision makers and formulating policy will be covered. The list of prospective authors that are experts in these respective research and management areas is impressive.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1008305</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ramarui</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>info@tos.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oceanography Society</Name>
      <CityName>Rockville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>208502113</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3012517708</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 Lynch Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
