<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Modeling of nonbonded interactions in graphene and carbon nanotubes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>186420</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Golovaty&lt;br/&gt;DMS-1009849&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Possible applications of graphene -- a sheet of bonded&lt;br/&gt;carbon atoms -- entail understanding and controlling the coupling&lt;br/&gt;between the mechanical deformation and electronic structure and&lt;br/&gt;transport properties. This coupling is not fully understood, in&lt;br/&gt;part because the basic mechanical response of interacting&lt;br/&gt;graphene sheets is not yet adequately described. Important for&lt;br/&gt;predicting this response are the nonlocal van der Waals forces&lt;br/&gt;between layers of graphene and between graphene and a supporting&lt;br/&gt;substrate. The aim of the project is to develop and investigate&lt;br/&gt;continuum models of graphene structures that incorporate van der&lt;br/&gt;Waals forces in a rigorous way, accounting for long-range&lt;br/&gt;ordering of atoms. Derived via a multiscale analysis, the&lt;br/&gt;continuum models are formulated within nonlinear rod and shell&lt;br/&gt;theories. Equilibrium configurations of various graphene&lt;br/&gt;structures -- involving multiple layers and different substrates&lt;br/&gt;-- under external loads are analyzed using the tools of&lt;br/&gt;bifurcation theory. Also, the thermal properties of nanotube&lt;br/&gt;composites are investigated within the framework of a network&lt;br/&gt;model taking into account the influence of van der Waals forces. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Interest in macromolecules composed of carbon atoms has&lt;br/&gt;stimulated a great deal of recent research in materials science&lt;br/&gt;and physics. Much of this work has focused on carbon nanotubes&lt;br/&gt;and, more recently, on the basic structural element of a nanotube&lt;br/&gt;-- graphene. Graphene is a single-atom-thick sheet of bonded&lt;br/&gt;carbon atoms. Despite many decades of effort, only within the&lt;br/&gt;last six years have scientists discovered methods for producing&lt;br/&gt;isolated individual graphene sheets. This discovery has&lt;br/&gt;stimulated a flurry of experimental and theoretical work on the&lt;br/&gt;exceptional mechanical, thermal, and electronic properties of&lt;br/&gt;graphene. Exploiting these properties could lead to significant&lt;br/&gt;advances in many technologies and yield, for example, more&lt;br/&gt;efficient solar cells, faster microprocessors, or lighter,&lt;br/&gt;stronger composite materials. The principal goal of this project&lt;br/&gt;is to employ mathematical modeling to gain a better fundamental&lt;br/&gt;understanding of how atomic-scale forces between layers of a&lt;br/&gt;carbon nanostructure influence its mechanical and thermal&lt;br/&gt;characteristics. The project investigators are developing and&lt;br/&gt;analyzing comprehensive multiscale models of interacting graphene&lt;br/&gt;layers by utilizing ideas at the forefront of existing theories&lt;br/&gt;as well as by introducing new mathematical tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1009849</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jw50@uakron.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dmitry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Golovaty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dmitry@uakron.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Akron</Name>
      <CityName>Akron</CityName>
      <ZipCode>443250001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3309727666</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>302 Buchtel Common</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
