<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Southern Hemispheric Climate and Carbon Cycle Reponse to Orbital Forcing During the Last ~400,000 Years</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>427199</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020108</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David J. Verardo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project involves running a series of transient climate model simulations with an earth system model of intermediate complexity. The goal is to examine the underlying mechanisms of orbitally-paced Pleistocene climate change in the Southern Hemisphere. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, a global atmosphere-ocean-sea ice model of intermediate complexity, coupled to a vegetation model and a marine carbon cycle model, will be used in the suite of transient climate simulations covering the last four glacial-interglacial cycles. The model will be forced by the history of greenhouse gas concentrations, orbitally-induced changes of solar insolation, and model-based reconstructions of the time evolution of the major glacial ice-sheets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will address three issues: i) how greenhouse gas variations and local orbital forcing affect sea-ice extent, climate, and ocean ventilation in the Southern Hemisphere; ii) how sensitive Southern Hemispheric Westerlies are to orbital-scale external forcing; and iii) how the marine carbon cycle responds to orbitally-induced changes in ocean ventilation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary broader impacts involve better modeling of climate and carbon cycling variations over long time periods as well as supporting a female post doctoral scholar.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1010869</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Axel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Timmermann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>axel@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1530</Code>
      <Text>PALEOCLIMATE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
