<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Diversification and evolution of major trophic modes in the Xylariaceae: exploring the role of previously unknown symbiotrophic and saprotrophic fungi</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11162</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Ranker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Fungi are one of the most diverse and ecologically important groups of living organisms, yet only a tiny fraction (&lt;5%) of the estimated diversity of fungal species has been discovered and described. Fungi which live within apparently healthy plants and lichens, are thought to represent a large fraction of this unknown diversity. These symbiotic fungi are ubiquitous and ecologically important, but basic knowledge regarding their origins and evolution, rates of diversification, and metabolic capacities remains limited. The goal of this proposal is to generate DNA sequences for a diverse collection of previously unknown variety of these fungi from numerous areas to examine the evolution of major ecological modes in fungi. This study will focus on one group, the Xylariaceae, a cosmopolitan and ecologically diverse family that encompasses decomposers of wood, litter, soil and dung, plant pathogens, and numerous fungi living within plants. Furthermore, this study will investigate the metabolic capacities of these fungi and relate their carbon- and nitrogen-metabolism to their evolutionary origins and ecological modes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will illuminate the evolution of large and ecologically dynamic family of fungi while also providing a first perspective on the functional biology of widespread and ecologically important symbionts of plants and lichens. Moreover, it will provide an important opportunity to mentor undergraduates in molecular and mycological techniques through the Arizona Biology Network, which provides community college students from traditionally under-represented groups with research training, and through the PI?s outreach program with Native American students in Arizona.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1010675</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Arnold</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>arnold@ag.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jana</FirstName>
      <LastName>U'Ren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>juren@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
