<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research on Out-of-School-Time Science Programs for Youth: Qualitative Research and Longitudinal Survey Design</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149062</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ellen McCallie</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project will conduct a mapping study to describe the contexts, characteristics and practices of a national sample of science-focused Out-of-School Time (OST) programs and identify exemplar programs for further study. A Field Study will seek more detailed knowledge about these programs by interviewing participants, alumni, and other stakeholders, and observing program activities. The results of these studies will be presented at a working conference at the end of the project to discuss how to develop a survey instrument to measure important youth outcomes from OST programs and collect baseline data for an anticipated longitudinal study. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide new descriptive materials about the operation and practice of the out of school learning of science. It will produce a literature review, a list of organizations that provide out of school science training and a plan for future data collection. A qualitative study will be conducted to answer questions such as to what extent OST science experiences spark interest or rather nurture or sustain it and how these outcomes fit within the broader context of lifelong learning and development. The study is intended to create a new typology of youth OST science programs that sufficiently describe crucial features that differentiate such programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1010935</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rht6h@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xitao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xfan@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7259</Code>
      <Text>AISL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7259</Code>
      <Text>INFORMAL SCIENCE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
