<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Catalytic C-H Amination with Late Metal Nitrenes and Amides</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>435000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carol Bessel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Timothy H. Warren of Georgetown University will develop catalytic carbon-hydrogen (C-H) amination reactions as a means of preparing new carbon-nitrogen (C-N) bonds without the need to pre-functionalize the reactive sites. The ability to directly affect the C-H to C-N transformation without the need to isolate, purify, and transform corresponding precursors offers the appealing prospect of reduced cost, energy consumption and environmental impact. Building on previous results, this approach connects the chemical and electronic structures of copper and nickel nitrene and amide complexes to their catalytic reactivity. The work specifically examines copper and nickel nitrene complexes derived from organoazides, the amine and substrate scope of the reactions, and new catalysts architectures to further enhance the efficiency and scope of the catalytic reactions. The broader impacts of this project include national and international collaborations that will expand the student's perspective on the way science is conducted within the larger scientific community. Professor Warren is active in mentoring high school students, undergraduates (especially through the NSF-sponsored REU program) and graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will expand the repertoire of methods that can be used in the chemical synthesis of compounds containing C-N bonds. The results of these studies could have many important long term impacts on a variety of applications in synthetic and materials chemistry, particularly in medicinal or pharmaceutical products.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1012523</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Warren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thw@georgetown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgetown University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200571789</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026250100</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>37th &amp; O St N W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
