<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>New Molecular Systems Based on Aryl-Acetylene Scaffolding: Experimental, Theoretical &amp; Materials Studies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>457860</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research program is based around the preparation and study of molecules derived from arylacetylene scaffolding, namely dehydrobenzoannulenes (DBAs), tetrakis(arylethynyl)benzenes (TAEBs), and azaacenes, to answer fundamental scientific questions as well as to explore their materials properties. With the support of this award from the Chemical Synthesis Program of the Division of Chemistry at the National Science Foundation, Professor Michael Haley of the Department of Chemistry at the University of Oregon will explore the development of facile synthetic methods for the assembly of functional molecules comprised of benzene and acetylene building blocks. The study of such molecules answers fundamental questions regarding the electronic structure of organic (carbon-based) materials, and also presents opportunities for practical applications, particularly in the area of nanotechnology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project serves as an excellent training ground for graduate and undergraduate researchers in fundamental and applied chemical synthesis. The studies will provide the researchers with broad experience in organic synthesis, computational chemistry, x-ray crystallography, and fundamental aspects of aromaticity, electron delocalization, and molecular architecture. The broader impacts of this program include industrial internships of graduate students at local and regional companies and national labs, the exchange of graduate students with those of foreign collaborators in Germany, Denmark, and Japan, the hosting of extended stays of visiting scientists including professors from PUIs, and continued substantial involvement of undergraduates in state-of-the-art chemical research via programs which promote the participation of underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1013032</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haley@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6878</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
