<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: A Single Power Source Optical Sensor for Bioaerosols</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179265</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory T. Baxter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project proposes the development of a device to detect M. tuberculosis instantaneously in patients and in open environments using a single laser source. The device will be portable and have the ability to provide essential information about the presence of bioaerosols within seconds, thus saving lives, time and money. The proposed system will use spatial light scattering methods to determine particle sizing, and 2-photon Laser Induced Fluorescence (2-PLIF) methods to identify the infectious organism. The novelty of the detection machine lies in the use of non-invasive techniques to measure these two important parameters simultaneously using a single laser source resulting in a far more simplified and accurate device from current technologies. The market added value over existing technology is instantaneous speciation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impact of this research is the deployment to the markets of a device for instantaneous detection of infectious and airborne transmitted diseases, such as tuberculosis. The identified markets include hospitals, medical offices, and open public environments. Expected sales for these niche markets are expected to generate revenues in excess of $20M/year. The short term outlook includes basic research and development to detect particle sizing and 2-PLIF using a single laser source, build and test a prototype unit with patients, and pursue approval by the National and International Agencies. The project is a partnership between Caribbean Biotechnologies, Inc., a small, minority owned company from Puerto Rico, and the capital arm of the Puerto Rico Development Bank.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1013988</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Holguin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>henryholguin@cbtpr.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Caribbean Biotechnologies Inc,</Name>
      <CityName>Mayaguez</CityName>
      <ZipCode>006805358</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7878345700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>177 Balboa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
      <StateCode>PR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
