<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Shipboard Scientific Support Equipment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>119269</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Matthew J. Hawkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;29 June 2010&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1015828&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Delaware&lt;br/&gt;PI: W. Byam&lt;br/&gt;Co-PI: [None]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal requests four Shipboard Scientific Support items for the University of Delaware for use aboard the R/V HUGH R. SHARP; namely up-grades to the CTD handing system, a new 70hp outboard for the vessel?s work boat, design for a new (aft) side load handling system, and noise treatments for the active anti-roll fins. All items will either enhance safety or provide greatly improved support capabilities to science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact and Intellectual Merit: The PI addressed the Broader Impact and Intellectual Merit of the proposed equipment specifically for the R/V HUGH R. SHARP. The research projects supported have been individually peer-reviewed for scientific merit. During operations, these vessels routinely expose graduate and undergraduate students to seagoing oceanography. Specifically, College of Marine and Earth Studies participates in a large number of outreach programs including open house events (Coast Day), participation the MATE program, and educational cruises. The College also hosts the UNOLS East Coast Van Pool. The R/V HUGH R. SHARP is scheduled to support 77 NSF-funded days in CY 2010.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/28/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1015828</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Byam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>byam@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
