<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Grapheotonics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective:&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this work is to investigate the controlled synthesis of a new material, graphene, that is structurally modified in order to artificially design its optical properties, and to characterize these for potential use in novel optoelectronic devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the work lies in its value in advancing and contributing an original approach to controllably synthesize graphene. Its immediate impact is generation of new experimental results on purposely-engineered graphene. These results will lead to a new understanding of the optical properties of graphene for photonic device applications, thus contributing to advancing the field of photonics in particular, and materials in general.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;In addition to creating new knowledge on a new material, this activity will broadly contribute to the training of (undergraduate and graduate) students in the conception, design, construction, and operation of a unique and original piece of equipment. It will extend the range of advanced instrumentation for research and education in photonics at Carnegie Mellon. The results of this work will be disseminated at key national and international conferences, including publications in leading journals, thus broadly impacting the field at large. If successful, the project has the potential to contribute to the understanding and development of a new material for nextgeneration concepts for advanced devices for information technology. Overall, the grapheotonics project represents the new frontier of nano-engineering at the atomic-layer level.It will create new material and knowledge for teaching and instruction in nanotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1016590</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elias</FirstName>
      <LastName>Towe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>towe@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
