<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Numerical methods for heterogeneity and nonlocality</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI proposes two main research thrusts. The first is to develop scalable &lt;br/&gt;solvers, in particular, iterative substructuring methods, for integral &lt;br/&gt;equation based nonlocal (NL) problems such as peridynamics (PD). As a &lt;br/&gt;component in the first thrust, heterogeneity is incorporated to study &lt;br/&gt;composite materials which is of utmost importance to numerous applications in &lt;br/&gt;material science and structural mechanics. Within the first thrust, &lt;br/&gt;robustness of the solvers with respect to heterogeneity and multiscale finite &lt;br/&gt;element discretizations are the subsequent directions to pursue. The second &lt;br/&gt;research thrust concentrates on preconditioning for partial differential &lt;br/&gt;equation (PDE) based (local) problems with rough coefficients. The robustness &lt;br/&gt;aspect strongly connects the first research thrust to the second. Since the &lt;br/&gt;impact of nonlocality on solvers has never been studied before, the first &lt;br/&gt;research thrust is unique, transformative, and has great potential to create a &lt;br/&gt;solver subfield: nonlocal domain decomposition methods (DDM).&lt;br/&gt;Solver research has the potential to reveal multiscale implications associated &lt;br/&gt;to NL modeling. The PI proved fundamental results indicating that the weak &lt;br/&gt;formulation of PD gives rise to conditioning bounds that are independent of &lt;br/&gt;the mesh size, meaning that the length scale is carried by the horizon instead &lt;br/&gt;of the mesh size. The study of composite materials requires solvers that are &lt;br/&gt;robust with respect to heterogeneity as well as discretizations supporting &lt;br/&gt;multiscale features and nonlinearities. For robustness, the PI will &lt;br/&gt;capitalize on his existing preconditioning technology for (local) PDE based &lt;br/&gt;problems. The second research thrust calls for a qualitative understanding of &lt;br/&gt;the PDE operators and their dependence on the coefficients because such &lt;br/&gt;understanding is essential for designing preconditioners. This process draws &lt;br/&gt;heavily upon effective utilization of theoretical tools such as methods in &lt;br/&gt;operator theory.&lt;br/&gt;The resulting control of the behaviour of the operators should allow the &lt;br/&gt;detection of the main features that provide a basis for the construction of &lt;br/&gt;robust preconditioners. After discretization, singular perturbation analysis &lt;br/&gt;(SPA) is used to detect and exploit algebraic features such as low-rank &lt;br/&gt;perturbations and decoupling of solution parts to construct computationally &lt;br/&gt;more feasible preconditioners.&lt;br/&gt;With the insights provided by operator theory and SPA, one acquires control of &lt;br/&gt;the effectiveness and computational feasibility simultaneously.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Scalable and robust solver technologies will create a great impact on modeling &lt;br/&gt;and simulation capabilities in material science and structural mechanics, the &lt;br/&gt;two vital fields that would maintain the nation's leadership in the aerospace &lt;br/&gt;industry. There is imminent need for effective numerical methods in these &lt;br/&gt;fields as composite materials have become industry standard. For instance, &lt;br/&gt;Airbus and Boeing heavily use light weight composite materials in modern &lt;br/&gt;aircrafts. NL models, especially PD, have become increasingly useful for &lt;br/&gt;multiscale material modeling as well. The effectiveness of PD has been &lt;br/&gt;established in sophisticated nanoscience applications such as fracture and &lt;br/&gt;failure of composites, nanofiber networks, and polycrystal fracture. In &lt;br/&gt;addition, the prediction of crack paths has been successfully modeled by PD. &lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, NL modeling has been used in abundant applications which include &lt;br/&gt;fracture of solids, stress fields at dislocation cores and cracks tips, &lt;br/&gt;microscale heat transfer, and fluid flow in microscale channels. There are &lt;br/&gt;other fields important to national interest where NL models are critically &lt;br/&gt;needed for the effective modeling and simulation of complex phenomena. &lt;br/&gt;Examples include evolution equations for species population densities, image &lt;br/&gt;processing, porous media flow, and turbulence.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1016190</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Burak</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aksoylu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>burak@wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/04/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
