<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III: Small: Simultaneous Decomposition and Predictive Modeling on Large Multi-Modal Data</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>489323</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Several modern data mining applications involve predictive modeling on large &lt;br/&gt;amounts of multi-relational data with added structures such as product &lt;br/&gt;hierarchies or social networks among customers. The broad goal of this proposal &lt;br/&gt;is to develop a comprehensive framework for predictive modeling on large, &lt;br/&gt;heterogeneous, multi-relational data based on "Simultaneous Decomposition and &lt;br/&gt;Prediction" (SDaP) approaches that iteratively partition the problem into more &lt;br/&gt;homogeneous and manageable pieces while concurrently building multiple &lt;br/&gt;predictive models, one for each piece. Such approaches lead to simpler and more &lt;br/&gt;accurate solutions. The proposed algorithmic strategies that determine how many &lt;br/&gt;models to learn and where they should apply, which data to discard and which to &lt;br/&gt;keep, how to learn multiple related tasks defined on multi-modal data, and how &lt;br/&gt;to scalably implement the solutions on distributed computers, provide practical &lt;br/&gt;solutions to certain real-world problems for which current learning and data &lt;br/&gt;mining techniques are severely lacking. Application domains of ecology, bio-&lt;br/&gt;informatics, market research and web mining are specifically identified and &lt;br/&gt;targeted. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are two broad research impacts of the proposed project: (a) it further &lt;br/&gt;vitalizes the research in data mining towards better algorithms for predictive &lt;br/&gt;modeling on rich and heterogeneous multi-modal data, and (b) provides and &lt;br/&gt;promotes the SDaP approach as a fundamental data analysis tool across multiple &lt;br/&gt;disciplines. The PI will organize a workshop and offer a tutorial at major data &lt;br/&gt;mining conferences to foster and promote research on various aspects of SDaP &lt;br/&gt;analysis. Moreover, the curated complex datasets and software developed under &lt;br/&gt;this project will be shared with the scientific community via a public web site &lt;br/&gt;as part of the proposed one-of-a-kind multi-relational data benchmarking &lt;br/&gt;facility. The PI will further develop a novel graduate course on Modeling and &lt;br/&gt;Analysis of Complex Data. Outreach modules that illustrate data analysis &lt;br/&gt;concepts and capabilities at levels appropriate for pre-college students will &lt;br/&gt;also be developed. For further information see the project web site at the URL:&lt;br/&gt;http://www.ideal.ece.utexas.edu/projects/sdap/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1017614</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joydeep</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghosh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ghosh@ece.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
