<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSR: Small: A Server-Centric Approach to Data Center Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>497169</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Data centers have become the main networking infrastructure to&lt;br/&gt;support online services, ranging from end-user applications (e.g.,&lt;br/&gt;Web search and IM) to distributed system operations (e.g., GFS and&lt;br/&gt;MapReduce). In this project, we explore a different design paradigm&lt;br/&gt;to data center networks (DCNs). We take a new server-centric&lt;br/&gt;solution approach, in contrast to the switch-centered paradigm. We&lt;br/&gt;push intelligence into servers, which generally have more open and&lt;br/&gt;standardized hardware architecture and software platforms. Multiple&lt;br/&gt;layers of low-cost, commodity off-the-shelf, mini-switches are used&lt;br/&gt;to connect servers. We leverage the large number of servers in a&lt;br/&gt;data center. Even when each server just adds one more link to the&lt;br/&gt;rest of servers, we obtain many links in the DCN system given the&lt;br/&gt;large server population. These added links, without using high-end&lt;br/&gt;switches but using only mini-switches, provide the foundation for&lt;br/&gt;enhancing scalability, inter-server capacity, and fault tolerance.&lt;br/&gt;Taking the approach, we can design DCNs with high scalability,&lt;br/&gt;enhanced fault-tolerance, and high inter-server capacity, and better&lt;br/&gt;support data center applications that exhibit various traffic&lt;br/&gt;patterns of one-to-one, one-to-several, one-to-all, and all-to-all&lt;br/&gt;communications. Our design also opens more space for stimulating&lt;br/&gt;innovations in the DCN software through the more open programming&lt;br/&gt;platform on servers, while abandoning expensive, proprietary core&lt;br/&gt;switches. The results in scalable and modular data centers and&lt;br/&gt;associated management tools are expected to show that, the added&lt;br/&gt;complexity into servers will incur only minor systems overhead but&lt;br/&gt;produce large performance gains.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1017127</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Songwu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slu@cs.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
