<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Collaborative Research: Federating Disjoint Wireless Sensor Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>304780</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project investigates effective and resource efficient establishment of connectivity among disjoint wireless sensor network (WSN) segments. The segments can belong to a structurally damaged network caused by the failure of multiple sensor nodes. In addition, the segments can simply be standalone WSNs that are normally operated by different agencies and are to be federated to serve a common application. The objectives of this project are to develop novel solutions for various aspects and contexts of the federation problems, to create a prototype for validation and to share the results/experience with application designers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technical approaches consider the availability of resources such as mobile sensors, mobile and static gateways and their count. Both optimal and heuristic solutions for repositioning of mobile sensors and placement of mobile gateways are studied to establish connectivity as well as achieving some desired performance (i.e., QoS). Finally, the results are validated via a real test-bed consisting of sensors and mobile robots. &lt;br/&gt;This project will boost the effectiveness of many civil and scientific applications. Example of such applications include crisis management, where existing WSNs may suffer an extensive loss of nodes due to fire, flooding, debris, etc., or when the services of networks owned or controlled by different parties or agencies need to be aggregated to assess in search-and-rescue. The results are made available in various forms including archival publications, tutorials and web-based resources. The project is enriching the curricula at UMBC and SIUC through hands-on projects and attracting K-12 students via prototype demonstrations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1018171</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mohamed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Younis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>younis@csee.umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland Baltimore County</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4104553140</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Hilltop Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
