<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Travel Support for Students and Young Investigators - 16th US National Congress of Theoretical and Applied Mechanics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Martin L. Dunn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides travel support for students and young investigators to attend and present their research at the 16th US National Congress of Theoretical and Applied Mechanics (USNCTAM). The congress will be held June 27 - July 2, 2010 at The Pennsylvania State University in University Park, PA. The funding will be used to help defray registration, hotel, food, and transportation costs of roughly 20 students and young investigators presenting their research at the Congress. Recipients will be selected by the organizers based on an application and review process that considers need and contribution. By encouraging the participation of the next generation of researchers, who typically have limited financial resources for conference travel, the long range interests of NSF in maintaining an engaged research workforce are served. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mechanics is a dynamic and evolving area of research with impacts in broad areas such as advanced transportation materials, energy storage and generation, and human health care. Fifteen professional societies belong to the US National Committee on Theoretical and Applied Mechanics (USNC/TAM)?the nonfinancial underwriting agency of the Congress. USNC/TAM represents the interests of the United States in international scientific activities relating to the field of mechanics, specifically to the International Union of Theoretical and Applied Mechanics (IUTAM). The committee is the focal point for the U.S. engineering, scientific, and mathematical communities working in mechanics and serves as the national forum for defining major issues in mechanics research, technology, and education. The proposed travel support provides the financial means for young researchers to attend the Congress, intermingle with leading researchers, and advance their professional and intellectual development in areas of national importance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1019012</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
      <LastName>Todd</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jtodd@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cusumano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpc3@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bakis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbakis@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
