<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Defects in Semiconductors Gordon Research Conference; New London, NH; August 3-8, 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Z. Charles Ying</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical. A Gordon Research Conference on Defects in Semiconductors will be held at Colby-Sawyer College in New London, NH, August 3-8, 2010. The goal of the conference is to promote fundamental understanding of defects and defect-related phenomena in homogeneous and structured semiconductors. These defects occur, or are introduced, during growth and/or processing of electronic materials. The conference deals with defects in a broad range of bulk and nanoscale electronic materials to assist advancing fundamental understanding in emerging materials such as wide-band-gap semiconductors, doped nanoparticles, and graphene. Electronic, magnetic, and optical properties of bulk, thin film, and nanoscale semiconductors will be discussed in detail. Control of defects in ZnO, nitrides, diamond, and photovoltaics during growth and processing are subjects of several sessions. Interface and extended defects that occur during heteroepitaxial growth of Si, SiC, and GaN will also receive significant attention. There are several sessions focusing on emerging materials, including spintronic semiconductors, ferroelectrics, graphene, and defective/doped nanoparticles. Discussions of atomic-scale imaging techniques, combined with state-of-the-art theoretical methods, will contribute to a fundamental understanding of the atomic-level mechanisms of defects. The conference will provide a forum for interaction between university, government and industrial scientists, and topics that are controversial and/or forward-looking will be emphasized. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical. An important impact of this conference will be to increase the attendance of young scientists from under-represented groups. The Gordon conference setting and format encourage interactions on multiple levels, and among senior staff and those early in their careers. Efforts will be made to improve the inclusion of women and minorities in fields related to electronic materials. Along with the opportunity to assess the field and future directions, it is expected that new ties will be established among universities, research institutions, and industry. The requested NSF funds will be used to facilitate participation in the meeting by young faculty, postdoctoral research associates and graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1019154</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shengbai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhangs9@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
