<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Plant diversity in Las Orquideas (Colombia): exploration and discovery in the endangered and biodiverse Tropical Andes and Choco biogeographic regions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>172939</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Colombia is one of the most biologically diverse countries in the world, but over the past 40 years major U.S. herbaria have observed a sharp decline (&gt; 85%) in the number of Colombian plant specimens received. Consequently, entire lineages are inaccessible to researchers, undermining their understanding of plant diversity, especially in the Tropical Andes and Chocó regions, which rank highly in the world's top priority areas for conservation. Thus, an inventory of Las Orquídeas National Park, strategically located in the confluence of the Tropical Andes and Chocó, will be carried out. Plants will be collected in poorly known rainforests between 800-4,080 meters in altitude. Approximately 3000 plant species, some new to science, are expected to be encountered as a result of this study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A catalog of the flora, the valuable specimens collected, and their on-line herbarium records will enhance the work of numerous researchers around the world. Training will be offered through internships in both Colombia and the U.S. To encourage and facilitate conservation of species at risk, educational guides will be designed for the park rangers and the Park's inhabitants. Finally, exhibits for the general public that aim to promote a greater understanding of the diversity of the region and the impacts of loss of biodiversity will be developed for museums in Colombia and the U.S.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1020623</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julio</FirstName>
      <LastName>Betancur</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jcbetancurb@unal.edu.co</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paola</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pedraza</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ppedraza@nybg.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York Botanical Garden</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104585126</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7188178840</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2900 Southern Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1198</Code>
      <Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1198</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY SURVEYS &amp; INVENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
