<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Course on Molecular Techniques in Plant Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>96680</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce Alexander McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Terri Grodzicker/Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory&lt;br/&gt;IOS-1021186&lt;br/&gt;Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory course on Molecular Techniques in Plant Science&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory course on Molecular Techniques in Plant Science is a highly competitive advanced laboratory short course covering a wide variety of plant systems, reflecting current research priorities in many US plant laboratories. The course allows students to take advantage of a wealth of technological resources applied to biological processes that are unique to plants. It fulfills a continuing demand within the plant science community for training in molecular and genetic approaches. The course teaches state of the art techniques to scientists already involved in plant research, and introduces scientists familiar with microbial or animal systems to cutting-edge plant research. The course includes a lecture series, a hands-on laboratory, and informal workshops. The instructors are chosen on the basis of their contributions to and knowledge of the fields covered in the course. The laboratory sessions provide intensive training in modern techniques in plant biology and reinforce the lessons learned in lectures. The broader impact of the course is the training of researchers in the most recent findings and techniques in plant biology. The students are chosen to include those who will disseminate information acquired in the course most broadly. Many of the students who take the course go on to lead their own laboratories and the course provides a foundation of knowledge for these new lab heads. Students come from a variety of backgrounds and are exposed to multiple approaches during the course increasing their chance of conducting interdisciplinary research that is so vital for scientific progress.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1021186</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grodzicker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grodzick@cshl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stewart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stewart@cshl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</Name>
      <CityName>COLD SPRING HARBOR</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117244220</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5163678307</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 BUNGTOWN ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
