<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The function of glycine in modulation of cone visual sensitivity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>416467</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sridhar Raghavachari</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project studies the potential role of glycine in fine-tuning cone visual sensitivity within retinas. Cone photoreceptors are sensitive in bright light and less sensitive in dim light conditions. Flickering light can enhance cone visual sensitivity in dim light conditions, and changing cone visual sensitivity is a neural modulatory process occurring within retina. The mechanism behind this altered cone sensitivity is unknown. Preliminary studies show that glycine released as a neurotransmitter in the retina results in an increase of cone signaling in dim flickering light. The goal of the proposed research is to discover the novel mechanism(s) involved in modulation of neurotransmission from cones to second-order retinal neurons in dim light. State-of-the-art techniques, including electrophysiological recording and fluorescence imaging, will be used to investigate the affects of flickering light-induced glycine release in the retinal neural network and the action of glycine in enhancing cone signaling to the second-order neurons. The experiments will be carried out in salamander retinas commonly used as a model system to study retinal network modulation. The results from the proposed project will serve for better understanding the functional interactions of neural networks and their behavioral adaptations. There will also be training of undergraduate and graduate students in the technically demanding areas of electrophysiology, in vivo imaging, and immunocytochemistry. This research and broader impacts will enable the important mission of training future scientists, many from underrepresented populations, in these technically demanding areas of science. Also, this work will promote teaching and learning in the lifelong learning program for seniors in southern Florida.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1021646</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wshen@fau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Atlantic University</Name>
      <CityName>BOCA RATON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>334316424</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5612970777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>777 GLADES RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7713</Code>
      <Text>ACTIVATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1096</Code>
      <Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
