<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RIG: Cryptic Speciation in Jumping Spiders: Multimodal Courtship Divergence in Jumping Spiders of the Sonoran Desert 'Sky Islands'</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle M. Elekonich</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Cataloging the diversity of life and the processes that drive and maintain this diversity is one of the most important goals facing scientists today. One important hotspot of diversity is the "sky-islands" of southeastern Arizona and northern Mexico. The so-called sky islands are named for their resemblance to islands as woodlands at the tops of mountain ranges are separated by desert "oceans". On different sky-islands, groups of animals have diversified into a variety of forms and this has served as a &lt;br/&gt;"natural experiment" to investigate species formation. The research proposal uses an innovative blend of techniques from behavioral and engineering sciences to look at the processes which lead to species diversification on the sky-islands, specifically in two groups of jumping spiders. Jumping spiders are one of the most diverse animal groups and their behavior has received attention as males use courtship "song and dances" to attract mates. The research proposal will look at courtship behavior and in particular (1) how behavior has diverged on the different sky-islands, (2) how females make decisions based on male behavior on the different sky-islands, and (3) how the environment influences the development of male and female mating behavior. Because differences in courtship behavior often define species, the proposal will be important to cataloging unknown diversity ("cryptic speciation") in one of the most important American habitats. In addition, by investigating a system where the process of species diversification is currently ongoing, the proposal will allow the researchers to test hypotheses on what drives the maintenance of species and how variation in the environment leads to the diversity of forms found in nature. Results from the proposal will be used to generate online educational materials which will freely available and used as a resource for educators interested in learning about behavior, ecology, animal senses, and conservation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1021385</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Damian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elias</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>doelias@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
