<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Processing of English Relative Clauses By Adult L2 Learners of Different Working Memory Capacity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9570</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Using a second language learned in adulthood efficiently and fluently is a formidable task. This project investigates how the processing of a second language by adult learners differs from the processing of a native language. The questions addressed by this research are (i) whether adult second language learners make use of different types of linguistic information, such as word order and animacy cues, in the same way as native speakers; and (ii) how individual differences in working memory capacity affect the use of each type of information in the processing of a native vs. a second language. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under the direction of Tania Ionin and with support from the National Science Foundation, Ms. Soondo Baek will investigate the processing of English relative clauses by native speakers and adult second language learners of English. Previous research shows that object relative clauses (e.g., the reporter who the senator attacked) are harder to interpret than subject relative clauses (e.g., the reporter who attacked the senator). It has also been shown that lexical-semantic properties of nouns modulate the degree of processing difficulty of the two types of relative clauses. For example, object relative clauses with an inanimate head noun and an animate relative clause subject (e.g., the movie that the director watched) are no more difficult to process than corresponding subject relative clauses, whereas those with an animate head noun and an inanimate relative clause subject (e.g., the director that the movie pleased) are harder to process than subject relative clauses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project tests whether adult second language learners are sensitive both to syntactic complexity, as represented by the subject-object asymmetry in relative clauses, and to lexical-semantic information, as represented by the animacy of the relevant nouns. Furthermore, this project examines how individual learners of different working memory capacity and different L2 proficiency differ from one another in the degree of sensitivity to these two types of information. The results will contribute to a better understanding of (i) sentence processing mechanisms employed for a native language and for a second language learned in adulthood and (ii) the factors responsible for the wide range of individual variability in the processing of a second language by adult learners. The results of this research also have potential pedagogical implications for second language teaching, through its attention to individual learner differences in language processing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1021455</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tania</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ionin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tionin@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Soondo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baek5@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1311</Code>
      <Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1311</Code>
      <Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
