<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A System Perspective on Uptake of the Neurotransmitter Glutamate in C. elegans.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>467726</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Evan Balaban</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Communication between neurons in the brain depends on secretion and removal of small signaling molecules called neuro-transmitters. Recent studies provided some insights into the structure and functional mechanisms of transporters, special proteins that remove neuro-transmitters from neuronal connections. However, we still do not understand the function of transporters at the whole-animal level. In the current project, the researchers employ an intriguing approach to this question, using a small, free-living, and transparent nematode. Numerous studies in the past have shown that basic biological mechanisms are conserved through evolution from these worms to humans. The researchers will take advantage of unique features of this tiny animal, including powerful molecular and genetic tools, and the ability to visualize neuronal activity in the whole animal. They will study how the tiny nematode, with its simple nervous system, uses neuro-transmitter transporters with special structures and unusual locations to control its neuronal activity. The study will increase understanding of the differences in molecular structure of transport proteins and their effects on neuronal signaling, whole animal physiology, and the strategies used by animals to control neuronal activity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study will enhance cutting edge scientific studies in a public university located in the heart of Harlem, New York City. The project is design in a way that puts special emphasis on the participation of undergraduate students from this minority-rich academic environment. Furthermore, it provides exposure to state-of-the-art neuroscience research to medical students from a unique program dedicated to the education and service of minority and underprivileged communities. Together, the current research project offers a unique and powerful perspective on neuronal function in evolution, and the translation of molecular structural differences to the whole-animal physiology. Furthermore, this study will encourage and facilitate the participation of minority and disadvantaged communities in cutting edge molecular neuroscience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1022281</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Itzhak</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>imano@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY City College</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7712</Code>
      <Text>ORGANIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1096</Code>
      <Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
