<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Origins of Numerical Competence: Assessment of Number Sense in Piraha</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199963</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This RAPID project focuses on "fundamental" research on three distinct aspects of number sense: (1) a small exact number system; (2) a large approximate number system; and (3) a system for set-based quantification. Recent exploratory research suggests a strong linkage between number sense (particularly large numerical approximation systems) and student abilities in other domains of mathematics. The investigators will research the links among these three aspects, and the study is designed to further the preliminary findings (cited above). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators propose a correlational study in which they test a population of the indigenous Piraha people of Brazil (a small, isolated, monolingual hunter-gatherer group from the Amazonas) and a sample of Americans (60 in each group) in a battery of cognitively-oriented tasks which measure different core numerical systems as well as other basic cognitive abilities like short-term memory and face perception (as control tasks). The Piraha are an ideal test case for understanding the relationship among core numerical systems because their language is has no words for numbers. In addition, the Piraha do not use exact number in their society and they do not adopt cultural or linguistic conventions from other cultures. A RAPID is justified because their population is threatened by imminent development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is important because a deeper understanding of the conceptual/cognitive components of number sense and how they interrelate can lead to perhaps changed understandings of how students learn and teachers teach this area of mathematics. And, because number sense is so foundational to mathematics and because preliminary research results show its potential importance to future mathematics learning, the project may have a transformative impact on the field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1022684</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gibson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>egibson@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1311</Code>
      <Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7625</Code>
      <Text>REAL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7719</Code>
      <Text>DEL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
