<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BECS: Collaborative Research: Engineering Complex Self-Assembling Systems Composed of Interacting Patterned Polyhedra: Theory and Experiments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>124370</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eduardo A. Misawa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is the investigation of interacting, precisely patterned polyhedral particles using a combination of experiment and theory. The two specific aims of the proposal are: (1) To understand folding pathways and aggregation of polyhedra such as cubes, parallelipipeds, tetrahedra and dodecahedra with sizes ranging from 10 microns to 1mm, and (2) To develop a model complex chemical reaction-diffusion system composed of arrays of interacting "chemical reactant'' releasing polyhedra with precisely patterned porosity. One of the key challenges limiting the understanding of complex systems is the chasm between physically realizable model experimental systems and theory. This research bridges this divide with the construction of experimental systems that are of technological importance, and also serve as model experimental systems for the development of mathematical models describing complex phenomenon. This project will study the interaction of particles with precise shape and surface patterning which is important in a broad range of scientific and technological areas such as crystal growth, colloidal physics and self-assembly. The goals are also of importance in the creation of patterned sub-millimeter scale three dimensional metamaterials and devices which are expected to display novel optical and electronic properties. The studies will also lend insight into new self-assembly techniques for micro and nanotechnology. Another goal of this project is to study the interaction of patterned polyhedra that release chemicals thereby representing chemically interacting particles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These studies will allow the PIs to take a step closer towards the creation of active, reconfigurable and adaptive self-assembling materials since feedback and control loops can be encoded into the kinetics of coupled chemical reactions. Moreover, the study of chemically releasing particles is important in explaining growth phenomena and pattern formation in biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1022638</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Govind</FirstName>
      <LastName>Menon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>menon@dam.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1403</Code>
      <Text>PROCESS &amp; REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7478</Code>
      <Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7552</Code>
      <Text>COFFES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7633</Code>
      <Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7722</Code>
      <Text>COMPLEXITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
