<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research in Political Science: Opposition Party Strategy in Electoral Authoritarian Regimes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11957</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Brian D. Humes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>During what Samuel Huntington called the Third Wave of Democratization, nearly 100 countries began the process of democratization. These countries set up democratic institutions, began holding elections, and many liberalized restrictions on the media and on civil and political rights. Although the democratization efforts of many Eastern European countries have generally been successful, many countries in Africa and the Middle East have belied expectations. In fact, just 20% of countries democratizing under the third wave successfully transitioned. As a result, there exists a wide range of countries that are neither fully democratic nor fully authoritarian. Moreover, these semi-democratic (or semi-authoritarian) countries hold regular elections at the national and local levels in which opposition groups participate and win some seats in the national legislature. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The failed transitions of the third wave have produced an interesting phenomenon: authoritarian elections. We do not fully understand whether and how these elections are important and the role of elections in democratic transitions. Do authoritarian elections create opportunities for further democratization or do they simply sustain authoritarian governments? In order to clarify the role of elections in authoritarian regimes, this project examines the causes and consequences of election boycotts, and the subsequent regime response. Determining the conditions under which governments respond to the demands of boycotting opposition parties will allow us to identify those elections that further democratization and establish the criteria that distinguish them from those elections that impede it. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although boycotts occur with increasing frequency, the literature has yet to sufficiently explain the following two questions: (1) Why do political parties decide to boycott an election? and (2) When and why are boycotts a successful strategy? This project argues that in order to answer these questions and better explain election boycotts, we need to account for the institutions under which elections operate (the electoral rules) and the existence of factionalism within opposition political parties. In this project, a theory of election boycotts is developed using a game theoretic model. The model is used to develop a causal account for the relationship between electoral rules and election boycotts and between intraparty factionalism and election boycotts. The propositions derived from the model are then tested using both qualitative and quantitative tools. The model was informed from research conducted in Jordan in 2009 and three months of field research will be undertaken in Algeria to evaluate the propositions derived from the model. The propositions will also be tested using a dataset consisting of over 700 national-level elections in both democratic and authoritarian regimes from 1990-2006. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the vast number of countries across Africa, Asia and the Middle East that are now holding elections, but have stalled in their democratization efforts, the present study represents a timely addition to the literature. The project has broader implications for both the historical understanding of Jordan and Algeria, and also for our understanding of democratic transitions. The broader impact is thus twofold. First, the information and data collected during fieldwork in Jordan and Algeria will increase our understanding of the recent electoral histories of both countries, and explain and clarify how the opposition?s recent pattern of participation and non-participation has affected the democratic transition in both states. Second, in determining the consequences of opposition party behavior this project will have more general conclusions about the process of democratic transition. This study, therefore, is important not only for enhancing our understanding of Algeria and Jordan, but also through an extensive study of these countries, the literature will gain an improved understanding of the role elections play in democratic transitions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1023988</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dion</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>douglas-dion@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buttorff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gail-buttorff@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Iowa</Name>
      <CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
