<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TC: EAGER: Investigations of Next-generation Network Reconnaissance Attack Techniques and Limitations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>145000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This goal of this project is to investigate next-generation network attack reconnaissance techniques, and explore the limitation for existing defenses. The result of this investigation offers understanding of potential game-changing in network reconnaissance attacks and how they can evolve in order to enable discovering and navigating the network quickly and safely. The project particularly explores novel scanning techniques to discover firewall security polices remotely via intelligent active probing, and without probing the end-hosts. The outcome of this project, if successful, is expected to offer transformative views to network defense, particularly counter-scanning techniques, beyond traditional intrusion detection/prevention systems. As this far-forward looking EAGER proposal exhibits high-risk, it also entails high-value that is to be always many steps ahead of attackers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research arises serious concerns about the privacy of security configuration and the effectiveness of existing counter-measures against future advanced attacks. The proposed research agenda may make researchers&lt;br/&gt;as well as vendors consider fundamentally new defense concepts beyond the current IDS and IPS.&lt;br/&gt;This project also stimulates theorizing and predicting next-generation network attacks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1023868</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ehab</FirstName>
      <LastName>Al-Shaer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ealshaer@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
