<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Flippase Recombination Method To Map Relevant Brain Circuits Underlying Different Fly Behaviors in Drosophila</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>446000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT PI (Zhang) Proposal # IOS-1025556&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The nervous system controls human and animal behavior. From behavioral analysis, neuroscientists can gain insights into brain function such as learning, memory, decision-making and other cognitive activities. Yet, the neural mechanisms by which behavior is produced and regulated remain poorly understood. Dr. Zhang and his associate propose to develop a new molecular genetic method to non-invasively dissect the neural circuitry underlying behavior in the fruit fly, Drosophila melanogaster. They will be developing and refining a genetic method that allows for restrictive expression of genes in subsets of neurons in the fly brain. They will then examine the behavioral consequence following the perturbation of these neurons or a neural circuit. This brain-behavior mapping effort is expected to significantly advance the understanding of brain function. Another important aspect of this proposal is to develop new genetic tools. Dr. Zhang has begun and will continue to make these reagents freely available to the fly community. These reagents will be deposited in a public domain (such as the Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center). The strategy developed in the proposed work is also expected to be applicable to other genetic model organisms. This proposal has strong outreach and broader impacts. Building upon the past record of excellence, Dr. Zhang will actively participate in education, training, and outreach to local communities. This includes mentoring undergraduate and graduate students, training a postdoctoral fellow, involving a local high school science teacher in summer research, and participation of science outreach activities in local schools and museums.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1025556</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhangbing@Missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
      <CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
