<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>New Mexico AMP Bridge to the Doctorate VIII - BD Site: University of New Mexico</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>987000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dr. A. James Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>New Mexico State University Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (NM-LSAMP) Bridge to the Doctorate (BD) Program is a collaborative effort between the National Science Foundation and New Mexico higher education institutions to increase the quality and quantity of underrepresented minorities matriculating to completion of the doctoral degree in science, technology, engineering and mathematics fields (STEM) fields. The 2010-2012 program, the second at the University of New Mexico, prepares students to meet the challenges of completing master's and doctoral programs of study preferably for academic careers in higher education. In addition, the program develops leadership skills necessary for success in the STEM workforce nationally and internationally. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Integrating research and education, the BD fellows will be nurtured over two years as a cohorted community that will benefit from a program of academic and personal development activities as well as social support to sustain their commitment and success to the terminal Ph.D. STEM degree. Program activities include linkages to the University of New Mexico Integrated Graduate Education in Research and Training (IGERT) as well as other NSF-funded research and education projects, including programs that provide mentoring opportunities for undergraduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A total of 12 students from underrepresented minority populations in STEM fields will participate in the program at the University of New Mexico during the 2010-2012 academic years. Results from this support will broaden the participation of Hispanics and Native Americans in the STEM pipeline, U. S. workforce and abroad. Results from rigorous evaluation of the project will add to the body of literature in successful recruitment and retention of underrepresented minority students in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1026412</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ricardo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jacquez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjaquez@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
      <CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
      <ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
