<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Customizable Meniscus Implant Prepared by Dielectrophoretic Biofabrication</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1041700</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project aims to develop a prototype meniscus implant of bacterial cellulose biomaterials fabricated by dielectrophoretic microweaving, an innovative biofabrication process. Nano-cellulose networks produced by the bacteria Acetobacter xylinum are biomaterials with unique hydrogel-like properties and biocompatibility that are ideal for cartilage tissue replacement. This technology is based on a new biofabrication process, in which bacterial motion is precisely controlled in an electric field to form nano-cellulose networks of desired morphology. Earlier feasibility studies have demonstrated bacterial cellulose deposition at the nanoscale during biaxial motion of bacteria in an electric field and the ability to control the assembly of cellulose layers into any desired three-dimensional architecture and control biomechanical properties. This Phase II project will develop a microweaver bioreactor for fabrication of customizable meniscus implants based on radiology images from patients. The structure and biomechanical properties will be evaluated in knee-model and compared with native meniscus. Biocompatibility and long term performance will be evaluated in large animal model studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impact of this Phase II project, if successful, is the availability of meniscus implants that mimic the structure of the natural meniscus to address knee-joint failures, estimated to affect 15+ million people worldwide each year. Each year, in the US, more than 1 million people undergo meniscus surgery. Irreparable meniscus injuries often progress and lead to osteoarthritis. Currently, there is no satisfactory solution for irreparable meniscus injuries. The potential market for a meniscus implant is more than $3 billion. By developing a meniscus implant that can substitute for the injured native meniscus, it will be possible to prevent osteoarthritis and its related huge economic costs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1026421</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gatenholm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pgatenholm@bcgenesis.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/16/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Constance</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ace</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cace@bcgenesis.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>BC Genesis</Name>
      <CityName>Riner</CityName>
      <ZipCode>241492578</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5408087552</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3335 Torrey Pines Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
