<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developing a Novel Scanning Magnetic Imaging Technique for Magnetically Labeled Molecules</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this proposal is to develop a noninvasive imaging technique for detecting magnetically labeled biological molecules with zeptomole sensitivity, micrometer spatial resolution, and a detection range of several centimeters. The technique is based on atomic magnetometry for magnetic field sensitivity and scanning imaging for spatial resolution. The research activities focus on four related areas: new-generation atomic sensors, novel imaging schemes, improved applicability, and unique biological applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;This proposed research represents a novel approach for molecular imaging. The unique long detection range distinguishes this new technique from existing surface techniques, making it well suited for three-dimensional molecular imaging at practical settings. Design of sensors with new engineering concepts will lead to a zeptomole detection limit. Unique scanning schemes will be developed to provide high spatial resolution for three-dimensional imaging. The applicability of the technique is enhanced by eliminating the magnetic shield which is currently required for most magnetic imaging techniques. The removal of magnetic shield is facilitated by the design of new sensors and a new compensating concept to overcome the nonlinear Zeeman effect which will otherwise degrade the sensitivity. On the application front, a novel method is proposed to provide critical details regarding bond rupture that have not been revealed with existing techniques. In addition, the new technique does not require a transparent environment since the laser beam does not interact with the molecular system, contrary to optical imaging techniques; this technique detects dc magnetic signal, avoiding the limited penetration depth of ac signal in conductors, which is a problem for magnetic resonance imaging. Therefore, the proposed research will have transformative impact on the field of molecular imaging.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts lie in both the research front and the educational aspect of this proposal. The proposed research will fill the technology gap between magnetic microscopy and long-distance magnetic field sensing. Consequently it will open up new imaging applications that are not experimentally feasible at present. The interdisciplinary research, which involves physics, engineering, chemistry, and biology, offers a wide range of training for students. Their education is central to this proposal, as their input determines both the success of the projects and the future of this new field. In addition, substantial effort will be continuously devoted to recruiting underrepresented undergraduate students into the research program. It is foreseeable these students will broadly impact the society in a positive manner by sharing their fruitful experiences with their classmates and friends. Outreach activities include hosting high school students during summer to work on specifically-tailored research tasks, interacting with local liberal arts colleges to expand the impact of cutting-edge research, and serving to guide worldwide science fairs held in the local area.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1028328</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shoujun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sxu7@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
