<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Contribution of Polyamines to N and C cycling in Marine Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>189915</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040302</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Donald L. Rice</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>While dissolved organic nitrogen (DON) plays a central role in global ocean N cycling, little is known about specific DON components. To address one aspect of this, investigators from Kent State University and the University of Georgia will examine polyamines, an under-studied microbially-produced DON component. They hypothehesize that, despite the low concentrations of these N-rich compounds, free polyamines have an important role in microbial ecology. To test this hypothesis, the investigators will examine the concentration, flux and fate of dissolved polyamines and dissolved amino acids at nearshore and open ocean sites using various chemical analyses. The composition of bacterial assemblages and of genes involved in polyamine utilization will also be determined using state-of-the-art molecular techniques. By integrating biogeochemical and molecular approaches, and linking functional genomics&lt;br/&gt;of plankton assemblages to material fluxes, the work will improve the understanding of the fate and dynamics of DON in marine environments, and the importance of polyamines as sources of C and N. This collaborative project will&lt;br/&gt;enhance inter-institution partnerships, and train graduate students while also&lt;br/&gt;reaching out to under-represented and promising first- and&lt;br/&gt;second-year undergraduate and high school students. The students will be involved with research opportunities, summer internships, and other activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1029742</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hollibaugh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aquadoc@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
