<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Collaborative Research: A Secure and Resilient Virtual Trust Routing Framework for Future Internet</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140370</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph Lyles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Current network-centric Internet service model is prone to&lt;br/&gt;resource exhausting attacks such as Distributed Denial of&lt;br/&gt;Services attacks. Due to the resource sharing nature and&lt;br/&gt;non-coordinated monitoring capability of the current Internet,&lt;br/&gt;it is difficult to quickly identify attack sources. Second, a&lt;br/&gt;new trend is to develop a user-centric Internet service model,&lt;br/&gt;in which traditional local network services are outsourced to&lt;br/&gt;remote service providers such as for cloud services. This new&lt;br/&gt;trend allows end users to fully control remote service nodes,&lt;br/&gt;their interconnections and routing, which imposes great threats&lt;br/&gt;on network resource allocations. Thus, it is highly desired&lt;br/&gt;that the future Internet is designed to provide a secure&lt;br/&gt;service domain that is both network-centric and user-centric.&lt;br/&gt;As a fundamental core to this goal, a secure and resilient&lt;br/&gt;virtualized routing architecture in a global inter-networking&lt;br/&gt;environment is explored to provide network resource reservation&lt;br/&gt;protection both at the network-centric and the user-centric&lt;br/&gt;level. A novel attribute-based, cryptography-based approach to&lt;br/&gt;construct secure virtualization is to be developed.&lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, an architectural solution to address the policy&lt;br/&gt;enforcement and inter-domain trust management is also&lt;br/&gt;considered. The end goal is to greatly improve the efficiency&lt;br/&gt;of attack monitoring and intrusion detection and to increase&lt;br/&gt;the resiliency of the future Internet. This is a collaborative&lt;br/&gt;exploratory project bringing together researchers from the&lt;br/&gt;University of Missouri-Kansas City, Arizona State University,&lt;br/&gt;and Osaka City University, Japan. All research results will be&lt;br/&gt;made available to the scientific community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1029562</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deep</FirstName>
      <LastName>Medhi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dmedhi@umkc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/05/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Kansas City</Name>
      <CityName>Kansas City</CityName>
      <ZipCode>641102499</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8162355839</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5100 Rockhill Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
