<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Design of CNT Composite Microstructural Characteristics for Enhanced Engineering Functionality and Manufacturability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>439500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The overarching objective of the proposed research is to study the effects of the three critical microstructural parameters, namely, (i) carbon nanotube-polymer interfacial strength; (ii) carbon nanotube orientation; and (iii) Level of carbon nanotube dispersion, on the manufacturability of carbon nanotube composites. To achieve this objective the machining mechanics will be examined by employing experimental techniques that include both machining inside an atomic force microscope and machining with a new micro-scribing process recently developed at the University of Illinois. The carbon nanotube polymer composite model developed earlier by the principal investigator and his colleagues, which assumed perfect interface bonding, will be enhanced by explicitly modeling the carbon nanotube-polymer interface using two possible approaches; modeling the interface as a third phase in the microstructure, and, using cohesive zone models for the carbon nanotube-polymer interface. Model validation will be accomplished using the micro-scribing processes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The benefits to society of this project include an enhanced understanding of the effects of carbon nanotube-polymer interfacial strength on the manufacturability of carbon nanotubes and a substantial increase of their potential for use in micro-scale applications that span fields including biomedical, electronics and defense; for example, applications such as microfluidic circuits for drug delivery, more effectively packaged micro-electronics. As a bridge between the nano- and the macro-worlds, the research pursued in this project will facilitate the education and training of a new generation of leaders in the field of micro-manufacturing. Further, the project researchers will strongly encourage participation of members from under-represented groups by proactively participating in several on-campus/off-campus programs, including Women in Engineering Program; Minority Engineering Program; the McNair Scholar program. An effort will be made to integrate new carbon nanotube composite applications and machinability issues developed in the proposed research into both new and existing courses at the University of Illinois.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1029221</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>DeVor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/24/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shiv</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kapoor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sgkapoor@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>K. Jimmy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hsia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kjhsia@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
