<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BRIGE: Testing the efficacy of concept inventories with bilingual students: The application of the Concept Assessment Tool for Statics at UPRM</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174990</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>bevlee watford</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This engineering education research award will explore language differences on the engineering concept inventory for engineering statics. The Concept Assessment Tool for Statics (CATS) is an instrument developed to identify students? conceptual understanding of statics concepts. In pilot tests at University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez, results demonstrated very low performance (28%) of students on CATS as compared with national standards which ranged between 30% - 70%. Because this test is in English, which is not the first language of most University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez students, the researcher proposes to test the efficacy of CATS with bilingual students. To accomplish this goal the study will be guided by the following research question: Do mechanical and civil senior engineering students? from the University of Puerto Rico at Mayaguez exhibit language difficulties with CATS? A mixed methods design is proposed in which data will be collected using quantitative (questionnaires and/or closed-ended questions) and qualitative (open-ended questions using focus groups) instruments. Similarly, data will be analyzed following quantitative analyses, but also applying open coding techniques for qualitative purposes. The expected results of this study will be the development of a beta version of CATS, in Spanish, to be tested further for validity and reliability. This project advances knowledge and explores creativity because it will be the first time that: (1) 100% of the sample of an engineering concept research study will consist of bilingual students; (2) an engineering concept inventory is developed in Spanish; (3) such a study measures language differences on engineering concept inventories. The results of the work are expected to enhance student learning of difficult concepts in statics, and particularly to improve the success of Hispanic students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1032563</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aidsa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Santiago-Roman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aidsa.santiago@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez</Name>
      <CityName>Mayaguez</CityName>
      <ZipCode>006819000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7878312065</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Call Box 9000</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
      <StateCode>PR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7741</Code>
      <Text>BROAD PARTIC IN ENG (BRIGE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
