<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>OISE Planning Visit</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5295</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This small award provides travel expenses for five participants from various US universities to an OISE planning activity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The meeting is to further develop OISE's plan for a bigger, broader workshop, to be held at a later date, to address issues affecting the ability of US universities to successfully support the international collaboration efforts of individual faculty members, and conversely, to address issues affecting the ability of individual faculty involved in international, collaborative projects, to help internationalize their US universities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning activiy coincides with the end of a meeting of Principal Investigators (individual faculty members) who run OISE-sponsored PIRE projects. The planning committee is made up largely of university-level administrators with responsibilities and experience in support of sponsored activities and/or international activities. Bringing these two groups together will allow cross-fertilization between them on current problems and successful approaches to them. The intended outcome is a well-designed workshop plan that will provide insight and examples of success in the various two-way chains of benefits and challenges that turn NSF support of individual faculty PI's into world-class projects that accomplish great science while simultaneously furthering the internationalization of US campuses and their constituents to the maximum extent possible.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1033735</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Killoren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>killoren.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7731</Code>
      <Text>OTHER GLOBAL LEARNING &amp; TRNING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5984</Code>
      <Text>TRANS-REGIONAL AFFAIRS (TRA)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7731</Code>
      <Text>OTHER GLOBAL LEARNING &amp; TRNING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
