<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Elucidation of Peptide Surface Structural Effects on the Catalytic Activity of Bio-Inspired Pd Nanomaterials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>260019</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George J. Antos</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1033334&lt;br/&gt;Knecht&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bio-inspired strategies have emerged as potential approaches to prepare and employ technologically important nanomaterials as catalysts that use eco-friendly and energy efficient reaction conditions. As a result, sustainable and efficient catalytic methods may be developed using these techniques. Peptide-based fabrication strategies have become unique examples of synthetic approaches as the sequences are composition specific, are able to generate nanoparticles of &lt;20 nm, and result in final structures which are highly active. However, the source of this activity is not understood. Principal Investigator Marc Knecht through the University of Kentucky Research Foundation believes a unique surface architecture is established leading to the activity. He intends to elucidate atomic-level structural information concerning the peptide surface ligands of biomimetic Pd nanoparticulate catalysts to isolate the motifs responsible for their enhanced catalytic reactivity for carbon-coupling reactions in water at room temperature. Unfortunately, little information is presently known about how the peptides coordinate to the surface of the catalyst particle, as it is this interaction which is likely responsible for the enhanced reactivity of the materials. The PI believes that the sequence binds in such a manner that it exposes a significant fraction of the metallic surface, from which reactivity occurs. By understanding this surface structure, the PI will be able to explore the catalytic mechanism for C-coupling, which could subsequently be exploited to expand the reactivity spectrum of these efficient catalyst materials. By understanding the surface structure and mode of sequence interactions, the rational design of peptides and other ligands could be possible to develop further enhanced nanocatalytic architectures. This is the broader technical impact of the project. The work has immediate potential to impact energy efficient and environmentally friendly catalytic schemes for use in delivering "green" chemical synthetic methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader outreach impact of the proposal employs the very visual nature of the catalytic research as a mechanism to increase interest in STEM disciplines in rural Kentucky students. The PI proposes to use the visual and colorful aspects of this research as a mechanism to grasp and maintain student interest in hopes of increasing their future educational development. From this topic, student exposure to eco-friendly/energy efficient catalysis, nanotechnology, and organic chemistry/molecules can occur.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1033334</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Knecht</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>knecht@miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>044E</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
