<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Cultural Validation of Geoscience Assessment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>59311</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jill L. Karsten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is a collaboration among educators from Blackfeet Community College, Diné College, Arizona State University, and Michigan State University to meet a need for culturally relevant geoscience assessment that complements place-based curriculum and pedagogy. Cultural validation of geoscience assessment contributes to more equitable assessment of undergraduate geoscience students, provides educators with a relevant means for assessing their students' conceptual understanding, involves educators in designing assessment appropriate for diverse students, and contributes to the conversation about cultural validity of science assessment in the broader science-education community. This project enhances Earth Systems Science Literacy by developing place-based assessment for diverse student populations engaged in learning geoscience through leveraging of local knowledge. As part of this collaborative work, this project provides in-service training to Tribal College educators in assessment design (including proper question layout, language use, and importance of cultural and communication validity), establishes new relationships between Tribal College and university educators, and leverages existing scholarly networks to help facilitate access to research-based educational assessment in the geosciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1034926</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Semken</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>semken@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
