<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Viologen-based Oxidation of Carbohydrate Fuels for a New Type of Low-Temperature Fuel Cell</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299455</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Principal Investigator: Dean R Wheeler&lt;br/&gt;Proposal No: 1034547&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will conduct fundamental studies to enable the development of new type of fuel cell that will operate on carbohydrate fuels, a feedstock previously considered impractical for electrochemical conversion to electricity. The process is based on a newly-investigated class of low-cost organic catalysts known as viologens that can, under the proper conditions, efficiently oxidize carbohydrates (e.g. glucose, xylose) to carbon dioxide at low temperature and generate electrons. Since carbohydrates are obtained by hydrolysis of the cellulosic components of plant biomass, the proposed direct carbohydrate fuel cell (DCFC) has the potential to be a renewable source of portable electrical energy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Development of DCFCs requires overcoming a number of technical barriers and gaining improved understanding of the action of the viologen electrocatalyst. To address these barriers, the proposed research plan will develop strategies to immobilize the viologen catalyst on anode surfaces, elucidate reaction processes, characterize the reaction kinetics and transport phenomena at the anode. Processes associated with the cathode and membrane components of the fuel cell will also be studied&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Successful development of a direct carbohydrate fuel cell will contribute to new technologies for providing future energy needs, particularly in remote regions where biomass is plentiful but electrical power is not. The proposed research activities will provide learning experiences for undergraduate and graduate students, as well as training for future careers in fuel cell and alternative energy technologies. Outreach efforts include introducing K-12 students and teachers to fuel cells and electric vehicle technologies through hands on demo kits.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1034547</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pitt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pitt@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wheeler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dean_wheeler@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brigham Young University</Name>
      <CityName>Provo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>846021231</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8014226177</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>A-285 ASB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>046E</Code>
      <Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
