<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pan American Advanced Studies Institute on Process Modeling and Optimization for Energy and Sustainability; Brazil; July 12-22, 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98100</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harold Stolberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Pan-American Advanced Studies Institutes (PASI) award, jointly supported by the NSF and the Department of Energy (DOE), will take place on July 12-22, 2011 in Brazil. Organized by Dr. Christos Maravelias of the University of Wisconsin Madison, the PASI will focus on the state-of-the-art methodologies for process modeling and optimization and their application to energy and sustainability. With the augmentation of energy usage, the decrease of conventional energy sources and their potential effects on ecosystems, there is a need to create sustainable solutions associated with the environment and energy. This Institute will consist of lectures, seminars and computer tutorials designed to provide an overview of process modeling and optimization approaches to these challenging problems. Leading researchers in the field as well as representatives from industry and government will contribute lectures and seminars. Participants will be drawn from several countries of the hemisphere and will include graduate students and postdoctoral researchers. Additional leveraged funding from various government agencies, chemical industries, and universities from the Americas, will reflect the importance of this activity to the international research community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A focus on state-of-the-art methods for process modeling and optimization, emphasizing synergy among methodologies and applications, will attract a diverse student body and provide a unique, global experience in education and research networking. At its conclusion, the PASI will identify future education and research opportunities, describe challenges in addressing emerging technologies, and enable networking and discussions between junior and senior researchers. Expected outcomes of this PASI include: 1) review of fundamental methods of the field and their application to new areas of research; 2) hands-on training for key computer-aided tools; 3) discussion of emerging concepts and approaches in process modeling and optimization as it applies to sustainability; and, 4) a forum for network building and exchange of ideas and research experiences. The results from the PASI will be disseminated through a virtual library that will contain presentations, educational materials, software, and exercises.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1036098</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mahmoud</FirstName>
      <LastName>El-Halwagi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>El-Halwagi@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maravelias</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>christos@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
