<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GLADE Workshop: July 26-29, 2010 at Scripps Institution of Oceanography San Diego, CA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Raffaella Montelli</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop on "Geodynamics of the Lithosphere and Deep Earth" (GLADE), held July 26-29, 2010 at Scripps Institution of Oceanography aims to bring the largely fragmented lithosphere and mantle dynamics researchers out of the ?forest? and into an open forum to begin discussing major scientific questions together as a community and address the challenges those provide. GLADE is intended to serve as a nesting ground for the US Geodynamics community to present and discuss both state-of-the-art and emerging research directions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the view that computational geodynamics has moved into the realm of predictive capability, this highly technical discipline needs a venue for in-depth and specialized discussion in order that we may learn from each other. However, the geodynamics community also recognizes the essential role that observations have in developing and constraining geodynamic models, in particular those coming from areas such as tectonics, plate reconstructions, and rheology of Earth materials. Towards this goal, the meeting strongly encourages participation from the tectonics community and aims to foster meaningful and continual engagement between the geodynamics and tectonics communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The content of the GLADE meeting will be focused upon ma jor outstanding scientific issues that transcend solid Earth geodynamics and related topics in planetary evolution and dynamics. The scientific content is spread over the first three days of the meeting, while the final day will be set aside for tutorials and technical workshops on geodynamics software. These demonstrations and tutorials are intended to emphasize next-generation geodynamics software and community-supported advances to existing software, much of which has been championed and maintained by the Computational Infrastructure for Geodynamics (CIG). All graduate students in attendance will be required to participate in the technical program, but other (senior) participants may leave after the scientific program. The meeting adopts a novel format that seeks to better integrate poster, oral, and discussion sessions, as well as designate time for students to meet with keynote speakers. In addition, the CIG steering committee will host a townhall discussion on the first evening of the meeting in order to gain input from the community regarding past and future software development priorities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This effort is supported by the Geophysics, Tectonics, and Marine Geology &amp; Geophysics Programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1037613</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dave</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stegman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dstegman@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1572</Code>
      <Text>TECTONICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
