<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improving Learning in Engineering Classrooms by Coupling Interactive Simulations and Real-Time Formative Assessment via Pen-Enabled Mobile Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>132408</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Donna Riley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This engineering education research project seeks to integrate readily available simulation tools with a variety of active learning pedagogies to teach engineering concepts. A unique feature of this project is to use tablet computers to permit students to explain concepts in a qualitative manner in real time, thus allowing rapid formative assessment by content experts. The project will pilot the innovation in several engineering classes and address issues of scaling the technique to larger class sizes. Fundamental insights on engineering misconceptions may arise from this project pending successful evaluation of the large number of student artifacts generated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project is to allow better use of existing computer-based simulation tools for teaching conceptual content to engineering students. The teaching methods developed will be piloted in classes with a large number of female students, who are often under-represented in STEM disciplines, as well as summer classes for minority students. The scalability of the teaching techniques to large classrooms will be investigated to more broadly disseminate the innovations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1037519</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kowalski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fkowalsk@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kowalski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>skowalsk@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tracy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gardner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tgardner@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
      <CityName>Golden</CityName>
      <ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
