<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for 20th International Workshop on Electromagnetic Induction in the Earth, to be held September 18-24, 2010 in Giza, Egypt</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Raffaella Montelli</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is to provide funds to partially cover registration, travel, and living expenses for students, young researchers (including post doctoral scientists, and young faculty), to attend the 20th International Workshop on Electromagnetic (EM) Induction in the Earth in Giza, Egypt on September, 18-24, 2010. This biennial workshop, which is sponsored by Working Group I-2 of the International Union of Geomagnetism and Aeronomy (IAGA), has become the premier venue for researchers around the world to meet and discuss new developments in EM geophysics. EM measurements provide a unique view into the Earth because of the sensitivity of electrical conductivity to temperature, fluids, ore minerals, and rock type. This sensitivity makes EM methods useful in a wide range of investigations, addressing both applied and basic science questions, from the very near surface to the deep mantle. For example, EM methods have long been the favored tool for exploration in the mining industry, and they play an increasingly important role in petroleum exploration. A plethora of near-surface applications exist for EM: general geological mapping, waste site assessment, aquifer mapping and vulnerability studies, exploration for construction materials, building and utility investigation, and UXO detection and discrimination. The sensitivity of conductivity to fluids, which strongly influence rock strength, also makes EM an essential tool for larger scale investigations of the structure, dynamics, and evolution of the deep Earth, and for assessing volcanic and seismic hazards.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The project will benefit the US EM induction community, by increasing participation of students and early career researchers from the US at this international meeting, by helping US researchers to develop the international contacts that will ultimately lead to collaborative projects around the world, and by promoting international exchange of software, data, and results. NSF support is also being used to leverage additional support from industry. Individual awards for travel support are determined by the working group financial support community, from applications submitted by students and early-career researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop was funded by the Geophysics, EarthScope, and Continental Dynamics Programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1038086</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Egbert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>egbert@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
