<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CCI: Chemistry effects on climate: Heterogeneous reactions on complex atmospheric aerosol particles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1525000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this Phase I CCI is to establish interdisciplinary bridges linking theoretical and laboratory studies of heterogeneous chemical reactions under atmosphere-like conditions with field data and observations of real aerosol particles, as the means to establish a fundamental understanding of how complex reaction processes occurring on surfaces of aerosol particles impact climate, marine and atmospheric chemistry, and biogeochemical cycling. There is limited understanding of the chemistry occurring on the surfaces of aerosol particles in the atmosphere, even though the chemistry affects the particles' physicochemical properties, and thus, determines their overall impact on the Earth's climate. Due to the extreme complexity of atmospheric particles, experimental and theoretical studies have traditionally focused almost exclusively on heterogeneous reactions of simplified model systems, establishing only tenuous relationships with the properties affecting the chemical reactivity of real atmospheric particles. In contrast, field studies, which give unique insight into the complexity of real aerosol particles, cannot resolve the fundamental mechanistic drivers that ultimately control their impact on atmospheric chemistry and climate. Thus, the Center for Aerosol Impacts on Climate and the Environment (CAICE) will perform fundamental chemistry studies on the surfaces of real, complex aerosol particles created in controlled environments using a unique ocean-atmosphere reaction chamber to produce sea spray aerosols. A range of modeling and measurement approaches will be used to probe the chemistry and molecular scale properties of the generated sea spray aerosols and their subsequent reactions. The studies will allow the CCI to begin quantifying how specific heterogeneous reactions change the climate relevant properties of aerosols. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center for Aerosol Impacts on Climate and the Environment (CAICE) will also have broad impact by educating the future researchers who will have to grapple with large scale complex interactions in our environment. An interdisciplinary teaching curriculum will be developed to enable the students to acquire a solid foundation in fundamental chemistry, while focusing on problems related to the ocean, atmosphere, climate, chemistry and biology. The research in the Center will be shared with the scientific community through education and outreach activities, publications, presentations, news media, the web, and public workshops. Both CCI faculty and students will be actively involved in education and outreach programs. A key element in the public outreach plans is the Birch Aquarium which will host a new exhibit highlighting the Center's research to its 400,000 annual visitors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Centers for Chemical Innovation (CCI) Program supports research centers that can address major, long-term fundamental chemical research challenges that have a high probability of both producing transformative research and leading to innovation. These Centers will attract broad scientific and public interest by sharing the results of their innovative approach to this challenging question.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1038028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prather</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kprather@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1995</Code>
      <Text>CHE CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1303</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE MODELING &amp; PREDICTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9156</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
