<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an ICP-OES for Multidisciplinary Environmental Studies and Training</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>245877</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1039502&lt;br/&gt;Li&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Determination of inorganic pollutants in liquid samples at parts per billion (ppb) levels is essential for the studies of environmental impact, waste toxicity characteristics, waste treatment, disposal, and utilization. Many environmental samples are time-sensitive and delivered in small quantities thereby limiting the number of tests that can be performed. This is especially problematic when a large number of elements or contaminants need to be analyzed within the same sample. Therefore, an instrument that can analyze multiple elements simultaneously in small sample volumes is highly desired. The Inductively Coupled Plasma-Optical Emission Spectrometer (ICP-OES) is an ideal instrument to meet these requirements. It can simultaneously measure all the heavy metals that are of environmental and health concerns at lower ppb levels. The objective of this project is to acquire an ICP-OES to improve the environmental studies at Jackson State University (JSU). The instrument will be housed in the Environmental Engineering Laboratory at the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, School of Engineering, Jackson State University, Jackson, Mississippi.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1039502</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lin.li@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yadong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yadong.li@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Jackson State University</Name>
      <CityName>Jackson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>392170002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6019792931</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 J R LYNCH ST.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>016E</Code>
      <Text>POLLUTION AVOIDANCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
