<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Molecular Imager for Undergraduate Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>66798</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Recent advances in molecular biology and biotechnology have opened up new opportunities in cell biology, biochemistry, and genomics. This Major Research Instrumentation award funds the acquisition of a molecular imager to support biology and biotechnology research at Dominican University of California. The new equipment will enable Dominican University faculty to advance their own active research programs and allow the University to better integrate education and research to train the next generation of scientists. The molecular imager will support undergraduate training in six research laboratories that represent a wide range of biological research. Dr. Louie is examining mechanisms of cadmium and nickel induced gene regulation in mammalian cells to correlate expression analysis to growth, development and homeostasis. Dr. Ghosh is studying how arsenic affects gene expression in different rice cultivars. Additional projects include research on pollen germination, neuroendocrine development, and COX-2 physiology. In total, these projects will impact 35-45 students/year, and the results of these research and teaching efforts will be broadly disseminated through abstracts and peer reviewed publications, as well as by active participation of students and faculty at professional meetings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1039728</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sibdas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghosh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sibdas.ghosh@dominican.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maggie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Louie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maggie.louie@dominican.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sheila</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson-Brousseau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sheila.johnson-brousseau@dominican.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Dominican University of California</Name>
      <CityName>San Rafael</CityName>
      <ZipCode>949012298</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4154853239</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>50 Acacia Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
