<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ARI-MA: Investigation of Energy Transfer Based Nanocomposites For Radiation Detection</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>253793</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;1039068&lt;br/&gt;Wei Chen&lt;br/&gt;University of Texas/Arlington&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This interdisciplinary proposal brings together expertise in nanophysics, particle physics, and nuclear engineering to develop a novel radiation detector, while simultaneously establishing a strong academic program for Homeland Security through integrated research and education activities at the University of Texas, Arlington. Cerium-doped nanocomposites have shown promise as scintillators, but typically emit in the ultraviolet (UV) and are difficult to convert into uniform and transparent crystals. The PI proposes to use energy transfer to quantum dots to convert the UV emission into the visible range, and to develop methods for encapsulating nanoparticles in thin films that can then be combined into crystals to form practical detectors. Various parameters, such as the size of the quantum dots and the details of the crystallization process, provide significant technical challenges, but the payoff of demonstrating a new scintillator combining the desirable properties of nanocomposites, such as high stopping power, high sensitivity, and excellent energy resolution, with the high quantum efficiency and short decay lifetime of quantum dots is potentially enormous. Replacing traditional crystals with these new nanocomposite crystals would have a huge broader impact, allowing low dose detection of nuclear materials to help prevent the illicit transport of radiological materials into the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1039068</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brandt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brandta@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weichen@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
