<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a Next Generation Polysonic Wind Tunnel for Transformative Active Control Technologies and Non-Intrusive Flow Diagnostics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3295029</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) development project is for a new polysonic wind tunnel blowdown facility consisting of a compressed air generation and storage system, test sections, and exhaust system. A wind tunnel is typically characterized by its speed range and the size of its test section. The facility has a 12-in x 12-in x 24-in test section with a Mach number range of 0.2 to 5 with a maximum Reynolds number capability of roughly 20 million/foot. This facility will be large enough to be useful to industry, ensuring its long-term, efficient use but small enough to be efficiently operated in a university. It will be used to develop innovative, practical active flow and noise control techniques and advanced diagnostics to study the design of, and fundamental problems in, high-speed flight vehicles. It will incorporate unique design features with low test-section noise and extensive optical access for flow diagnostics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PolySonic Wind Tunnel will create a unique shared resource to a) produce fundamental advances in gas dynamics, material science and other areas; b) develop transformational flow control technologies; and c) attract, educate, and help retain a diverse pool of engineers and scientists, including underrepresented minorities from our partner institutions. The facility will thus produce critical knowledge while dramatically accelerating transformative research leading to next-generation designs. It will also leverage and augment the resources of the Florida Center for Advanced Aero-Propulsion, a multi-university, statewide Center of Excellence, led by Florida State University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1039825</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Farrukh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alvi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>falvi@fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rajan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rkumar@fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chiang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shih</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shih@eng.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cattafesta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cattafes@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>025E</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
