<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CBMS Regional Conference in the Mathematical Sciences - Global Harmonic Analysis - June 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>43556</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Global Harmonic Analysis&lt;br/&gt;NSF/CBMS Regional Conference in the Mathematical Sciences&lt;br/&gt;University of Kentucky, June 20-24, 2011&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Global harmonic analysis may be viewed as an extension of classical&lt;br/&gt;Fourier theory on the line and on the circle to the geometric setting of&lt;br/&gt;Riemannian manifolds. Riemannian manifolds provide models of both com-&lt;br/&gt;pletely integrable and chaotic dynamical systems, and also provide a setting&lt;br/&gt;in which the connection between "classical" and "quantum" behavior can be&lt;br/&gt;carefully studied. Moreover, just as harmonic analysis on the line and the&lt;br/&gt;circle are a fundamental tool in the study of both linear and nonlinear differ-&lt;br/&gt;ential equations in these settings, so global harmonic analysis is fundamental&lt;br/&gt;to the study of di¤erential equations, such as the wave and Schrödinger equa-&lt;br/&gt;tion, on manifolds. On a general Riemannian manifold, harmonic analysis is&lt;br/&gt;the study of eigenfunctions of the Laplacian in the given Riemannian metric.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Global harmonic analysis refers to the use of the global dynamics of geo-&lt;br/&gt;desic fow on the manifold to study the large-eigenvalue asymptotics of the&lt;br/&gt;eigenfunctions and eigenvalues of the Laplacian on a manifold. Since global&lt;br/&gt;eigenfunctions of the Laplacian on a manifold are eigenfunctions of the wave&lt;br/&gt;group, and the wave group propagates singularities along geodesics, the high-&lt;br/&gt;frequency properties of eigenfunctions are connected to the long-time dy-&lt;br/&gt;namics of the geodesic flow. Two cases of particular interest are quantum&lt;br/&gt;complete integrability, where the underlying geodesic flow is completely in-&lt;br/&gt;tegrable, and quantum chaos, where the underlying geodesic flow is ergodic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Professor Steve Zelditch of Northwestern University will given ten lectures&lt;br/&gt;on global harmonic analysis. He will begin with basic examples (constant&lt;br/&gt;curvature spaces), develop material on pseudodi¤erential and Fourier inte-&lt;br/&gt;gral operators, derive trace formulas including the celebrated Duistermaat-&lt;br/&gt;Guillemin trace formula, and discuss applications to properties of eigenfunc-&lt;br/&gt;tions and eigenvalues and inverse eigenvalue problems. Completely integrable&lt;br/&gt;and ergodic systems will be considered in depth.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/07/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1040927</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Perry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peteraperry@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hislop</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peter.hislop@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
