<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Powder X-Ray Diffractometer for Research and Education at Wake Forest University.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>362054</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Guebre X. Tessema</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical: This project is for the acquisition of a flexible, multi-purpose powder X-ray diffractometer (PXRD) for use by researchers in the Chemistry, Physics, Anthropology departments, and the center for nanotechnology and molecular materials at Wake Forest University. The PXRD system will enhance and expand research and education in the development of (1) hybrid inorganic-organic multifunctional cluster materials for use in catalysis, energy storage, and environmental remediation using the molecular building block synthesis strategy (2) organic materials and devices for nano- and macro-electronics applications to better understand the structural features that control electrical performance, 3) materials for organic-based photovoltaics to determine the foundational basis for engineering ideal heterojunction systems for a broad range of polymer absorbers, (4) nano-composite materials formed from conducting organic polymers grown within electroactive metal organic frameworks for use as lithium insertion electrodes, and (5) the study of anthropogenic processes and enviromagnetic minerals in the geoarchaeological record. The PXRD system has capabilities for fast and reliable collection of high quality X-ray diffraction data from polycrystalline materials, thin films, and nanomaterials, and for the collection of microdiffraction data from archaeological samples. The instrument represents a cost-effective way to satisfy current and future needs of diverse users with a wide range of interests. The equipment will be used to enhance collaboration with two historically black institutions Winston Salem State University and North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University, and with faculty and students in the nanotechnology program at Forsyth Technical Community College. A series of weekend workshops entitled "X-rays in Art, Archaeology and Axe Murders" will include topics in materials, cultural heritage and forensics.&lt;br/&gt;NonTechnical: This acquisition of a multipurpose powder x-ray diffractometer (PXRD) is for advancing research, education and outreach at Wake Forest University. It will increase access to shared scientific instruments; improve the quality and expand the scope of research in science and engineering; and foster the integration of research and education in research-intensive learning environments in western North Carolina. PXRD instrumentation utilizes the analytical technique of x-ray diffraction, allowing the study of a variety of samples in a nondestructive fashion to probe structure at the atomic level. This technique has evolved to include applications in areas such as new materials development, nanomaterials, polymers, thin films, drug discovery, forensics, and archaeological sciences. The multipurpose powder x-ray diffractometer will provide research capability not currently available anywhere in the northwestern part of North Carolina and represents a cost-effective approach to satisfy the diverse requirements of its users. The research programs of users from the departments of Chemistry, Physics and the WFU Center for Nanotechnology are directed at the development of multifunctional hybrid inorganic-organic materials, organic electronics, conducting polymers, and materials for photovoltaics. For researchers from the Anthropology department, the instrument enables the microanalysis of small and heterogeneous samples of cultural materials, such as artifacts. These studies can be conducted in a nondestructive fashion so that the original samples of cultural heritage can be preserved. Since the x-ray facility at WFU also serves as a key resource for researchers at other institutions in the area, the equipment will enhance collaboration with two historically black institutions (Winston Salem State University and North Carolina Agricultural and Technical state University) and with faculty and students in the nanotechnology program at Forsyth Technical Community College. The capabilities of the new instrument will be heavily utilized in a series of weekend workshops offering topics in materials and cultural heritage and forensics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1040264</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Noftle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>noftle@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abdessadek</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lachgar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Lachgar@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carroll</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>carroldl@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thacker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thackep@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jurchescu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jurchescu@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wake Forest University</Name>
      <CityName>Winston Salem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>271098758</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3367585888</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1834 Wake Forest Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
