<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-India Planning Visit: Collaborative Research on Algorithms for Digital Microfluidic Biochips</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4367</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Lueck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>104108&lt;br/&gt;Krishnendu Chakrabarty &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the U.S.-India Planning Visit: Collaborative Research on Algorithms for Digital Microfluidic Biochips. Professors K. Chakrabarty, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Duke University and Bhargab Bhattacharya, Advanced Computing and Microelectronics, Indian Statistical Institute (ISI), Kolkata, India intend to identify collaborative research directions on algorithms for the optimization of digital microfluidic biochips. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The initial focus will be on dilution and mixing of liquids on a biochip. Prof. Chakrabarty from Duke University brings to this collaboration his expertise on digital microfluidics and chip design. Prof. Bhattacharya is an expert on design and analysis of algorithms. The proposed collaboration will explore new algorithms and optimization techniques for making digital microfluidic biochips more efficient and practical for healthcare applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The planning visit will lead to a longer-term collaborative research proposal to be submitted to the National Science Foundation (NSF) and to the Department of Science and Technology (DST) in India for consideration under the NSF-DST Joint Program. In the follow-up research proposal, t, PhD students from both countries will work in close collaboration. In addition to receiving&lt;br/&gt; interdisciplinary education and training in different aspects of biochip design, US students will gain professional experience and cultural exposure beyond the nation?s borders.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1041708</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Krishnendu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chakrabarty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krish@ee.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
