<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Proposal for Partial Support for an International Symposium on Surface Hardening of Corrosion Resistant Alloys</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5197</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan J. Ardell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The field of surface engineering is an emerging one with multiple areas of active research. There have been major advances in understanding the technology and its application to corrosion-resistant alloys. The International Symposium on Surface Hardening of Corrosion Resistant Alloys will be held May 25-26 on the campus of CWRU. This event serves as a "state of the art" meeting, bringing together researchers from universities, industries, and government agencies all over the world, as well as providers and end users of low-temperature surface hardening techniques. The technical program will explore the emerging technology of surface engineering. The research community, suppliers and end users of low temperature processes (gas, vacuum, ion and plasma processes) for surface enhancement of corrosion resistant alloys by interstitial hardening (carburizing, nitriding, nitrocarburizing) will benefit. The program includes domestic speakers and speakers from several countries in Europe as well as China and Japan. This project will support the attendance of graduate students and some of the domestic speakers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042597</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arthur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heuer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Heuer@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
