<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BPC-AE:Collaborative Research: The ARTSI Alliance: Advancing Robotics Technology for Societal Impact</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>65828</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Janice E. Cuny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Hampton University, in collaboration with Carnegie-Mellon University, Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University, the University of the District of Columbia, Norfolk State University, Winston-Salem State University, Morgan State University, Jackson State University, Elizabeth City State University, Duke University, the University of Alabama Tuscaloosa, and the University of Michigan, proposes the ARTSI Alliance (Advancing Robotics Technology for Societal Impact). ARTSI is a consortium of Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) and major research universities (R1s) working together to increase African American participation in computer science, with a focus on robotics. This extension proposal will expand ARTSI to seventeen Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) and roughly 10 major research universities (R1s). Hampton University is the new lead institution; Carnegie Mellon University remains the lead R1 school. The extension introduces three new initiatives that (1) improve the quality and uniformity of robotics instruction by developing robotics curriculum modules specific to the needs of HBCUs, (2) pilot a program to attract STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics) students to HBCUs by offering robot programming activities in local high schools, and (3) pilot skill-building program for rising sophomores to better prepare them to become involved in robotics research. The extension also includes new collaborations with the Caribbean Center for Computing Excellence (a BPC Alliance in Puerto Rico and the US Virgin Islands) and the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042306</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mona</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rizvi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mrizvi@nsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thorna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Humphries</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thumphries@nsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Norfolk State University</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235048060</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7578239053</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>700 Park Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7482</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTIC IN COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7482</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTIC IN COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
