<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BPC-DP: SpelBots: African American Women Showcasing Robotics and Computer Science to Underrepresented K-12 Students Nationally</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>525000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Janice E. Cuny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Spelman College will expand its work with women and underrepresented students in computer science and robotics nationally through the SpelBots robotics and computing program and the creation of the National SPELBOTS Club for K-12 students. The SpelBots are a team of female, African American students who conduct robotics research, compete worldwide in robotics and computer science competitions, and conduct K-12 outreach. The long-range vision of this project is to leverage the SpelBots activities to provide career role models in cutting-edge computer science and robotics from underrepresented communities. This project will bring attitude-changing computer science and robotics showcase presentations to underrepresented students and their teachers, and in conjunction with these showcases, promote the formation and mentoring of robotics and computer science clubs among K-12 students using social media as well as local workshops. Further, it will recruit, mentor and train undergraduate African American women students in computer science and robotics research, outreach, and competition projects. In addition, this project will provide advising for these activities for students at local historically black colleges and universities. The goals are to (1) investigate the effectiveness of the showcase approach to exposing, exciting, recruiting, and mentoring underrepresented middle and high school students in computing, (2) study the impact of our recruitment and retention activities in computer science among African American women, specifically, and underrepresented students, generally, in order to disseminate best practices, and (3) increase the amount of autonomous humanoid and mobile robotics research performed by African American undergraduate women.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042454</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jakita</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thomas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jnt0020@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/29/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lawrence</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lawrence@spelman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>andrew.williams@mu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/30/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Spelman College</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303144399</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4042705897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>350 Spelman Lane SW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7482</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTIC IN COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7482</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTIC IN COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
