<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Accelerating biodegradation of hydrocarbons from the Deepwater Horizon Oil Spill in the Gulf of Mexico with Naturally Occurring Marine Substrates</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>130462</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The primary goal of this proposal is to determine means of enhancing rates of biodegradation of the hydrocarbons in the coastal zone of the Northern Gulf of Mexico resulting from the catastrophic Deepwater Horizon oil spill. The scope and impact of the this ongoing oil spill disaster are of unprecedented scale and information on key environmental data is critically needed as quickly as possible. The objectives of this research include (1) identify sources of endogenous organic matter in the affected areas that accelerate biodegradation rates, (2) identify the composition and genomic potential of the indigenous microbial consortium to promote polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) degradation and to undergo horizontal gene transfer off PAH genes, and (3) examine changes in rate processes and composition of the microbial consortium as the oil is weathered over the course of a year. The suitability of local marine substrates for enhancing the biodegradation of the hydrocarbons reaching the shore will be determined experimentally. Field experiments with the suitable organic source will be conducted to determine rates of in situ degradation. The composition and genomic potential of the microbial consortium to promote PAH degradation in laboratory and field settings will be investigated. A longer term objective is to develop feasible engineering solutions based on sound biological data to assist in mitigating the long-ranging effects of offshore and coastal oil contamination. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bruce Hamilton&lt;br/&gt;Program Director&lt;br/&gt;Environmental Sustainability&lt;br/&gt;5/24/10</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042743</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sobecky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>psobecky@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Behzad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mortazavi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bmortazavi@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7643</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>021E</Code>
      <Text>Water management</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
