<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Detangling Flow Regimes and Paleoclimate in the Deepest Section of the EDML Ice Core using U-series Ages.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>217858</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julie Palais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Aciego/1043367&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the development of a new method for determining the absolute age of samples from deep ice cores. The project will: (1) prove the efficacy of the Uranium-series dating method on a high accumulation rate ice core, and (2) address the uncertainties in the age dating of the EPICA Dronning-Maud Land (EDML) ice core in the lower 300 m. The well-dated upper section of the ice core (down to 150,000 years at 2415.7 m) will provide excellent constraints to validate the ages determined by the U-series method. After verification, and possible adjustments to the laboratory chemistry, the method will be applied to a suite of ice samples of unknown age in the lower part of the EDML ice core. Within the lower 300 m of this ice core, the climate records are disturbed by tilting and folding of the ice, and, due to the uncertainties in how the ice has flowed, it is impossible to determine if accurate age dates can be obtained to access the record of climate change, or if mixing of the ice is too incoherent. As part of the methodology, the PI will measure surface area of dust included in the ice using a gas adsorption technique developed for ultra-small samples; these measurements will be made on a BET nano-scale which is to be purchased from the funding of this project. Intellectual Merit: The proposed research will contribute to our understanding of geophysical processes that fold and tilt ice. This will allow new paleoclimate records to be recovered from ice cores that have been physically deformed and disturbed and previously did not permit accurate dating. Broader Impacts: This funding will provide support for one PhD graduate student and contribute to their training as a researcher in geochemistry and paleoclimate studies. The PI will teach classes in earth surface processes (including glaciology) and in advanced isotope geochemistry. Work related to this research will be integrated as a teaching tool into the classroom to provide a hands-on, relevant learning experience. Furthermore, samples examined as part of this research will be made available from the AWI archive in Bremerhaven, Germany as part of the collaboration between the PI in the United States and the European ice core community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1043367</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aciego</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aciego@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
