<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Professional Readers for STEM Student Writers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199879</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myles G. Boylan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Interdisciplinary (99)&lt;br/&gt;This project is investigating a new approach to developing the writing skills of STEM students. A key issue and important impediment to writing requirements for students in STEM courses is the ability of the institution to provide prompt feedback. This project is providing students with feedback on a course writing project by capitalizing on an otherwise untapped educational resource: university alumni and employees with scientific or technical backgrounds who normally play no direct role in the institution's educational mission. Students are being paired with alumni or employee volunteers whose backgrounds make them suitable readers for a particular STEM writing assignment. These pairs are guided through a series of interactions (in person or via IT) through which students get feedback on their work-in-progress from rough drafts through final polishing. Volunteers are being given instruction in how to give "reader-based" feedback (describing their reactions to the drafts as a user of the text) rather than focusing on editing or judging the text. In a pilot effort it was found that many alumni and employees are eager and qualified to help their institution's undergraduates develop their scientific writing and reasoning skills and that the students benefit from such interaction. &lt;br/&gt;Eight different STEM courses are participating in this project for at least two semesters each. Formative assessment data from each semester are being used in making revisions for subsequent semesters. Participating instructors, who have attended training workshops, consult with project personnel to develop assignments and protocols tailored to their particular course, and participate in assessment activities. The primary objectives of this project include (1) identifying the types of STEM courses for which this approach is most likely to be successful and developing protocols and volunteer reader pools appropriate for those settings, (2) improving student attitudes toward and understanding of scientific and technical writing, (3) helping students develop mature writing processes that include drafting and making use of feedback, and (4) increasing student engagement in STEM writing assignments. Evaluation includes on-line surveys of student and volunteer participants, interviews with faculty members, and focus group conversations with student, volunteer and faculty participants. &lt;br/&gt;Although this approach is being developed at a single institution, it is replicable. Part of this investigation will see to identify ways to simplify and automate procedures needed to facilitate effective student-reader interactions. Dissemination will include online venues such as the Science Education Resource Center (SERC) web server, publication in writing studies, science education and education columns in STEM discipline journals, and presentations at conferences on student writing, science education, and university administration.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1043674</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moskovitz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cmosk@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/22/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
