<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Synthesis, Characterization, Modelling and Simulation of Polymer Nanoencapsulated Aerogels</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49063</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Martin L. Dunn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Aerogels are lightweight porous materials with high thermal insulation and sound attenuation values. Nevertheless, practical use has been slow because they are also very fragile materials. This problem has been addressed by casting a polymer coating around their entire internal porous surface. That coating connects (crosslinks) the skeletal nanoparticles, reinforces the interparticle necks while the internal void space is not compromised. The new material combines the ultimate specific compressive strength of carbon fiber reinforced epoxies with the thermal conductivity of glass wool. A critical factor that controls the distribution of forces across the skeletal framework, potentially increasing the ultimate strength of the material is the nanostructure morphology. Thus this project will study experimentally the effect of the structural morphology on the thermal and mechanical properties of crosslinked aerogels. Synthetic conditions will be varied systematically by using statistical experimental design methods, while modeling and simulation will help understand the nanostructure-property relationships. Major factors will be identified to condense the design space of crosslinked aerogels in order to provide optimal materials and structures in the shortest time period. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Strong lightweight materials is a National Priority for energy conservation, the National Defense, Homeland Security and the Space Program. Polymer crosslinked aerogels are multifunctional materials that combine low mass density with mechanical strength suitable for armor and thermal properties suitable for thermal insulation. Applications in energy efficient buildings, vehicles, cryogenic fuel tanks are clearly visible. Commercialization will boost the local State economy while in the academic setting the project will create an excellent interdisciplinary intellectual environment for the education of graduate and undergraduate students in all aspects of material science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1043695</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hongbing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hongbing.lu@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
      <CityName>Richardson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1630</Code>
      <Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>026E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
