<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Assessing Functional Diversity of Algal Communities at the Single Cell Level with a Compact Multi-function Microfluidic Cytometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>205000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Irwin Forseth</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Photosynthetic microalgae are dominant primary food producers in aquatic systems, and algal mass culture has a strong potential to produce oil-based fuel and to remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere. However, algal production of foods/oils fluctuates strongly, and the reasons for this are unknown since information on individual algal cells under natural conditions is currently inaccessible. This need is addressed here with novel technology (a custom-designed, multifunction, ultra-compact cytometer) able to simultaneously assess the efficiency with which individual algal cells utilize solar energy for photosynthesis and their oil content. In light of the critical importance of microbes for human health, energy needs, and ecosystem sustainability ? and in the absence of established technology for the characterization of microbial functional diversity ? this research addresses an urgent need. Specifically, this research will (i) first confirm proper cytometer performance with laboratory-grown algal cultures, (ii) add further monitoring parameters needed to differentiate individual algal cells in mixed natural communities, and (iii) assess the functional diversity of algae in these communities in Colorado lakes. The results of this study are expected to allow a better prediction of toxic algal blooms and repercussions of changes in microbial oil content throughout food chains as well as identification of algae with superior properties for biofuels production. This highly diverse collaborative team of researchers includes an ecologist, a biophysicist, and photobiologists, thus providing not only the necessary intersection of novel technology and ecological expertise, but also providing an interdisciplinary educational opportunity for students, especially for training in biology (algal physiology and ecology) of students with a background in math, physics, or engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1044552</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ralph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jimenez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjimenez@jila.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lewis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>William.Lewis@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>william.adams@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Demmig-Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>barbara.demmig-adams@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7657</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Ecologi Physiology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
