<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ZagApps: Mobile Device Applications Laboratory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>133341</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jane Prey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Computer Science Mobile Device Application Lab project (ZagApps) at Gonzaga University is creating a curriculum to enhance computer science study with mobile device/smart phone application development. The laboratory and curriculum use Apple 'Touch' technology. Gonzaga computer science students work closely with area STEM teachers to create applications for use in K-12 classrooms. The STEM teachers are involved in both the design and the use of the applications and provide feedback on the usefulness of the applications. As a result of working with their high school teacher and student 'customers', Gonzaga students are better prepared for the software industry processes of developing applications based on user needs and of testing the final application for reliability. They expand their technical skills in mobile device/smart phone application development, testing, and field deployment and their people skills in customer relations, active listening, and problem solving. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project impacts high school students in the selected STEM classrooms by generating positive experiences between teachers, students, and collegiate computing majors. The high school students meet college undergraduates and learn about the importance of computer science as well as the importance of their math and science studies. The project also provides a foundation for better collaboration between university computer science programs and high school STEM teachers and students. The developed curriculum is applicable to other colleges and universities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1044921</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>csmith16@lssu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gonzaga University</Name>
      <CityName>Spokane</CityName>
      <ZipCode>992580087</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5093136102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>502 East Boone Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7513</Code>
      <Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
