<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EMSW21-RTG: Training the Research Workforce in Geometry, Topology and Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal calls to continue our research training program in geometry, topology and dynamics at the University of Michigan. Recent Ph.D.'s and advanced graduate students will be the main beneficiaries. The Mathematics Department at UM has one of the largest and most vigorous post-doctoral and graduate programs in the country, with an excellent record of producing high-quality researchers in geometry, topology and dynamics. We will bolster the training of post-docs and graduate students in these areas by deepening and broadening their education and providing the trainees with ample opportunities to excel in their research. Five senior faculty members (Richard Canary, John Erik Fornaess, Gopal Prasad, Yongbin Ruan and Ralf Spatzier) will lead this project in collaboration with other senior faculty. We introduced various innovations into our current training program, and will continue them and expand on them: We will provide intensive exploratory seminars, lecture series and workshops. All trainees will develop lecturing skills, and will benefit from intensive mentoring. Some trainees will deepen their scientific training by traveling to other institutions at the forefront of research. Finally, we will expose undergraduates to research in the these areas via REU's. We involve postdocs in REU activities, thus training them to supervise research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Geometry, topology and dynamical systems are core areas of mathematics. Geometry investigates the shape of spaces, through invariants such as curvature. Topology explores the properties of spaces which remain invariant under continuous deformations. One basic such invariant, the genus, is the number of "holes" in a surface. Dynamical systems concern the evolution of a physical or mathematical system over time. Especially in recent years, geometry and dynamics have developed in mutually beneficial interaction. Case in point are topology, geometry and complex dynamics in low dimension which in many aspects mirror each other. Many of the most exciting developments in these areas are truly interrelated, and benefit from each other either by idea, analogy or actual tool. At the same time, connections with other fields such as group theory, algebraic geometry and mathematical physics have strengthened dramatically. These developments have been amazing in their breadth and depth, and demonstrate the vitality of these areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1045119</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ralf</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spatzier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spatzier@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fornaess</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fornaess@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yongbin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ruan@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gopal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prasad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gprasad@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Canary</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>canary@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1265</Code>
      <Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1281</Code>
      <Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7335</Code>
      <Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7301</Code>
      <Text>RES TRAINING GROUPS IN THE MATH SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
