<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER-Enabling Partnerships to Enable Science (TOOLS): AnyFish: a User-Friendly Software Package for Creating Realistic Animations for Animal Behavior</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>314000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle M. Elekonich</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project seeks to develop user-friendly software, anyFish, for researchers, educators, and students seeking to develop realistic, scientifically rigorous computer animations of fish based on real-world data on behavior, shape, and color. The software will be used to produce stimuli for use in behavioral experiments, as well as interactive modules for educational use. The software will allow rigorous testing of theories of collective behavior, social interactions, and cognition. Students will be widely familiar with analogous systems in computer games, making it a particularly powerful tool to bring students into STEM programs by piquing the interest of students in science, biology, and animal behavior. A module based on anyFish will be integrated into the Virtual Biology educational software package for inquiry-based education at high school and college levels. anyFish will also make it easy for students to participate in original research on a minimal budget. A single desktop computer can be used to create and play back stimuli, and a handful of aquaria are required for the experiments. Students at smaller and minority-serving institutions will be able to design and execute rigorous, state-of-the-art experiments in animal behavior.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1045226</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rosenthal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grosenthal@bio.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wyan@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jerald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jerry.johnson@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
