<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NIRT: Fabrication of carbon nanotube based dry adhesive surfaces mimicking gecko-feet</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/03/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>510766</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce M. Kramer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: NIRT 0609077&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI and Co-PIs: Liming Dai, Ali Dhinojwala, Pulickel Ajayan and Ajit K. Roy&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI Email: ldai@udayton.edu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Title: NIRT: Fabrication of carbon nanotube based dry adhesive surfaces mimicking gecko-feet&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal was received in response to Nanoscale Science and Engineering initiative, NSF 05-610, category NIRT. The objective is to develop a fundamental and technological platform for using aligned carbon nanotube (CNT) "hairs" on flexible plastic to create strong elastic adhesives that are inspired by the gecko foot hairs. The research will focus on the synthesis and microfabrication of aligned CNT structures; surface modification of these aligned CNT to tailor adhesion and wetting; embed these CNT in flexible polymer matrices maintaining the microfabricated structure; and, develop a fundamental understanding of the surface/interfacial and mechanical properties of such hybrid material in controlling dry adhesive performance. Multi-scale modeling of such structures to evaluate the adhesive and mechanical properties will be done in synergy with the experiments to understand the adhesion of aligned carbon nanotube ends with various substrates. &lt;br/&gt;The knowledge acquired from mimicking the structure found on gecko foot will lead to not only a strong fundamental understanding of new scientific principles of tailoring adhesion and friction, but also developing new dry adhesives in the areas of microelectronics, robotics, and space applications. The knowledge acquired will benefit in developing thin film devices and smart materials for a broad range of applications in the field of coatings, smart textiles, and photonics. This technology will be transferred to the vibrant polymer industry involved in development of nanoscience and nanotechnology in Ohio. The education impact will be to create an environment where students (graduate, undergraduate, high school, and students from underrepresented groups) from multidisciplinary background work together on the development of a common platform. The research experience will be incorporated in interdisciplinary classes taught at Dayton (Nanotechnology), Akron (Polymer Technology), and RPI (Materials inspired by Biology).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1047655</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liming.dai@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/07/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1674</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1675</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>027E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>028E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>081E</Code>
      <Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>Nanomanufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
