<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Workshop on Software Development Environment for Science &amp; Engineering Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gabrielle D. Allen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Current software development practices and tools are inadequate for the computing power that is now becoming available. Applications that will run on today?s and tomorrow?s most powerful supercomputers will help improve our world in a variety of fields, including the study of severe storms, epidemic disease, earthquakes, and new product development. These applications must fully exploit hundreds of thousands of compute cores, hundreds of terabytes of memory, and tens of thousands of disk drives. In the future, such systems may well combine many different types of specialized computing elements. The workshop on ?Software Development Environment for Science &amp; Engineering Applications? will focus on the tools and practices needed to develop software for these incredibly complex supercomputers. It will also consider an integrated software development environment for science and engineering applications. Such an environment would allow researchers to build, edit, fix, and improve the performance of their software using more straightforward and graphically based tools than exist today.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop on ?Software Development Environment for Science &amp; Engineering Applications will focus on the set of software tools (editors, compilers, debuggers, optimization tools, etc.) needed to develop applications for petascale and beyond computers. It will also cover the numerical and communications libraries, programming languages, and software engineering practices needed by the scientists and engineers. The workshop will consider the feasibility of developing an integrated software development environment for science and engineering applications, similar in concept to the IDEs used in the commercial world. The workshop will help establish requirements for maximizing developer productivity. It will also address issues of application portability and maintenance in light of emerging architectural trends in high-performance computing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1048964</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Snir</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>snir@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gropp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wgropp@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alameda</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alameda@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunning</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thdjr@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8004</Code>
      <Text>Software Institutes</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
