<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF/DOE Thermoelectrics Partnership: Automotive Thermoelectric Modules with Scalable Thermo- and Electro-Mechanical Interfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1219001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruey-Hung Chen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1048796&lt;br/&gt;Goodson&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project involves researchers at Stanford University, The University of South Florida, and Robert Bosch LLC and addresses various topics relevant to vehicle waste heat recovery using thermoelectrics. These topics include novel interface materials and designs that can accommodate very large thermomechanical strains, high temperature thermoelectric materials that are efficient and can be reliably mated to heat sinks and electrodes, practical metrology for assessment of performance and durability, and systems-level integration of advanced materials and thermal management concepts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Fundamental investigations of interface materials, thermoelectric materials, and heat transfer relevant to thermoelectric harvesting of waste heat in vehicle applications will be conducted. A new tape design for implementing carbon nanotube films as thermal interface materials will be developed. This approach will reduce both electrical and thermal interface resistances, and enhance the durability of the interfaces as they undergo thermal cycling inherent in the application. Experiments will be designed to determine the microscale characteristics of interface (and adjoining) materials and how these characteristics evolve in response to thermal cycling. The knowledge acquired from the experiments will ultimately be used to design interfaces in a manner that will improve performance and increase durability. The influence of filling fraction, doping, grain size, and inclusion concentration in skutterudites will be quantified through experimentation and modeling, leading to improved thermoelectric materials. Fundamental and new metrology methods will be developed in partnership with the National Institute of Standards and Technology and, in conjunction with first principles modeling, will enable tuning of the relevant properties of both thermoelectric and interface materials. A combined fundamental and systems-level approach will be employed to integrate the knowledge pertaining to thermoelectric and interface material performance with advanced thermal management concepts such as but not limited to multiphase vapor cooling, to thermoelectric waste heat harvesting. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The project directly addresses fundamental issues associated with waste heat harvesting in vehicle applications. In addition, the research will be integrated with education and outreach including a new collegiate design competition specific to thermoelectric energy harvesting applications to promote teaching and learning and engage the broader community in energy technology activities. Research discoveries will be integrated in undergraduate and graduate classes at both Stanford and The University of South Florida. Additional activities include but are not limited to development of research experiences for both high school students and teachers, targeting high schools with large numbers of students from underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1048796</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goodson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>goodson@vk.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nolas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gnolas@chuma1.cas.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Boris</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kozinsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Boris.Kozinsky@us.bosch.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>J429</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>KX51</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>LX31</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>065E</Code>
      <Text>Radiation heat transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>099E</Code>
      <Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>104E</Code>
      <Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1761</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
