<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop Proposal: Student Research Workshop at AMTA-2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9954</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tatiana D. Korelsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NSF is providing partial financial support for a Student Research Workshop &lt;br/&gt;at the AMTA-2010 conference in Denver, Colorado. The Association for Machine &lt;br/&gt;Translation in the Americas (AMTA) is a non-profit professional organization &lt;br/&gt;in the area of Machine Translation (MT) in the US and the American continent. &lt;br/&gt;The main mission of AMTA is to facilitate and promote the exchange of &lt;br/&gt;knowledge and information between the communities of researchers, developers &lt;br/&gt;and users of Machine Translation and related translation technologies. In its &lt;br/&gt;effort to foster the professional growth of the next generation of MT &lt;br/&gt;researchers, AMTA-2010 is featuring a Student Research Workshop, embedded &lt;br/&gt;as an integral part of the research program at the conference. Students at &lt;br/&gt;all levels of study (undergraduate, graduate and post-graduate) are invited to &lt;br/&gt;submit papers describing their research work. NSF is providing funding to &lt;br/&gt;subsidize travel, conference and accommodation expenses for up to 10 students &lt;br/&gt;that have been selected to present their research work at the workshop. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The AMTA-2010 Student Research Workshop will greatly facilitate professional &lt;br/&gt;growth for the brightest young researchers in the field of MT, in the early &lt;br/&gt;stages of their professional career. The workshop will contribute to the &lt;br/&gt;professional development of a skilled and diverse workforce in the area of &lt;br/&gt;Machine Translation and computational processing of natural language. MT and &lt;br/&gt;other language processing applications are becoming vital technologies in the &lt;br/&gt;global information age. Strength in these areas is crucial to American &lt;br/&gt;competitiveness in the global economy of the 21st century.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1048559</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vogel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stephan.vogel@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
