<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Rates of Carbonate Formation in the Samail Ophiolite, Oman: Implications of Ultramafic Weathering for the Carbon Cycle</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29632</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030107</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sonia Esperanca</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In the last few years, considerable attention has been focused on carbon capture and storage to mitigate anthropogenic input of atmospheric CO2. One proposed option for mitigation is to increase conversion of CO2 gas to stable, solid carbonate minerals during chemical weathering of tectonically exposed mantle rock (or peridotite). While natural carbonation of peridotite is commonly observed, its rate, and therefore the rate of CO2 uptake via this weathering mechanism, is poorly known. Determining the natural rate of peridotite carbonation is critical for understanding the influence of this potentially important ?sink? in the global carbon cycle. The natural peridotite carbonation rate is also an essential, but poorly constrained, parameter in calculations evaluating the viability of using artificially-enhanced, in situ alteration of peridotite to mitigate the buildup of anthropogenic input to atmospheric CO2.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary objective of this research is to determine natural carbonation rates of exposed mantle peridotites. The Samail Ophiolite, Oman, is one of the largest and best-exposed ophiolites in the world, and hence is an ideal natural laboratory for investigating natural carbon storage in mantle peridotites. The research team has selected and carefully mapped eight sites that include roadcuts exposing carbonate veins, travertine deposits, and one site located on the natural peridotite weathering surface and containing abundant carbonate veins. The work plan consists of determining the ages of carbonates using two independent radiogenic dating techniques: 14C (for carbonates as old as ~50,000 years) and 238U-230Th (for carbonates as old as ~350,000 years). In addition, they will determine exposure ages for the host mantle peridotite to test the hypothesis that carbonate weathering primarily occurs in a thin weathering horizon that keeps pace with erosion rates. This project constitutes the Ph.D. thesis research for MIT/WHOI Joint Program student Evelyn Mervine. An improved understanding of natural carbonate formation in ultramafic rocks will aid efforts to develop CO2 capture and storage in ultramafic rocks to offset anthropogenic CO2 emissions and mitigate global climate change.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1049950</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth W.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sims</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksims7@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/23/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
      <CityName>Laramie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
      <StateCode>WY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
