<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Erosional Effects of Climate Change from Single-Clast Be-10</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Devin McPhillips is awarded the NSF Earth Sciences Postdoctoral Fellowship to implement a program of research and education at the University of Vermont. The project's goal is to evaluate how the style and rate of surface erosion responds to glacial-interglacial climate change. The particular focus is on landscapes that were never covered by glacial ice. Dr. McPhillips will compare concentrations of the cosmogenic radionuclide Be-10 from modern stream cobblestones to concentrations in nearby terrace deposits of glacial-stage cobblestones. First, bulk concentrations will be used in a conventional manner to understand the variability of erosion rates in high- and low-order streams. Second, the statistical distribution of individual cobble concentrations will be used to estimate the relative importance of 'deep' versus 'shallow' erosive processes, such as landslides and hillslope diffusion. The results will provide insight into the mechanisms of erosion, including potentially destructive mass movements. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Several students will be trained in geomorphology in the course of the project. Dr. McPhillips will co-advise at least one undergraduate student and act as mentor for graduate students at the University of Vermont. The undergraduate(s) will participate in field work and develop a complementary senior thesis project. The senior thesis will provide the student(s) with a strong foundation in research and further the professional development of Dr. McPhillips as teacher as well as a scientist.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1049300</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Devin</FirstName>
      <LastName>McPhillips</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>McPhillips Devin</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208109</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber></PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress></StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
