<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Drosophila Ultraconserved Elements: Function and Evolution</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>295849</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: Comparative genomics, as a field, aims to identify functional regions in the genomes of plants and animals by comparing entire genomic DNA sequences. These bioinformatic comparisons have revealed regions of genomes that are highly conserved over long evolutionary times, yet little is known regarding their function. Most of these highly conserved DNA sequences occur in non-protein coding regions of genomes. This project aims to elucidate the function and evolution of the most slowly evolving portions of the Drosophila (fruit fly) genome. Because they are so highly conserved, it is anticipated these regions of the Drosophila genome have important functions. Fruit flies will be studied because they can be experimentally manipulated using sophisticated genetic and molecular methods. This project is a collaborative effort led by computational biologist Andrew Kern, responsible for the bioinformatic aspects of the research, and by developmental biologist Daniel Barbash, responsible for the experimental studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The PI will collaborate with Nancy Serrell, the Director of Dartmouth College?s Office of Outreach, to identify interested high school science teachers in the local area and coordinate organization of on-site hands-on workshops for high school students. The project will use a ?cascade? approach to bring computational biological methods into the high school classroom, whereby Dr. Kern will collaborate with local high school teachers to develop lesson plans that will be tested and refined by Dr. Kern and the high school teacher partners,and implemented in classrooms with assistance from graduate and undergraduate students in the Kern Lab. Lesson plans will provide students with significant hands-on application comparing genomes using bioinformatic programs and web-based analysis tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1050980</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barbash</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dab87@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
