<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: North/East Under/graduate Research Organization for Neuroscience (NEURON-2010-2011 Program), to be held at CUNY Hunter, New York, NY, April 2011.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 20th NorthEast Under/graduate Research Organization for Neuroscience (NEURON) conference will be held on April 10th, 2011 at The City University of New York (CUNY) Hunter College. The goal of this meeting is to encourage professional development in Neuroscience. The approach is to provide an ideal learning and outreach environment while enhancing accessibility to all young scientists making their first impressions in an academic setting. Congruent with previous meetings, a high participation of underrepresented groups in neuroscience is anticipated, attracted by the exemplary keynote speaker and high quality workshops/symposia. The keynote speaker will be Dr. Dolores Malaspina, who is a Steckler Professor of Psychiatry at NYU Behavioral Health Programs. She will give the keynote address on "Sex differences: From germ cells to brain cells". Additionally, four professional development workshops/ symposiums will be offered. Students will be offered advice in a session entitled, "Getting into graduate or medical school" led by Daniel Dacosta. There will be a symposium on "Animal models of neurodevelopmental disorders" led by Anthony Santarelli. Dr. Angela Seliga will host the "Brain Primer" docent program. Ruth Russell will use her extensive background in outreach to host "Outreach: Public awareness in neuroscience" while demonstrating its practice with the interactive exhibit "Brain: The Inside Story" at the Museum of Natural History. These experiences will provide neuroscientists in training with exposure to new research, networking, and tools to improve their professional development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1052327</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cheryl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Frye</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cafrye@albany.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
      <CityName>Albany</CityName>
      <ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5184374550</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
