<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CDI-Type I: Collaborative Research: Development of computational algorithms and analysis tools for molecular-level understanding of complex atmospheric nucleation processes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>116123</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Evelyn M. Goldfield</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Newly formed atmospheric aerosol particles exert a considerable impact on global climate by affecting the Earth's radiation balance. Nucleation plays a pivotal role in the formation of these particles. Understanding how particles nucleate in a multi-component gas mixture has important implications not only for climate and weather but also wide-ranging technological applications including gas separations, pollution control, and nanotechnology. Atmospheric nucleation involves multi-scale processes ranging from proton transfer to molecular condensation and evaporation events and culminating in the rare formation of the critical nucleus. The goals of this project are (i) to develop computational algorithms and analysis tools for efficient investigations of multi-component gas-to-particle nucleation processes, (ii) to elucidate atmospherically relevant nucleation processes and to validate the rate predictions through strategically selected laboratory experiments measuring cluster size and mass distributions at the sub-3 nm scale, and (iii) to deploy a freely-available cyber-tool that transforms data to knowledge by enabling large-scale modelers and experimental researchers to harvest predicted atmospheric nucleation rates and learn about mechanisms, by providing a general framework to visualize and analyze the abundance of digital data generated by particle-based simulations for any type of gas-to-particles nucleation process, and by being an aid for teaching about nucleation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project impacts our understanding of atmospheric nucleation pathways and sheds light on how quantitative modeling of the nucleation kinetics affects global climate models and impacts the ability to influence atmospheric nucleation. Driven by the partnership of researchers from different fields, diverse academic institutions, and international collaborators, the education, training, and mentoring of undergraduate and graduate students is advanced in a unique way that broadens participation. Knowledge gained from this project infuses the excitement of discovery in courses and laboratories taught by the team members. Outreach activities to junior high schools and science museums allow a broader community to learn about atmospheric nucleation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a Cyber-Enabled Discovery and Innovation Program award and is co-funded by the Division of Chemistry, the Division of Civil, Mechanical &amp; Manufacturing Innovation, the Office of International Science &amp; Engineering, and the Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1052015</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>binchen@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7750</Code>
      <Text>CDI TYPE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1303</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE MODELING &amp; PREDICTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5935</Code>
      <Text>FINLAND</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5939</Code>
      <Text>US/USSR ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7721</Code>
      <Text>FROM DATA TO KNOWLEDGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7752</Code>
      <Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
