<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Scalable quantum photonic devices based on vertical quantum dots and photonic crystals</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>428587</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective: The objective of this program is to address the problem of scalability of semiconductor quantum photonic devices currently limited by the inherently random nucleation process of self-assembled quantum dots. The approach is to design, fabricate, and characterize a novel type of vertical quantum dot, which can be precisely positioned in large quantity by top-down fabrication techniques with respect to photonic crystal resonator modes. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Quantum information science is a fast growing and highly interdisciplinary field with the potential to cause revolutionary advances in science and engineering. Spatial arrangement of several quantum dots with respect to a cavity mode is still an open issue and formation of quantum networks seems quite challenging. The proposed approach offers a pathway to overcome these challenges and demonstrate scalability. If successful, this work will also lead to the demonstration of multi-photon entanglement on a chip and opens up fascinating possibilities to investigate advanced quantum optical effects such as photon blockade in cleaner systems and under very controlled conditions.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The proposed work is transformative in nature since the anticipated scalable quantum photonic devices enable novel applications in on-chip quantum information processing, quantum communication, quantum lithography, and national security. The educational activities integrate research in nanotechnology in form of a Nanophysics Summer School for undergraduates, as well as high-school and community college teachers. Underrepresented groups will be motivated and encouraged to participate via the Stevens Technical Enrichment Program and the research will be disseminated to K-12 students within the NSF GK-12 program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1053537</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strauf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>strauf@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stevens Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>HOBOKEN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2012168762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CASTLE POINT ON HUDSON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>091E</Code>
      <Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>094E</Code>
      <Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
