<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Taming Uncertainties in Reliable, Real-Time Messaging for Wireless Networked Sensing and Control</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>494999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Message passing in wireless networked sensing and control systems must be reliable and in real-time. Such design challenges require new models and distributed protocols for messaging that can handle interference locally and accurately, given the basic problem of computing probabilistic path delays is NP-hard. Focusing on single-hop transmission scheduling and multi-hop spatio-temporal data flow control, this project makes novel contributions by proposing two major research tasks: 1) investigation of control-theoretic approaches to online model instantiation, based on the physical-ratio-K (PRK) interference model, and addressing the challenges of large interference range as well as anisotropic, asymmetric wireless communication; 2) developing a lightweight approach to computing probabilistic path delays followed by a multi-timescale adaptation framework for real-time messaging. In particular, the PRK interference model integrates protocol model's locality with physical model's high-fidelity, thus bridging the gap between the suitability for distributed implementation and the enabled scheduling performance. By controlling network operations at the same timescale as the corresponding dynamics, the proposed multi-timescale adaptation framework ensures long-term optimality while simultaneously addressing short-term dynamics. Additionally, this project includes an integrated, multi-level, multi-component education plan. The education activities will raise public awareness, improve student retention and participation of underrepresented groups in computing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1054634</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hongwei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hongwei@wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wayne State University</Name>
      <CityName>Detroit</CityName>
      <ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5057 Woodward</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
