<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Discoveries in compressible turbulence and turbulent mixing through Petascale simulations and analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>421240</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sushil Prasad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Compressible turbulent flows, characterized by a wide range of spatial and temporal scales,&lt;br/&gt;occur in many natural (supernovae explosions, volcanic eruptions, solar wind) and engineering&lt;br/&gt;systems (commercial and supersonic flight and propulsion, reacting flows). Due to their complexity,&lt;br/&gt;though, our fundamental understanding remains very limited, especially at high Reynolds numbers,&lt;br/&gt;restricting our ability to predict natural phenomena and design better engineering devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research advances the knowledge of compressible turbulence only possible through massive&lt;br/&gt;simulations enabled by Cyberinfrastructure pushing, in turn, the frontiers of computational fluid&lt;br/&gt;dynamics. The simulations, unprecedented in size and detail, require novel software that efficiently&lt;br/&gt;uses hundreds of thousands of processors at Petascale levels and set the path for simulations at even&lt;br/&gt;larger scales. The emphasis is in extreme parallelism exploring advanced features likely to exist&lt;br/&gt;in future architectures including communication libraries, programming models and accelerators.&lt;br/&gt;The tremendous details unveiled by the simulations provide a unique opportunity for investigators&lt;br/&gt;to understand long-standing issues such as small-scale universality, inertial-range scaling, intermittency and largely unexplored areas such as mixing and dispersion of contaminants. Results are&lt;br/&gt;made available through a portal which allows the community to obtain flow fields, statistics and&lt;br/&gt;codes, and analyze massive datasets remotely.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research and education are integrated at the interface between high-performance computing&lt;br/&gt;(HPC) and fluid mechanics. The educational goal is to (i) inspire students, including those from&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented groups, to pursue careers in HPC and fluid mechanics, and (ii) educate future&lt;br/&gt;scientists and engineers capable of deploying Petascale solutions to important societal and technological problems. Educational and research activities are integrated through curricular innovation,&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate research and the portal which is also used to disseminate results to a broader audience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1054966</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diego</FirstName>
      <LastName>Donzis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>donzis@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>057E</Code>
      <Text>Thermodynamics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>060E</Code>
      <Text>BIO-TRANSPORT &amp; FLUID MECH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
