<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Development of a Robotic Prosthetic Hand with Programmable Passive Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>93066</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Voyles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A prosthetic robot hand is designed and developed with programmable passive dynamics modeled after human hands. The goals include the development of mathematical models of variable passive dynamics in human hands, the study of the role of passive dynamics in hand operations, the design of novel joint mechanisms, development of a hand prototype and an EMG control interface, and the development of pedagogical laboratory modules for education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project develops technology to substantially improve rehabilitation and quality of life for persons with hand disabilities, including amputees returning from ongoing wars. This work addresses the acute need for substantial improvement in the functionality and control mechanisms for prosthetic hands. Most current prosthetic hands do not address the underlying design constraints of a useful prosthetic hand, namely, weight and size limitations, limited control, ease of control and suitable aesthetics. In addition, students learn this new subject and contribute to the advance of science and technology in this domain. Finally, programs are in place to recruit women, individuals with disabilities, and Native American students in engineering research and education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1054354</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ashish</FirstName>
      <LastName>Deshpande</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ashish@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maine</Name>
      <CityName>ORONO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5717 Corbett Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maine</StateName>
      <StateCode>ME</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
