<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Synthesis, Microstructure, and Properties of Novel Magnesium-based Nanoporous Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>455296</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diana Farkas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY: This CAREER project aims to acquire fundamental and comprehensive understanding of the relationships among processing, microstructure and properties of magnesium-based nanoporous materials. The specific technical objectives of the research are to synthesize magnesium-based nanoporous materials, characterize their microstructural features using the state-of-the-art tools, experimentally investigate their properties and mechanical behavior and evaluate these behaviors in the light of current theoretical understanding. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY: The success of this research will allow full advantage to be taken of nanoporous magnesium for a variety of applications that utilize combinations of mechanical properties, ultralight weight, excellent energy absorption capability, and multifunctionality that accompany the introduction of nanopores into non-porous metals. The research will also advance the underlying understanding of the processing-structure-property relationships in other nanoporous metallic materials. This project will integrate research and education/outreach activities to train undergraduate and graduate students for the workforce, and stimulate the interest and participation of high school students and underrepresented student groups (Hispanic and Women) in science and engineering. The results will be disseminated to other researchers and the general public through a variety of channels such as international journals, technical conferences and the internet. These activities are expected to increase the general public awareness of advanced nanostructured metallic materials and their scientific importance, and to enhance the broader public interest in science, engineering, and the pursuit of technology-oriented careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1055073</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qizhen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qizhen.li@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1771</Code>
      <Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
