<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Soft Matter Self-Assembly: Protein Crystallization and Colloidal Microphase Formation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daryl W. Hess</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award is funded through the Division of Materials Research and the Division of Chemistry. It supports theoretical and computational research and education on soft matter self-assembly. Soft materials are substances whose physical states are easily deformed by thermal-scale energies, and include, among others, liquids, colloids, gels, and a number of biological materials. Though soft matter ordering is a promising approach to assembling complex and interesting materials on the micron and sub-micron scale, a microscopic understanding of even some of the simplest processes involved remains elusive. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will investigate the equilibrium and non-equilibrium behavior of some key contributing microscopic factors to assembly in two families of soft matter systems: proteins and colloidal microphase-formers. This program aims to advance purposeful design strategies for controlling assembly morphology and function.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) Project on proteins: The PI will research the microscopic contributions to pair protein interactions that control nucleation, in order to suggest novel rational mutagenesis approaches and experimental conditions that facilitate protein crystallization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2) Project on colloidal microphase-formers: The PI will research the equilibrium and non-equilibrium assembly of microphase patterns in systems of spherical and rod-like particles, in order to understand and control the range of possible morphologies in colloidal assembly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational component supports efforts along two main thrusts:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) Promoting multidisciplinary learning at the interface of physics, chemistry, and materials science by developing a focus section on soft matter for the general chemistry curriculum, and a materials science concentration for chemistry majors; and&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2) Broadening the participation of underrepresented groups in the theoretical sciences by developing an outreach program for high school students in the Durham, NC, community that builds on Duke University's Center for Theoretical and Mathematical Sciences and the Duke-Durham Neighborhood Partnership Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award is funded through the Division of Materials Research and the Division of Chemistry. It supports theoretical and computational research and education on soft matter. Examples of soft materials can often be found or transformed in a kitchen. Foams, gels, grains, and many biological materials are common examples. Under controlled conditions, soft matter can also form complex and useful structures that have features smaller than a micron, a millionth of a meter. In order to take advantage of these processes for designing new materials and functionalities, a detailed understanding of their assembly at the microscopic level is necessary. The PI will investigate design strategies for controlling the assembly shape, dynamics, and function in two families of soft matter system: proteins and pattern-forming particles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational component supports efforts along two main thrusts:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) Promoting multidisciplinary learning at the interface of physics, chemistry, and materials science by developing a focus section on soft matter for the general chemistry curriculum, and a materials science concentration for chemistry majors; and&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2) Broadening the participation of underrepresented groups in the theoretical sciences by developing an outreach program for high school students in the Durham, NC, community that builds on Duke University's Center for Theoretical and Mathematical Sciences and the Duke-Durham Neighborhood Partnership Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1055586</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Charbonneau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>patrick.charbonneau@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1765</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6881</Code>
      <Text>Theory, Models, Comput. Method</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7569</Code>
      <Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
