<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Multidimensional Selective Excitation in NMR</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kelsey D. Cook</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This CAREER award from the Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program supports work by Professor Jamie Walls at the University of Miami (UM) to develop a new class of techniques utilizing nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), the fundamental spectroscopy behind magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). In conventional NMR, multiple measurements are needed in order to acquire full chemical information, often requiring very long experimental acquisition times. Dr. Walls is developing an alternative "multidimensional" approach that generates signal in a single experiment. The method is based upon correlations between spin transitions rather than individual spin transition frequencies, and may help speed up structural and dynamical NMR studies of biomolecular and other systems, and reduce MRI imaging times. It may also prove applicable to other spectroscopies and disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the course of training undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral researchers, Dr. Walls is developing a new imaging and spectroscopy lab that uses NMR to illustrate the importance of numerical simulations in experimental science. Working with his undergraduate and graduate students, Dr. Walls is also developing a weekly science radio program, La Semana en Ciencia (The Week in Science), that will be produced in both English and Spanish at the UM School of Communication's radio studio. The program will highlight the excitement and importance of new scientific discoveries, with aims of enhancing science literacy and inspiring students to consider careers in science. La Semana en Ciencia will make cutting edge science more accessible to Hispanic students, who are traditionally underrepresented in scientific disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1056846</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walls</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwalls@miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami</Name>
      <CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1108</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7203</Code>
      <Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
