<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Synthesis, Characterization and Physical Properties of Pr-Based Heavy Fermions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>484309</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In recent years, studies on quantum phase transitions (QPTs) in Ce-based heavy fermion compounds have transformed our understanding of magnetism and superconductivity. This CAREER project, supported by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry Program, will expand our repertoire of heavy fermion materials beyond Ce-based compounds and towards Pr-based materials. Exploratory synthesis, structural characterization, and magnetic property measurements will be used to determine structure-property relationships that impact crystal-field splitting of the localized Pr3+ ion 4f2-electronic configuration. Efforts will placed on synthesis of single-crystals, which will increase the availability of single crystals in the United States and enable unambiguous determination of crystal structure and physical behavior. Collaborative work in inelastic neutron scattering studies will be conducted to determine structural effects on crystal field splitting as a function of chemical composition, pressure or magnetic field. Investigations of PrAu2-xCuxSi2 and PrAu2Si2-x Gex and the Heusler compounds, PrInT2-xT?x (T, T'= Cu, Ag, Au), will be the foundation for a long-term research program of exploratory synthesis and characterization of PrxTyMz (T = transition metal and M = main-group metal).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is integrated into education and outreach activities involving undergraduate students, postdoctoral scholars, and high school teachers. Undergraduate research experiences will be enhanced by materials chemistry seminars and research opportunities at national laboratories. Postdoctoral researchers will receive comprehensive training by participating in both solid-state chemistry research and undergraduate education. High school teachers will gain hands-on research and teaching experience in solid-state chemistry during summer research opportunities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Investigations on quantum phase transitions have transformed our understanding of magnetism and superconductivity. This project will expand the current repertoire of quantum phase transition materials towards Praesodynium-based compounds, thereby enhancing our ability to design magnetic and superconducting materials in the future. Emphasis is placed on exploratory synthesis, structural characterization, and physical property measurement of single-crystals of Praesodynium-intermetallic compounds. Crystallography experiments at neutron and synchrotron facilities will be correlated with magnetic, thermodynamic and electrical property measurements. Growth of single crystals will address the deficit of single crystals available for research in the United States. In addition, collaborations between academia and national laboratories will expand single-crystal growth capabilities to University of Northern Colorado, yield more productive synthesis efforts, and engage students and postdoctoral researchers in national laboratory environments. High school teachers will gain hands-on research and teaching experience in solid-state chemistry during summer research opportunities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1056515</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Macaluso</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robin.macaluso@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Northern Colorado</Name>
      <CityName>Greeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>806396900</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9703511932</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1762</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7731</Code>
      <Text>OTHER GLOBAL LEARNING &amp; TRNING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1762</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7969</Code>
      <Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CL10</Code>
      <Text>Career-Life Balance Supports</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
