<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Intrinsically-Compensated Ultra-High-Q Silicon Resonators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>INTRINSICALLY-COMPENSATED ULTRA-HIGH-Q SILICON RESONATORS&lt;br/&gt;PROJECT SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;As MEMS technology evolves, it finds its way in an ever growing number and range of commercial&lt;br/&gt;applications. In particular, silicon micromechanical resonators have the potential to replace conventional&lt;br/&gt;electronic and mechanical devices in a variety of timing, sensing and spectral processing applications,&lt;br/&gt;thus enabling the development of completely new products. There are, however, a number of areas where&lt;br/&gt;the performance of such resonators lags significantly behind that of currently existing discrete&lt;br/&gt;alternatives. These areas include the sensitivity of the resonant frequency to process fluctuations, its&lt;br/&gt;stability with respect to changes in temperature, and the fact that the quality factor and impedance of&lt;br/&gt;current silicon resonators degrades dramatically in the high UHF range (1 GHz and above). The goal of&lt;br/&gt;the proposed research is to develop and demonstrate radically new technologies that will bring the&lt;br/&gt;performance of silicon MEMS resonators to a level suitable for widespread insertion into commercial&lt;br/&gt;applications. Specifically, the proposed research will advance the state of silicon MEMS resonator&lt;br/&gt;technology in the following areas (intellectual merits of the proposed research):&lt;br/&gt;(a) Deeper understanding of intrinsic loss mechanisms in silicon, and consequent development of ultrahigh-&lt;br/&gt;Q silicon resonators that are completely compatible with standard IC fabrication processes, and (b)&lt;br/&gt;development of zero-power temperature compensation techniques based on the engineering of material&lt;br/&gt;properties and resonator geometries that avoid degradation of the Q of the resonator.&lt;br/&gt;Dissemination of the scientific results will take place in the form of presentations at national and&lt;br/&gt;international professional conferences, articles in technical journals, and university seminars. Technology&lt;br/&gt;transfer to the commercial sector will be facilitated by the Georgia Electronic Design Center, whose goal&lt;br/&gt;is to sustain the technology growth of the semiconductor industry by placing an emphasis on significant&lt;br/&gt;long-term research.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact of the proposed research&lt;br/&gt;This effort will promote advanced research and education in the area of micro and nano-mechanical&lt;br/&gt;signal processing. Integration of research and education will be pursued through graduate and&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate courses developed by the PI. These courses cover the principles of micro- and nanoelectromechanical&lt;br/&gt;system analysis and design, with an emphasis on MEMS resonators. The course&lt;br/&gt;material is constantly updated, and will include the results of research activities that are undertaken during&lt;br/&gt;the course of the research project described in this proposal. The existing graduate level course on&lt;br/&gt;?Interface IC design for MEMS and Sensors? will be augmented by hands-on laboratory sessions.&lt;br/&gt;Involvement of undergraduate students in research and educational activities is another important task of&lt;br/&gt;this proposal. To this end, the PI will seek applicants among the participants in the Summer&lt;br/&gt;Undergraduate Research in Engineering/Science Program at Georgia Tech, a ten-week summer research&lt;br/&gt;program designed to attract qualified minority students into graduate school in the fields of engineering&lt;br/&gt;and science. The program has received highly favorable evaluations from past participants. It is hoped&lt;br/&gt;that this unique experience will encourage these students to become applicants for graduate school in&lt;br/&gt;ensuing years.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1057320</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Giorgio</FirstName>
      <LastName>Casinovi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>giorgio.casinovi@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Farrokh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ayazi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>farrokh.ayazi@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
