<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Further Discovery and Elaboration of Metallacrowns</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>513000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program supports Professor Vincent L. Pecoraro at the University of Michigan-Ann Arbor whose research emphasizes the development of metallacrowns, metal-based molecular recognition agents that may eventually be used in applications of practical importance. Two key objectives guide the metallacrown research. The first is to understand molecular recognition of these hosts with a variety of guests in the solid state and in solution. Professor Pecoraro hopes to exploit the environment within chiral metallacrown cavities to carry out catalytic chemical transformations. The second objective seeks to exploit the solid state properties of metallacrowns to make chiral, soft non-linear optical materials, porous solids, and molecular magnets. The proposed molecular magnets, if successful, would revolutionize data storage and provide greater fundamental insight on magnetic phenomena.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation, Professor Pecoraro explores the utility of metallocrowns as molecular recognition agents, catalysts, optical materials and molecular magnets. This work specifically targets the use of these materials as catalysts as well for the design of optically transparent chiral compartments for guests that display second harmonic generation for nonlinear optical materials applications. Professor Pecoraro will continue an excellent track record for producing scientists at all levels and for mentoring women and minorities in both his laboratory and the department. The PI is the Director of the Michigan Chemistry Biology Interface Training Program, which mentors second and third year graduate students and has had about 17% minority participation and 50% female trainees. The intent of this training program is to cross train students in chemistry and biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1057331</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vincent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pecoraro</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vlpec@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
