<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Learning Shape Representation in Somatosensory Cortex and Their Applications to Upper Limb Prosthetics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>196000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Abstract: 1057644&lt;br/&gt;The human hand, wrist and arm make up one of the most complex portions of the human body. Using our arms and hands, humans are able to perform extremely complex functions, ranging from the delicate and dexterous tasks involved in artistic design, through dynamic ones involved in playing musical instruments, to forceful ones involved in sports and labor. Scientific studies demonstrate that, even without seeing our hands, a person can effortlessly recognize hundreds of objects with his hands. Unfortunately, none of the arm and hand prosthetics that have been developed to-date are remotely capable of providing touch sensation that approaches that of the natural limbs. Yet, it is known that the touch sensation is indispensable for humans to effectively manipulate and explore objects. So it is a challenge is to assimilate amputees into society and provide them the tools to contribute to the workforce unless they are provided prosthetics limbs that move by thought, as well as feel what the prosthetic hand touches. This EAGER proposal specifically aims to improve our scientific knowledge of how touch is represented and learned by the brain, develop electronic systems that can be implanted to communicate touch directly to the brain, and to test the effectiveness of providing the sensation of touch to a monkey by circumventing its arm and communicating directly to the brain. If successful, this high-risk/high-pay-off project could make Luke Skywalker's replacement arm in Star Wars: The Empire Strikes Back a reality.&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop new transdisciplinary knowledge involving neuroscience and engineering. The goal is to record and stimulate directly from the parts of the brain where the sense of touch is normally represented. Current research shows that normal perception of touch is provided by the activity of large groups of brain cells (i.e. neurons). The Investigators will study the possibility of using electrical stimulation to restore the sense of touch to amputees in the same way that cochlear implants restore hearing to the deaf or visual implants the sense of vision to the blind. They plan to exploit the natural representations of the brain and to stimulate, using new electronic circuitry, large groups of neurons that represent movement and from in the animals brain. Ultimately this research will lead to an understanding of how to recreate the feel of objects. &lt;br/&gt;Throughout this work, the investigators will train students to have unique neuroscience, biomedical, and engineering skills, a combination of which is invaluable to the modern high-tech health related workforce. They plan to train both undergraduate and graduate students and expose K-12 students who regularly rotate through their laboratories to the research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1057644</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ralph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Etienne-Cummings</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>retienne@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hsiao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>steven.hsiao@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
