<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Uncrowding, rehousing, and electronic migration of the mammal collection at the Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>504417</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An award was made to the Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science (DMNS) to: 1) purchase replacement cabinets to uncrowd and rehouse approximately 80% of the mammal collection; 2) support a full-time collections technician to assist with inventory, uncrowding, and rehousing of specimens, data validation, and database work; 3) migrate mammal collection records to the web-accessible, multi-institutional database, Arctos; and 4) continue to build on the exceptional record of delivering science and collections to the general public in a multitude of different ways. The mammal collection contains approximately 14,000 specimens that record 140 years of biodiversity and change in the Rocky Mountain and Great Plains region and beyond. Since 2006, the collection has experienced the greatest period of growth in the museum's 110-year history, including establishment of new frozen tissue and parasite subcollections. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a strong suite of broader impacts associated with this project capitalizing on DMNS's role as the largest public natural history museum in the region. Due to the greater web visibility afforded by the database Arctos, the value of the mammal collection to the scientific community and public will increase along with the novel questions and methods being applied to museum collections from the fields of biogeography, biosystematics, community ecology, morphology, and biological informatics. The team will continue to build on an exceptional record of providing public access to view and learn about DMNS collections. The mammal collection will continue to be leveraged to enhance DMNS exhibits, visitor programming, and various educational programs. The team will utilize the Museum's large volunteer program, which unites the public with collections and science, to assist with project-related tasks. The mammal collection and its importance will be highlighted in a series of Scientists-in-Action satellite broadcasts that connect a curator with grades 4-12 students from the field or collections. Additionally, underrepresented high school students interested in careers in science will work in the mammal collection on research projects through the Museum's successful Teen Science Scholars Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1057336</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Demboski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.demboski@dmns.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeff</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stephenson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jeff.Stephenson@dmns.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Denver Museum of Nature and Science</Name>
      <CityName>Denver</CityName>
      <ZipCode>802055732</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3033708304</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2001 Colorado Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
