<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Collected Papers of Albert Einstein</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Introduction&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Einstein Papers Project began publishing The Collected Papers of Albert Einstein in 1987. It has published 12 volumes to date; each volume is a scholarly, annotated, print and electronic edition of the writings and correspondence of Albert Einstein (1879-1955). The project aims to provide complete and widely available access to a massive written legacy that authoritatively documents the most important developments in 20th century science and technology in the context of profound social and political transformations. This award would support work to collect, digitize, research, edit, translate, and eventually publish several additional volumes of Einstein's work and letters from the period 1923 to 1933, and to expand and improve the free electronic, searchable availability of Einstein-related original documents and scholarly material&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award would make possible the publication of more than 100 scientific and non-scientific articles, lectures, notebooks, diaries, interviews and speeches by Einstein during the ten year period indicated above. Some 1200 letters by and to him are to be published as full text together with the detailed explanations, annotations, and other apparatus. The additional elements will serve to provide proper context to and understanding of his work on major topics in physics during this period, such as far-reaching developments and controversies in quantum mechanics regarding the nature of matter and energy. Needless to say, this is a critical period in Einstein's career. At this juncture, he fully emerges as the preeminent scientist of the era, as a world figure engaged in international reconciliation among former enemy nations, and an admired humanitarian in the context of interactions around the globe with leading scientific and political figures, fellow physicists, astronomers, mathematicians, and engineers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Potential Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Einstein Papers Project aims not only to uncover unknown or unpublished documents related to Einstein's life and work, it also aims to explain and contextualize in great detail (on the basis of extremely rich and untapped sources and the most up-to-date scholarly literature and methods) the development of scientific and technological practice, innovation, and dissemination. The Collected Papers is the product of interdisciplinary team-work, employing the expertise of a multi-lingual group of researchers in science, history, philosophy, linguistic and mathematical techniques. Its broader aims include providing a deeper understanding of modern scientific communities, the sources and practices of scientific and humanist teaching, publication, communication, and collaboration. The Project supports and enhances teaching and training of undergraduate, doctoral, and post-doctoral students, and relies upon international collaboration among various institutions, scholars and scientists. The free electronic version of the Collected Papers is a widely available and valuable resource for the study of the modern era. It has and will continue to serve generations of scholars, scientists, engineers, writers, journalists, science policy makers, educators, students, and artists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058125</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kormos-Buchwald</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>diana_buchwald@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
