<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Dynamic Broadband Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599799</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will demonstrate&lt;br/&gt;the ability of an adaptive antenna system ? a radio with an antenna that changes its&lt;br/&gt;radiation pattern to provide coverage where it is needed ? to automatically optimize&lt;br/&gt;coverage. Harsh RF environments, for example those with shifting reflective surfaces&lt;br/&gt;such as shipping container yards, make it hard to set up reliable communication even&lt;br/&gt;when there is only one radio. When several radios must work together to provide&lt;br/&gt;coverage in an extended area, it is extremely difficult and time-consuming to manually&lt;br/&gt;tailor the radiation pattern of each antenna so that every portion of the area receives&lt;br/&gt;adequate signal and the radios do not interfere with each other. Through a combination of&lt;br/&gt;innovative pattern computation algorithms and active sensor feedback, the system&lt;br/&gt;resulting from this project will automatically tailor coverage to meet these goals. The&lt;br/&gt;system will not just be able to set up the initial coverage of an area, it will also&lt;br/&gt;continually monitor the quality of the coverage and automatically adjust to changes in the&lt;br/&gt;system or the environment that may affect the quality of that coverage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is decreased deployment&lt;br/&gt;costs and substantially increased reliability. In the short run, the system will be built with&lt;br/&gt;a WiFi platform for use in the maritime ports market as a more reliable communication&lt;br/&gt;system to run their mission critical scheduling application. The deployment savings result&lt;br/&gt;from not only a quicker and more reliable initial setup but also from automated&lt;br/&gt;adjustments to coverage as environmental factors change ? including such radical&lt;br/&gt;changes as the failure of one radio. Because the system is agnostic to the frequency and&lt;br/&gt;the protocol used by the radio, it is not limited to WiFi deployments. The project will&lt;br/&gt;demonstrate this by creating and operating a prototype WiMAX version of the adaptive&lt;br/&gt;antenna system. In the long term, this adaptive antenna technology offers significant&lt;br/&gt;benefits to any large scale radio deployment. For example, as providers roll out the next&lt;br/&gt;generation of cellular, cell sizes will shrink significantly which will substantially increase&lt;br/&gt;the deployment cost. An adaptive antenna system offers not only the promise of reducing&lt;br/&gt;these costs but also adding increased connection reliability to these next generation&lt;br/&gt;systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058597</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weaver</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robert.weaver@fidelity-comtech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>FIDELITY COMTECH INC</Name>
      <CityName>LONGMONT</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805037600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3036788876</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2400 TRADE CENTER AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
