<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: RAPID: Taxonomic and metagenetic analysis of species distributions for marine meiofauna from the Gulf of Mexico</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>38784</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles Lydeard</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Oceanic sediments harbor most of the world's biodiversity, primarily comprised of minute organisms that perform key ecological functions such as nutrient cycling, critical to the biodegradation of hydrocarbons. Unfortunately, knowledge of these communities of organisms in the Gulf of Mexico is sparse, thus precluding informed mitigation and remediation of the BP Deepwater Horizon oil spill. Knowledge-based action requires that three key questions be addressed: 1) How unique are the sediment communities in the Gulf? 2) How structured are the sediment communities within the Gulf? and 3) What has been the effect of anthropogenic disturbance on these communities? Cutting-edge, high-throughput DNA sequencing technologies will be employed, together with traditional taxonomic methods to assay the diversity of virtually all complex organisms from sediment samples collected prior to the April 2010 spill, representing diverse habitats across the Gulf of Mexico. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BP Deepwater Horizon oil spill represents a dramatic anthropogenic event of historic proportions. It will both require and inspire the interest of future biologists for decades. This funding will specifically provide new opportunities for student engagement in the long-term characterization of biodiversity, using new tools to understand the response of organisms to environmental change and the consequences, mitigation and remediation of such an environmental disturbance. Training will include support for undergraduate students to attend a workshop in Gulf of Mexico biodiversity assessment as well as graduate and postdoctoral training. In all cases participation by underrepresented groups in science will be actively encouraged. Most importantly, all data collected will be made openly accessible to the public and scientific communities to facilitate ongoing research and maximize the engagement of all stakeholders.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058489</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Halanych</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ken@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Auburn University</Name>
      <CityName>Auburn University</CityName>
      <ZipCode>368490001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 Samford Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7978</Code>
      <Text>Global Systems Science</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1198</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY SURVEYS &amp; INVENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5987</Code>
      <Text>GULF OF MEXICO OIL SPILL-2010</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
