<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High-Resolution Secondary Ion Mass Spectrometry for Chemically Imaging Cell Membrane Organization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program, Prof. Mary Kraft and her group at the University of Illinois are developing a new approach to chemical imaging of organized structures like membranes using high-resolution secondary ion mass spectrometry. The work entails development and optimization of functionalized protein-specific affinity labels, metabolic labeling strategies, cell preservation protocols, and statistical methods to evaluate component co-localization. The method will significantly impact our understanding of how plasma membrane organization affects cellular function, and the molecular interactions that produce this organization. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide interdisciplinary training of graduate students. Other educational activities focus on promoting the professional development of K-12 math and science teachers and educating middle and high school students about the chemical interactions that drive biological membrane organization. Results will be incorporated into laboratory activities and supplemental teaching materials for middle and high school students that will be provided to teachers through the Nano-CEMMS Center at the University of Illinois.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058809</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kraft</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mlkraft@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1982</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
