<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research - Symmetry in the Foundations of Quantum Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6864</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Introduction&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is for a doctoral dissertation research improvement grant. The Co-PI, the doctoral candidate, is working under the supervision of his mentor, the PI, on a project whose central aim is to generalize a foundational account of time reversibility in physics. The PI has requested support for the Co-PI to engage in intensive training with two researchers at the University of California at Irvine who specialize in the topic of his dissertation. The requested funds will be used to support a five week research stay in Southern California, from February 1 - March 6, 2011.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The requested funds will provide the Co-PI with an important opportunity to work face to face with top researchers in his field as he strives to develop a rigorous, unified foundation for the meaning of time reversal, which stems from a symmetry principle. Although the physics community recognizes the important implications of a certain definition time reversibility, there is little attention paid as to why this definition is chosen and not some other. This project aims to fill that gap. Substantial improvements to the Co-PI's dissertation are likely to come about as a result of this research visit. In the longer term, the Co-PI expects to use a similar approach (using symmetry principles) to analyze related concepts in physics such as physical equivalence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Potential Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although the work is of particular interest to philosophers of science, in that it seeks to explicate a central concept in the foundations of modern physics, it will also be of interest to physicists who are concerned with the conceptual basis for time reversibility, a concept considered of fundamental importance in the practice of physics. The Co-PI plans to disseminate the results of his research at philosophy of science conferences, at physics conferences, and through publications in peer-reviewed journals in both fields. Doing so will serve to contribute to and to enhance interdisciplinary interaction.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058902</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Norton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdnorton@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/02/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roberts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bwr6@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/02/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
