<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STEM Scholars Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>595880</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Immaculata University is implementing the STEM Scholars Program (SSP), which is awarding scholarships to community college students transferring to the university who have successfully completed two years in the STEM areas. The scholarships support the completion of a four-year STEM degree program in Biology, Chemistry, Mathematics, or Mathematics-Computer Science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Program objectives include: (1) recruiting four cohorts of students, 7-10 each; (2) recruiting students from under-represented populations, including women and minorities, with a goal of 50% of the scholarship students from these groups; (3) providing opportunities for all SSP students to develop research and leadership skills through networking with the scientific community on and off campus; (4) creating a supportive learning community in order to achieve at least a 75% degree completion rate for scholars in the STEM fields in two years; and (5) demonstrating at least an 80% placement rate for the graduates in a STEM career or graduate program. The program is producing talented graduates well prepared to pursue careers or advanced study in the STEM areas without the burden of excessive debt. Applicants submit written scholarship applications (reviewed by the Admission/Scholarship Committee) and participate in an interview. Scholars receive support through department faculty mentors, advising, a cohort learning community, and SSP courses. Senior year activities spotlight career placement as well as internships, research, and graduate study preparation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SSP derives intellectual merit from rigorous academic content combined with an integrated learning community with a focus on academic research and community connections through site visits, internships, symposia, conferences, and colloquia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of SSP include demonstrating how engaging talented students in scholarship leads to academic success while suggesting a model for creating a path between community college STEM students and achievement of a baccalaureate degree.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1059993</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cronin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scronin@immaculata.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Immaculata University</Name>
      <CityName>Immaculata</CityName>
      <ZipCode>193450648</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6106474400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1145 King Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
