<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>II-NEW: Robust Carbon Nanotube Technology for Energy-Efficient Computing Systems: A Processing and Design Infrastructure for Emerging Nanotechnologies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>675000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Almadena Y. Chtchelkanova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award focuses on creating a comprehensive processing and design infrastructure to enable and accelerate research on robust VLSI technology using Carbon Nanotube Field-Effect Transistors (CNFETs) for next generation energy-efficient computing systems. CNFETs represent a significant departure from traditional silicon technologies, and can potentially enable computing systems with more than an order of magnitude better energy efficiency compared to silicon-CMOS. Moreover, a unique aspect of CNFET technology enables massive monolithic three-dimensional integration. However, several fundamental challenges must be overcome before such benefits can be achieved. This requires significant inventions in inter-disciplinary fields of devices, processing, VLSI design and CAD, and integrated computing system design. Hence, a significant amount of infrastructure is required, where robust and repeatable processing and design flows are established (unlike stand-alone prototypes). Such a comprehensive infrastructure for CNFET VLSI, created in this project, will enable easy adaptability and integration of new inventions. This will help build a research community around a common CNFET VLSI processing and design platform.&lt;br/&gt;It will also provide unique opportunities for exploring new research frontiers, and solid training of the next generation of researchers and practitioners.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1059020</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhenan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zbao@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>H.-S. Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hspwong@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Subhasish</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mitra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>subh@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7359</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7359</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
