<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Excitation Transport and Coherence in Nano-Plasmonic Wire Materials by Experiment and Simulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>515556</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry (MSN) program of the Division of Chemistry will support the research program of Prof. Norbert Scherer of the University of Chicago. Prof. Scherer and his students will investigate how light could be used to control the plasmonic behavior of metallic nanowire systems. Combining theoretical work and simulations with spectroscopic measurements, the team of investigators will strive to achieve coherent control of plasmon propagation in nanowires and nanowire interferometers, and to create delocalized excitons by coupling quantum dots with silver nanowires.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The resulting new plasmonic-coupled materials will advance fundamental ideas for sensing, information and energy transport, computing and perhaps (solar) energy harvesting. The integrated program could lead to new functions of nanomaterials, such as nanolensing and excitonic coupling over long distances, and to the development of linear and nonlinear optical nanoscale circuits. The experimental, theoretical and intellectual challenges of the proposed research will provide a rich environment for graduate student and postdoctoral training in nanoscience and nanotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1059057</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Norbert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scherer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nfschere@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
