<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Mathematics and Science Talent Scholarships</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599710</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The U.S. faces a critical shortage of skilled professionals in STEM fields, and unless this shortage is corrected, the country will lose a preeminent position in the world economy and in scientific research. Moreover, demographic trends in the U.S. and a desire for equity require that many more STEM professionals be drawn from women and underrepresented minorities. Attracting such talented students is difficult because of the rising cost of public and private colleges and universities. Northeastern University has developed the Mathematics Science Talent (MST) Scholarship Program to increase the number of students receiving degrees in mathematics, biology or physics by offering scholarships to those with large financial need. This program is targeting students from the Boston Public Schools and school districts in the greater Boston region, especially those who have participated in Northeastern's outreach programs in math and science. The target group is very diverse, but largely female, and Hispanic and African-American students make up a majority of the group. These students have previously proven their academic ability and diligence in school and in Northeastern's outreach programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MST scholars also participate in the concurrent, non-scholarship NSF-sponsored PRISM program. PRISM is an acronym for "Proactive Recruitment in Introductory Science and Mathematics." Consequently MST scholars have the complementary opportunity to work with outstanding faculty researchers in mathematics, biology and physics on scientific research beginning in the freshman year. The visibility of MST scholars and their progress in the PRISM program serves to encourage more underrepresented students to excel in mathematics and science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1060555</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Case</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>r.case@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/06/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>King</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>d.king@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
