<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Zoogeomorphology and Ecosystem Engineering: 42nd Annual Binghamton Geomorphology Symposium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30080</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas J. Baerwald</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Scientists study animals and their changes to the environment from different viewpoints, which are generally influenced by research within their own discipline. In geomorphology, the study of the geomorphic effects of animals is called zoogeomorphology; whereas, in ecology, ecosystem engineering refers to the concept that habitats are created, modified, or maintained by organisms. These two concepts share commonalities; however, much work done in zoogeomorphology and ecosystem engineering has run parallel to each other without integrating each other's research; or in some cases, without even being aware of the similar studies on the same species. This project will help bridge research on these two concepts by funding the 42nd Annual Binghamton Geomorphology Symposium (BGS) on "Zoogeomorphology and Ecosystem Engineering", to be held in October 2011 at the University of South Alabama. The symposium will present current research, hypotheses, and methodologies from zoogeomorphology and ecosystem engineering scientists. This project aims to provide a venue for researchers to discuss animals as geomorphic agents or ecological engineers and to foster communication between ecologists and geomorphologists. Participants in the 2011 BGS will include scholars ranging in rank from graduate students to senior researchers from geomorphology and ecology disciplines in the academic, private, and government sectors. This project will assist in publication of a proceedings volume, conference logistics, and travel support for invited speakers, graduate students, and junior scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The lack of synthesis between geomorphology and ecology research regarding the concepts of zoogeomorphology and ecosystem engineering restricts the holistic study of the impact of animals on the environment. This project seeks to encourage synthesis and dissemination of knowledge between zoogeomorphology and ecosystem engineering research in addition to strengthening the bonds between the geomorphology and ecology disciplines. A broader impact of the symposium will be an improved awareness of the research within the geomorphology and ecology disciplines, which may encourage increased future interaction between scientists involved in examining the role animals play in modifying the environment. The symposium will expose junior scholars and graduate students to relevant and innovative studies and possibly encourage these scientists to consider the role of animals in their own geomorphic and ecological research. For long-term impact, invited papers will be published in Geomorphology, a major international geomorphology journal, to ensure widespread dissemination of research presented at the symposium. This project is jointly funded with Geography and Spatial Sciences Program and the Geormophology and Land use Dynamics Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1060960</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sawyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sawyer@usouthal.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Alabama</Name>
      <CityName>Mobile</CityName>
      <ZipCode>366880002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2514606333</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>307 University Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
