<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU SITE: Undergraduate Research on Complex Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>286000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at the University of Vermont offers undergraduates a unique experience working in the emerging area of complex materials, including research related to nanotechnology applications. Over a three year period a total of 27 undergraduates participate in 10-week summer research projects on collective phenomena through studies of self-assembled discotic organic semiconductors, metallic nanopillars and relationships between electronic and magnetic properties of graphene. REU participants also explore how novel deposition methods can drive the self-assembly process towards different ordering with radically different properties, understand the role of short and long range interactions in biological molecules or experiment with new chemistry of polymers, ceramics and nanoporous building blocks for biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A diverse group of students is recruited from across the nation. REU participants gain experience identifying research problems, searching the literature, conducting research, and communicating their findings. Research on complex materials, in addition to contributing fundamental knowledge, has applications in the important areas of nanotechnology and biotechnology, where many of most challenging current problems and issues are found. The research impacts potential solutions in areas such as emerging mass-production organic technologies, air pollution monitoring and mitigation, new energy-efficient consumer products, and technology for medical treatment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1062966</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Madalina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Furis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Madalina.Furis@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clougherty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dennis.clougherty@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Vermont &amp; State Agricultural College</Name>
      <CityName>BURLINGTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>054050160</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8026563660</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>85 SO. PROSPECT ST.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Vermont</StateName>
      <StateCode>VT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7222</Code>
      <Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
