<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>UnIPhy - REU (Undergraduate Institute in Physics - Research Experiences for Undergraduates</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>117000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is to support the renewal of the UnIPhy-REU site program at Hampton University. The main focus of UnIPhy-REU is to introduce undergraduate students to the process of conducting advanced scientific research in physics. UnIPhy-REU allows student participants to conduct research in exciting, cutting-edge fields at the frontiers of scientific research such as electron-ion beam detector design. Mentors for UnIPhy-REU have years of faculty and institutional experience and a wealth of experience providing research opportunities for undergraduates. Students will conduct research in labs on the campus of Hampton University, at the Hampton University Proton Therapy Institute, and at the nearby Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility. Four students will participate in the UnIPhy-REU/MIT Summer Program for Undergraduate Research with an Electron Ion Collider at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Laboratory for Nuclear Science. The program seeks to get students excited about research, disseminate their results, and become effective, confident researchers. UnIPhy-REU also emphasizes the importance of seeking advanced degrees while better preparing the students to succeed in post-graduate studies. This award is funded by the Division of Physics with co-funding from the HBCU-UP program in the Directorate for Education and Human Resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1062978</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whitney</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Donald.Whitney@Hamptonu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hampton University</Name>
      <CityName>Hampton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>236680108</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7577275363</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 E. Queen Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
