<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Research Incubator REU Site in Chemistry at Furman University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>311625</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry (CHE) and the Department of Defense (ASSURE Program) supports a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site led by Timothy W. Hanks at Furman University. The research projects supported in this site are in a broad number of areas of chemical research. Undergraduates will be recruited to this site from Furman University and from local and regional colleges, with emphasis on recruitment of students in the first two years of undergraduate school as well as from groups that are underrepresented in the sciences. The site will support ten students per summer in a ten week program. In addition to supporting students, the site will also support faculty from partner institutions lacking in research infrastructure. A sample of the projects that undergraduates and faculty would work on include: (1) the synthesis and study of biosensors based upon polydiacetylenes; (2) the development of materials for brain-machine interfaces, e.g. for use in prosthetics and artificial sensing organs; (3) the study of HMGA proteins' binding to DNA; (4) the synthesis of biologically-active small molecule natural products and the development of new synthetic methods; (5) the study of the photochemistry of transition metal complexes; and (6) the development of new, therapeutically-interesting small proteins via semi-random nucleic acid libraries. In addition to conducting research during the summer, the students participating in this program will participate in a number of professional development activities, as well as development of an outreach activity designed and implemented by the participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Young scientists need exposure to modern research methods and tools as part of their training. This REU site aims to provide cutting-edge research training in the chemical sciences. The research projects are in diverse areas of chemistry, many of which will have an impact in areas of national need. The diverse student cohort participating in research at this site will be well-prepared for graduate school, and eventual employment as part of the country's technical workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1062714</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hanks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Tim.Hanks@FURMAN.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buchmueller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>karen.buchmueller@furman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Furman University</Name>
      <CityName>Greenville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296131000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8642943470</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3300 Poinsett Highway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
