<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ABI Innovation: Barcoding-Free Multiplexing: Leveraging Combinatorial Pooling for High-Throughput Sequencing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>428635</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne Maglia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of California, Riverside is awarded a grant to develop&lt;br/&gt;an innovative sequencing protocol for hierarchical (i.e., BAC-by-BAC)&lt;br/&gt;genome sequencing of large eukaryotic genomes. At the core of the&lt;br/&gt;protocol is the ability to solve a set of hard computational&lt;br/&gt;questions, which are the focus of the research plan. The computational&lt;br/&gt;challenges require the study of novel combinatorial optimization&lt;br/&gt;problems, the development of innovative time- and space-efficient&lt;br/&gt;algorithms, and ultimately the implementation and deployment of&lt;br/&gt;user-friendly web-based software tools. The new combinatorial&lt;br/&gt;sequencing protocol is going to be tested to the cowpea genome. Cowpea&lt;br/&gt;Vigna unguiculata, also known as China bean or black-eyed pea,&lt;br/&gt;is one of the most important food legume crops in the semi-arid&lt;br/&gt;tropics covering Asia, Africa, and Central and South America. A&lt;br/&gt;drought-tolerant and warm-weather crop, cowpeas are well-adapted to&lt;br/&gt;the drier regions of the tropics, where other food legumes do not&lt;br/&gt;perform well. Its modest genome size makes it an excellent candidate&lt;br/&gt;to demonstrate the utility of our protocol. We expect the final&lt;br/&gt;assembly to provide a sufficient depth of knowledge to support most&lt;br/&gt;downstream applications including map-based cloning of trait&lt;br/&gt;determinants, development of markers for marker-assisted breeding,&lt;br/&gt;microarray development for gene expression studies and analysis of&lt;br/&gt;synteny with related species.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will advance sequencing techniques for complex genomes,&lt;br/&gt;using cowpea, an essential food source in developing&lt;br/&gt;countries. Software tools and the assembled data will be placed into&lt;br/&gt;the public domain, which will benefit researchers and the public&lt;br/&gt;worldwide, and potentially lead to new international and industrial&lt;br/&gt;collaborations. This project will directly support one graduate&lt;br/&gt;students in a highly interdisciplinary environment, building on UCR's&lt;br/&gt;strengths in Computer Science and Agricultural&lt;br/&gt;Sciences. Undergraduates will have opportunities to participate in&lt;br/&gt;research through a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site&lt;br/&gt;at UCR, a collaboration with a nearby community college, and a new US&lt;br/&gt;Department of Education Title V Hispanic Serving Institution grant&lt;br/&gt;(UCR is an accredited HSI).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More details and information about this project will be available at&lt;br/&gt;http://www.cs.ucr.edu/~stelo/dbi.htm</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1062301</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Close</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>timothy.close@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefano</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lonardi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stelo@cs.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
