<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III: Medium: Collaborative Research: Scalable Kinship Inference in Wild Populations Across Years and Generations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>954730</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Scalable kinship inference in wild populations across years and generations&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A cornerstone of research in molecular ecology is the reconstruction of family groups (kinship analysis).&lt;br/&gt;Understanding how individuals in free-living populations are related to each other provides the best&lt;br/&gt;opportunity to study many important biological processes, ranging from sexual selection to patterns&lt;br/&gt;of dispersal and recruitment. Recent advances in molecular DNA technologies and computational&lt;br/&gt;methods have made these studies possible. However, many conceptual and computational challenges&lt;br/&gt;remain and need to be addressed in order to advance these studies. To date, existing research work&lt;br/&gt;on kinship analysis has primarily focused on computational methods that address a single relationship, such as parentage assignment or reconstruction of full sib groups. Inclusion of multiple objectives, such as half-sib reconstruction with minimum parentage assignment, or hierarchy over multiple generations, makes formulation of the underlying computational problem extremely challenging, and simple extensions of previous methods do not address in a practical, scalable, and robust manner the problem of kinship reconstruction for data sets that include multiple generations of species or involve multiple optimization functions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposed research is to design robust, parsimonious, and versatile computational&lt;br/&gt;approaches for inferring multi-generation kinship relationships in wild populations from multiallelic&lt;br/&gt;markers. Parsimony assumption is fundamental to these approaches as it requires no prior knowledge,&lt;br/&gt;assumptions about sampling methodology, or existence of models, which is the case for most free-living&lt;br/&gt;populations. The diverse tasks of this project include formulating computational kinship inference&lt;br/&gt;problems based on existing biological studies, analyzing computational complexity of and providing&lt;br/&gt;solutions to the resulting combinatorial optimization problems, and designing robust, scalable and&lt;br/&gt;efficient high performance implementations. The resulting computational methods will be evaluated&lt;br/&gt;on datasets collected from existing biological studies and will be deployed to the biological community&lt;br/&gt;through the Kinalyzer web-based service, currently actively used for sibship inference only.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research proposed in this project will greatly impact diverse application areas including funda-&lt;br/&gt;mental research in combinatorial optimization and data mining, and within biology, areas as diverse as&lt;br/&gt;behavioral ecology, evolutionary genetics, conservation, forensics, and epidemiology. The multidisci-&lt;br/&gt;plinary nature of the project and the research team will enhance curriculum design of related areas and&lt;br/&gt;introduce new cross-disciplinary courses. This cohesive, multidisciplinary project will provide training&lt;br/&gt;opportunities in biology, operation research, algorithms analysis, bioinformatics and high performance&lt;br/&gt;computing, within a single application framework. The project will leverage the diverse scientific ex-&lt;br/&gt;pertise and extensive mentoring experience of the team to foster a true interdisciplinary collaboration&lt;br/&gt;and to provide a thriving environment for a new generation of interdisciplinary scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1064681</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ashley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ashley@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ashfaq</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khokhar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ashfaq@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bhaskar</FirstName>
      <LastName>DasGupta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dasgupta@cs.uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tanya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berger-Wolf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tanyabw@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1165</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1165</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
