<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SHF: Medium: Type-Specific Instruction Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>799990</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Almadena Y. Chtchelkanova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project develops hardware software interfaces to enable standard&lt;br/&gt;software programs to benefit from specialized hardware accelerators.&lt;br/&gt;Standard CPUs are general purpose meaning that they are designed to execute&lt;br/&gt;all types of applications -- from graphics processing in video games to&lt;br/&gt;spreadsheets. Because of the diversity of workloads they are expected to&lt;br/&gt;execute, general purpose processors can never be overly specialized for any&lt;br/&gt;individual one. By contrast, processors which are tailored to a single&lt;br/&gt;workload or workload domain are narrower in their applicability but more&lt;br/&gt;efficient at executing applications in their target domains.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project examines specialized processors that target abstract&lt;br/&gt;datatypes: moderate to large scale data structures and their associated&lt;br/&gt;operations. Modern software engineering practice encourages the use of such&lt;br/&gt;abstract types to improve programmer efficiency and software reliability.&lt;br/&gt;Abstract datatype processors thus align with these practices making the&lt;br/&gt;mapping of software to hardware intuitive and streamlined. By delivering&lt;br/&gt;energy-efficient, application-specific hardware in an easy-to-program fashion,&lt;br/&gt;this research empowers programmers to write faster software that consumes less&lt;br/&gt;energy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research activities span three fields of computer science: Hardware system&lt;br/&gt;and architecture research is carried out in software simulation. This portion&lt;br/&gt;of the research explores multiple aspects of the hardware system including&lt;br/&gt;efficient implementations of software-style polymorphism and mechanisms to&lt;br/&gt;enforce data encapsulation. The project is grounded in a specific,&lt;br/&gt;performance-critical, real-world problem of database query processing. This&lt;br/&gt;component of the research identifies target types for hardware acceleration&lt;br/&gt;that are used in common, complex database operations such as range&lt;br/&gt;partitioning. Performance results will be obtained both by direct measurement&lt;br/&gt;and by simulation. Finally, the compiler segment of the project develops&lt;br/&gt;compiler techniques to link high-level languages to the accelerators available&lt;br/&gt;on the target hardware system. The compiler adapts software at runtime to&lt;br/&gt;best utilize the available accelerators and to partition code among&lt;br/&gt;general-purpose and specialized processing cores. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As power and energy become the most critical resource in computing systems,&lt;br/&gt;mechanisms to conserve these resources have come under significant scientific&lt;br/&gt;scrutiny. The broader impact of this research project is to harness software&lt;br/&gt;abstractions in specialized, energy efficient hardware. By prioritizing&lt;br/&gt;programmability and efficiency equally, this research strives for usable,&lt;br/&gt;energy-efficient, next-generation computing platforms. As a first area of&lt;br/&gt;application, this project targets databases, the software engines that store&lt;br/&gt;and index and compute on society's information.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1065338</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ross</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kar@cs.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edwards</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sedwards@cs.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>martha@cs.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7329</Code>
      <Text>COMPILERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
