<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Biological Hybrid Materials for Life Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David A. Brant</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ID: MPS/DMR/BMAT(7623) 1065676 PI: Wolf, Sandra ORG: Materials Research Society&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Biological Hybrid Materials for Life Sciences&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT: The goal of this multidisciplinary symposium is to bring together researchers working at the interface between materials science, biology, and chemistry through an approach that integrates dissemination of latest advances in the field with educating young students and researchers and broadening participation of underrepresented categories in interdisciplinary research. New technologies are needed to design devices that have the required sensitivity, flexibility and ease of manipulation and, when necessary, biocompatibility. Starting from well-known biological structures such as diatom and sponge silica, seashells and bone, and structures with hierarchical organization and high mechanical strength (e.g. organic fibers like spider silk), principles for design of novel nanomaterials with superior properties are being developed using biomimetic nanotechnogy. The symposium will cover research on bioinspired and biointegrated materials with novel properties and will expand into the rational design and development of functional devices that are assembled based on the interconnections of traditional materials science, chemistry and biology disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACTS: The organizers of the symposium have organized the event to encourage and facilitate the participation of underrepresented groups, students, and postdoctoral scientists. &lt;br/&gt;Specific plans in this direction include: (1) a session for student and postdoctoral talks, (2) student award for best oral and best poster presentations, (3) inviting young researchers, females and members of underrepresented groups to present talks and chair sub-sessions, (4) promoting participation of undergraduate students by submitting information about the symposium, targeting undergraduate institutions, and facilitating abstract acceptance in a manner that gives special attention to these categories of researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1065676</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stanciu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lstanciu@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
      <LastName>DeVincent Wolf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swolf@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
      <CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7623</Code>
      <Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
