<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CIF: Medium: Collaborative Research: Toward a General Theory of Information Transfer via Timing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>614965</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Information theory, communication theory, and statistical signal &lt;br/&gt;processing have proven spectacularly successful as innovation engines &lt;br/&gt;for communication, data compression, and information processing &lt;br/&gt;technologies. Although in principle these theories are quite general, &lt;br/&gt;in practice they are most useful for a particular family of models, &lt;br/&gt;such as discrete Markov sources and channels with additive &lt;br/&gt;Gaussian noise. Although this family is quite rich and encompasses &lt;br/&gt;many practical technologies, there are several important scenarios that&lt;br/&gt;fall outside of these models. In particular, the timing of discrete events is &lt;br/&gt;the modality of interest in many applications, such as neuroscience&lt;br/&gt;and certain problems in network security, and this modality does &lt;br/&gt;not fit neatly into the standard classes. This research involves&lt;br/&gt;extending information theory, communication theory, and statistical signal&lt;br/&gt;processing to develop a general theory of information transfer via timing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first phase of this research involves solving several concrete&lt;br/&gt;problems involving information transfer via timing, such as the&lt;br/&gt;secrecy capacity of timing channels and how to minimize information&lt;br/&gt;transfer via timing side channels in both wireless and wireline&lt;br/&gt;networks. The second phase involves interconnecting these disparate&lt;br/&gt;problems to form a general theory of information transfer via timing.&lt;br/&gt;By elevating the role of timing in information transfer,&lt;br/&gt;this research better positions the fields of information theory,&lt;br/&gt;communication theory, and statistical signal processing to&lt;br/&gt;impact allied fields such as networking, neuroscience, and &lt;br/&gt;operations research, where timing and delay are of fundamental&lt;br/&gt;importance. This impact is facilitated through special topics &lt;br/&gt;courses and invited sessions at conferences, both of which are &lt;br/&gt;designed to attract participants from a range of areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1065022</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coleman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tpcoleman@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/05/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Negar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kiyavash</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kiyavash@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Negar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kiyavash</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kiyavash@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/05/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7797</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
