<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IGERT: Person-centered Technologies and Practices for Individuals with Disabilities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2972183</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010103</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship (IGERT) award will train a new generation of doctoral graduates to become future leaders in the field of disabilities through an integrated and interdisciplinary education-research-practice model. Intellectual Merit: The unique features of this IGERT include: 1) Development of person-centered solutions to address the complex needs of individuals with disabilities; 2) Innovative cross-disciplinary research and training at the convergence of computer science and engineering, bioengineering, mechanical engineering, science education, psychology, science and public policy, and industrial design; 3) Novel threads of learning such as entrepreneurship and global leadership; on-field activities, such as service learning; and use-inspired projects involving collaborations with caregivers, industry and government organizations; 4) The melding of a Ph.D. granting institution(ASU) and a teaching and research intensive institution (CSULB) to extend this training opportunity to a large number of students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project will not only have a significant impact on the lives of individuals with sensory, cognitive, learning and developmental disabilities, but it will also enrich the lives of injured veterans, the elderly, and - in a broader sense - a very large portion of society. The students trained by this IGERT will be amply qualified to choose between a variety of career opportunities such as in academia, as leaders in the disability technology industry, as entrepreneurs or research scholars, or as directors and policy makers in federal or service agencies. The diversity of the faculty team will promote the active recruitment, retention and mentoring of students with disabilities, women and underrepresented/minority students across the STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IGERT is an NSF-wide program intended to meet the challenges of educating U.S. Ph.D. scientists and engineers with the interdisciplinary background, deep knowledge in a chosen discipline, and the technical, professional, and personal skills needed for the career demands of the future. The program is intended to catalyze a cultural change in graduate education by establishing innovative new models for graduate education and training in a fertile environment for collaborative research that transcends traditional disciplinary boundaries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1069125</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sethuraman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Panchanathan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>panch@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Clark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clark.miller@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marco</FirstName>
      <LastName>Santello</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marco.santello@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shireen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pavri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spavri@csulb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Forouzan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Golshani</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>forouzan.golshani@csulb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1335</Code>
      <Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1335</Code>
      <Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
