<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Self-Rising Approach to Synthesize Hierarchically Porous Mixed Ionic and Electronic Conducting Cathodes for Solid Oxide Fuel Cells</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>280000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this award is to elucidate the mechanism of a novel self-rising approach for the synthesis of hierarchically porous electrodes for solid oxide fuel cells (SOFCs). SOFCs convert chemical energy from the fuel directly to electricity, offering high efficiency with zero to low emissions. SOFCs operating at reduced operating temperatures (400-600 degrees C) have commercial advantages, but the cell performance is mainly limited by the sluggish electrode reactions at reduced temperatures. The advantages offered by hierarchically porous electrodes include dramatically increased active surface areas for fast electrode kinetics and enhanced mass transport. The project will study the different parameters influencing porous network formation to achieve hierarchically porous microstructure and to apply the hierarchically porous electrode to improve the performance of SOFCs at reduced temperatures. A fundamental understanding of the synthesis, processing, and properties of hierarchically porous electrodes is essential to the rational design of a new generation of SOFCs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is expected to create a unique self-rising method in the dynamic control of the pore size and geometry so that hierarchically porous materials can be economically and reproducibly fabricated. Utilization of hierarchically porous electrode is expected to bring significant enhancement of SOFC performance at reduced operating temperatures. This project is expected to have significant impacts on improving energy conversion efficiency and environmental quality. By active dissemination of the self-rising approach, it will offer the scientific community a unique technique to economically and efficiently produce hierarchically porous materials in other applications such as drug delivery, sensing, catalysis and adsorption. Outreach to high school students and the general public to promote the interest and awareness of the fuel cell technology as well as the training of graduate and undergraduate students through this project will help transfer the solid oxide fuel cell technology to US industry, thus enhancing its global competitiveness.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1000068</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xingjian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xue</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xue@cec.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fanglin (Frank)</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chenfa@cec.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1633</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1444</Code>
      <Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
