<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The parameterization of algebraic structures, and applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>380776</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is part of an ongoing research program. It revolves around understanding how various fundamental algebraic objects occurring in mathematics---such as rings, class groups, algebraic curves and varieties, and maps relating such structures---are parametrized. Our goals in understanding these parametrizations are at least fourfold: 1) to describe how these fundamental algebraic objects are distributed with respect to their most basic invariants; 2) to discover new invariants of these objects, and their applications; 3) to develop efficient and practical algorithms for performing computations with these algebraic objects; and, perhaps most importantly, 4) to discover and understand how various seemingly different algebraic structures are in fact closely related to each other.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Such parametrizations have been already used by the PI over the past few years to obtain precise information on the distribution of number fields with respect to basic invariants such as discriminant and class number divisibility. Applying refined counting methods to these parametrizations has led, for example, to a proof of the first known case of the Cohen-Lenstra-Martinet class number heuristics for higher degree number fields, and other theorems of this nature are forthcoming. We expect similar theorems for ranks of elliptic curves, and other data of this kind for algebraic curves and surfaces, in the near future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1001828</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Manjul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bhargava</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>manjulb@math.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
