<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanotechnology from Basic Science to Emerging Applications: Institute for Functional Nanomaterials (IFN)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8665091</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01120000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>EPSCoR</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy VanReken</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: EPS-1002410 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: Nanotechnology from Basic Science to Emerging Applications: &lt;br/&gt; Institute for Functional Nanomaterials (IFN)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Puerto Rico&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Research Infrastructure Improvement (RII) Award would strengthen academic research and education in nanoscience and technology in the institutions of higher education in Puerto Rico. Establishing partnerships among research universities and four-year colleges in Puerto Rico and training of junior researchers and students at all levels is among the primary focus of the RII program. Efforts to translate basic research results into commercially viable products and transfer of the know-how to nano, bio technology related businesses and start-up companies in Puerto Rico would be pursued. This RII project aligns well with Puerto Rico?s Science and Technology Policy and is expected to lead to the economic development in the commonwealth and increase its competitiveness at the national and international level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;Research focus is on experimental and computer modeling studies in interdisciplinary areas of nanoscience and technology. The work involves cutting edge research for the development of novel nanomaterials and nanostructures with potential applications in bio-nanotechnology, water remediation and CO2 sequestration, logic and memory devices for use in information technology, and devices for efficient light harvesting. Collaborations among scientists and engineers from five institutions of higher education in Puerto Rico as well as strategic partnership with five universities on the mainland, four national laboratories/facilities and M.D. Anderson Cancer Center in Texas are included. The RII project would build the necessary expertise, resources and workforce in Puerto Rico to enable significant advances in the chosen areas of research. The RII program would create intellectual property through the research projects, use testbeds to evaluate potential commercial viability, and partner with private sector to bring the technological innovation to commercialization stage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The implementation of the RII projects has a high potential to impact environment, energy, and nano-bio-medicine related applications. The program would lead to the creation of a Multidisciplinary and Multicampus Institute of Functional Nanomaterials in the University of Puerto Rico System. The facilities and expertise available at this Institute would serve the biotechnology and nanotechnology industries in Puerto Rico. The RII program has a strong workforce development plan that includes a broad range of activities for the educational training of junior researchers, technicians, and K-20+ continuum. The University of Puerto Rico System has a large enrollment of Hispanic students in the nation and by targeting minority participation in the research and educational activities this RII program would contribute to increasing the diversity of the nation?s science and engineering workforce. The public-private partnerships for technology transfer as well as outreach programs to engage and educate the public on nanoscience and technology innovations would help build a knowledge-based economy in Puerto Rico.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1002410</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weiner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brad@hpcf.upr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gomez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mgomez@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/01/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arturo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hernandez-Maldonado</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>arturoj.hernandez@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Puerto Rico</Name>
      <CityName>San Juan</CityName>
      <ZipCode>009313334</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7877656696</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Central Administration</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
      <StateCode>PR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7217</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
