<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Barnard Interdisciplinary Workshop on Embodiment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20506</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally Dickerson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a workshop aimed at coalescing disparate approaches to the study of mind. The common thread relating these approaches is a conception of the mind called embodiment. At its core, embodiment emphasizes the importance of studying the mind or brain from the perspective that it is situated in a body, and exists to serve that body as it interacts with the world. This workshop on embodiment includes a two-day gathering of 25-30 people intended to help coordinate thinking and catalyze research in this burgeoning area in the study of mind. Towards that end, the workshop has three main objectives: 1) to lay out a course for progress; 2) to provide necessary crosstalk and common ground between disciplines and researchers; and 3) to create an enduring educational forum for the growth of embodiment research. This workshop will bring together emerging and established faculty and students, from multiple disciplines, to build collaborative relationships, establish lines of communication, and discuss what role embodiment theories of mind can play in their own and each other?s research. To address the needs to provide crosstalk between disciplines, to organize the work on embodiment, and to educate future students of embodiment, a primary product of this workshop will be an ongoing interdisciplinary website (www.embodiedmind.org) dedicated to review and communication of ideas and research on embodiment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1002595</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdavis@barnard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Barnard College</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276598</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128542708</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3009 BROADWAY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
