<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ATE Workshops for Physics Faculty</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599979</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technician education focuses on preparing students for workforce jobs that deal with complex technical systems. Such technicians not only need to have specific technical knowledge, but also a strong base in physics knowledge so they have the competence to recognize, formulate, document, and solve real problems now and in the future; as well as deploy new technology. Typically, this core knowledge and problem solving capability related to physics is expected to be obtained in mostly conventional physics courses taught in high schools (HS) and/or two-year colleges (TYC) by traditionally trained, physics educators with limited support and heavy workload demands. These courses are generally isolated from technical education specialists and focus on few workforce issues. Frequently, these physics courses do not provide the foundational physics knowledge base or the activities that build and enhance workforce physics related problem solving. This situation can be improved by supplying the physics faculty at HSs and TYCs the tools that produce a more competent and competitive workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project is providing a series of three-day, intensive, focused, hands-on professional and curriculum development workshops/conferences and follow-up activities for physics teachers in TYCs and HSs who serve students involved in technology-based or technician careers. Each year, workshops/conferences are being held at various TYCs with special incentives to encourage teams of HS and TYC teachers. Additionally, a series of working conferences are being conducted to develop laboratory activities and curriculum appropriate for technician/technology education. Educators from TYCs, HSs, and colleges/universities, which include implementation leaders and developers from business and industry, lead these workshops and working conferences. Workshops deal with effective integration, technology implementation, and learning strategies in areas such as microcomputer-based laboratories, digital video, computer simulations, conceptual tasks and tools, web and internet activities, group work, assessment of learning, and physics-related technician education. Efforts are being featured in workshop sessions, DVDs/CDs, electronic newsletters, and a web site. For participants, these workshops, working conferences, and activities: &lt;br/&gt;(a) build and enhance understanding and appreciation of the needs of students, educational programs, business and industry, and the workforce in areas dealing with physics and technology; &lt;br/&gt;(b) provide knowledge of and experience with recent advances and applications of computer-based technology, ATE supported centers and projects, assessment of student learning, and relevant curriculum materials and activities; &lt;br/&gt;(c) identify and evaluate the appropriateness of the workshop ideas in meeting the needs of students and programs; &lt;br/&gt;(d) equip them with the background and incentive to develop, adapt, adopt, and implement workshop activities and materials into courses and programs; &lt;br/&gt;(e) prepare them to impact student learning in physics and workforce related issues; and &lt;br/&gt;(f) furnish them with ways and ideas for building bridges and developing working relationships between TYC and HS physics, technology programs, and with businesses and industries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact: The project is helping improve the level of scientific understanding of the fundamental concepts, principles, and relations of physics that are critical to an understanding of the physical world and how it relates to the technological workforce. These workshop and working conference materials are applicable to secondary and two-year college courses throughout the country and provide student-tested laboratory activities and curriculum appropriate for introductory physics courses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1003633</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Kuma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tokuma@lee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dwain</FirstName>
      <LastName>Desbien</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dwain.desbien@emcmail.maricopa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lee College</Name>
      <CityName>Baytown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>775220818</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2814256339</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P. O. BOX 818</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
