<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Project W.A.T.E.R.S: Ways to Amplify Teaching and Education in Regard to Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>V. Celeste Carter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project "Ways to Amplify Teaching and Education in Regard to Science" (W.A.T.E.R.S.), in conjunction with the Chemical Technology Program, is enhancing student learning by strongly reinforcing difficult theoretical concepts in the laboratory environment through the use of state-of-the-art equipment commonly found in an industrial job environment. Students are gaining hands-on training on the use and operation of a Purge &amp; Trap Gas Chromatography system coupled with a mass spectrometer (GC/MS) and an ion chromatography (IC) system. &lt;br/&gt;Students are learning how to: follow standardized methods enforced by regulatory bodies such as the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), carry out multifaceted and advanced experiments, interpret chromatograms and mass spectra data, and operate computer-based instrumentation. Results from project W.A.T.E.R.S. are showing that fundamental changes within a science curriculum involving laboratory objectives coupled with appropriate discussions on theoretical concepts allows STEM students to clearly understand advances within the scientific field. Project W.A.T.E.R.S. is providing professional development opportunities to Cape Fear Community College faculty and local K-12 STEM educators. Underrepresented groups in the STEM community are benefiting through the introduction of new instrumentation that is allowing students to become more competitive in today's job market and/or to provide a better transition to a research-intensive university.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1003564</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tracy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Holbrook</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tholbrook@cfcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cape Fear Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Wilmington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>284013910</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9103627000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>411 North Front Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
