<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF ATE Regional Center for Semiconductor and Nanotechnology Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3052498</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>V. Celeste Carter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Regional Center for Semiconductor and Nanotechnology Education (RCSNE) fulfills the needs of nanotechnology and semiconductor manufacturing industries in New York State and Western New England through development, demonstration, and utilization of new materials, curricula, and delivery methods by utilizing the resources of academia, industry, and government. The Center represents a collaborative partnership including AMD/GlobalFoundries, IBM, General Electric, SEMATECH, Applied Materials, Tokyo Electron, Hudson Valley Community College, regional Boards of Cooperative Educational Services in New York State, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI), Rochester Institute of Technology (RIT), the University at Albany's College of Nanoscale Science and Engineering (CNSE), The State University of New York Institute of Technology (SUNYIT), Excelsior College, Mohawk Valley Community College (CC), Fulton Montgomery CC, Dutchess CC, Adirondack County CC, Schenectady County CC, Ulster County CC, and additional community colleges in NY, VT, MA, and CT.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nanotechnology and semiconductor manufacturing industries are already established in the region and are undergoing an explosive expansion. A prime example of this expansion is the recent groundbreaking of AMD/Global Foundries' $4 billion-plus leading edge semiconductor foundry facility in Saratoga County. When complete, this facility will be one of the most technologically advanced in the world and the most advanced semiconductor foundry in the U.S. Approximately 1,465 permanent manufacturing jobs will be created by the end of 2012 (including 390 engineers and 800 technicians). In addition, IBM has committed to investing $1.5 billion in establishing an advanced Integrated Circuit Packaging Research and Development Center in upstate New York in 2010 and will be recruiting for 475 engineers and 200 technicians. Similar expansion is occurring in the advanced energy sectors such as General Electric's advanced battery manufacturing center slated for construction in Schenectady, New York.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In response to these needs, the RCSNE is implementing and enabling (a) expansion of advanced semiconductor and nanotechnology related AAS/AS degree programs among its community college partners, (b) on-the-job co-op and internship-based training, (c) distance learning options, (d) just-in-time training, (e) K-12 pipeline development programs, (f) coordinated student recruitment, and (g) research into emerging workforce trends and training needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The RCSNE can improve community college student learning in science and engineering by providing a broader range of students access to the educational materials, facilities and faculty of several premier U.S. science and engineering schools. Several of the partners (HVCC, UAlbany, RPI and RIT) have successfully teamed to develop and disseminate existing nano and semiconductor manufacturing programs that have leveraged semiconductor cleanrooms at UAlbany's College of Nanoscale Science and Engineering, RPI, HVCC's TEC-SMART facility, and other community colleges. A RCSNE industrial advisory board and external evaluation processes assures student learning is effectively assessed. HVCC and other partners have indicated commitment to the proposed ATE Center through their existing education programs, articulation agreements and outreach activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The Center's industrial partners such as IBM, AMD/Global Foundries, and General Electric are providing guidelines regarding the technical skills required for highly effective employees. Regular workforce skill assessments are being performed to match the needs of the industry. The Center is adapting educational programs from other ATE Centers and the Center's regional partners and developing material where none already exists. These materials are being disseminated by a network of community colleges to educate the next generation of the technical workforce in the nanotechnology and semiconductor manufacturing industries. The project activities are being presented at technical and educational conferences and published in scientific and educational journals. The Center is educating the public through outreach activities. The Center is conducting active recruiting to increase the number of women and under-represented minorities in nanotechnology and semiconductor manufacturing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1003574</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Decker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdecker@mvcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rahmi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ozisik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ozisik@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Esmel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Essis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>essisesm@hvcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Geer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rgeer@sunypoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abraham</FirstName>
      <LastName>Michelen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amichelen@sunypoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hudson Valley Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121806025</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5186298177</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>80 Vandenburgh Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>MX29</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
