<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Bridging Engineering, Science, and Technology (BEST) for Elementary Educators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>899072</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>V. Celeste Carter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Bridging Engineering, Science and Technology (BEST) for Elementary Educators is designed to provide professional development for science and education faculty who prepare future elementary educators to strengthen faculty and pre-service teachers' understandings of engineering content, inquiry-based pedagogical techniques, and career pathways in technical fields. This project builds on the successful NSF-funded ATLAS project (DUE 07-02853), designed to enrich teacher education courses with engineering and technology. The BEST project expands this innovative approach to include community college science courses, which are modified to incorporate open-ended engineering design activities. The project goals are as follows: provide materials for teacher education courses using hands-on approaches to technology and engineering while integrating science and mathematics; strengthen knowledge and ability to teach technology, engineering and science; develop articulation pathways related to elementary education between community colleges and four-year institutions; create a cadre of faculty to disseminate their knowledge at state, regional, and national levels; and increase awareness of technology and engineering elementary education programs. The project partners include Greenfield Community College, MA College of Liberal Arts, Massasoit Community College, Bridgewater State College, Middlesex Community College, Fitchburg State College, North Shore Community College, and Salem State College. The Massachusetts Board of Higher Education, Massachusetts Biotechnology Education Foundation, The Engineering Center, and the Boston Society of Civil Engineers are key educational and industry partners. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BEST targets Life Science faculty in Year 1 and Physical Science faculty in Year 2. During the first year, Faculty Leadership Teams comprised of two science and two education faculty from each of the eight colleges participate in a four-day Leadership Institute at the Museum of Science. The Leadership Institute emphasizes team building, disciplinary knowledge, modeling effective pedagogies, exploration of career options, reviewing the research and resources, examination of course models and the development of a project plan for introducing technology and engineering into STEM courses. Next, science and education faculty pilot course components and modify or create new courses with technology and engineering integration. Year 2 focuses on new course implementation and workshops for the teachers that host pre-service educators during their teaching practicum. Finally, in Year 3, the emphasis is on institutionalization, professional development, and dissemination of models, materials, and findings via conferences, publications, and websites. A statewide articulation and transfer workshop is also planned. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BEST is designed to reach 62 community college and 25 four-year college faculty. Additionally, approximately 800 pre-service educators and 7,000 elementary students are impacted. The project evaluation plan compares the technology and engineering integration models included in the ATLAS and BEST projects to determine which are most effective, sustainable and scalable. The evaluation also examines regional, state and national dissemination, development of transfer pathways, and curricular changes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By developing course syllabi, sequences, and lesson plans, BEST documents how technology and engineering can be integrated into science and education courses for pre-service teachers. As more states include technology and engineering in their standards, the case studies, resources, and models resulting from this project can provide a powerful foundation to guide community college and pre-service efforts nationwide. BEST leverages opportunities at community colleges and four-year colleges that prepare tomorrow's teachers to enhance technological literacy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1003060</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccunningham@mos.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cratsley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccratsley@fitchburgstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francesca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Purcell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lhiggins@mos.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/14/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frances</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCutcheon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lhiggins@mos.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katharine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gravino</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lhiggins@mos.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/26/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Museum of Science</Name>
      <CityName>Boston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021141099</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6175890118</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 Science Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
