<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium: 27th International Symposium on Rarefied Gas Dynamics, July 10-15, 2010, Alexandria, Virginia.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1004000&lt;br/&gt;Levin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant provides partial support for graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and assistant professors in the United States to attend the 27th International Symposium on Rarefied Gas Dynamics to be held during the summer of 2010. The Symposium is a premiere meeting for modeling and simulation of low density, nonequilibrium flows and will return to the United States after a twenty-two year absence. It typically attracts about 200 participants from 30 different countries, spanning academia, government, and industry. Members of the organizing group are experts in rarified gas dynamics from academia, government, and industry. The conference will be run by Penn State Conferences and Institute and has received support from the Department of Aerospace Engineering and the College of Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit and Broader Impact: The Symposium includes topics in nanotechnology and plasmas, both of which we are paying particular attention to attract more of the more semiconductor community participates by locating the meeting close to Silicon Valley. Since its initiation, the Symposium topics have grown to include both the engineering applications of plasma processing, space, materials, and propulsion, as well as, the basic physics of molecular interactions, gas-surface interactions, kinetic theory, astronomical observations, transport, multi-phase flows, combustion, and non-equilibrium hypersonic gas dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1004000</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Levin Fliflet</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>deblevin@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1414</Code>
      <Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>065E</Code>
      <Text>Radiation heat transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
