<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Summer Program in the Biochemical Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>306317</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award, made to the University of Kentucky, is supported by the Department of Defense ASSURE program and the NSF Division of Biological Infrastructure in the Directorate for Biological Sciences (BIO) and the Division of Chemistry (CHE) and in the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences (MPS). The University of Kentucky will provide research training for 10 weeks for 8 students, during the summers of 2010-2013. Students will complete an intensive ten week program in the biochemical sciences, participating in cutting-edge research in structural biology, biophysics, molecular biology and genetics, and cell biology. All participants will be assigned a faculty mentor and are expected to conduct their research in an ethical and responsible manner. The Program includes seminar series on careers in the biochemical sciences and the research process, including presentation and publication of data, and research ethics. Participants will also have the opportunity to participate in a number of organized social events. The Program will culminate in a widely-attended symposium featuring oral research presentations by participants. Recruitment is focused on the students from the Appalachian area and under-represented groups. Successful applicants will receive a stipend, housing in student dormitories, and reimbursement for travel to and from Lexington, Kentucky. Success will be tracked through surveys of participants both during and in the years after attending the Program. Assessment will involve use of a common tool developed by the NSF BIO REU and tools developed by the Program. Additional information and application materials can be found at http://www.mc.uky.edu/Biochemistry/REU/, or by contacting the Program Director, Dr. Trevor Creamer, at Trevor.Creamer@uky.edu or 859-323-6037.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1004931</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dutch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdutc2@pop.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Trevor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Creamer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Trevor.Creamer@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7972</Code>
      <Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>J103</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>J243</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>K629</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7736</Code>
      <Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
