<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Summer Research Experience on the Impacts of Land Use and Land Cover in the Upper Green River Watershed of Western Kentucky, USA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>349806</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of Western Kentucky has been granted an NSF award to establish a Research Experience for Undergraduates Site (REU). The unifying environmental theme of this REU site is focused on land use and land cover and its impacts on water in the Upper Green River Watershed, a karst hydrologic system. The research components are all directly related to water quality, contaminant transport, and near surface atmospheric water cycling. REU students will spend 10 weeks during summer at Western Kentucky University working with a faculty mentor from the Department of Biology, Chemistry, or Geography and Geology. Students will learn in standard field techniques, collect samples and analyze data in the laboratory. In addition, they will also analyze existing environmental data sets. Eight undergraduates and four students from the Kentucky Math and Science Academy will participate in this REU site. The Academy provides advanced academic opportunities for gifted high school juniors and seniors. Each student will develop a research project linked to the impacts of land use and land cover in the Upper Green River Basin. The Upper Green River supports a great biodiversity of fish, macroinvertebrates and freshwater mussels, many of which exist only in this part of the watershed. In addition, there are rare and endangered cave-dwelling invertebrate species that have never been fully identified. The change in Land Use/Land Cover in this sensitive ecosystem further complicates these issues, including hydrologic and atmospheric responses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The student participants will also be provided opportunities to discuss ethical issues related to collection and use of data, experimental design, professional standards, and the broader impacts that environmental research may have on society. The broader impacts of this proposal are first addressed by the creative scientific research investigations undertaken by undergraduates with the corresponding promotion of training and learning. Secondly, the recruitment focus of disadvantaged students from Appalachia clearly broadens the participation of underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1004655</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cathleen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Webb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Cathleen.Webb@wku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rezaul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mahmood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rezaul.mahmood@wku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Western Kentucky University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Bowling Green</CityName>
      <ZipCode>421011016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2707454652</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Western Kentucky University</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1575</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
