<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Oklahoma Optical Initiative</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1176470</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01120000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>EPSCoR</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sian Mooney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Oklahoma Optical Initiative &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: EPS - 1006919 &lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Oklahoma Norman Campus&lt;br/&gt;Project Director: Henry J. Neeman&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This OK Inter-campus and Intra-campus Cyber Connectivity (RII C2) project would be led by the University of Oklahoma Norman Campus to benefit the entire state.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;Through the Oklahoma Optical Initiative (OOI), the OK RII C2 project plans to facilitate the ability to provision a substantial number of dedicated high performance connections, both within Oklahoma and to national and international networks (e.g., Internet2, NLR). OOI would transform Oklahoma's existing research ring from routed to optical, leveraging existing infrastructure while advancing optical switching components to a new level, facilitating substantial improvement in reliability, robustness, availability and potentially bandwidth, as well as enabling the ability to provision dedicated lambdas. This initiative will leverage extant and emerging investments by OneNet and University of Oklahoma (OU). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Individual Oklahoma institutions will achieve substantial connectivity transformations, so they can take advantage of OOI. In particular: &lt;br/&gt;(a) OU's supercomputer will have its world-facing network connectivity upgraded to 10 Gbps (10X increase);&lt;br/&gt;(b) OSU (Oklahoma State University) will be upgraded to 10 Gbps intra-campus (10x increase), from its current 1 Gbps intra-campus (but 10 Gbps ring-facing); &lt;br/&gt;(c) University of Tulsa will be upgraded to 1 Gbps (5X increase), for research use only, at no upcharge; &lt;br/&gt;(d) Langston University (LU) bandwidth for High Energy Physics (HEP) projects will be increased to 10 Gbps (100X increase), at no upcharge; &lt;br/&gt;(e) Noble bandwidth will be increased to 250 Mbps (5X increase) via a fiber Indefeasible Right to Use agreement, at no upcharge; &lt;br/&gt;(f) Rural and nonmetro connectivity will be improved, via redeploying extant optical components from the research ring to OneNet's remote hubsites. &lt;br/&gt;(g) The Oklahoma Telepresence Initiative will make High Definition telepresence available to all higher education campuses in Oklahoma.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Oklahoma currently has an RII Track 1 on bioenergy and an RII Track 2 on ecoinformatics. The Track 1, a collaboration among Oklahoma State University, the University of Oklahoma and the Samuel Roberts Noble Foundation (Noble), isn't a large consumer of network connectivity, but Noble currently is at only 45 Mbps, expected to be inadequate for emerging needs; the Track1 also includes the Oklahoma Cyberinfrastructure Initiative (OCII), which provides CI resources to 540 users at 24 institutions (including 11 of Oklahoma's 13 public universities), mostly without usage charges. The Track 2, a collaboration among OU, OSU, the University of Kansas and Kansas State University, uses substantial data, with constant collection and transformation of NASA data made available from a web portal. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Other Data-Intensive Projects include: &lt;br/&gt;(a) Oklahoma has been a longstanding leader in meteorology research, especially in real time forecasting of severe storms, including: the Center for Analysis and Prediction of Storms; the Linked Environment for Atmospheric Discovery collaboration (NSF Large Information Technology Research); development of the Advanced Regional Prediction System as an NSF Science and Technology Center and now a key developer of the Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) model; a just-awarded NSF Petascale Applications grant for Ensemble Kalman Filtering on the NSF's Blue Waters multi-petaflops system. &lt;br/&gt;(b) For the past 6 years, Oklahoma's DOE EPSCoR has supported a High Energy Physics collaboration among OU, OSU and LU, Oklahoma's only Historically Black University. In addition, OU and LU, with two other institutions, form the NSF-funded ATLAS Southwest Tier2 Center. At OU, HEP projects are expected to consume roughly 5 Gbps starting in 2010; at LU, campus networking capability is inadequate for LU's growing computing and data responsibilities. &lt;br/&gt;(c) The OU and OSU HPC centers support dozens of research teams. &lt;br/&gt;(d) The state's Science &amp; Technology (S&amp;T) plan includes bioenergy, plant science, weather and weather sensors, plus other areas that are supported under OCII but not called out in this RII C2 proposal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The Oklahoma Networking Mentorship Program will provide networking professionals from OU and OneNet to institutions across the state (20 institutions have expressed interest), to deliver presentations on the practicalities of the networking profession and job shadowing opportunities, both physical and virtual. In addition, each of the science projects described has its own extensive education program, Oklahoma Cyber-infrastructure Initiative (OCII) has its longstanding and successful SiPE education program, and Oklahoma EPSCoR has comprehensive educational and outreach programs, links to economic development and to initiatives designed to enhance public awareness of the importance of science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;K-12 students and teachers are being exposed to cutting-edge science and CI through summer technology academies, mobile science vehicles, and teacher training workshops. Undergraduate student research experiences in industry and academia are supported and talented students are being recruited into bioenergy based graduate programs. Workshops are being geared towards the education, training and integration of CI in the outreach and research components of Oklahoma's RII projects. Conferences to encourage multidisciplinary, multi-campus collaborations and to enhance faculty competitiveness in future grant submissions are being supported. An entrepreneurial workshop, a business plan competition for students along with commercialization vouchers to assess the commercial potential of researcher's inventions would foster the spirit of entrepreneurship of both students and faculty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Along with publications, website and wiki, outcomes of this RII C2 project are proposed to be disseminated via the Oklahoma Supercomputing Symposium, which in 8 years has had over 2000 attendees from 84 academic institutions in 23 states and Puerto Rico (32 in Oklahoma and 19 in 12 other EPSCoR jurisdictions), including PhD-, masters- and bachelors-granting universities, community colleges, career techs, a high school and public school systems, as well as 79 private companies, 29 government agencies (21 in Oklahoma) and 13 non-governmental organizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;RII education outreach initiatives embrace the inclusion of underrepresented groups and women, and strengthen competitiveness and diversity through collaboration with LU (Oklahoma's HBCU) and tribal college, facilitating transition from high school to college, providing culture-attuned counseling support, and promoting enhancement programs to retain students pursuing STEM disciplines. Other initiatives promote effective communication of scientific advances to enhance public awareness of the value of science to the state legislature and the general public. Collectively, the RII investments would position Oklahoma to enhance competitiveness for mainstream NSF funding.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>1176470</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>1006919</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Deaton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jed@osrhe.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neeman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hneeman@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brunson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dana.brunson@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
      <CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7217</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
