<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Characterization of Melt Stable Polyacrylonitrile Copolymers and Blends</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will provide the scientific and technological foundation for the synthesis, characterization, processing, and performance verification of melt-stable, polyacrylonitrile (PAN) copolymers and blends with poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO or PEG). These systems will provide for the first time valuable fibers, films, and molded objects that will have the solvent-free, environmental attractiveness afforded by melt fabrication. The project will largely focus on classical free radical statistical copolymerization of acrylonitrile with ion-containing comonomers and with methacrylate functional poly(ethylene oxide) macromonomer oligomers. They can be efficiently prepared in high molecular weight in DMSO. The rheological properties of the copolymers and blends will be measured as a function of temperature, time, and shear rate to confirm the thermoplastic nature of these systems and to determine compositional limits. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is based upon the growing need for sustainable, environmentally attractive, advanced macromolecular materials systems for high performance film and fiber applications ranging from energy to packaging materials and wastewater purification systems and polymer matrix carbon composites -- the latter of interest for aerospace, transportation, and windmill power. The first priority will be to investigate systems that are melt-processable and permit very low gas permeabilities and melt-spun acrylic fibers. Such materials would open broad new vistas for textile synthesis and production, which is currently not practiced in the Unites States. A major feature will involve interactions with minority women professors and students at Fisk University and at the University of South Carolina Upstate. The goal will be to develop talented diverse scientists; summer internships will be provided involving faculty and students from HBCUs and 4-year schools to broaden students' perspectives well beyond their own research projects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1006630</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>McGrath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmcgrath@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
