<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Variational methods for materials science, mechanics, and imaging</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>302464</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eugene Gartland</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Leoni&lt;br/&gt;DMS-1007989&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The central theme of this project is the application of&lt;br/&gt;modern calculus of variations to materials science, mechanics,&lt;br/&gt;and imaging. The principal investigator emphasizes the following&lt;br/&gt;specific topics:&lt;br/&gt; - Material Voids in Elastic Solids with Anisotropic Surface&lt;br/&gt;Energies. Here he studies how the qualitative features of the&lt;br/&gt;equilibrium shape of the void depend on the smoothness and&lt;br/&gt;convexity (or lack thereof) of the interfacial energy. &lt;br/&gt; - Evolution by Surface Diffusion. The principal investigator&lt;br/&gt;studies the short-time existence and regularity of solutions of a&lt;br/&gt;model of second-phase particles and material voids in a linearly&lt;br/&gt;elastic solid. &lt;br/&gt; - Non-Local Operators for Image Recovery. Here he studies&lt;br/&gt;regularity and qualitative features of solutions of a non-local&lt;br/&gt;model for image and signal processing proposed by Gilboa and&lt;br/&gt;Osher. He also takes up problems in water waves and&lt;br/&gt;micromagnetics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The central theme of this project is the application of&lt;br/&gt;modern calculus of variations to materials science, mechanics,&lt;br/&gt;and imaging. When an elastic material is subject to stresses, it&lt;br/&gt;can stretch and develop voids within the material; the shape of&lt;br/&gt;the voids affects other properties of the material. The&lt;br/&gt;principal investigator studies how the shape depends on the&lt;br/&gt;energy at the interface between the material and the void. The&lt;br/&gt;movement of interfaces by means of surface diffusion is not well&lt;br/&gt;understood when the interfacial energy is highly anisotropic. &lt;br/&gt;The investigator studies this problem, focusing on the short-time&lt;br/&gt;behavior; rigorous results here improve our understanding of&lt;br/&gt;various behaviors of materials. He also considers problems in&lt;br/&gt;image processing, water waves, and micromagnetics. The results&lt;br/&gt;and methods developed in the project are incorporated in new&lt;br/&gt;graduate courses, and some are included in a series of books that&lt;br/&gt;the investigator is writing in collaboration with I. Fonseca. &lt;br/&gt;Graduate students are involved in the project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1007989</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Giovanni</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leoni</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>giovanni@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
