<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A 2010 Workshop on Quantum-Classical Modeling of Chemical Phenomena</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Evelyn M. Goldfield</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Eitan Tadmor of the University of Maryland is supported by an award from the Theory, Models and Computational Methods program and the Computational Mathematics program for activities related to a workshop entitled "Quantum-Classical Modeling of Chemical Phenomena" to be held on March 8-10, 2010. The Center for Scientific Computing and Mathematical Modeling at the University of Maryland is hosting the workshop. In addition to Tadmor , the organizing committee consists of Victor Batista (Yale), Shi Jin (University of Wisconsin), and Millard Alexander (Maryland). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of the meeting is to bring together a group of experts to examine the current state of development of numerical techniques and to foster interdisciplinary research in the development of computational methods at the interface of quantum and classical dynamics. The list of invited speakers is multi-disciplinary, international and very diverse. The workshop organizers actively encourage participation from graduate students, postdocs, junior faculty and members of under-represented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Further information may be found at http://www.cscamm.umd.edu/programs/qcp10/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1007674</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eitan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tadmor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tadmor@cscamm.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
