<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fast simulation, large deviations, and associated Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>280000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project is concerned with developing efficient Monte Carlo algorithms for rare event simulation and the associated large deviations theory. We consider two broad classes of problems where rare events are either of direct interest or a determining factor of the performance of the Monte Carlo scheme. For the first class of problems, importance sampling and particle branching methods have proven to be powerful tools. A unifying approach for the design of these types of schemes is to exploit an important connection between well-designed schemes and the subsolutions to an associated Hamiltonian-Jacobi-Bellman equation. The approach has been successfully applied in the setting of piecewise homogenous dynamics such as queueing networks. The research project aims to consider more complicated models such as small noise diffusions with fast oscillating components where the dynamics are fully nonlinear. With regard to the second class of problems, a particularly important topic is the approximation of the invariant distribution for systems with multiple metastable states by the occupation measure of a related Markov process. Moving from one metastable state to another is a rare event, and its treatment is the key question in the design of efficient Monte Carlo schemes. There are many ad hoc algorithms available. However, these algorithms do not always work well and have to be applied with some care. The research project will rigorously analyze some existing algorithms as well as design new ones with better performance. Two classes of fast simulation schemes that are of particular interest for this problem are parallel tempering and importance sampling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In many branches of science, such as biology, chemistry, physics, and engineering, the study of rare events or events with very little chance of happening is often of central interest. For example, in the study of proteins or biomolecules, physics-based models are employed to study the interaction of atoms or molecules. Due to the complexity of the model, analytical calculation is impossible, and the primary tool of analysis is simulation, which provides valuable insight into the dynamic evolution of the system. However, the simulation can take an exceedingly long time before the system moves from one configuration to another (a rare event). In the context of highly reliable and secure systems, the rare event is something to be avoided, and accurate assessment is a key tool for purposes of design. To accelerate simulations in situations with important rare events, many ad hoc algorithms have been proposed. For the many schemes that lack a firm theoretical foundation, key design quantities are usually selected only on the basis of prior experience. As a consequence, these schemes may work in specialized situations, but can also perform quite poorly in general. This research project has two goals. One is the rigorous analysis of existing schemes, which can be very useful in understanding the power of the schemes as well as their limitations. The second goal is to develop, based on the analysis of existing approaches, new schemes whose performance is provably better than the existing ones. This work will be of use not only to theoreticians who are interested rare event simulation, but also to a large community of practitioners and scientists who use simulation as a basic tool for their research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1008331</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dupuis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dupuis@cfm.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hui</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>huiwang@cfm.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
