<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RET Site in Engineering:Connecting with Community Colleges</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>449948</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a three-year continuing award to support a Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) in Engineering Site program at the University of Maryland (UMD)College Park entitled, "RET Site in Engineering:Connecting with Community Colleges under the direction of Dr. Isabel K. Lloyd. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RET in Engineering Site proposes a transformative exchange between five Maryland community colleges (CC) and UMD faculty over a six-week summer program. These community colleges provide most the UMD College of Engineering's transfer students and serve large numbers of students from underrepresented groups, including minorities, women, and economically disadvantaged students. The focus of the program is to forge intellectual connections across disciplines as well as institutional connections across campuses. A total of thirty-six, community college faculty, twelve each summer for three years, will be mentored by UMD faculty and will pursue cutting edge research in engineering, integrate fundamental concepts in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) together with technological innovation into community college STEM classrooms. Institutional connections will be developed and strengthened, to facilitate successful transition of associate degree students into the Clark School st the University of Maryland. This RET Site will demonstrate that two-year colleges and research universities can work together to prepare students to join the 21st Century workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1009823</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Isabel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lloyd</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>illoyd@eng.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leigh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>labts@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
