<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: The Evolution and Systematics of the Opuntia humifusa complex (Cactaceae)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13450</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Ranker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Among cacti, the genus Opuntia is a large group of plant species occurring naturally in a variety of dry habitats throughout the Americas. The evolution and genealogical relationships of this group remains poorly understood; consequently, this study will include the majority of species in the genus to assess their evolution using advanced molecular methods. A smaller group of species occurs in the United States and the Caribbean, this smaller group is known as the Opuntia humifusa complex. This smaller group will be studied in more detail to determine the genetic diversification of the member of this subgroup and what are the processes that potential give rise to new specie. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Species of Opuntia are known for their many medicinal and commercial uses, such as to lower blood glucose levels in diabetics and to provide edible products for people and livestock. These species also are important components of the areas in which they live, providing shelter and nourishment for wildlife and soil stabilization. Understanding relationships of these species will allow researchers to pinpoint those that may be of more medicinal, commercial, and conservation value. This project will allow for the understanding of species formation and help scientists determine how this and other groups of plants may add to biodiversity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1011270</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lucas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Majure</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lmajure@dbg.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Soltis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dsoltis@botany.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
