<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Interspecific interactions over a latitudinal resource gradient: a graphical modeling approach using fig wasps</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13411</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saran Twombly</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Ecological interactions between species are often inferred by looking for correlations in abundance between species pairs while disregarding influences of other members of the community. Through the use of computer simulations and available abundance data from a complex insect community (fig wasps), this project will determine the accuracy of a multi-species graphical modeling approach to reveal networks of beneficial and antagonistic ecological interactions among species. After determining the most accurate method of modeling ecological interactions, additional fig-wasp abundance data will be collected from six locations along the Baja Peninsula to test whether or not these interactions, both at the level of species pairs and communities as a whole, are static or dynamic over a large geographic range.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Food webs often rely on predator-prey interactions, and more complete models of ecological networks involving all types of interspecific interactions (including competition, mutualism, and parasitism) are still rare. This project will develop a more inclusive model of ecological communities. The resulting model will also show how the structure of ecological networks is affected by changing environmental conditions, including human-caused habitat fragmentation and global climate change. A graduate student and an undergraduate student will participate in the research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1011277</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nason</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jnason@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Duthie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aduthie@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
