<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Synthetically Versatile C-H Activation Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will focus on the development of broadly useful Pd- and Cu-catalyzed C-H activation/trifluoromethylation and C-H activation/halogenation reactions (including fluorination). Despite recent progress on this front using classic cyclometalation, the discovery of analogous reactivity with synthetically useful substrates containing weakly coordinating functional groups remains a significant challenge. Extensive experimental work will be performed to find solutions to such problems based upon well supported hypotheses. In addition, the knowledge learned from the studies to establish new catalytic transformations and to probe the underlying reaction mechanisms will be applied to develop enantioselective C-H halogenation reactions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Chemical Synthesis program is supporting the research of Professor Jin-Quan Yu of the Department of Chemistry at The Scripps Research Institute. Professor Yu's research efforts focus on the discovery and development of synthetically versatile C-H functionalization reactions. These transformations represent environmentally benign methods for chemical synthesis in that they may drastically shorten synthetic sequences. New technologies based on these reactions could have a substantial impact on synthetic planning and immediate practical applications in the pharmaceutical and agrochemical industries. In addition, this project will provide excellent training to both graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. It also involves outreach activities to high school students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1011898</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jin-Quan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yu200@scripps.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The Scripps Research Institute</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920371000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8587848653</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10550 N TORREY PINES RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6878</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1948</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
