<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Inferring weak and strong selection with comparative genomic data from sea urchins</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14216</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George W. Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Genetic differences that accumulate between species can result from the action of either random genetic drift or natural selection. However, the relative importance of drift vs. selection in causing the differences observed between species remains poorly understood. This study will use closely related species of Strongylocentrotid sea urchins to address several fundamental questions in the field of evolutionary genetics. First, what proportion of the genetic changes observed between species has been caused by natural selection? Second, have the selected changes occurred recently within existing species or do they reflect adaptation occurring further back in time? Third, what are the specific DNA regions that show evidence of past natural selection and can these changes be explained by known biological processes (such as reproduction or disease resistance)? The PIs will use complete genome sequences from eight species of sea urchin to investigate these questions. Their results will provide new insights into the importance of selection as a force for genome evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will initiate collaborations between biologists and biological statisticians. Undergraduates will participate in the project and learn techniques of experimental design and data analysis. The project places a high priority on the dissemination of computational and analytic tools to the broader scientific community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1011061</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Grant</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pogson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pogson@darwin.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kord</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kober</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kober@biology.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
