<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Preparation and Characterization of Dendrimer Templated Au-M Nanoparticles and Catalysts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>260000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Bert D. Chandler of Trinity University is supported by the Chemical Catalysis Program in the Division of Chemistry to develop new synthetic techniques for the preparation of solid oxide supported bimetallic nanoparticle catalysts and study reaction mechanisms over these heterogeneous catalysts. The bimetallic nanoparticles will be prepared in solution, using a dendrimer encapsulation synthetic route and then deposited onto high surface area support. Two kinetics-based analytical techniques will be employed to probe and evaluate the catalytic activity of the bimetallic nanoparticles: Selective inhibition will be used to interrogate the CO oxidation active sites and Hammett relationships for aerobic benzyl alcohol oxidation will be used to probe changes in nanoparticle surface charge. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Supported bimetallic nanoparticles are an important class of heterogeneous catalysts that are employed throughout the chemical industry. A fundamental understanding of the interplay between metal functions in bimetallic catalysts will informs the design of new catalysts with less reliance on expensive platinum group metals. Integrating undergraduate students in a primarily undergraduate institution into this research project early in their chemical career will motivate them to pursue this line of research and consequently enhance the chemical catalysis workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1012395</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chandler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bert.chandler@trinity.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trinity University</Name>
      <CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782127200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2109997246</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Trinity Place</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
