<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Biotechnology of Supramolecular Complexes of Pyrene-Based Fluorescent Dyes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>391825</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Vladimir Sidorov and coworkers at the Chemistry Department of Virginia Commonwealth University have identified a family of cyclen-based receptors for water-soluble anionic dyes. With the support from the Macromolecular, Supramolecular, and Nanochemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry at NSF, the Sidorov group is developing techniques based on cyclen-based receptors for monitoring biomembrane processes. Cyclen-based receptors that bind anionic dyes and dyes conjugated to biologically-relevant substrates will be designed and synthesized. Techniques based on these receptors will be developed for membrane leakage assay, intra-cellular trafficking of the liposomal content, the analysis of drug delivery systems, and the separation of heparin oligomers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research, which employs supramolecular chemistry in techniques for monitoring biomembrane processes and for separating bioactive compounds, would have implications for human therapeutics and broadly impact the bioorganic and biological communities. The research training and educational activities of this project would contribute to human resource development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1012884</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sidorov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vasidorov@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
      <CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1982</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
