<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Building a Flexible, Technology Adaptive Architecture to Support Processing of Content by Knowledge Workers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Errol Arkilic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project addresses the gap between the capabilities of today's natural language processing systems and the accuracy requirements of knowledge workers (analysts and researchers) in language-sensitive fields such as public relations, foreign affairs, and crisis management. Knowledge workers in many organizations monitor and analyze print and web coverage for content of interest. When the volume of search results is large, some filter, classify and score the results with Natural Language Processing (NLP) systems using complex libraries of words, patterns, and context-specific algorithms. However, users complain that these systems fall short of desired accuracy, missing rhetorical devices such as irony, sarcasm, metaphors, double entendre, and improperly interpreting references. Users with high thresholds for accuracy thus turn to manual processes to either supplement or substitute for technology. This project will test a prototype architecture allowing rapid insertion, testing, and adaptation of text analysis algorithms and a workflow process efficiently integrating human review judgment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Once commercialized, the system will enable more rapid adoption of technology by knowledge workers. In fields with high accuracy requirements, the need for human judgment has constrained technology use to discrete areas like search, while in subsequent processing steps, analysts must manually capture, classify, score, analyze, and report on the output.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1013935</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koefoot</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ekoefoot@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>PublicRelay, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Reston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>201910000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7034728337</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>12310 Pinecrest</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
