<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Toward a full vector model of depositional remanent magnetization and the global sedimentary paleointensity data base</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>208846</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stephen S. Harlan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The geomagnetic field acts both as an umbrella, shielding us from cosmic radiation and as a window, offering one of the few glimpses of the inner workings of the Earth. Ancient records of the geomagnetic field can inform us about dynamics of the early Earth and changes in boundary conditions through time. Thanks to its essentially dipolar nature, the field has acted as a guide, pointing to the axis of rotation thereby providing latitudinal information for both explorers and geologists. Human measurements of the geomagnetic field date to about a millenium and are quite sparse prior to about 400 years ago. Knowledge of what the field has done in the past relies on accidental records carried by the magnetization of geological and archaeological materials. Obtaining meaningful information from such materials requires an understanding of complex recording processes, which are poorly understood for most natural materials as these deviate from the ideal tractable to theory. Some of the most important archives for the history of the geomagnetic field are found in sediments and sedimentary rocks. Such materials can preserve quasi-continuous records of the geomagnetic field vector, which can be turned into time series with rather tight age control. Because of their many advantages, sediments and sedimentary rocks have been the subject of intense study by paleomagnetists for over sixty years. There are over 100 publications reporting results of ancient field intensity based on sedimentary materials. Yet how sediments get magnetized and how best to retrieve the geomagnetic field vector are still not well understood. This is the topic of the present proposal. In this study, we are constructing numerical models designed to explain experimental data that we are obtaining through laboratory redeposition experiments under carefully controlled conditions. These models with then be used to make specific predictions testable with published data sets. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Our work has significant impacts throughout the geosciences, contributing to the understanding of one of the most important physical properties of planet Earth, its magnetic field. It will contribute to the understanding of many fundamental processes, including plate motion constraints from paleomagnetic data, the role of the inner core in controlling the geomagnetic field, and establishing the average strength of the dipole moment to place recent observations in perspective. Constraints on the geomagnetic field are important to those in the deep Earth community who study the dynamical processes in Earth's deep interior. Through this grant we will augment the publicly accessible database for magnetic information (MagIC), greatly expanding its utility to the broader geoscience community. This is particularly important as the role of the Earth's magnetic field in the climatic system undergoes increased scrutiny. Finally, it will serve as the doctoral dissertation project of a graduate student at the Scripps Institute of Oceanography.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1013192</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tauxe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ltauxe@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
