<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IDR: Rapid, three-dimensional microscopy of cell-cell interactions in suspension</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>605639</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1014838&lt;br/&gt;Huser&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a unique state-of-the-art technology to obtain rapid three-dimensional maps of the function and structure of an extremely important class of cells: immune cells. It will utilize rapid optical imaging at high spatial and temporal resolution of suspension cells in their most natural environment (i.e. freely suspended without substrates present). This new instrument will allow one to measure and record physiological changes in cells in 3 dimensions at millisecond time scales. This system will lead to significant advancement in multiple scientific disciplines, i.e. cellular imaging, cell biology, immunology, virology, etc. by enabling the quantitative assessment of cellular organization and reorganization due to changes in their environment at the sub-cellular level in real-time. This novel instrumentation will significantly enhance the ability to quantify rapid cellular processes of suspended immune cells at the molecular level, something that is not possible with current technology. It will enable the study cellular interactions with a great degree of control by enabling one to manipulate and increase the number of cellular interactions and follow them dynamically.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1014838</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>trhuser@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7236</Code>
      <Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>005E</Code>
      <Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>014E</Code>
      <Text>NANOBIOTECH AND NANOTOXICOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7951</Code>
      <Text>ENG INTERDISC RES (IDR)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7236</Code>
      <Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
