<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Heterogeneous Network Connectivity and Capacity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>424524</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>phillip regalia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A common characteristic of the emerging generation of wireless networks is their heterogeneity: these networks consist of devices with very different capabilities and requirements sharing overlapping spectrum. Intelligent home networks consisting of HD streaming, gaming consoles, wireless routers, and energy monitoring devices is one example; cognitive networks (utilizing white spaces), and femtocell networks being two more. Somewhat surprisingly, nearly all engineering design, analysis, and knowledge is based entirely on the assumption of node homogeneity Our research involves obtaining fundamental new laws and limits for the connectivity and capacity of heterogeneous wireless networks. The nature of such limits is expected to provide a roadmap for better design principles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The novelty of this research is based on a new application of marked point processes, where the points model the node locations and marks characterize essential traits of the node, like their bandwidth and power. To calculate the desired statistical properties of the network, we introduce and advance new mathematical tools such as Tauberian theory, series of random functions, Stein approximation theory, and sub-ergodic theory. In addition to the basic research aspect of this project, we are pursuing an energetic program of technology transfer with several leading companies developing heterogeneous networks and planning standards contributions and other intellectual property development. This is consistent with the PI's past track record.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1016649</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>RadhaKrishna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ganti</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rganti@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Andrews</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jandrews@ece.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
