<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dynamical and Chemical Diagnosis of Stratosphere-Troposphere Analyses of Regional Transport 2008 (START08) Data</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>477158</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anjuli S. Bamzai</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intrusions of tropospheric air can have a significant effect on the concentrations of radiatively active trace gases in the extratropical lower stratosphere and thus on the global energy balance. This project will analyze the transport of tropical upper tropospheric air into the extratropical lower stratosphere using in situ observations and model simulations. It will use data collected by the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR)/National Science Foundation (NSF) Gulfstream V (GV) aircraft during the Stratosphere-Troposphere Analyses of Regional Transport 2008 (START08) field program to study transport in the upper troposphere and lower stratosphere (UT/LS) and its impact on atmospheric composition. The research will characterize the composition, frequency, location, and magnitude of tropospheric intrusions during the START08 period. The methods to be applied include trajectory analysis, trace species analysis, and correlations between multiple trace species to establish source air mass and mixing properties. Dynamical systems methods will be used to study the detailed structure of irreversible transport events and map their occurrence. The START08 data will also be used to evaluate the performance of NCAR Whole Atmosphere Community Climate Model (WACCM) simulations of chemistry and transport.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will advance our scientific understanding of dynamical, chemical, and radiative processes in the UT/LS, which has the potential to improve model simulations of anthropogenic climate change. Analysis of the START08 data will also advance the development of the GV aircraft as a high-capability observing system. This project will also contribute to the development of human resources in science by training graduate students for research careers and preparing undergraduate students for future graduate study or technical careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1016191</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bowman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>k-bowman@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5740</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
