<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III: Small: Active Learning of Language Models for Information Extraction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>183736</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project studies methods for extracting accurate knowledge bases from the &lt;br/&gt;Web. Fully-automated Web information extraction techniques are massively &lt;br/&gt;scalable, but have accuracy and coverage limitations. This proposal &lt;br/&gt;investigates how to improve automated extraction techniques by introducing &lt;br/&gt;carefully-selected human guidance. The proposed system continually extracts &lt;br/&gt;knowledge from the Web, along the way dynamically synthesizing and issuing &lt;br/&gt;queries to humans to increase the accuracy of the system's knowledge base and &lt;br/&gt;extractors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The approach extends the PI's previous work utilizing statistical language &lt;br/&gt;models (SLMs) for information extraction. Novel SLMs are investigated for &lt;br/&gt;unifying the extraction of relational data expressed in Web tables with &lt;br/&gt;extraction from free text. New active learning techniques utilize the models &lt;br/&gt;to identify "high-leverage" queries -- requesting, for example, textual &lt;br/&gt;extraction patterns that when retrieved from the Web yield thousands of novel &lt;br/&gt;extractions. The queries investigated are mostly amenable to non-experts, &lt;br/&gt;meaning that much of the human input can be acquired at scale via online &lt;br/&gt;mass-collaboration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this project lies in the potential for accurate Web &lt;br/&gt;extraction to radically improve Web search, allowing users to answer &lt;br/&gt;complicated questions by synthesizing information across multiple Web pages. &lt;br/&gt;In domains like medicine and biology, mining extracted knowledge bases could &lt;br/&gt;lead to important discoveries and novel therapies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Further information may be found at the project web page:&lt;br/&gt;http://wail.eecs.northwestern.edu/projects/activelms/index.html</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1016754</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Downey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddowney@eecs.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
