<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Discrete Simulation of Fluid Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>22500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leland M. Jameson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The conference on discrete simulation of fluid dynamics (dsfd.org) is the premier forum to discuss novel numerical methods for fluid flow including lattice gas automata (LGA), the lattice Boltzmann equation (LBE), discrete velocity methods (DVM), dissipative particle dynamics (DPD), smoothed-particle hydrodynamics (SPH), direct simulation Monte Carlo (DSMC), stochastic rotation dynamics (SRD), molecular dynamics (MD), and hybrid methods. The 19. meeting is held July 5-9, 2010 in Rome. Because of the significant cost of airfare underfunded researchers need additional support to attend meeting. The NSF funds provide partial support for 18 junior faculty members, postdocs and students from the US to present their research at this meeting. A local committee at North Dakota State University selected the travel support based on need, whether the applicant belongs to an underrepresented group, and the scientific soundness of the proposed research presentation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advances in materials, nanotechnology, information technology and biotechnology increasingly rely on novel numerical algorithms. So the training of students and postdocs who are developing the next generation of these methods is of paramount importance. This grant provides the most promising young researchers with the opportunity to learn about the newest developments from their peers, to exchange ideas with researchers who share similar interests, and the opportunity to present their own research results at a specialized conference in the field of novel numerical algorithms for the simulation of fluid dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1016578</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wagner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alexander.wagner@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Dakota State University Fargo</Name>
      <CityName>FARGO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7012318045</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Dept 4000 - PO Box 6050</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>ND</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
