<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI: Small: RUI: Spatial Prototypes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>245168</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project uses humanoid robots to study how the human perceptual process drives the creation of spatial representations suitable for memory and for spatial reasoning. The primary goal is to take extended visual streams of information and to parse them into individual events. Each of these events in turn can be represented by a generic spatial data structure capable of supporting both memory for the event and reasoning about it. Because the representations are generic, future events should also be able to evoke them allowing them to be used predictively. To do this the research team models certain aspects of the human visual system, namely that it is split into two parts. The spatial part of the visual system is called the ?dorsal? system. The dorsal system is highly sensitive to change in the visual field that therefore serves as the critical component in our parsing algorithm. Moments of great visual change trigger the creation of a generic visual representation. When these individual representations are linked they form a kind of episodic memory of an event. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A significant aspect of the project is that it involves training undergraduates to do research. The application is RoboCup, a global competition featuring autonomous soccer-playing robots. The Bowdoin College RoboCup team was formed to get undergraduates involved in research early in their academic careers. The students on the team not only attend competitions worldwide, but also get to share their work with their peers internationally. The team?s codebase is publicly available and is monitored and used by numerous universities worldwide.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1017983</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>echown@bowdoin.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Bowdoin College</Name>
      <CityName>Brunswick</CityName>
      <ZipCode>040118451</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2077253767</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6000 COLLEGE STA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maine</StateName>
      <StateCode>ME</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
