<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Paper Competition and Student Volunteers for Virtual Participation at the 2010 IEEE MTT-S International Microwave Symposium. To be Held in Anaheim, CA on May 23-28, 2010.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this activity is to provide partial travel support for ten students from U.S. universities to attend the 2010 IEEE MTT-S International Microwave Symposium (IMS). The IMS is the annual meeting of the Microwave Theory and Techniques Society (MTT-S) of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, Inc. (IEEE). The IMS is also the major international symposium in the microwave field and a focus of research results in wireless telecommunications. The 2010 IMS will be held in Anaheim, CA, USA on May 23-28, 2010.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The main impact is primarily educational, as the travel support allows students' participation in IMS 2010. This participation is an important part of the education process. It provides students with the opportunity to be exposed to new areas of research and to interact with more experienced researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: Student participation at the IMS not only promotes education but also fosters the next generation of microwave engineers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1018259</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Satish</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ssharma@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Institute of Electrical &amp; Electronics Engineers, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088544141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7325626520</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>445 HOES LANE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
