<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pan American Current Research on Fluid Inclusions Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>21350</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030107</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William P. Leeman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: This proposal requests funds to pay costs for students, post-doctorates, assistant professors, and other early-career scientists to attend the June, 2010, Pan American Current Research on Fluid Inclusions conference (PACROFI). This conference focuses on fluid inclusion research that aims to elucidate magmatic hydrothermal processes associated with ore deposit formation, volcanic hazard mitigation and element recycling in subduction zones. This research provides the most direct opportunity to determine compositions of ancient geologic fluids, as well as pressure, temperature and chemical conditions attending their formation. The PACROFI meetings provide an important forum for exchange of scientific results and ideas, and communication between established and early-career scientists in this reseach area. The attendance of early-career scientists is considered essential, because they bring innovative ideas to the science, and because they will lead future research in this field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The requested funds will offset participation costs for some 25 student attendees, as well as partial support for 10 early-career scientists. Financial support for these individuals is necessary as many lack the resources to attend otherwise. The $21,350 requested will cover registration, housing and travel for the student attendees, and registration and housing for 10 early-career scientists (approximately 33% and 8%, respectively, of the total attendees). This support may make a significant difference in the make-up of attendees at the meeting and it will have an important and positive impact on the younger generation of inclusion researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1019587</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cline</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jean.cline@unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Simon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>simonac@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nevada Las Vegas</Name>
      <CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
      <ZipCode>891541055</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7028951357</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4505 MARYLAND PARKWAY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1573</Code>
      <Text>PETROLOGY AND GEOCHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
