<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Conference Sponsorship for the Third International Conference on Social Computing, Behavioral Modeling, and Prediction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ephraim P. Glinert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Conference on Social Computing, Behavioral Modeling, and Prediction provides an interdisciplinary platform to encourage researchers of traditionally disjoint fields such as sociology, psychology, behavioral science, cognitive science, mathematics, computer science, religious studies, and engineering to exchange ideas and findings, enhance mutual understanding of state&amp;#8208;of&amp;#8208;the art development in individual fields, develop cross&amp;#8208;discipline awareness, promote collaborative research opportunities, and offer a conducive environment for graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the last few years, the emergence of the social web has had a profound influence on computing and on society. A pertinent example stems from social networks where individuals from various cultural and social backgrounds interact and exchange information. In such a scenario, it will be useful to understand the development of such social networks and the behavior of individuals who are part of such networks to gain insight into different cultures and patterns of social behavior that can form the basis for predictive models. The focus of this workshop is not only on applications pf social computing but also on the encompassing research from varied areas that can provide insight. Computer scientists are key members of this community of researchers but social scientists are integral as well.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is the third event in a series on this topic and it has developed into an international conference. The conference provides a common ground for emerging research topics in the area. This conference will create awareness among the community about the uses of such research to various areas and will result in a proceedings published as a book by Springer.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1019597</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Huan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hliu@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
