<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Correlated Electron Systems Gordon Research Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniele Finotello</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will support student and postdoc participation at the 2010 Gordon Research Conferences (GRC) on Correlated Electron Systems to be held at the Mount Holyoke College, MA, June 13-18. The subject is developing rapidly, driven both by high-resolution and novel measurement techniques and remarkable recent theoretical developments. The conference consists of a broad swath of emerging ideas such as topological insulators, non-Abelian statistics and quantum computation, novel superconductors, and graphene amongst other topics. It is very likely that new technologies will emerge from these ideas and it is important that students and postdocs are well versed in these ideas to make important contributions to the society in the future. The conference will provide a unique opportunity for students and postdocs to further their careers by not only engaging in leading edge science, but also an opportunity for them to network with the leaders and their peers in the field. The guiding principle of a GRC is unique because of its emphasis in presentation of new, unpublished work and the free, unhampered discussion that follows, consistent with its "off the record" policy. Every effort is being made to involve a diverse group of participants and underrepresented minorities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1019153</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sudip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chakravarty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sudip@physics.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
