<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Factorization and Quark Imaging in Exclusive Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>316228</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kenneth Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project covers a research program of fundamental importance for our understanding of the structure of matter and the origin of mass. The focus is on experimental investigations of hadron structure through exclusive production and detection of a single meson or photon. Such processes allow us to gain both a quantitative description and a visualization (tomographic image) of the behavior of strongly interacting systems. This is achieved through the language of Generalized Parton Distributions (GPDs), which can be measured in a regime where the hard scattering of the probe on a single quark can be factorized from the residual soft interaction that carries the information about the GPDs. Thus, tests of factorization in the kinematics of Jefferson Lab, both today and after the 12 GeV energy upgrade, are essential for the interpretation of GPD data, and in turn for our understanding of nucleon structure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The participation of postdoctoral researchers, graduate students, and undergraduate students is an integral part of the project, providing young scientists with opportunities to further their training and education. These will include learning nuclear physics concepts, getting hands-on experience in development of hardware and software, as well as participating in and contributing to cutting edge experiments at a major national laboratory, providing exposure to a broad international scientific community. The PI has considerable experience working with minority students, and by providing a female role model, she could encourage women to pursue advanced studies in physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1019521</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tanja</FirstName>
      <LastName>Horn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hornt@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Catholic University of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200640001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026355000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>620 Michigan Ave.N.E.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1232</Code>
      <Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
