<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Tribology Gordon Research Conference: Challenges at the Buried Interface; Colby College, Waterville, Maine; June 27 - July 2, 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Clark V. Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will provide partial support for attendees of the 2010 Gordon Conference on Tribology: Challenges at the Buried Interface to be held June 27 - July 2, 2010 at Colby College, Maine, USA. Tribology is the study of friction, wear &amp; lubrication. It is an extremely complex and multi-disciplinary field that involves processes over a wide range of size and time scales. The biennial Gordon Research Conference on Tribology is a unique forum for gathering experts in disparate fields to advance our understanding of the complex problems tribology presents. Leading scientists and engineers from universities, national laboratories and industry meet with young scientists and newcomers to tribology for one week of formal and informal discussions on state-of-the art issues. This opportunity for a lively and open exchange of new ideas shapes the future of the field. Addressing many of the great challenges in tribology will require an improved understanding of the buried interface that transmits forces between sliding solids. The 2010 Gordon Research Conference will focus on new experiments, theories and computer simulations that further understanding of the physics, chemistry and mechanics of the buried interface&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tribology affects nearly every aspect of our daily lives and technology. Improved understanding of the buried interface will have a profound impact on applications in aircraft and car engines, hip joints and cosmetics, shrinking devices to micro- and nanometer scales, and expanding the range of temperatures, speeds, and chemical environments where devices operate. The Gordon Conference is a key mechanism for linking the basic sciences with an engineering discipline of significant importance to the U.S. and World economies. Tribology advances require a constant flux of new ideas between these researchers and disciplines. The conference also provides opportunities for young investigators, students and those new to tribology to learn from those with a deep understanding of tribological problems and cutting edge approaches. This proposal focuses on providing support for conference fees and/or travel expenses that will enable key participants to attend the Gordon Conference. We will strive for gender balance and also favor under-represented ethnic minority or disabled individuals that apply. Support from this grant will play a particularly important role in allowing attendance of students, postdoctoral fellows and junior faculty that would otherwise not have funds.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1019403</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Robbins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mr@pha.jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/01/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
