<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transition to College Mathematics and Statistics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3495494</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen King</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Transitions to College Mathematics and Statistics project is developing a mathematics course for the fourth year of high school. The course builds on the NSF-supported Core-Plus Mathematics curriculum and provides an alternative to the Calculus course that is now in place. The new course is being designed for students who will enter post-secondary education and will major in programs not requiring Calculus. The new course includes mathematics from a problem-solving or applications perspective, and serves as a bridge to college mathematics and statistics. Unit topics include functions, modeling, algebraic strategies, binomial distributions, and information processing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is creating both a print version and a digital version of the course. Students are taught to use software tools such as spreadsheets, data analysis tools, interactive geometry programs, and computer algebra systems. These tools are embedded in the curriculum and allow students to apply the mathematics they are learning in interesting and relevant problems. The lessons include hyperlinks that allow students to have immediate access to related text. The designers are exploring the incorporation of video, access to language translation software, and the use of public domain, learner-centered software tools. One goal of the course is to increase student access to needed tools and information and to promote flexibility in how the materials are used. The project will conduct field tests of the materials and will implement an extensive formative evaluation plan where staff will visit classrooms and interview students. The summative evaluation will be conducted by an evaluator at the University of Missouri, and will focus on student achievement as measured by ACT/SAT scores, GPA, placement data, and course-taking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Transitions to College Mathematics and Statistics course provides a mathematics course that prepares high school students to transition into college mathematics and statistics courses that are designed to support non-scientific fields. It provides a viable, interesting, and useful technology-based course in the fourth year of high school. The course will also provide an effective way to help schools meet the college and career readiness standards that states have adopted.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1020312</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hirsch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>christian.hirsch@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Western Michigan University</Name>
      <CityName>Kalamazoo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2693878298</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1903 West Michigan Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7645</Code>
      <Text>DISCOVERY RESEARCH K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
