<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RIG: Aboveground and belowground effects of multi-species herbivory across a successional gradient in tallgrass prairie</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>184021</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010209</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda Deegan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Mammalian herbivores are a significant driver of plant species composition in tallgrass prairie. Despite their demonstrated importance and ubiquity in prairies, considerable uncertainty remains concerning the interactive effects of mammalian herbivores in prairie ecosystems. This project will use an existing long-term prairie restoration with sites of different ages to examine the interactive effects of three dominant herbivore species -- deer, rabbits, and voles -- on plant community composition and rates of soil carbon and nutrient cycling. Herbivore exclosures will be established in prairies of different ages to determine how the influence of herbivory changes through time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will improve our understanding of the role of herbivory in restored prairie ecosystems. Prairie restorations rarely take into account the importance of herbivores, thus the project has important implications for the management and restoration of grassland ecosystems. This research will integrate research, outreach, and education with undergraduate students, K-12 students, and the community. The project will recruit students from underrepresented groups for summer research opportunities for undergraduates. In addition, the proximity of the project to the college campus provides opportunities for both K-12 and community education. Finally, the project will enhance undergraduate education in ecology through the development of new inquiry-based laboratory activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1021194</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hernandez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dhernand@carleton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carleton College</Name>
      <CityName>Northfield</CityName>
      <ZipCode>550574001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5072224303</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One North College Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
