<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RIG: Crosstalk between the Endocytosis and Cell Division machineries</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174946</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: Endocytosis is the process by which cells engulf portions of the plasma membrane to uptake nutrients and to control membrane composition and surface area. Upon completion of this research, this concept is expected to change by demonstrating that Endocytosis can also lead to changes in cell proliferation by removing key molecules from the cell surface. Specifically, the central hypothesis of this project is that the yeast endocytic protein Ent2 binds the cell division regulator Bem3 and promotes its Endocytosis. This hypothesis will be tested by pursuing the following goals: 1. To determine the intracellular dynamics of fluorescently-tagged Ent2 and Bem3 together and in relation to other endocytic proteins using time-lapse microscopy. 2. To establish the nature of the functional link between Ent2 and other endocytic proteins for Bem3 endocytosis using molecular and genetic techniques. This project is innovative and important because it will contribute to establish novel mechanisms by which endocytosis and cell division are coordinated. &lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: The second equally important objective of this project is to contribute to the education of the public on the topics of Endocytosis, cell regulatory mechanisms and the importance of the baker yeast as model organism. This objective will be fulfilled by pursuing the following goals: 1. To disseminate knowledge relevant to this investigation. 1.1-Development of a webpage entirely dedicated to this project. This hyperlinked page will be devoted to the dissemination of general concepts related to Endocytosis and cell division as well as of the novel results of this project. 1.2- Tours to the lab: Open to students and the public, aimed to learn about the objectives, methods and results of this research area. 2. To integrate research and education. 2.1. New lectures will be developed for undergraduate and graduate courses including findings resulting from this project. 2.2. To educate about the importance of yeast as relevant eukaryotic model. 3. Active recruitment of new students to research, with special emphasis towards underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1021377</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>R. Claudio</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aguilar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>raguilar@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
