<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Spatial and Temporal Mapping of the Suprachiasmatic Nucleus Transcriptome</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>382000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Edda (Floh) Thiels</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological rhythms in physiology and behavior, such as the sleep/wake cycle, are regulated by an internal biological clock located at the base of the brain in the hypothalamus. This clock (located in a brain region called the suprachiasmatic nucleus, or SCN) has a well-defined structure that has many features that are conserved across mammalian species. The ways in which the complexities of this brain region contribute to the function of organisms are not fully understood. The SCN appears to have regions devoted to processing sensory input and generating rhythmic output. Using a gene-expression based approach, this project aims to distinguish the functions of these subregions of the clock and how they contribute to the overall function of the organism. It is anticipated that the results of these experiments will reveal novel information about how the structure of the biological clock relates to its function, and how different portions of the clock carry out different functions. This project will significantly impact our current understanding of clock function, which has common mechanisms in nearly all animals. Gene expression data will be deposited in the National Library of Medicine's Gene Expression Omnibus where it will be available to other researchers and the public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1021957</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mintz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>emintz@kent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kent State University</Name>
      <CityName>KENT</CityName>
      <ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3306722070</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF THE COMPTROLLER</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7714</Code>
      <Text>MODULATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1096</Code>
      <Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
