<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research (Arabidopsis 2010): Ecological Genomics of Adaptation to the Environment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>587908</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Scheiner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research investigates the ecological and genetic mechanisms that allow the plant Arabidopsis thaliana to adapt (grow, survive and reproduce) to different natural environments. Using wild populations from the extremes of a natural gradient in temperature and length of daylight, the investigators will identify the traits and genes that govern plant performance in nature. Traits of particular interest include flowering time, freezing and drought tolerance, and the capacity of plants to photosynthesize (make energy from sunlight) under conditions of physiological stress. The investigators will identify the genes that contribute to adaptation in nature and the magnitude of the effect of individual genes. A major goal of this work is to investigate the importance of genes that have positive effects in one environment but negative effects in other environments. Such genes are poorly understood but are thought to play a key role in adaptation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study will provide a deeper understanding of the mechanisms that allow plants to cope with different environments and has the potential to provide genetic tools for producing new varieties of plants/crops. In addition, the study system is well suited to investigate the possible consequences of global climate change and the potential of plants to adapt to rapidly changing conditions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1022236</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>william.adams@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Demmig-Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>barbara.demmig-adams@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1141</Code>
      <Text>PHYSIOLOG &amp; STRUCTURAL SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1684</Code>
      <Text>THE 2010 PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
