<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Epigenetics of RNA Based Silencing and Transposon Control in Drosophila virilis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>678711</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anthony Garza</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In sexual species, selfish genes known as transposable elements (TEs) can spread within the genome to the detriment of the host. In fact, nearly 40% of the human genome is comprised of such elements. While generally harmful, TEs have a complex symbiotic relationship with their hosts. Recent studies in plants, fungi and animals have demonstrated the existence of an ancient, RNA-based immune system that protects against these selfish genes. Studies have also shown that the female germline plays a special role in genome defense by transmitting small silencing RNAs to ward against TE activation in the progeny. This form of trans-generational immunity defines a new mode of inheritance, but the mechanisms by which inherited silencing RNAs limit TE proliferation across generations are very poorly understood. The goal of this project is to determine how inherited silencing RNAs protect the genome of the offspring. This will have broad implications for our understanding of epigenetic and mutational phenomena.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This project will provide training in interdisciplinary research at a time when technological advances are joining previously disparate fields of biology. Two undergraduate students currently in the lab are being trained in molecular genetics, evolutionary genetics, bioinformatics and cytogenetics. The University of Kansas has a strong commitment to the participation of underrepresented groups in biological research through the Office for Diversity in Science Training. This office currently coordinates five federally funded NIGMS Minority Opportunities in Research programs and one undergraduate trainee for this project is funded through this office. An additional broader impact also includes the production of genetics teaching modules on YouTube at: http://www.youtube.com/user/GeneticsBlumenstiel.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1022165</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blumenstiel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jblumens@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
