<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developing research-based Tutorials in Upper-division Electricity and Magnetism</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>530906</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>One of the greatest impacts of physics education research has been the development of research-based introductory curricula. Such student-centered pedagogies improve student learning and can positively impact student attitudes and beliefs about the nature of physics and learning physics. The physics community is, however, still in need of a corresponding base of research, materials, assessments, curricula, and teaching guides that move beyond the introductory topics, to allow effective transformations and improved student learning at the upper-division level. This process has begun in a CCLI phase I project, by piloting research-based practices and approaches to begin transforming the first semester of two year-long upper-division physics courses. Student difficulties were investigated, faculty learning goals established, and curricular materials were developed, including validated conceptual assessment tools, a suite of clicker questions, and pilot weekly Tutorials, which are student-centered activities, developed around known common learning difficulties. Published outcomes demonstrate consistent, improved student learning across multiple implementations by non-PER faculty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The present project is developing, and disseminating a complete suite of Tutorials in upper-division electricity and magnetism (E&amp;M), with corresponding evaluation tools as well as implementation and assessment at multiple sites. Tutorial content areas are being identified by faculty-consensus learning goals, student difficulties, and common coverage. Each tutorial includes a validated pre-post assessment. Materials are being developed and evaluated with diverse student populations, and comprehensive instructor support is provided to facilitate adoption and adaptation of these materials. The project brings together a cross-institutional team of curriculum developers, researchers, and faculty. The project is improving student mastery in this critical junior-level course, without requiring significant structural changes to typical courses or to the physics major. All materials are being made freely available. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: The project uses a development methodology that is strongly grounded in research. It advances PER work by significantly extending the limited base of research on student thinking and difficulties in upper-division E&amp;M as well as on implementation and adoption of research-based curricula at this level. The project team brings a successful history of course transformation, evaluation of the impact of these practices, and research on sustainable and scaleable models of reform. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: This program directly impacts the education of hundreds of physics majors at eight institutions and is disseminating these practices across the nation. From the materials, students are expected to develop a robust conceptual understanding of the physics and of the underpinning meaning of the mathematics and formalisms used in these sequences. This project provides resources for faculty to appropriately adapt material to their local environments, improving their own pedagogical expertise. Thus, the materials can be of value, relevance and likely significant interest to the roughly 750 colleges and universities in the nation that offer undergraduate physics programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1023028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dubson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael.dubson@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pollock</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>steven.pollock@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beale</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paul.beale@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Perkins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>katherine.perkins@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7492</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
