<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: Toward Documenting Biodiversity Change in Arctic Lichens: Databasing the Principal Collections, Establishing a Baseline, and Developing a Virtual Flora</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>168417</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marc Stieglitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lichens are symbiotic organisms that are highly sensitive to environmental change, and have been used for decades as bioindicators to monitor air pollution. Their past, current, and future patterns of distribution in Arctic and Subarctic ecosystems are likely to be reflective of significant ecosystem change in temperature, water and nutrient cycling, as well as population dynamics of migratory animals such as caribou. Most of the data concerning current and historical distributions of Arctic lichens presently resides in the literature and within the natural history collections of North America, the two largest of which reside in the herbaria of the University of Alaska Museum (Fairbanks) and the University of Wisconsin State Herbarium (Madison). This project would identify, update nomenclature, barcode, georeference, and database this pair of collections. At the same time, an updated checklist of all Arctic &amp; Subarctic lichen species will be generated, photographs will be collected, and taxonomic characters for each species will be coded for use in creating dynamic taxonomic keys and species descriptions. Together, this dataset will be integrated using the Symbiota software package to generate an online virtual Flora of Arctic Lichens. Virtual floras, with their interactive keys, color photographs, species descriptions, real-time distribution maps, and direct access to complete specimen metadata, represent a revolution in the way that biodiversity information is shared in a democratic manner with all who are interested. The creation of what promises to be a relatively comprehensive Flora will expose the discipline of lichenology to a larger community, and help to further advance an appreciation of ecological complexity within the Arctic biome. In addition to the online databases and information technology tools that will be generated, data gathered for this project will be disseminated through a series of regional and national workshops. The project will also serve as the basis for Arctic lichen-themed science camps, exhibits, lectures, and activities created for the greater public, including the K-12 student/teacher audience. Finally, the collaborative effort includes both undergraduate and graduate students who will receive training from a diverse team of researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1023497</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ffbmm@uaf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ickert-Bond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smickertbond@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5407</Code>
      <Text>POLAR CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
