<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Collaboration in Chemistry: Improving understanding of ice nucleation and growth inhibition mechanisms via new isotopic tracer studies in the AIDA aerosol chamber</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>550550</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The National science Foundation (NSF) Environmental Chemical Sciences (ECS) program of the Division of Chemistry and the Atmospheric Chemistry (ATM) program of the Division of Atmospheric and Geospace Sciences, and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft(DFG)(German research Foundation will fund the international collaboration in chemistry (ICC) project of Prof. Elisabeth Moyer of the University of Chicago and a collaborative team of German investigators which includes Volker Ebert, Ottmar Mohler and Steven Wagner of the University of Heidelberg and Harald Saathoff of the University of Gottingen. Prof. Moyer and her collaborators will study the mechanism of ice nucleation and growth via measurements of the isotopic composition of water under atmospherically-relevant conditions at the AIDA (Aerosol Interactions and Dynamics in the Atmosphere) experimental chamber in Karlsruhe, Germany, a uniquely suitable facility for this study. The study will add new measurement capability to AIDA that will support future research in the area of ice nucleation and growth. The project will provide excellent training opportunities to students at the University of Chicago and the University of Heidelberg. It will also provide a valuable educational experience to high school students from the Woodlawn School, a University of Chicago-operated charter school serving the low-income African-American community surrounding the university.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project stands to greatly increase understanding the mechanism of ice nucleation and growth and the role of water in the stratosphere. It will improve stratospheric ozone and climate predictions, which are of major importance to science policy and economics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recognizing the unique international training opportunities to US students, the Office of International Science and Engineering (OISE) contributed funds towards this international collaboration in chemistry project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1026830</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elisabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>moyer@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6882</Code>
      <Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1303</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE MODELING &amp; PREDICTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5936</Code>
      <Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
