<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of a Sub-Diffraction-Limited Microscope with Molecular Resolution, Wavelength Tunability, &amp; Picosecond Time Resolution for Research in Biophys., Chem., &amp; Materials Sci.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>219537</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tanja Pietraß</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, funded by the CRIF Program of the Division of Chemistry, Professors Jacob W. Petrich and Emily A. Smith of the Department of Chemistry at Iowa State University will construct a stimulated emission depletion microscope (STED) with simultaneous molecular scale resolution (i.e., ten times better than conventional optical microscopes), wavelength tunablilty, and ~120-picosecond time resolution. The STED system will be capable of imaging micron sized features with 10-20 nm resolution in the focal plane. The added capacity of time resolution permits in some cases the observation of events as they actually occur in the spot being interrogated. This combination of capabilities provides the ability to study a host of systems in the areas of biology, chemistry, physics, and materials science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The construction of the STED microscope and the research that it permits will enable a range of collaborative endeavors to be performed. A diverse population of students, including women and underrepresented groups, will have access to this learning experience. The most significant broader impacts of this work can be grouped into five main areas. 1. Training of undergraduates. Advanced undergraduates will be given the opportunity to operate the STED system under supervision. The presence of the STED apparatus on campus will also provide a stimulating opportunity for discussing lasers, spectroscopy, microscopy, and light. 2. Training of graduate students. Once the STED instrument is operational, graduate students from user groups on (and off) campus will have access to it after they are sufficiently trained or appropriately supervised. 3. Training and mentoring of postdocs. 4. Augmenting the quality of collaborative research on the ISU campus and complementing and enhancing existing facilities and infrastructure. 5. Involvement of women and underrepresented groups and recruiting new faculty to ISU. The instrumentation provided in this proposal will certainly enhance the ability to recruit new faculty to ISU in conjunction with the Department?s role in an NSF funded ADVANCE program, which has enhanced the recruiting of women and other underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1026028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esmith1@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
      <LastName>Petrich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwp@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7969</Code>
      <Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
