<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: A Novel Approach for Production of Freestanding GaN Wafers for III-Nitride Light Emitters and Detectors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>719000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to demonstrate a novel technique for producing large-diameter freestanding GaN wafers and substrates. Despite the research efforts in the last decade, affordable GaN wafers and substrates of large diameters have not been widely available commercially, which hinders commercialization of high performance GaN-based devices. This Phase II project will demonstrate a unique approach to growth of GaN thick films and fabrication of freestanding GaN wafers and substrates with low densities of dislocations and low wafer bow/warp in an efficient manner. This Phase II research includes crystal growth of GaN thick films, fabrication of GaN wafers and substrates, and extensive characterization of GaN wafers. If this Phase II project is successful, high-quality freestanding GaN substrates of large diameters will become widely available commercially at an affordable price, which will enable volume production and commercialization of high-performance GaN-based light emitters and ultraviolet light detectors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is in the areas of GaN-based light emitting diodes (LEDs), lasers, and ultraviolet (UV) light detectors. GaN-based blue and green high brightness LEDs hold a great promise for solid-state lighting applications because of their tremendous energy savings potential, long lifetime, compactness, and high energy efficiency. Solid-sate lighting will dramatically improve the nation?s energy sustainability in the near future. In addition, freestanding GaN substrates are also needed for fabrication of variety of other high-performance semiconductor devices, such as blue laser diodes for data storage/displays, UV LEDs for water/air purification, high-power RF devices for wireless communication, high-power switching devices for harnessing renewable energies (e.g. wind, solar), and UV detectors for detection/analysis of chemical and biological agents for homeland security applications. Finally, this project will help create jobs in business sectors of energy conservation and renewable energies, and will increase competitiveness of US companies in these business sectors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1026380</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shaoping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swang@fairfieldcrystal.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fairfield Crystal Technology, LLC</Name>
      <CityName>New Milford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>067764200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8603542111</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8 South End Plaza</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
