<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Grant for the fifth international workshop in interfacial fluid mechanics and transport processes-IMA 5</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert M. Wellek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1028778&lt;br/&gt;Narayanan&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project provides funding to support the travel of approximately about 7 US scientists and researchers to present papers at the fifth international workshop and conference on thermal, fluid and interfacial phenomena in physico-chemical, materials and bio-processes. Problems of materials processing, nanotechnologies and drug delivery as well as space technologies will be addressed. The conference will be held at the Florence campus of Univ. of Paris between June 7 and June 10 2010. The scientists will represent a broad base of research funded by NSF, through its Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems (CBET) organization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed activity lies in the fact that scientists from various countries will be able to discuss their research and foster collaboration for future work. Because the workshop will involve discussions and responses to papers, new ideas will be generated in areas of materials science, nanotechnology and bio-processes. The scientists will represent academia, industry and government research and this collaboration will therefore benefit the cooperative science programs between the US and other countries as well as university industry collaboration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The speakers and participants will come from all over the world, representing the research and work funded by a variety of national science and research councils. Over 90 presentations will be offered. It is expected to have speakers from the United States, Great Britain, France, Germany, Italy, Belgium, Spain, Israel, the former Soviet Union, Japan and China. The participants will include members of the National Academy and Fellows of Royal and National Societies as well as a number of young scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proceedings of the conference will be published by a well known journal, the European Journal of Physics. This publisher like others also have an electronic publishing format aside of a paper format. Thus the research ideas will be widely disseminated via libraries and the electronic media making a broad impact on the community of scientists and engineers. The published research ideas and discussions will encourage future novel research and fresh perspectives on problems of technological content.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1028778</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ranga</FirstName>
      <LastName>Narayanan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ranga@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
