<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a high performance liquid chromatograph for the enhancement of biogeochemical education and research of trace element speciation in environmental systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1029246&lt;br/&gt;Johannesson&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funding for a high performance liquid chromatograph for biogeoechmical and trace element research and training. The HPLC will be coupled with an existing NSF-funded magnetic sector ICP-MS for high-resolution elemental measurements. The main research use will be for assessing trace element concentrations and speciation in natural waters in order to understand biogeochemical transformations. The oxidation-reduction state will be able to be inferred from the speciation distribution in environmental samples. A principal research theme will address inorganic-organic interactions through ligand complexes. The PIs arsenic geochemistry studies in groundwater will immediately benefit. Researchers in the School of Science and Engineering, the School of Medicine, and the School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine will be engaged in sharing the instrumentation. Xavier University of Louisiana, a historically African American university, has scientists who routinely use Tulane?s coordinated instrumentation facility (CIF). They will given access to the new instrumentation. The acquisition will play an important role in encouraging the participation of under-represented groups in the areas of science and engineering through such programs as the Louisiana Alliance for Minority Participation in Research Program, as well as through the PI?s outreach to women in sciences through the Newcomb College Institute. The will be incorporated into environmental geochemistry coursework ? including an outreach component investigating local water quality issues. The instrument will be incorporated into the CIF. A full-time staff scientist maintains the laboratory. The staff scientist will provide routine instrument service and maintenance. Per hour cost structure for CIF resources (HR-ICP-MS) will be used initially for cost-recovery. Instrument time will be scheduled according to CIF policy. The PI and staff scientist will train new users. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1029246</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johannesson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kjohanne@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tulane University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
