<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Women's Employment Around the Globe: Evidence from 94 Countries: 1985-2004</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES-1029870&lt;br/&gt;Elizabeth Boyle,&lt;br/&gt;Minzee Kim&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Considering women's increased levels of employment globally, this project addresses a crucial question: Is women's increased employment linked to women getting good jobs? Extensive research shows that women-friendly policies at the national level and national integration into the global economy increase women?s employment. However, it is unclear if either or both of these factors are linked to the quality of women's employment. This research proposes that the way women are incorporated into the labor force is critical in determining if increased female labor force participation is linked to women's representation in higher status positions. In order to test the proposed influences of global and national policy environments, research for this project comprises quantitative pooled time-series analyses on women's relative chances to be employed in two higher-status occupational groups'managerial/administrative and professional/technical occupations. As key independent variables, this project creates original indicators of anti-discrimination and maternity leave policies that are comparable across developed and developing countries. This study will not only provide a crucial test of those theories that suggest women's increased labor force participation leads to women's employment in high quality jobs and those that suggest the opposite, but also explain the factors that make one or the other outcome more likely. This research will also advance sociological theories about the links between globalization, state policies, and actual employment outcomes on the ground by integrating state-centered and global theories of women's employment and testing the scope of theories in both developed and developing countries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Results from this research will be disseminated not only in the academic community but also among policy makers and social movement networks as men's predominance in the top positions in the public sphere is recognized not only as a reflection of existing gender inequality but also as a key factor maintaining or altering gender inequality in societies. Findings from this research will provide insights for international and national policies that ultimately contribute to improve women?s share in powerful positions globally. The cross-national, historical research design makes findings from this project particularly applicable to diverse national contexts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1029870</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boyle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>boyle014@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Minzee</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kimx0939@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
