<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High Speed Picosecond Laser Scribing of Multilayer Thin Films in Solar Cell</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>425162</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhijian Pei</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research project is to gain a fundamental understanding about the physical mechanisms of high speed picosecond laser scribing of multilayer thin film materials and determine optimal processing conditions. Research approaches will include both physics-based computational modeling to better understand the physical processes and an experimental work to characterize the resultant morphological, microstructural and electrical properties. The relationship between process parameters and associated physical mechanisms, such as photo-thermal and photo-mechanical reactions will be developed and optimal process conditions for high speed scribing of multilayer thin film materials will be identified.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The successful completion of this work will provide a scientific understanding of the laser-material interaction under the picosecond regime, high power laser, plasma formation, and its interaction with the target material of various thin film layers used for solar cells. Furthermore, this work will produce fundamental technology advances in the manufacturing of thin film electronics, such as photovoltaic devices, flat panel displays, flexible electronics and advanced semiconductor logic devices and thus will bring a broad impact on manufacturing related issues on these areas. High frequency, ultrashort lasers have many applications from pulsed laser fabrication of thin films to laser micro/nano fabrication. Therefore, improving the understanding of high frequency, ultrashort laser-material interaction can significantly improve the potential applications of picosecond lasers. This project will also bring a positive impact on undergraduate education through the manufacturing classes, undergraduate research fellow programs and undergraduate independent projects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1030786</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shin@ecn.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gjcheng@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
