<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Risk-informed Management and Post-disaster Operations of Lifeline Networks by Rapid, Condition-based System Reliability Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>311568</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dennis Wenger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The society is increasingly demanding scientific accountability behind risk management of lifeline networks such as hazard mitigation planning, infrastructure maintenance and post-disaster responses. For rapid and condition-based risk management of lifeline networks, it is essential to have system reliability analysis (SRA) methods that can integrate analyses across physical scales, and can interface models and data from multiple fields of science and engineering smoothly for quantifying system-level risk. The proposed project will develop multi-scale SRA methods employing advanced network clustering algorithms for efficient, accurate and collaborative risk assessment of large-size networks. The project will also create a near-real-time network risk alert system through integration of a rapid SRA method with a hazard alert system to facilitate rapid decision support on hazard responses. In addition, an efficient time-varying network SRA method will be developed in which network reliability is continuously updated based on inspection results of network component deterioration in order to sustain the network reliability with optimal use of limited resources.&lt;br/&gt;The analysis methods and numerical tools developed in this project will help practitioners understand the hierarchical structure of lifeline networks and its impacts on network risk and decision making, develop network risk alert systems customized for actual risk management practice, and perform condition-based maintenance considering actual deterioration progress and its impacts on network-level risk. Education-focused research tasks include the development of interactive cyber-environment on network theory, virtual experiment on network downtime, interactive computer software simulating network flow and connectivity, and mobile phone applications to demonstrate IT-based risk management. The research results will be incorporated into the graduate level courses on risk and reliability of complex infrastructure systems. Active efforts will be made to recruit students from the groups that are underrepresented in science and technology fields using the well-established institutional fellowship programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1031318</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Junho</FirstName>
      <LastName>Song</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>junho@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Work</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbwork@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1638</Code>
      <Text>INFRAST MGMT &amp; EXTREME EVENTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>041E</Code>
      <Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>042E</Code>
      <Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1576</Code>
      <Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
