<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Junior Faculty and Invited Speakers to Attend the "Nanostructured Polymers" Symposium at the 2010 ACS Spring National Meeting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Freddy A. Khoury</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL ABSTRACT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a growing interest in well-defined nanostructured polymers&lt;br/&gt;because of their unique properties and their ability to be employed in areas such as power generation, nanocomposites, nanopatterning, optics, and charge transport phenomena. These advances could have major impact in accelerating the emerging era of electronics for applications in many areas of information technologies and in portable power sources. The ACS National Meeting on Nanostructured Polymers will provide a setting to discuss in depth of transformative developments with leading scientists from academia, government, and industry. Various sessions will be devoted to the chemistry,physics, materials science, nanoscience, engineering, and device fabrication of electrically-active and optically-active polymer materials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ACS National Meeting on Nanostructured Polymers will provide a setting to discuss in depth of transformative developments with leading scientists from academia, government, and industry. Leading researchers will be present to address the critical questions through a combination of presentations and informal discussions. Invited speakers and session chairs represent the highly interdisciplinary nature of this field with experts from chemistry, physics, material science and engineering, chemical engineering, and electrical engineering with both fundamental and technical approaches. Speakers&lt;br/&gt;and session chairs are from a diverse background. A primary goal of this funding is to assist researchers in the early stages of their careers to participate in the conference and become active in the nanostructured polymers community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1032028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alejandro</FirstName>
      <LastName>Briseno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abriseno@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/04/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
