<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: SDCI Net Improvement: Web10Gig - Taking TCP instrumentation to the Next Level</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniel Katz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Web10Gig Project enables ordinary users, from the broadest range of fields and technical abilities, to effectively use the network to its full capacity. The research associated with the Web10Gig project builds upon the very successful Web100 project, whose prototype software is still heavily used six years beyond the end of the project funding. Under Web10Gig, the investigators produce a produce a production quality implementation of standard TCP instrumentation, based on the existing Web100 prototype, and groom it for inclusion in the Linux main line. It eliminates barriers to development associated with the original Web100 software suite, addresses a number of weaknesses in the Web100 prototype implementation and migrates the non-kernel code to a public open source code development site where anyone can contribute future additions and improvements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the Web10 Gig code propagates out to all Linux users it enables network measurement and diagnosis underneath all types of Internet applications. Like the autotuning software developed before it, it will be replicated in other operating systems, such that everybody, Linux user or not will reap to the benefits of having standard TCP instrumentation. Once incorporated into the Linux main line, the TCP instrumentation passes beyond the control of the Web10Gig investigators where maintained by the commercial world through production implementations and the researchers and developers actually using the code.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1032622</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brett</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bode</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbode@ncsa.illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Estabrook</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jestabro@ncsa.illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7683</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE DEVELOPEMENT FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
