<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: Sea Level Changes into MIS 5: from observations to predictions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24234</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bonnie Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will support an international workshop to establish a dialog between field- and modeling-based scientists that will efficiently advance the understanding of sea level changes. Global sea level and the Earth?s climate are closely linked, and sea-level history throughout Quaternary time shows a complex spatial and temporal pattern that provides a globally averaged record of continental ice volume variations. Observations of this variability provide key constraints on the timing and amplitudes of the forcing mechanisms that trigger the growth and decay of ice masses. The goal of this workshop is to produce an integrated research agenda aimed at better constraining the relationships among solar insolation, greenhouse gases, ice sheet response, and sea-level change, with the aim of estimating future sea level rise. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will foster communication between an interdisciplinary group of experts in the fields of paleoceanography, Quaternary geology, glaciology, geophysics,paleoclimatology, and karst geology. The identified participants are at various stages of their careers and come from diverse international training perspectives. Junior researchers and students from the United States will have a unique opportunity to interact with leading international experts on the topic of sea level change and develop the working relationships critical for their career development. Dissemination of the workshop activities will come through a special edition of a journal and a video archive of the workshop sessions suitable for researchers and teachers alike.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1032243</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dorale</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jeffrey-dorale@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bogdan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Onac</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bonac@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5920</Code>
      <Text>ITALY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5952</Code>
      <Text>SPAIN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
