<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanofiber Composite Ion-Exchange and Bipolar Membranes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>234751</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This NSF award by the Chemical and Biological Separations program supports work by Professor Peter Pintauro at Vanderbilt University to develop new fabrication strategies and new nano-morphologies for anion-exchange, cation-exchange, and bipolar membranes. Membranes will be prepared by electrospinning simultaneously nanofibers of a functional ionomer (ion-exchange polymer) and an uncharged (inert) reinforcement polymer. The resulting dual fiber mat will be processed into a membrane with one of two phase-separated morphologies: (i) ionomer nanofibers surrounded by an uncharged polymer matrix or (ii) uncharged polymer nanofibers surrounded by charged ionomer. In these two nanofiber composite membrane designs, the function of the charged polymer (providing pathways for ion and solvent transport) is decoupled from that of the inert/uncharged polymeric material (providing mechanical strength to the membrane and restricting ionomer swelling). Thus, the use of embedded nanofiber networks represents a paradigm shift in the way membranes are made and the way membrane nano-morphology is controlled/manipulated. Experimental work will focus primarily on anion-exchange and bipolar membranes. The resulting films will have improved mechanical properties, higher ion fluxes and conductivity, and better separation selectivity. Applications for such membranes include electrodialytic salt separations, industrial electrochemical processes, bipolar membrane water splitting, and chemical sensors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1032948</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pintauro</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peter.pintauro@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
      <CityName>Nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1417</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL &amp; BIOLOGICAL SEPAR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>052E</Code>
      <Text>MAT &amp; PROC FOR CHEM SEPARATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
