<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sensing in Living Cells: Expressable RNA-based FRET Probes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Over the past several years our understanding of the important role that small ribonucleic acids (RNAs) play in controlling intracellular processes has grown tremendously. The goal of this interdisciplinary project, combining chemistry and molecular biology, is to add an additional artificial function to the intracellular small RNAs: the fluorescent reporting of intracellular process. For this purpose, we will engineer new small RNAs that will be both responsive to metabolites and bind light-up dyes (dyes that that increase fluorescence upon binding to the receptor). &lt;br/&gt;New fluorescent probes for metabolites would help increase our understanding of intracellular processes, leading to immediate basic science benefits and longer-term impact on human health. A postdoctoral scientist or a graduate student, undergraduates, and high?]school students will all be exposed to the multidisciplinary approach and will learn how to develop and optimize useful intracellular reagents. One of the organisms we will use to demonstrate the function of new RNA-based probes is the social amoebae, Dictyostellium; thus, we may produce highly visually attractive movies that will be used to spark the interest of participating K-12 students in science and to explain basic principles of multicellularity, evolution, parasitism, social behavior, origins of altruism and cheating.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1033288</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kessin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rhk2@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Milan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stojanovic</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mns18@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
