<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative: Investigation of Electrocatalytic Trends on Core/Shell Structured Palladium Bimetallic Surfaces for Renewable Energy Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>217409</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1033601&lt;br/&gt;Ha&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The power generation from most renewable energy sources such as wind, solar and tidal energy is not coincident with power demand. To address the discontinuous nature of power generation from these renewable energy sources, an efficient and cost-effective means of energy storage device needs to be integrated with them. Regenerative fuel cells, particularly those capturing CO2 with H2O to produce formic acid, have been suggested. Thus, by combining the CO2 electrochemical reduction process with direct formic acid fuel cells, the prospects for future energy systems based on non-fossil energy sources are apparent. However, the reality is that the technology does not work so well and the promise goes unfulfilled.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PIs Su Ha and Louis Scudiero of Washington State University, and Sheng Dai of the University of Tennessee Knoxville ascribe the shortfall to the catalyst in the formic acid fuel cell. They point out that the existing anode electrocatalyst is Pd, and the cell performance is prevented from reaching its full potential by promotion of the undesired reaction pathways for formation of surface poisoning species. Improvement of the fuel cell catalyst could be had through bimetallic catalyst design. However progress is limited by the lack of understanding of how the various transition-metals used as supports influence the catalytic performance of supported Pd. It is proposed that improved catalyst selectivity will be had from catalysts made by coating transition-metals centers with a Pd shell in the core/shell structure. They intend to make these catalysts for test.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; By treating the preparations to characterization of the surface electronic structure, chemical properties and catalytic performance for formic-acid oxidation, the current understanding will be improved upon. Based on the improved understanding of the bimetallic effect, one should be able to design superior bimetallic catalysts that increase the specific activity and inhibit further the undesired reaction pathways in formic acid oxidation. These superior bimetallic catalysts can be used to develop high efficiency regenerative DFAFC systems which make tractable the issue of intermittent power from renewable energy sources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The success of the proposed research activities has the potential for broad societal impact because it leads to high performance and stable regenerative formic acid fuel cell systems. Such a system can capture CO2 and convert it into a fuel that is consumed in the fuel cell to produce electrical energy. &lt;br/&gt;The PIs have plans for disseminating this new knowledge to those outside the scientific community. At the Palouse Discovery Science Center, the PIs and graduate students will demonstrate the scientific principle of regenerative fuel cell technology to increase middle and high school students interest in pursuing science and engineering degrees. Furthermore, the PIs will disseminate the research findings to high school classrooms by continuously participating in the NSF funded Research Experiences for Teacher (RET) program at Washington State University. Undergraduate students will be given an opportunity to experience the latest fuel cell and renewable energy technologies using several in-class and out-of-class approaches, including building formic acid fuel cells for the national Chem-E-Car Competition. The PIs will actively involve the undergraduate students, especially females and underrepresented males at WSU and University of Tennessee into the proposed research activities. At WSU, this will be accomplished by working directly with the director of the Office of Multicultural Student Services.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1033601</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Su</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>suha@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scudiero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scudiero@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington State University</Name>
      <CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>044E</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>046E</Code>
      <Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
