<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>FSML: A safe sampling and survey tool for subtidal research and education on the Oregon Coast.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>183465</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests funding to purchase a Phantom ROV (remotely operated vehicle) capable of being deployed in shallow water from a relatively small boat or in water to 600m depth for survey and experimental work on the Oregon continental shelf. The Oregon Institute of Marine Biology (OIMB) faculty would make use of the proposed equipment for studies of recruitment dynamics, marine snow, reproductive biology, larval transport, developmental biology and marine reserve science. The ROV would be readily available to visiting investigators and visiting student groups. Several courses at OIMB would make use of ROV technology for visualizing marine habitats and for collecting specimens needed for courses. The ROV would open new possibilities for research and teaching at all levels and will be an additional draw for visiting investigators to the Oregon coast. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The OIMB has an excellent track record of teaching and outreach productivity on site (including extramural COSEE and MIMSUP support). Training students to use an ROV is relevant to current growing needs in the field. Making exploratory videos available to the public was seen as a positive approach to increasing public awareness of coastal areas and environmental issues.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1034864</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Young</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cmyoung@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7593</Code>
      <Text>FIELD STATIONS AND MARINE LABS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
