<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Organizational Communication and Information Systems (OCIS) Doctoral Research Consortium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>22625</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Crowston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports an Organizational Communication and Information Systems (OCIS) Doctoral Colloquium at the 2010 Academy of Management (AOM) Annual Meeting to be held August 6-10, 2010 in Montreal, Canada. The OCIS division within the AOM conference brings together researchers in areas of communications and information systems who study issues related to the contemporary information-based society. The focus of the OCIS Doctoral Consortium is the intellectual content of the students' doctoral dissertations. These represent cutting edge research in the field of organizational communication and information systems. The OCIS doctoral consortium brings together highly talented students and several senior researchers, facilitating the development of a social network that will play a major role in the career success of new researchers. Since both faculty and students are diverse on several dimensions (research topics, methodological approaches, national and cultural background), the students' horizons are broadened at a critical stage in their professional development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1035231</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davidson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>edavidso@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
