<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CPS: Medium: Collaborative Research: Dynamic Routing and Robotic Coordination for Oceanographic Adaptive Sampling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>345000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Radhakisan S. Baheti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is the design of innovative routing,&lt;br/&gt;planning and coordination strategies for robot networks, and their&lt;br/&gt;application to oceanography. The approach is organized in three&lt;br/&gt;synergistic thrusts: (1) the application of queueing theory and&lt;br/&gt;combinatorial techniques to networked robots performing sequential tasks,&lt;br/&gt;(2) the design of novel distributed optimization and coordination schemes&lt;br/&gt;relying only on asynchronous and asymmetric communication, (3) the design&lt;br/&gt;of practical routing and coordination algorithms for the USC Networked&lt;br/&gt;Aquatic Platforms. In collaboration with oceanographers and marine&lt;br/&gt;biologists, the project aims to design motion, communication and&lt;br/&gt;interaction protocols that maximize the amount of scientific information&lt;br/&gt;collected by the platforms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal addresses multi-dimensional problems of relevance in&lt;br/&gt;Engineering and Computer Science by unifying fundamental concepts from&lt;br/&gt;multiple cyberphysical domains (robotics, autonomy, combinatorics, and&lt;br/&gt;network science). Our team has expertise in a broad range of scientific&lt;br/&gt;disciplines, including control theory and theoretical computer science and&lt;br/&gt;their applications to multi-agent systems, robotics and sensor networks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will have a positive impact on the emerging&lt;br/&gt;technology of autonomous and reliable robotic networks, performing a broad&lt;br/&gt;range of environmental monitoring and logistic tasks. Our educational and&lt;br/&gt;outreach objectives are manifold and focus on (1) integrating the proposed&lt;br/&gt;research themes into undergraduate education and research, e.g., via the&lt;br/&gt;existing NSF REU site at the USC Computer Science Department, and (2)&lt;br/&gt;mounting a vigorous program of outreach activities, e.g., via a&lt;br/&gt;well-developed collaboration with the UCSB Center for Science and&lt;br/&gt;Engineering Partnerships.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1035866</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gaurav</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sukhatme</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gaurav@cs.usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
