<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for 24th "International Union of Pure and Applied Physics" Triennial Conference on Thermodynamics and Statistical Mechanics (STATPHYS-24) Australia, 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daryl W. Hess</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports travel for students, postdoctoral associates and young faculty in order to attend STATPHYS-24, the 24th International Conference on Statistical Physics, to be held in Cairns, Australia 19-23 July, 2010. The award is supported by the Office of Multidisciplinary Activities, the Chemistry Division, the Physics Division and the Division of Materials Research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Statistical mechanics is a cross-disciplinary field with practitioners coming from chemistry, mathematics, biology, physics, computer science and the engineering sciences. Every three years, this community assembles a major international meeting. These meetings are sponsored by the International Union of Pure and Applied Physics (IUPAP). This triennial series of meetings started in Florence in 1949 and continues to the present day. Starting with the 1986 meeting in Boston, the NSF has awarded travel grants to enable young investigators without other support to participate. This award will enable 12-15 graduate students and young researchers to participate in STATPHYS-24. A selection committee representing a cross-section of senior scientists has committed to undertake a fair selection of a balanced group of "NSF Scholars," representing all disciplines of the statistical mechanics community and paying particular attention to qualified female and minority candidates. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award will contribute to the scientific infrastructure of U.S. science by permitting young people to participate in a major international meeting. It will strengthen the ties of these young people to their peers from Australia and around the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1036217</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Landau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dlandau@physast.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
