<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Piezoelectric Nanoribbon Assemblies Printed onto Rubber for Highly Efficient, Flexible Energy Harvesting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce M. Kramer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Early Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) award provides funding for the development of a method for integrating highly efficient energy conversion materials onto stretchable, biocompatible rubbers which could yield breakthroughs in implantable or wearable energy harvesting systems. Being electromechanically coupled, piezoelectric crystals represent a particularly interesting subset of smart materials which function as sensors/actuators, bioMEMS devices, and energy converters. Yet, the crystallization of these materials generally requires high temperatures for maximally efficient performance, rendering them incompatible with temperature-sensitive plastics and rubbers. Overcoming these limitations by presenting a scalable and parallel process for transferring crystalline piezoelectric nanoribbons of lead zirconate titanate (PZT) from host substrates onto flexible plastics over macroscopic areas is a goal of this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, it is anticipated that this work will have a substantial positive effect on the science of piezoelectric materials, the large-scale nanofabrication of piezoelectric nanoassembles, and the implications of being able to generate flexible yet highly efficient power sources self-sustaining systems on stretchable, biocompatible substrates. The ribbons will be nanomanufactured from single crystal, stoichiometric films of PZT, allowing for exceptional control over the composition and, consequently, the performance characteristics of these materials. Preliminary data in the form of fundamental characterization of the ribbons by piezo-force microscopy (PFM) indicates that electromechanical energy conversion metrics of the PZT ribbons are among the highest reported on a flexible medium. The excellent performance of the piezo-ribbon nanoassemblies coupled with stretchable, biocompatible rubber may enable a host of exciting applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1036055</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>McAlpine</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcalpine@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/07/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
