<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SHF: Small: EAGER: Architectural Support for Improving Cloud Computing Security</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Hong Jiang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The rapid deployment of cloud computing services and their attraction for small and medium businesses requires a thorough examination of security issues. Indeed cloud computing brings a host of new security issues that have not been addressed in the past research, namely the lack of trust between the infrastructure provider and customers (e.g., service providers) and potential for misuse of cloud computing resources for data exposure or service disruption. In this research, the PI addresses major security issues brought about by cloud computing. In particular, it plans to investigate underlying hardware/architectural mechanisms for three main issues related to cloud computing security: (a) simultaneous encryption and access control to protect service provider's data from infrastructure provider, (b) securing cloud resident data by scattering the data, meta-data, or encryption keys in the cloud, and (c) coordinated monitoring of both incoming and outgoing traffic of VMs in the cloud in order to detect any spyware installed in the cloud. &lt;br/&gt;The research could have a significant impact on providing security for cloud computing. The other broader impacts of the research include graduate student training and integration of the research findings into graduate courses. The scholarly discovery of this project will be disseminated broadly through publications and, where appropriate, technology transfer to industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1037987</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sushil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jajodia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jajodia@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Mason University</Name>
      <CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
