<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Building SPEED (Science Partnerships in Engagement, Education and Diversity)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>28284</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the project Building SPEED, which addresses challenges to US global competitiveness by linking math, science and engineering to motorsports and, in particular, NASCAR. NASCAR has 75 million fans from a surprisingly broad range of demographic backgrounds, including a large group of people underserved by traditional STEM outreach. &lt;br/&gt;Three types of materials will be developed: 1) student worksheets and hands-on activities that reinforce the content knowledge mandated by state and national Science and Math Education Standards; 2) career information about how STEM is used in motorsports featuring people from a broad range of educational levels and companies, and demonstrating the full diversity of people involved in STEM and 3) hands-on materials to enhance the public?s understanding of the math and science behind motorsports. Dissemination is accomplished by partnerships with industrial sponsors, informal science venues and other academic institutions. Dissemination mechanisms include teacher workshops, public science events at race tracks, street festivals and science museums, and visits to schools. Dissemination will occur in three locations (Dover, DE; Dallas/Fort Worth, TX and Charlotte, NC), with each dissemination consisting of a week of events prior to races in fall 2008 and spring 2009.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1038772</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Royster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>droyster@ms.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
