<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Global Enterprise Technology (GET) Curriculum Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19936</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project organizes a curriculum workshop designed to bring industry and academic leaders together in order to explore the knowledge and skills needed to work effectively in large technology driven global organizations. It explores transformational models of industry-academic partnership providing practice-based learning, such as the Global Enterprise Technology (GET) curriculum that is currently being developed via a collaboration between Syracuse University and JPMorgan Chase &amp; Co.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participants of the proposed workshop include a diverse array of liberal arts, technical, research institutions and industry representatives from a number of global, technology-intensive enterprises. Findings from the workshop are disseminated through conference presentations, articles, a white paper distributed to participant and a summary of findings in a form that can be used by academic institutions to inform high school students of their participation in the GET community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This one-day workshop promotes awareness of the expanding collaboration, explores industry educational requirements and seeks ways of broadening the reach and impact of the GET collaboration to new industry partners, as well as liberal arts, technical, and research institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1038065</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heckman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rheckman@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
