<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: The Role of Ochre in the Development of Modern Human Behavior: A Case Study From South Africa</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19962</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In recent years, southern Africa has figured prominently in the modern human origins debate due to increasing evidence for precocious behaviors considered to be unique to our species. These significant findings have included bone tools, shell beads, engraved ostrich eggshell, and heavily ground and engraved ochre fragments. The presence of ochre, geological material ground to produce early paint, in Middle Stone Age (MSA, ~250-40kya) archaeological sites in southern Africa is often proposed as evidence for the existence of artwork or symbolism, a uniquely modern human behavior. However, there is no remaining artwork from this period and there is significant debate about what the ochre may have been used for. With a few exceptions, ochre has gone largely unstudied. This project will test competing models for ochre use in the MSA. A series of related research questions will be addressed: Within MSA archaeological sites at Pinnacle Point (PP), South Africa, what activities involving ochre were likely taking place? Was ochre used as a pigment for artistic activities or was it for more basic everyday activities? Where is the ochre being collected? Are there distinct color preferences being procured or are materials being heat treated to achieve desired colors?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research includes the application of a unique combination of research approaches to identify early symbolic human behavior. Taken together these new analyses will provide more conclusive answers to the proposed research questions. The PP site complex adds further merit to the project as an ideal case study. The research area has a well developed excavation and research infrastructure in place for the South African Coast Paleoclimate, Paleoenvironment, Paleoecology, and Paleoanthropology (SACP4) project. Previous and current excavations have yielded adequate ochre assemblages for study that are available to the Co-PI. Further, the archaeological ochre at these sites is well dated and may be among the earliest modified ochre in the world. Lastly, insights gained from this research will be incorporated with work on other artifact types in the future to achieve a broader understanding of the development of modern behavior in this time period.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this study include a contribution to one of the most prominent debates in paleoanthropology, that of modern human origins. This study will also impact the field of archaeology by filling a gap in knowledge about the MSA and improving methods of ochre analysis in this time period.. This work will further provide the Co-PI with interdisciplinary training, and outcomes will be shared with the anthropological community through presentations at professional conferences and in journals. The project will also be made accessible to the general public through community lectures in the United States and South Africa as well as the Institute of Human Origins' BecomingHuman.com website, and the SACP4 project's public website.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1040913</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Curtis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marean</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>curtis.marean@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jocelyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bernatchez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jocelyn.Bernatchez@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
