<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 400 MHz FT-NMR For Undergraduate Research and Education at the University of the District of Columbia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>290500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) with support from the Chemistry Division and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Professor Xueqing Song and Isadora J. Posey from the University of the District of Columbia, Vadim D. Knyazev from the Catholic University of America and Paul Sabila from Gallaudet University will acquire a 400 MHz nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer that will be shared among the three institutions. The proposal is aimed at enhancing research training and education at all levels, especially in areas of study such as organotin research; initial stage pyrolysis of polymers; synthesis of quinine-derived natural product-like compounds; monitoring pesticide and other hazardous chemical wastes; and chemical composition of biogas production in an anaerobic digestor.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. The results from these NMR studies will have an impact in a wide range of areas including organic and organometallic synthesis, natural products synthesis, analytical chemistry, environmental science, biochemistry, and chemical engineering. Moreover, the presence of the shared NMR will stimulate additional competitive research requiring this tool and catalyze new multi-disciplinary collaborations involving researchers in several disciplines at these campuses. This instrument will be an integral part of teaching as well as research and be used by large numbers of students underrepresented in science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1040094</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Isadora</FirstName>
      <LastName>Posey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>iposey@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sabila</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paul.sabila@gallaudet.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xueqing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Song</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xsong@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vadim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Knyazev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>knyazev@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of the District of Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200081122</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2022746260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4200 Connecticut Ave NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
