<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an Automated Isothermal Titration Microcalorimeter for the Emory Macromolecular Structure and Interactions Suite</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation award funds the acquisition of an automated small cell isothermal titration microcalorimeter for the Emory University Department of Biochemistry's "Macromolecular Structure and Interactions Suite." A long-term goal for the assembled team of investigators is to understand the biochemical basis for macromolecular interactions using a combination of structural biology and biophysical techniques. The new microcalorimeter enhances Emory's diverse research programs that include the investigations of protein synthesis regulation by the ribosome; protein, DNA and RNA modifications in epigenetics, protein sorting, protein degradation and antibiotic resistance; lipid transport; and nuclear receptor function. Understanding the biophysical parameters that govern macromolecular interactions adds a complementary dimension to Emory University structural biology programs. The new equipment therefore enhances training in biophysical experimental methods by improving access to state-of-the-art instrumentation for post-doctoral fellows, graduate students and undergraduates. Furthermore, high school students and teachers will get hands-on experience in a joint Emory-Georgia Tech summer program designed to study the biophysical characterization of extremophile ribosomes. The results of these research and teaching efforts will be broadly disseminated through abstracts and peer reviewed publications, as well as by active participation of students and faculty at professional meetings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1040177</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilkinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>genekdw@bimcore.emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaodong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xcheng@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cmdunha@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Graeme</FirstName>
      <LastName>Conn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gconn@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ortlund</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eortlun@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Emory University</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
