<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Demonstration Project: Arkansas Minority Cyberinfrastructure Training, Education Consortium (AMC-TEC)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>266195</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark Suchman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff and Philander Smith College has formed the Arkansas Cyberinfrastructure Minority Training, Education Consortium (AMC-TEC) to develop a unique interdisciplinary cyberinfrastructure (CI) educational community within Arkansas. This consortium is educating a majority minority student population, and faculty in cyberinfrastructure-oriented concepts, theories, practices, and principles within Science Technology, Mathematics, and Engineering (STEM) at the teaching-oriented Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) in the area of the project. This is a demonstration project focused on developing the capacity of the participant institutions within three core areas as they relate to cyberinfrastructure resources, (1) institutional faculty development (2) tangible cyber-based student activities (3) CI curriculum enhancement. These activities are producing strategies that can be deployed on a national scale to institutionalize a renaissance in STEM education at student-focused universities, through the sharing of resources and expertise to transform STEM education and research through the introduction of cyberinfrastructure resources. The project is creating new local, national partnerships to enable the sharing of pedagogical models, best practices, and curricula to achieve maximum regional and rapid national impact. Distinct partnerships between the listed HBCUs, the University of&lt;br/&gt;Arkansas (UARK) High Performance Computing Center, Arkansas Research and Education&lt;br/&gt;Optical Network (ARE-ON), the Supercomputing Center for Education &amp; Research (OSCER) at the University of Oklahoma (OU), the Shoder Education Foundation, and the Minority Serving&lt;br/&gt;Institutions-Cyberinfrastructure Empowerment Coalition (MSI-CIEC) have been formed. The partners are providing resources, expertise, and support services, that did not previously exist at the HBCUs campuses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;This project is creating a community of learners composed of a majority minority student population, and STEM faculty to address the national challenge of engaging an underrepresented population within STEM to utilize cyberinfrastructure research, and educational resources. The magnitude of the challenge that the U.S. faces with respect to ensuring that it retains its intellectual capacity within STEM research and innovation through the production of a workforce that is capable of serious science using both local, national and international cyberinfrastructure resources requires all capable individuals within STEM to take an active role in the intellectual discourse. The proposed project offers a replicable approach to increasing the participation of historically underrepresented communities and regions within&lt;br/&gt;Cyberinfrastructure oriented research and education. The project achieves these goals by partnering mature cyberinfrastructure communities, local resources to inject cyberinfrastructureoriented materials into existing curriculum and to expand the expertise of faculty with practical skills at HBCUs in Arkansas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project include:(1) new collaborations to expand the workforce within the domains of cyberinfrastructure research and education to include greater numbers of historically underrepresented minorities, and women, (2) developing avenues for sharing knowledge and resources as innovation takes place within the domains of cyberinfrastructure research, and education (3) expanding the diversity of faculty members engaged in cyberinfrastructure-oriented research and teaching. (4) Increasing the enrollment of students interested in cyberinfrastructure-oriented careers within STEM particularly within the computing fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1041420</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abbiatti</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mabbiatt@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mansour</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mortazavi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mortazavim@uapb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pummill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpummil@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jessie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jessie.j.walker@jsums.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Apon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aapon@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/20/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>RAlo@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/27/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff</Name>
      <CityName>Pine Bluff</CityName>
      <ZipCode>716012790</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8705758751</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7477</Code>
      <Text>CI-TEAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7477</Code>
      <Text>CI-TEAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
