<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Extension of the ADCIRC Coastal Circulation Model for Predicting Near Shore and Inner Shore Transport of Oil from the Horizon Oil Spill</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>58180</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Irene M. Qualters</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Grant for Rapid Response Research (RAPID) will employ modeling and simulation based research which, if successful, will assist in a more effective emergency response to the Horizon oil spill catastrophe. In particular, the proposal complements satellite imagery and in situ observational tracking with 3-D computational modeling and simulation in order to accurately predict the movement of the oil plume associated with the very recent, massive and continuing Deepwater Horizon oil spill. To date, both movement and quantity of the oil has been largely unpredictable hampering optimal use of available resources to contain, mitigate and clean up the oil. Given the current 200,000-2,000,000 gallon/day estimate, the longevity of the oil in seawater will require a sustained response.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are five research topics which will be pursued incrementally over the next twelve months: linking existing high resolution coastal circulation and wave models with an unstructured grid particle model (representing the spill movement); moving the linked models from 2D to 3D; refining the model based on real time observational data; optimizing the model to allow graphic output concurrent with model runs; introducing hurricane implications into the combined coastal model. Each individual topic as it is implemented, will improve predictability of the oil movement as it approaches shoreline.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the direct benefit of damage mitigation with improved oil tracking and prediction, the research from this award will have sustained value. The new simulation capabilities will be incorporated into existing coastal models, particularly those of the Gulf of Mexico, potentially giving benefit to any future emergency involving shoreline ecosystems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042314</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Luettich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rick_luettich@unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
      <CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
      <ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
