<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Sri Lanka Planning Visit: Hydraulics and Hydrology of Sri Lanka's Dry Zone Tank Cascade Systems in a Changing Landscape</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Lueck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Thomas Soerens&lt;br/&gt;OISE- 1042778 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;U.S.-Sri Lanka Planning Visit: Hydraulics and Hydrology of Sri Lanka?s Dry Zone Tank Cascade Systems in a Changing Landscape &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning visit will initiate a new research collaboration between University of Arkansas (UA) Civil Engineering Professor Thomas Soerens and University of Sri Jayewardenepura (USJ) Geography Professor G.M. Bandaranayake to study the hydraulics and hydrology of the reservoir cascade system in Sri Lanka's dry zone. Sri Lanka, which has no natural lakes, has a network of about 18,000 small to large water reservoirs, called 'tanks', which date back to at least the fourth century BC. Their purpose is to reuse water over and over and to recharge groundwater. The tank cascade systems show a high degree of sophistication in their construction and design. During the visit, the co-investigators will visit field sites in the dry zone to identify research sites, design the subsequent research project, and meet with Sri Lankan government officials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit- Professor Bandaranayake has studied the tank cascade systems using Landsat imagery and other geographic data, but now hopes to incorporate the engineering aspects of the systems. The collaboration with Dr. Soerens will bring expertise in hydraulics, water monitoring, and groundwater modeling and access to advanced geographic tools at UA?s Center for Advanced Spatial Technologies; Soerens will gain access to the field sites in Sri Lanka and the geographic expertise of his counterpart. This research collaboration will advance the study of the tank cascade systems, which to date have been studied only from historical, cultural, and geographic perspectives. The inclusion of quantitative investigations of their hydraulics and hydrology will advance understanding or these systems and enable the creation of a comprehensive model to analyze and predict the reaction of this important water resource in a changing landscape. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts- The tank cascade systems are the critical water resource for Sri Lanka's dry zone, which faces stresses from climate change and changes in population. The results of the proposed research could be key in planning and management of water resources and other infrastructure. The proposed collaboration will lead to an ongoing program for students and researchers from UA and USJ to work together in the field and at the universities. The connection between the PIs, USJ, and CAST will strengthen the capability of the PI and his students in geographic analysis and hydrologic modeling. For UA students, the work will broaden their education as they consider the historical and social perspective of the tank systems. For UA students that participate in the field research, it will be a transformative experience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042778</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Soerens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tsoerens@messiah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
      <CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5976</Code>
      <Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7497</Code>
      <Text>SRI LANKA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
