<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: EAGER--Dual-Polarimetric Doppler-On-Wheels Observations of Long Lake-Axis-Parallel Lake-effect Storms over Lakes Erie and Ontario</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34711</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020105</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nicholas F. Anderson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lake-effect snowstorms are a key source of wintertime precipitation and high-impact weather over the Great Lakes region. These storms typically evince one of two contrasting morphologies: Wind-parallel roll circulations in which elongated precipitation features are preferentially oriented along the prevailing low-level flow (and accompanying vertical wind shear), versus long lake-axis parallel (LLAP) precipitation bands that are typically more intense with a preferred mid-lake location. LLAP-type storms are more common over the Eastern Great Lakes (viz. Erie and Ontario), but have been studied far less than wind-parallel bands. This exploratory project will field a newly polarized single "Doppler on Wheels" (DOW) mobile radar to observe LLAP-type snowbands. These data, which will be collected during a five-week period during winter 2010-11, will be complemented by mobile rawinsonde-derived thermodynamic profiles obtained both within and external to these bands.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this effort centers on improved specification of the mesoscale morphology, evolution and precipitation mechanisms within intense LLAP-type lake effect snowbands. In view of this first-ever deployment of a polarized DOW in a cool-season setting, attention will be directed to a critical evaluation of polarization quantities and hydrometeor classification output from this recently upgraded platform.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts will accrue through support of research at a primarily undergraduate academic institution and via direct involvement of a group of undergraduate students in both the collection and analysis of this exploratory dataset. Results will be disseminated via conference presentations and formal publications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042854</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Frame</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>frame@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1525</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
