<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Support for the 2010 Integrated Photonics Research, Silicon and Nano Photonics Topical Meeting on July 25-28 in Monterey, CA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence S. Goldberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the 2010 Integrated Photonics Research, Silicon and Nano Photonics Topical Meeting, to be held at the Monterey Plaza Hotel in Monterey, California, on July 25-28, 2010, is to discuss the rapidly evolving technology, in a small group, with leaders in the field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit:&lt;br/&gt;The conference will assemble the key leaders in the field to present recent advances in Integrated Photonics research and will discuss future developments and applications in optical telecommunication, computing, storage, displays and monitoring. The meeting discussions will advance the leading edge of the research by bringing together researchers from the different disciplines, to define and answer their emerging needs of the next decades.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact:&lt;br/&gt;The Integrated Photonics research Topical Meeting has been the premier forum addressing the technology since 1972. It gathers both theoretical and experimental international experts in the field. The meeting offers a small platform conducive to direct dialog and discussions in identifying novel directions in photonics integration, enabled in particular by novel silicon and nano photonic technologies. This research covers multidisciplinary fields of science and impacts a broad range of applications, from the information technology to biomedical sensing.&lt;br/&gt;This Topical Meeting of the Optical Society of America will contribute to the training of participating students and the topics will be disseminated through the Conference Technical Digest.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1042572</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rogan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grants@osa.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liming.zhang@alcatel-lucent.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Optical Society of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200361012</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2024166102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2010 Massachusetts Avenue NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
