<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SREB-SBE Doctoral Scholars Institute Initiative</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>76520</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES-1043054&lt;br/&gt;Ansley Abraham&lt;br/&gt;Southern Regional Education Board&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Southern Regional Education Board (SREB) and the National Science Foundation (NSF) Alliances for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP) formed a partnership in 2002. This partnership resulted in the inclusion of 900+ AGEP Doctoral Scholars to attend and participate in the Annual Compact for Faculty Diversity Institute on Teaching and Mentoring. The Institute initiated in 1994 is the largest gathering of underrepresented minorities seeking a Ph.D. and who plan a career in postsecondary education. This grant will support the inclusion of 60 social, behavioral and economic sciences (SBE) scholars to attend the Institute in 2010. The SBE scholars will participate in services and activities that have contributed to the success of previous scholars attending the Institute. The inclusion of SBE scholars will achieve two broad goals: (1) provide SBE scholars with the knowledge, skills, and support that will increase the likelihood of success in graduate school; and (2) enhance preparation of SBE scholars for a career as a college or university faculty member. The Institute focuses on helping scholars build their teaching and mentoring skills and networks with other scholars and faculty representatives. Scholars attend workshops that enhance their skills and knowledge as they prepare for entry into the ranks of college and university faculty. Selected SBE scholars will participate in the Institute with scholars in different disciplines, but with the same goal of entering academia. Other agencies that participate are the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation Minority Ph.D. Program; Gates Millennium Scholars Program; National Institute of General Medical Sciences; Robert Wood Foundation; and the Ronald E. McNair Post-baccalaureate Achievement Program and the Southern Regional Education Board State Doctoral Scholars Program. The Institute is hosted by the Southern Regional Education Board (SREB), Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education (WICHE), and participating colleges/universities and states agencies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact. The Compact for Faculty Diversity Institute on Teaching and Mentoring has become the centerpiece activity that combines the strengths of both national and regional programs. As a national program, each fall the Compact convenes an Institute on Teaching and Mentoring which brings together all participating students and faculty for three days of intensive professional development experiences. The Institute has been successful in attracting faculty and minority and underserved doctoral scholars from every state and Puerto Rico. Since it was initiated in 1994 over six thousand attendees have participated in the Institute. The Institute is the largest gathering in America of racial/ethnic minority and underserved Ph.D. scholars seeking faculty careers in academia.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1043054</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ansley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abraham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ansley.abraham@sreb.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Regional Education Board</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303185776</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048759211</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>592 Tenth Street NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
