<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multi-Modal Modules for Learning Introductory Astronomy Concepts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>194196</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is developing interactive modules for teaching introductory astronomy. They focus on major topics that are covered in most introductory college courses. The modules are programmed in HTML5/Javascript so as to run on the widest possible spectrum of devices, including most moble devices (iPod, smart phones, etc.) and have a lengthy period of usability. Thus, this project also focuses on the underlying technology. The project is also developing a knowledge base that allows creation of effective learning materials for mobile and touch technologies and serve as a launching pad for other developers. The team is experienced in developing astronomy curriculum, interactive computer simulations, and web-based assessment software, and it is well-connected in the astronomy education community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the project consists of designing modules that work on the multitude of different computer, tablet, and smart phone platforms, operating systems, browsers, and touch capabilities. Considerable creativity is involved in designing simulations that function with mouse, touch-drag, or simply touch-push depending upon the device and are still useful at low resolution. All of this is being accomplished while retaining the best practices of interactive engagement by allowing students to explore with computer simulations, quizzing them over the concepts, and providing extensive feedback. The project is collecting usage data, allowing it to learn exactly how effective these modules were in promoting an understanding of astronomy concepts and a knowledge base related to how students make use of mobile technology that can inform pedagogy for these devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: It is clear that mobile devices are going to be a huge part of education in the very near future and that they hold a special appeal for today's students. However, very little work has been done on making use of mobile devices in STEM education. This project is creating a public library of code for mobile devices that is consistent with established web standards and a set of guidelines for future developers in the STEM community on how to effectively target mobile devices. There is a recognized need for trailblazing projects like this that lay the foundations for the mobile revolution that is just beginning.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1044658</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Claes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dclaes@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>klee6@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/07/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Orr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jorr@math.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/07/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7513</Code>
      <Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
