<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Enhancing the Electrical and Computer Engineering Curriculum by Integrating Applications of Wireless Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>134794</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The primary objective of this project is to enhance the Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) undergraduate curriculum through integration of applications of wireless technology. Specifically, the authors propose application-oriented projects to explore healthcare-related applications into the engineering curriculum. This modern curriculum in wireless communications and networking is aligned with ABET accreditation criteria. It consists of a course stream for wireless communications and networking specialization. Wireless technology and real world healthcare applications are integrated into four courses including the senior design projects of this specialization. These enhancements familiarize students with theoretical and practical aspects of wireless networked systems design, expose them to progressively more sophisticated theory and applications, and culminate in design projects applicable to real-life problems, including wireless networked human body monitoring systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project develops ECE students to become wireless technologists and engineers with knowledge and skills to explore the potential of wireless technology for biomedical applications. A close integration of engineering education and research improves the preparation of undergraduate students for careers in industry and academia. This plan includes a network of faculty from Computer Engineering departments at collaborating universities, including the University of Puerto Rico at Mayaguez, actively participating in the development and testing of the proposed curriculum. It is anticipated that this innovative approach, bridging connection between the healthcare and engineering fields, increases overall enrollment, especially females, in the engineering programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1044596</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tzhang@nyit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>McPherson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smcphers@nyit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Colef</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcolef@nyit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Old westbury</CityName>
      <ZipCode>115688000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5166867737</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Northern Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7513</Code>
      <Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
