<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Development Of Nanoporous Geopolymer Composites As Adsorbent For Arsenic Removal</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory T. Baxter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will focus on the development of novel environment-friendly nanoporous materials that can effectively absorb and thus remove arsenic from ground water at a very low cost, while providing a means for the safe disposal of the spent arsenic-containing materials. This will be accomplished by (1) preparing the nanoporous geopolymer materials by employing a patented, sustainable, and energy- and materials-efficient production method; (2) characterizing and improving the arsenic absorption capacity of the materials; and (3) examining the arsenic leaching behavior of the spent materials after stabilizing the materials through heat treatment at various temperatures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impacts of this research are (1) providing to the rural areas in the US and to the arsenic-ridden areas in developing countries, such as Bangladesh and India, an environment-friendly, cost-effective and easy-to-operate arsenic removal technology solution, and (2) providing to the environmental remediation industry a new class of materials that may be utilized in removing other water contaminants, such as heavy metals. The success of this research is critical in meeting the stricter requirement for arsenic in drinking water recently set by the US EPA, and also in helping foreign countries eradicate arsenic poisoning, one of the most devastating environmental disasters in the world. The novel material will be offered to replace the existing sorbent media, will provide performance/cost benefits for residential and commercial systems, and will enable a new water treatment plant design with both cost and environmental advantages.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1046473</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>ChangGong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>changgong.wang@nanovoltaix.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NanoVoltaics, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Phoenix</CityName>
      <ZipCode>850445673</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4802953505</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9831 S. 51st Street, C-112</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
