<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Nanoparticle Antimicrobial Coatings on Natural Scaffolds for Tissue Reconstruction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>171525</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruth M. Shuman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project addresses the important problem of combating hospital acquired infections with the development of novel tissue matrices aimed at preventing nosocomial microbial infection. The aim of this project is to combine antimicrobial nanomaterials and a natural dermis product to help prevent infections that occur during reconstructive surgeries. This proof-of-concept study will develop methods for the production of uniform and conformal coatings on natural tissue matrices using layer-by-layer assembly of antimicrobial nanoparticles. Importantly, this project will evaluate the efficacy of nanocoated natural dermis in eliminating or inhibiting bacterial growth in liquid and solid media. In vitro studies also will be conducted to establish mammalian cell toxicity and viability of the engineered dermis in supporting mammalian cell growth. Phase I results are expected to produce an optimized antimicrobial dermis scaffold that will be carried onto a focused Phase II evaluation in animal experimental wounds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will address the growing problem of hospital acquired infections from antibiotic resistant pathogens. With nearly 1.7 million hospital-acquired infections and 99,000 deaths per year, increases in antibiotic-resistant bacterial strains represent a critical safety concern and a significant cost burden to our nation's health care system. The proposed technology is a versatile option that provides a broad spectrum solution in combating bacterial infections and the prevalence of antibiotic resistance. Furthermore, the methods used to characterize the proposed composite materials will add valuable insight into mechanisms associated with nanoparticle-derived antimicrobial activity, and will help guide future efforts in the arena of nanobiotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1046687</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strickland</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>astrick@ifyber.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>iFyber, LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148500194</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6073302307</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2415 N. Triphammer Rd Ste 6</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9163</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9239</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>017E</Code>
      <Text>Cellular and Tissue Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>123E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8038</Code>
      <Text>Biotechnology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
