<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: A Real-time Infrared Raman-based Microalgal Analyzer for Monitoring Biofuel Production</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anthony Walters</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to develop an innovative Raman-based real-time microalgal biofuel analyzer. Although microalgae are popular feedstock with great potential for biofuel production, there is currently no suitable, fast and field-deployable analytical tool available. Current Raman systems cannot be deployed for microalgal applications due to deleterious broad interferences from microalgae?s abundant pigments, which emit fluorescence thousands times more intense than Raman signals from the components of interest. The proposed analyzer enables the characterization of microalgal productions of oil (bio-diesel) and other valuable components both qualitatively and quantitatively, in a non-destructive and real-time manner. This project is based on recent technology advances at BaySpec, Inc. in ultra-compact and narrow-line 1064-nm fiber lasers, volume-phase gratings, fiber optic probes and infrared detector arrays, coupled with Raman analyzing algorithms developed at Sandia National Labs. &lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impacts of this research will provide the biofuel industry and research institutions an unprecedented means of rapid and comprehensive algal and oil characterization in a compact, low-cost, rugged, field-deployable, universal analyzer. It will help to solve the problems due to the enormously large biodiversity and unexplored territories in microalgae. In addition to its commercial potential, the efficiency of R&amp;D efforts being undertaken around the world towards a sustainable and economic algal biofuel production will be greatly facilitated. Furthermore, this algal analyzer will have much wider applications, including environmental monitoring, homeland security, life science, and chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1047347</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pullins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spullins@bayspec.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/22/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>BaySpec, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951311706</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4085125928</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1101 McKay Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
