<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF/DOE Thermoelectrics Partnership: Integrated Design and Manufacturing of Cost-Effective and Industrial-Scalable TEG for Vehicle Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>530535</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1048744&lt;br/&gt;Zuo&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The objective of this research project is to establish and demonstrate a cost-effective and industrially scalable fabrication process of magnesium silicate (Mg2Si) and filled skutterudite thermoelectric (TE) components directly on cylindrical exhaust pipes using advanced thermal spray technology. The research approach progresses from non-equilibrium material synthesis and bench mark study of initial process optimization using low-cost FeSi2, and then transitioned to Mg2Si and filled skutterudites. A combined additive (thermal spray) and subtractive (laser cutting) processes will be used to pattern the various TE and support materials onto cylindrical pipes as most vehicle exhaust components. And the thermoelectric property of the TE device will be fully characterized. The proposed research will be completed by a multidisciplinary team consisting of expertise from the Departments of Mechanical Engineering and Materials Science, and the Center for High Pressure Research at Stony Brook University, and the Advanced Energy Materials group in the Condensed Matter Physics and Materials Science Department at Brookhaven National Laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: If successful, the results of this research will provide a low-cost, large-scale, workable solution to integrate vehicle TEGs for significant fuel savings with concomitant benefits to energy usage and the environment. It creates a new approach for low-cost manufacturing of silicide and filled skutterudite thermoelectric materials and devices for higher ZT. The proposed process eliminates the complicated assembly steps required in conventional, module-based TEGs. The interface adhesion between material layers is intrinsically strong, with no adhesives or mechanical clamping required, and thus enhances heat transfer, interface performance and durability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is integrated with are educational activities that will benefit both quality and diversity of graduate and undergraduate education as well as K-12 students through our one-of-a-kind outreach facilities and programs. The interaction with a national lab and industry at different ends of the application spectrum enable accelerated implementation of the developed knowledge.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1048744</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qiang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qiangli@bnl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Baosheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Baosheng.Li@sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Longtin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jon.Longtin@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sanjay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sampath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sanjay.sampath@sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zuo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leizuo@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8008</Code>
      <Text>NSF/DOE Thermoelectric Partner</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>J429</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>KX51</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>LX31</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>065E</Code>
      <Text>Radiation heat transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>099E</Code>
      <Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>104E</Code>
      <Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1761</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
