<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAR-PF: Large-scale climate controls on water isotopes in the tropical Pacific: an integrated observational and modeling strategy to improve paleoclimate interpretations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Jessica Conroy has been awarded an NSF Earth Sciences Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a research and education plan at Georgia Institute of Technology. Dr. Conroy will carry out a multi-year precipitation and seawater sampling program to assess stable isotopes variability on diurnal, seasonal, and interannual timescales across the equatorial Pacific Ocean. This information will then be coupled with instrumental climate data to investigate the climate controls on stable isotopes in precipitation and seawater. The data produced from this project will fill a critical gap in observational networks for water isotopes, providing for rigorous comparisons to isotope-equipped global climate models and satellite-based water isotope retrievals. An improved knowledge of the relationship between large-scale climate dynamics and water isotope variability in the tropical Pacific will also allow for more accurate interpretations of key tropical Pacific proxy records across a range of timescales.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Much of the importance of stable water isotopes lies in their ability to provide information on past climate change. The vast majority of tropical Pacific paleoclimate reconstructions from corals, speleothems, lake sediments, and marine sediments are based on the stable isotope values of oxygen and/or hydrogen, which reflect changes in large-scale hydrological processes, and, in the case of carbonate archives, temperature. Accurate interpretation of these records is critically important, since climate variability in this region impacts climate across the globe, most notably through the El Niño/Southern Oscillation phenomenon. Typically, output from isotope-equipped global climate models aids in the interpretation of isotope archives of past climate information, and forward modeling of proxies provides insight into the dominant controls on isotope-based proxy climate records. However, there are few real isotope measurements from the tropical Pacific to validate climate models and incorporate into forward modeling of proxies. The new dataset generated from this project will provide these measurements, helping us to understand the controls on stable water isotope variability and accurately interpret past climate variability in this important region. The planned education activities associated with this fellowship include the development of a "Stable Isotopes and Climate" curriculum for a local public high school and student science-fair projects, and the exposure of native Pacific Islanders to scientific data collection and interpretation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This fellowship is supported by the Paleolimate Program in the Division of Atmospheric and Geospace Scieneces.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1049664</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Conroy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>03/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Conroy Jessica L</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857164651</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber></PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress></StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
