<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Simulation-Aided Design and Synthesis of Bio-inspired Membranes for Water Desalination and Purification</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Membranes are well suited to desalinate or purify water, while using little power. Innovation is required, however, as scarcity of pure, fresh water is a growing concern. To guide the design of new membranes, we propose to learn from protein channels in cell walls, some of which are remarkably efficient for separations such as water desalination. This EAGER proposal focuses primarily on the high-risk, high-reward endeavor that consists of the synthesis of nanoporous silica membranes with tunable, controlled pore sizes and functional groups of the desired chemistry and charge, tethered to the surface. These will form the basis for realizing a proof-of concept bio-inspired membrane. We will extend our preliminary molecular simulations of biological nanopores to obtain fundamental understanding in the physico-chemical principles that are responsible for their superior performance. These principles will then guide the design of the artificial membranes. Permeance and selectivity of this proof-of-concept will be tested to validate the methodology, and as a basis for further performance and optimization studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite a vast literature on membrane separations, innovative chemical synthesis and molecular simulation-based design are rarely integrated. To date there is no validated, simulation-aided methodology to design artificial membranes based on the critical mechanisms underlying the performance of biological membranes. In a cell membrane, each aquaporin protein channel of nanoscale dimensions allows for the passage of three billion water molecules per second, while blocking protons from entering the cell. Discovering the principal molecular and cooperative interactions leading to the high permeation and selectivity of such pores is relevant to biology, but our main aim is to use the insights offered by these systems to implement an artificial membrane design for a purpose that mirrors that of the biological pores. To synthesize such a design is a non-trivial, high-risk effort, yet tremendous progress and our own experience in nanoscopically precise materials synthesis should allow us to implement structured designs, including ordered arrays of functionalized nanopores, as guided by the computations. This project merges innovation in materials science with state-of-the-art computational methods and guidance from biology to rationally design membranes for pressing water needs, using an approach that could extend to many other separation problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More than a billion people live without access to safe drinking water, making more effective water desalination and purification one of the National Academy of Engineering Grand Challenges. This research is a step toward high-performance membranes that seek to address those needs in a transformative way. The simulation-based design methodology is applicable to membranes for other separation processes, in pharmaceutics, biochemical processing or the energy field. In addition, this project offers a multidisciplinary educational experience for undergraduates. The New Visions Math, Engineering, Technology and Science (METS) program will continue to be used to involve high school students and attract them to studies in science and engineering. International exchanges will be strengthened, including collaboration with colleagues in Germany and at the National Institute of Materials Science in Japan.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1049207</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc-Olivier</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coppens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>coppens@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
