<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Social-Computational Systems (SoCS) Community Meeting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>48801</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Crowston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Systems in which people and computers work together in a socially intelligent manner represent a new form of computing that brings together the challenges of traditional computing (e.g., algorithms, information representation, information acquisition, data quality) with those of human interaction (e.g., cognition, social interaction, culture, learning) and indeed a whole host of new challenges related to the combination of humans and computers (e.g., computer reasoning about human knowledge and abilities, socially-intelligent human-computer interaction, social computing). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a workshop for researchers from the wide range of SoCS related disciplines. This SoCS community meeting (June 9-11, 2011) will provide the opportunity for researchers who are not currently involved in the SoCS program, but who are doing SoCS related research to engaged in critical cross-fertilizing discussions. This workshop is designed to build on and leverage two other SoCS related workshops that will be temporally and physically co-located.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1049455</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Loren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Terveen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>terveen@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
