<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Towards an Open Source Backpressure Protocol Stack for Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>While it has been shown theoretically that stochastic network&lt;br/&gt;optimization techniques utilizing queue backpressure can result in&lt;br/&gt;high performance cross-layer protocols, there has been limited prior&lt;br/&gt;work on translating them into practice. In this exploratory research&lt;br/&gt;project, we develop and demonstrate a novel cross-layer backpressure&lt;br/&gt;protocol stack for wireless sensor networks, building on our&lt;br/&gt;implementation of the backpressure collection protocol (BCP). The&lt;br/&gt;possible gains of this highly agile approach to cross-layer wireless&lt;br/&gt;networking are substantial and include increased throughput even in&lt;br/&gt;the presence of mobility, handling of bursty external interference&lt;br/&gt;events with reduced losses, and reduced protocol implementation&lt;br/&gt;complexity. We incorporate techniques for MAC-layer backoff&lt;br/&gt;prioritization, transport layer utility optimization, mechanisms to&lt;br/&gt;handle various kinds of network dynamics, and interoperability with&lt;br/&gt;asynchronous low power sleep schedules. Protocol implementation code&lt;br/&gt;developed in the project will be released publicly as open-source. It&lt;br/&gt;is expected that the successful completion of this project will&lt;br/&gt;provide an important proof-of-concept that stochastic optimization&lt;br/&gt;theory-driven protocols can be successful in practice.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1049541</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bhaskar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krishnamachari</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bkrishna@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neely</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mikejneely@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
