<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Studies of Deep Cavity Cavitands</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>134000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Bruce Gibb at the University of New Orleans is supported by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division to study the supramolecular chemistry of self-assembling systems in aqueous solution and to devise chemically complex systems possessing unusual properties. The first aim of this project is to investigate new separation protocols that utilize selective molecular encapsulation. In these systems, supramolecular structures encapsulate selected targets of complex chemical mixtures, isolating them from the bulk reactive environment. The second aim is to devise multi-(supra)molecular systems that evolve to equilibrium slowly and demonstrate unusual relationships between the components and the net overall state of the system. The third aim focuses on understanding supramolecular chemistry in the fluorous phase&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed studies investigate the properties of nano-sized capsules that are formed in water. The capsules trap other molecules within their interior and, much like familiar capsules for drug formulations, engender a physical separation between what is within the capsule and what lies outside. At the molecular level this separation leads to many unusual phenomena, two of which are being investigated in this program of study. They are: 1) New ways to bring about the separation of chemicals that cannot be separated by current technologies, with impact in areas such as biological and dietary science; 2) Complex chemical systems whose overall properties are greater than the sum of their parts. Complex systems demonstrate emergence, or properties and phenomena that only arise through synergism. Life-forms are considered complex systems, and the proposed studies will aid in disentangling the complex intertwining of different processes. The research project will offer a stimulating research environment for the education and training of students, including members of the underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1052806</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gibb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bgibb@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Orleans</Name>
      <CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
      <ZipCode>701480001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5042806836</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2000 Lakeshore Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
