<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Identity and Function of Heliconius Mimicry Genes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>365000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven L. Klein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A primary goal of modern biodiversity research is to identify the genes underlying adaptation and diversification. Despite the intense interest in this topic, relatively few such genes have been characterized from natural populations, and fewer still have been compared between species. Butterfly wing patterns represent an exceptional opportunity for identifying and studying adaptation genes. Indeed, for over a century wing patterns have been a favorite system for studying adaptation, primarily because the links between variation and adaptive value are so easy to understand - especially in cases such as mimicry, camouflage, startle response, and mate-choice. In this particular project the investigators will work to identify the major genes controlling mimicry-related color pattern variation in Heliconius butterflies. Remarkably, over the last 20 millions years it appears that only three major genes have been responsible for much of the dramatic color pattern variation in this genus. The investigators will apply modern genetic and developmental methods to characterize these genes and assess their functions across different species. By understanding these genes at a molecular level biologists will be better poised to understand why some genes tend to facilitate biological diversification more than others.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators of this project have strong records of involving students, including undergraduates, in laboratory research. The Reed Lab will continue to participate in the Bridges to the Baccalaureate program, which allows prospective community college transfer students from underserved populations to participate in summer research experiences, and W.O. McMillan and R. Papa will help develop and enhance Latin American Internship Programs at the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute at the University of Puerto Rico, respectively. This project will support the training of one graduate student and one postdoctoral researcher in the fields of genomics and developmental biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1052541</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>McMillan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>McMillanO@si.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reed</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robertreed@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Riccardo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Papa</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rpapalab@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1080</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTION OF DEVELOP MECHANISM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
