<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Particle Tribology Symposium: Convening Students &amp; Researchers to Increase Synergy &amp; Collaboration to Solve Complex Particle Problems; San Francisco, CA; October 17-20, 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides funds for the principal investigator to organize an international Particle Tribology Symposium (PTS) as a one-day event on the fundamental studies of particle related tribology and its application to manufacturing processes, energy related problems, and other related engineering areas. Tribology is the study of friction, lubrication, wear, and material removal. Particle tribology affects many areas of science and technology such as computer chip nano-manufacturing, magnetic hard disk drive technology, solar energy wafer processing, wind energy, agriculture, space technology development, and environmentally-benign lubrication. For example, particle slurries are used in special processes that polish computer chip and solar cell wafers to mirror smooth finishes. Magnetic hard disk drives and wind turbines are both technologies that are damaged by particulate contamination. While particle science scholars are often spread out amongst many different non-intersecting research communities, the PTS aims to increase the synergy by assembling these international and domestic scholars to have broader impact and ultimately create more innovative solutions to the world?s particle tribology challenges. The PTS will be held within the 2010 International Joint Tribology Conference (IJTC), which is co-sponsored by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers and the Society of Tribologists and Lubrication Engineers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The expected benefits from this symposium are that: (1) researchers from different sectors will convene to exchange ideas about solving various particle tribology problems; (2) students from America and other countries will convene to learn about their peers? research in a poster session/competition; (3) companies will have a vehicle to identify experts who are conducting innovative research to tackle their problems; (4) a larger than average number of researchers from underrepresented minority groups, at the junior professor and graduate student levels, are scheduled to participate in the PTS ensuring that the field of tribology and related fields benefits from America?s diverse population; and finally, (6) particle tribology researchers will receive supplemental support to bring more students to the PTS (and IJTC) ensuring a healthy pipeline of future innovators in this area.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1053147</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cecil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Higgs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>higgs@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>080E</Code>
      <Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
