<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Determining the molecular mechanisms of the Arabidopsis circadian clock: the role of the pseudo-response regulators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>882414</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gerald Schoenknecht</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The circadian clock is a self-sustained biological oscillator that enables organisms to both anticipate environmental changes and to coordinate different aspects of their physiology. In plants, the circadian clock is necessary for optimal growth and survival and regulates a wide range of physiological processes such as flowering and photosynthesis. The long-term goal of Dr. Farre's laboratory is to understand the design principles of circadian clocks as well as the role of the clock in plant growth and development. In particular, this project will help elucidate the molecular role of the morning expressed pseudo-response regulators PRR7 and PRR9 in the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana using molecular and biochemical approaches. These studies will define not only the molecular function of the PRRs in the circadian oscillator but also the direct role of clock components in the control of physiological responses in plants. Due to the architectural similarities between circadian networks in different organisms, this work will complement the analyses in other systems and advance our understanding of circadian clocks and their mechanisms to impact a large number of processes ranging from biomass production to human circadian disorders. Dr. Farre will also establish a two-year program at Michigan State University for students aimed at becoming secondary biology teachers to gain experience in scientific inquiry in a laboratory setting and to teach laboratory courses. Students will do a research internship in the Farre laboratory where they will work on their own research project associated with this award as well as establish a teaching unit that can be used in a high school class. Students will also be able to practice their teaching skills as teaching assistants of an undergraduate laboratory course.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1054243</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eva</FirstName>
      <LastName>Farre</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>farre@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
