<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Structure-Function Analysis of Germ Cell Organelles in Drosophila</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>778791</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual merit. Embryonic germ cells are eventually specified to become sperm and egg, and therefore are responsible for continuity of life. These cells belong to an intriguing class of stem cells, which are both highly specialized and able to give rise to all cell types after the union of egg and sperm produces an embryo. In many organisms, as diverse as rotifer and human, germ cells contain organelles, known as germ granules. Although germ granules were discovered more than 100 years ago, their composition, assembly, and function are not well understood. Since some of the identified granule components are crucial for germ cell specification, it has been hypothesized that these organelles play a major functional role in germline development. Proteins containing small structural modules (Tudor domains) have been identified in germ granules of various organisms. Recently these domains were found to directly interact with methylated amino acids of Piwi family proteins in flies (Drosophila), frogs, and mammals, demonstrating the remarkable evolutionary conservation of this interaction mechanism. The Tudor Piwi complex is required to safeguard the next generation of DNA against harmful mutations caused by mobile genetic elements, thus highlighting the fundamental biological role of this complex. Although Tudor domain proteins and Piwi interact in germ granules, the structure of this conserved Tudor Piwi complex and of its individual components is not known. This structural analysis, which is part of this project, will greatly advance the understanding of the assembly of these components and their functional arrangement within germ granules. The studies will provide the first structural snapshot of this large macromolecular complex of the granules. In addition, the project will test the idea that Tudor domain proteins frequently contain multiple domains that interact with different Tudor targets. Specifically, the aims of this project are (1) to determine the structure of the Drosophila Tudor Piwi protein complex in collaboration with an expert in single-particle cryo-electron microscopy, and 2) to test the hypothesis that the multiple Tudor domains of the Drosophila Tudor protein recognize novel targets in embryonic germ granules. Experiments will also be undertaken to identify potential new Tudor targets using a novel in vivo chemical crosslinking approach to stabilize Tudor and its interacting proteins in living embryos, and a subsequent mass spectrometry analysis of resulting purified complexes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts. This research will be integrated with educational activities, including training and mentoring of a postdoctoral researcher and graduate and undergraduate students. Under the supervision of the principal investigator, the postdoctoral scholar and graduate students will design and teach a molecular genetics laboratory course for college seniors and graduate students. In addition, high school interns will be actively recruited to carry out research during the summer. A Personal Response System (PRS) will be used to evaluate the impact of research topics incorporated into course lectures based on immediate student interest and motivation as measured by computer-logged responses using remote input devices. The postdoctoral researcher, students, and the principal investigator will actively participate in several university-supported outreach activities, including the Posters-at-the-Capitol conference at the Kentucky state capitol, during which students present their research to their state representatives and the general public. Furthermore, the students and investigator will discuss their research on the university radio, which has a listening audience in five states, and in the university weekly newspaper. Students at Murray State University, who are 60% women and 35% first-generation college students, including a large proportion from groups underrepresented in science, will be recruited to participate in this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1054962</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Arkov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aarkov@murraystate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Murray State University</Name>
      <CityName>Murray</CityName>
      <ZipCode>420713318</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2708093534</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>328 Wells Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1114</Code>
      <Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1114</Code>
      <Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
