<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PECASE: Implementing K-12 Engineering Standards through STEM Integration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400109</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Donna Riley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This engineering education research project seeks to understand different mechanisms of integrating engineering content and standards into K-12 classrooms. The project will use a mixed methods design incorporating multiple case studies and data sources to elucidate the strategies teachers use and the obstacles they encounter in addressing engineering standards in the K-12 classroom. The project seeks to provide theoretical understanding of various methods of integrating engineering content into classrooms by working closely with teachers in custom-designed teaching laboratories.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project are to understand various ways of integrating STEM content into K-12 classrooms and thus potentially broaden the pipeline into college STEM programs and STEM careers. As more states integrate engineering into K-12 content and standards, this study which will elucidate effective means to support this integration has potentially broad impact. The projects rigorous focus on a diverse cross-section of schools may help to make the results broadly generalizable.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1055382</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tamara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tamara@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
