<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Structural and Electronic Contributions to Reactivity in Peroxomanganese(III) Compounds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>488931</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program supports the CAREER award of Professor Timothy Jackson at the University of Kansas who performs research to understand the mechanisms of Manganese (Mn) enzymes and improve synthetic catalysts that catalyze a diverse array of reactions including the detoxification of reactive oxygen species in humans, the degradation of aromatics in bacteria and fungi, and the conversion of nucleotides to deoxynucleotides in pathogens. Peroxomanganese(III) (MnIII-O2) adducts have been proposed as crucial intermediates in these biological and synthetic systems. Professor Jackson will use spectroscopic and computational tools to define the structural, electronic, magnetic, and reactivity properties of peroxomanganese (III) intermediates supported by ligands relevant to biological and synthetic systems. This work will advance our understanding of Mn enzymes and aid in the development of Mn oxidation catalysts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation, Professor Timothy Jackson will perform research that can lead to better catalyst design and improved understanding of enzymes. This can ultimately translate into improved diagnostic and therapeutic medicinal agents. The outreach program is very creative and extremely well organized and planned. The proposed outreach activities will provide an opportunity for 100 middle school girls, minorities, and those from economically-disadvantaged backgrounds to explore how electromagnetic radiation (light) affects their daily lives. To integrate research and education experiences, graduate and undergraduate students will serve as camp mentors. The summer camps should have a direct and positive impact on underrepresented groups in science at the important age of middle school students. The development of a camp website with pedagogical videos will provide broad dissemination of camp materials. Some of the initial research data have already been presented in peer-reviewed journals and at professional meetings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1056470</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jackson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>taj@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
