<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Synthesis of Covalent Organic Frameworks with Novel Optoelectronic Properties</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>650000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, William Dichtel of Cornell University will study covalent organic frameworks (COFs) that exhibit efficient charge transport as a consequence of their long-range order. Despite their great promise, the limited syntheses of COFs have remained a significant roadblock to increasing their complexity. The research objectives include developing new methods for COF formation, preparing COF-based materials with morphologies long thought to be ideal for organic photovoltaic performance, and studying their charge separation and transport properties. The project integrates several educational initiatives with these research efforts, including science workshops on solar energy for middle school students, professional support for high school science teachers, and developing engaging content that will enhance public awareness of organic chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work offers a new strategy for improving the performance of organic electronic devices, whose economic importance is expected to grow significantly over the next decade. New synthetic methods for COFs will enable and inspire many other applications for these exciting materials. The project will also contribute to a deeper understanding of charge separation and transport in organic materials, key processes for increasing the efficiency of organic photovoltaic devices. New photovoltaic technologies are critical to sustainable energy generation and the future of the United States economy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1056657</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dichtel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wdichtel@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5560</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY CONVERSION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
