<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Engineering of III-Nitride Quantum Heterostructures Doped with Lanthanides</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>443956</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tania Paskova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical: The research component of this CAREER award is to study low-dimensional quantum structures of group-III nitride materials doped with rare-earth ions. The research includes materials characterization using optical, electrical, magnetic, and pressure stimulus, comprehensive modeling, as well as molecular beam epitaxy and pulsed-laser deposition growth in collaboration with other scientists on and off the Ohio University campus. The energy transfer processes between rare-earth ions and III-N hosts and rare-earth ion-defects formation and their nature are the main factors contributing to the quantum efficiency, ferromagnetism, and electronic transport of this materials system. The project investigates approaches to significantly increase radiative quantum yield. Strategies such as modification of the rare-earth ion center environment, through engineering stress/strain parameters during the materials growth process, and localization of carriers in the vicinity of emitting rare-earth ion center, by using quantum structures, are employed. The fundamental atomic level mechanisms and phenomena coupled with synthesis and material processing affecting luminescence, energy excitation processes, and local site symmetry of rare-earth impurities are studied in the project.&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic research issues in a topical area of materials science with high technological relevance. The development of new materials is important to the future needs of semiconductor industries. The project, if successful, can have impacts on the advancement of photonics. The research and education activities of the project are integrated. The central theme of the education activities is to develop photonic curriculum in the PI's department at Ohio University. New photonic courses and laboratories are designed to allow active engagement of undergraduate and graduate students in solving real-world problems. In addition, the outreach component of the project provides intellectual opportunities and stimulation for secondary school and pre-engineering students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1056493</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wojciech</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jadwisienczak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jadwisie@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/03/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio University</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7405932857</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>108 CUTLER HL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
