<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Hydrophilic and Reactive QDs: Ligand Design, Surface Characterization and Effective Strategies for Coupling to Biomolecules</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry (MSN) program of the Division of Chemistry will support the research program of Prof. Hedi Mattoussi of Florida State University. Prof. Mattoussi and his research group will develop luminescent quantum dot-based probes for biological applications. The project focuses on the development of a set of modular compact and multifunctional ligands for capping luminescent quantum dots (QD)-based nano-probes and the development of analytical tools to characterize them. Characterization entails determining the density of surface ligands, the number of functional groups per nanoparticle, and the development of covalently coupled QD-peptide assemblies that can be used as fluorescence resonance energy transfer substrates to evaluate the enzymatic activity of two matrix metalloproteinase proteins. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide a chemical platform to prepare stable hydrophilic luminescent quantum dots and quantum dot constructs that could be used to interrogate complex biological systems in real time. For example, quantum dot-constructs could be used to study the kinetic activity of specific enzymes and the kinetics of ligand-receptor binding. Improved understanding of enzyme kinetics and ligand-receptor binding interactions is crucial to understanding the molecular mechanism of disease development and progression and for the development of new drugs. The study will provide excellent training opportunities to students and postgraduates who seek interdisciplinary research training in synthetic chemistry and biological imaging. Prof. Mattoussi and his students will carry out extensive outreach activities to undergraduate students, including students from underrepresented groups at Florida A&amp;M to broaden participation of students from underrepresented groups in nanoscience research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058957</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hedi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mattoussi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mattoussi@chem.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
