<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanoscience Scholars II</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>590299</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Connie K. Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Nanoscience Scholars II program is providing scholarships and academic support to science students pursuing a baccalaureate in any science discipline, with either a minor in nanotechnology or a secondary associate of applied science in nanotechnology degree (in addition to the baccalaureate). The program uses nanoscale science and nanotechnology - exciting fields at the interface between disciplines to attract and engage new students. It builds on an NSF sponsored S-STEM program. This project is accomplishing two important goals. First, it is enabling the institution to thoroughly evaluate whether this strategy that focuses on interdisciplinary nanotechnology, intensive support through the Global Honors Program and the Nano Club science learning community, and increasingly independent research opportunities is an effective and replicable means to encourage more students to pursue education and careers in science and to help them succeed and graduate. Second, by enabling the institution to support additional cohorts of students for four years each, it is creating sufficient critical mass in terms of successful students and graduates over a long enough duration to institutionalize and sustain the program without external funding.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A new emphasis during this phase is on more intensive recruitment, focusing on high school guidance counselors in school districts with a high proportion of underrepresented and economically disadvantaged students. Scholarships are being determined by verified unmet need. Participants also receive a one-time scholarship for a Nanomanufacturing Technology Semester at the ATE Center at Penn State University. The Global Honors Program is helping students succeed through small, dynamic classes, a required first year seminar that introduces students to nanoscience and basic research and presentation skills, and the student directed Nano Club science learning community that helps support, motivate, and engage students throughout their undergraduate career. Optional opportunities to engage in meaningful research with faculty mentors involve students and arm them with the experience and motivation to pursue graduate education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Nanotechnology is inherently interdisciplinary. It offers opportunities for collaboration across disciplines and is an ideal focal point for attracting students to all sciences. The faculty Nanotechnology Group at the college supports students and models interdisciplinary collaboration. Science curricula require sequential acquisition of knowledge and skills along directed paths. Scholarships help students stay in college and in the sequences critical to success. The program features peer support and research opportunities, and provides the societal and implementation context that math and science courses often lack and are important factors in retaining underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: As lead institution in the Pennsylvania Collaborative for Applied Nanotechnology (PACAN), the college is situated to share experience and successes with other universities in the Pennsylvania State System of Higher Education, more than half of which are also developing nanotechnology programs. If nanotechnology and nanoscale sciences prove a logical entry into all sciences, the project plans to encourage other small institutions in Pennsylvania and around the nation to replicate this model.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058829</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whitling</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwhitlin@lhup.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cullin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcullin@lhup.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cullin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcullin@lhup.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/06/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goonewardene</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>agoonewa@lhup.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/06/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>McGinn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmcginn@lhup.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/26/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lock Haven University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Lock Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>177452390</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5704842001</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>401 North Fairview Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
