<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Gold Catalyzed Polymerizations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Catalysis Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation supports Professor Alexandru Asandei of the University of Connecticut, for the development of novel gold-based organometallic polymerization catalysts. The goal of this work is to understand the balance of ligand properties surrounding gold in various oxidation states needed to effect addition, condensation, coordination and free radical polymerizations. Possible substrates include diynes, dienes, and dicarbonyls. The nature of this research is that of a survey, taking a "broad strokes" approach to ligand design, catalyst properties, and the desired polymerization reactions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of broader impacts, much of this research is uncharted territory in terms of chemical reactivity and has the potential to lead to many new and interesting materials. The proposed investigations concern a comprehensive but rational approach to finding opportunities and applications of gold catalysis in polymer chemistry, based on knowledge emerging from current organic/organometallic Au chemistry developments, and from established polymerization principles. Professor Asandei has the general goal of being able to "tune" material properties with appropriate catalyst design. The work is amenable to undergraduate research, and there will be significant outreach to the community through workshops in local high schools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058980</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexandru</FirstName>
      <LastName>Asandei</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>asandei@ims.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
