<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Role and Formation of Tyrosine-Cysteine Protein Cofactors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>344015</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David A. Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will investigate the ability of tyrosine and cysteine sidechains of proteins to crosslink through an arylalkylthioether bond (abbreviated as Tyr-Cys). Tyr-Cys crosslinks participate in oxidation catalysis and are formed by two proton-coupled oxidations. Metal-oxygen chemistry and the correct sidechain geometries are necessary for Tyr-Cys crosslink formation. Only four examples have been identified using X-ray crystallography that suggests limitations from the chemistry, sidechain geometries, or detection methods. A search of all protein structures in the protein databank showed many proteins with appropriate sidechain geometries for Tyr-Cys crosslink formation. Based on conditions for dityrosine formation, the chemistry for Tyr-Cys should be facile under biological conditions. Tyr-Cys identification by X-ray crystallography, however, requires careful analysis of high-resolution data. In order in better identify Tyr-Cys crosslinks a proteolysis and HPLC separation method will be employed using mass spectrometry and nuclear magnetic resonance detection. Cysteine dioxygnease contains a Tyr-Cys crosslink and will be examined for method validation. The three other proteins where Tyr-Cys have not been previously observed will be used to test if the combination of these detection methods and a previous protein databank search will expand the number of Tyr-Cys crosslinks simply examining static protein structure. This information, along with reexamining the function of Tyr-Cys in cystiene dioxygenase, will determine if the biological scope of Tyr-Cys containing proteins is significantly broader than currently thought.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this award come from the potential to expand the biological scope of the Tyr-Cys crosslink and parent crosslinked protein derived cofactors. Additionally, this award will use NSF-supported instrumentation and a newly renovated interdisciplinary laboratory. This work will prepare four undergraduate chemistry/biochemistry majors for graduate work in areas related to protein chemistry. This award will also provide indirect training for up to ten additional undergraduate researchers in a shared interdisciplinary research lab. Two high school students who are underrepresented minorities in the sciences will be mentored by the PI and co-PI in conjunction with ACS Project SEED.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058391</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Benson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>deb22@calvin.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tatko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cdt2@calvin.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Calvin College</Name>
      <CityName>GRAND RAPIDS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>495464301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6165266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3201 BURTON ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6883</Code>
      <Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1982</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6883</Code>
      <Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
