<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Functional Augmentation of Existing Networks with New Neurons</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Krastan B. Blagoev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The discovery that new neurons are born in adult brains and integrate into functional networks raised questions about the dynamics of this process. Namely, what are the activity dependent queues guiding the integration of the new cells into existing networks and how do these queues depend on the intrinsic properties of the augmented networks? The focus of this project is to develop an integrated computational and experimental framework, which will allow for investigation of dynamical mechanisms underlying migration and incorporation of newly born neurons into existing networks. We specifically want to understand whether, and how, network augmentation depends on the ongoing activity of the original network, and to discern the collective changes in the network activity patterns specifically due to network augmentation. To do so the PI will develop a computational approach that will allow him to elucidate links between cellular mechanisms of network augmentation and their network-wide outcomes. In addition the PI will use an in vitro experimental system based on dissociated cell cultures to monitor patterns of network augmentation and changes in spatio-temporal activity, after GFP labeled neuroblasts are added. The neural activity using multi-electrode arrays and calcium imaging will be recorded, and then labeling studies to elucidate structural patterns of neural augmentation will be performed. The proposed project will provide a better understanding of the interaction of cellular and network mechanisms underlying function-dependent network augmentation. This is critical for identifying dynamical mechanisms of self-reorganization in these types systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will allow three collaborating laboratories to serve as a training resource for undergraduate and graduate students. The students will have the opportunity to gain experience in truly interdisciplinary research combining theoretical physics, modeling and neurobiology. They will further gain experience in the scientific process through participation in interdisciplinary meetings to present their results. The knowledge gained through this research will be disseminated to members of the scientific community through publications, seminars, and workshops. Additionally, the obtained results will be incorporated in the "Biocomplexity" course that the PI has developed for the advanced undergraduates.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1058034</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lsander@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zochowski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michalz@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Parent</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>parent@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7246</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
