<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF GRFP Engineering Innovation Fellows Programs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>749285</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding in FY 2010 to the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) to establish the Graduate Research Fellows Program (GRFP) Engineering Innovation Fellows program that will provide 40 2nd year and beyond GRFP fellows in engineering disciplines the opportunity to participate in research activities in an industrial setting during the summer of 2011. This project will be under the direction of Dr. Frank Huband.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the challenges that the country faces today, there is an urgent need to tranform the economy with science and technology. Research challenges include energy independence, climate control and the development of credible economic models for a successful and sustained recovery of our economy. It is very important to have engineers and scientists looking for the next great discovery, creating jobs in cutting-edge technologies and making informed investments that will help industries succeed in a global economy. Of primary importance is the development of industrial R&amp;D opportunities for the next generation of technology leaders in an environment that will stimulate innovation and invention.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This pilot program will be a partnership between the federal government and various industrial sponsors. The program will aim to encourage the involvement of creative and highly trained engineers already participating in the NSF GRFP in areas of research that have a great interest and relevance to the nation as we face current economic challenges. The benefits of this program will include both the enhancement of the knowledge and skills of the GRFP Fellows through their corporate research experience and the enhancement of the entrepreneurial businesses' innovation capabilities through the infusion of the research capabilities of the Fellows. With the U.S. leadership focusing more on the potential contributions of academic research and development efforts to enhance the competitiveness of U.S. industries, this program provides a complement to their discipline specific training. Fellows are expected to gain an understanding of business value and an ability to work in multi-cultural environments on their journey to becoming innovators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1059472</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huband</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>f.huband@asee.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/04/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fortenberry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>N.Fortenberry@asee.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lyle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feisel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>l.feisel@asee.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/23/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Society For Engineering Education</Name>
      <CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200362476</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023313500</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW STE 600</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7172</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE RESEARCH FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1414</Code>
      <Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1385</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL STUDIES AND ANALYSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>118E</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>119E</Code>
      <Text>FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
