<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SHINE: Observationally Constraining the Physical Processes that Generate the Solar Wind</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>575454</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ilia I. Roussev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposers will investigate Alfven waves and magnetic reconnection as primary sources for the heating and acceleration of the solar wind. This research team will analyze new spectroscopic data from the "Extreme ultraviolet Imaging Spectrometer" onboard the Hinode spacecraft in order to resolve the current debate as to whether Alfven waves carry sufficient energy to heat and accelerate the solar wind. The proposers note that these results will provide much needed empirical data to constrain the competing wave-driven and turbulence-driven models of the solar wind, and ultimately help to determine the true solar wind acceleration mechanism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By providing hands-on research experiences for individual teachers each summer at Columbia University's "Summer Research Program for Science Teachers," this team will help improve the commitment and scientific understanding of middle and high school science teachers from the New York City metropolitan area. This activity will have far reaching benefits, since analysis of Columbia's 21-year-old outreach program shows that the teachers who have participated go on to teach about 1,000 students each over the next ten years and also see a 10% increase in the pass rate of their students on the New York State Regents science exam. The proposers will also visit middle and high school science classes to explain their research and answer questions directly from students. Given the fact that New York City has a diverse student population with a high percentage of underrepresented groups and minorities, these education and outreach efforts constitute a high impact program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1060194</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel Wolf</FirstName>
      <LastName>Savin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>savin@astro.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
