<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Keck Geology Consortium--Providing Collaborative and Year-long Research Experiences for Undergraduates</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>783894</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Keck Geology Consortium, comprising 18 primarily undergraduate institutions, will offer summer research experiences for ~51 undergraduates each of three years, building on 23 years of successful programming involving over 1100 students (56% women). Students will be recruited from the 18 schools, and 30% will come from non-Consortium institutions. Summer research projects will be continued in the following academic year as independent study projects, with presentations at the culminating Keck Annual Research Symposium in the spring. Students will publish short contributions in the annual proceedings volume and will be encouraged to present their work at regional and national disciplinary meetings. The proposed projects involve a mix of field and laboratory research experiences that will make meaningful scientific contributions in the areas of structural geology, paleontology and paleoecology, and paleoclimatology as well as igneous and metamorphic petrology, sedimentology and stratigraphy, volcanology, geomorphology and geoarchaeology. The yearlong Keck Consortium program enhances students' scientific and geoscience research skills and provides a robust scientific experience culminating in presentation of results at the annual research symposium and publication in the proceedings volume.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1062720</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Varga</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bob.varga@pomona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pomona College</Name>
      <CityName>Claremont</CityName>
      <ZipCode>917114434</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9096218328</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Alexander Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
