<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Phylogenetic Systematics of Orthoptera (Insecta): Evolution of Male Genitalia and Study of Nuclear Mitochondrial Pseudogenes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/04/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>122992</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elliott Francis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A team of entomologists at Brigham Young University will investigate the evolutionary relationships within Orthoptera, an insect group that contains grasshoppers, crickets, and katydids. They will generate DNA sequences from 168 species to address three fundamental questions: How are the major groups of Orthoptera related to each other? How has the male reproductive system, one of the most important characters in orthopteran classification, evolved? How do non-functional copies of mitochondrial genes evolve in Orthoptera? Investigators will conduct international field studies to collect specimens and then analyze the data using advanced analytic software and high-resolution digital imaging technology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The results from this project will not only advance our understanding of orthopteran diversity, but also provide an excellent model system to study the evolution of the male reproductive system and mitochondrial DNA. The comprehensive scope of this project will facilitate domestic and international collaborations. A six-week summer workshop for each of the three years of funding will provide training in modern methods of systematic analysis and scientific communication to three undergraduates of Pacific Island descent. Additionally, one postdoctoral researcher and two undergraduates will be trained by thoroughly being involved in all aspects of this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1064082</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hojun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Song</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hsong@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1355</Code>
      <Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
