<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AF: Medium: Collaborative Research: Optimality in Homology - Algorithms and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>276121</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jack Snoeyink</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Many applications in science and engineering encounter the problem of&lt;br/&gt;identifying and processing topologically interesting features in the&lt;br/&gt;digital representation of a geometry or data. Such features often need&lt;br/&gt;to be optimal with respect to some metric (measurement). It is&lt;br/&gt;recognized that homology groups from algebraic topology play an&lt;br/&gt;essential role in these computations. Although the study of structural&lt;br/&gt;properties of the homology groups has a rich history in mathematics,&lt;br/&gt;their computations in combination with geometry are not that well&lt;br/&gt;studied. The principal investigators (PIs) propose to study these&lt;br/&gt;fundamental questions thoroughly, along with their connections to&lt;br/&gt;practical problems from science and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: Efficient solutions of the optimality questions in&lt;br/&gt;homology computations require both mathematical and algorithmic&lt;br/&gt;developments. The PIs bring aboard these required expertise. Apart&lt;br/&gt;from the synergistic effect of the proposed study on mathematics and&lt;br/&gt;theoretical computer science, the close ties with various applications&lt;br/&gt;in science and engineering will play a synergistic role between&lt;br/&gt;computational fields such as computer graphics, computer vision,&lt;br/&gt;sensor networks, computer aided design, and scientific fields such as&lt;br/&gt;biology, physics, chemistry, and others.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: Optimization of aspects of homology groups provides&lt;br/&gt;important insights in many scientific and engineering applications&lt;br/&gt;ranging from tunnels in protein molecules to voids in large&lt;br/&gt;machines. Solutions of such problems can aid in the manufacturing of&lt;br/&gt;better machines, designing of new drugs, and rapid modeling of&lt;br/&gt;customized objects. The educational impact of this project is in a&lt;br/&gt;large synergy between mathematics and computer science motivated by&lt;br/&gt;real applications. Course notes, internet distributions, and software&lt;br/&gt;systems developed through the project will enable the scientific&lt;br/&gt;community to study challenging problems in geometry, topology, and&lt;br/&gt;algorithms. Graduate students supported by the project will develop&lt;br/&gt;skills in mathematics and theoretical computer science and also in&lt;br/&gt;writing robust, efficient, and user-friendly software.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1064600</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bala</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krishnamoorthy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bkrishna@math.wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington State University</Name>
      <CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7796</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7929</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL GEOMETRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
