<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SHF: MEDIUM: Collaborative Research: Architecture, Programmability, and Performance of Large Scale Parallel Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>439733</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tao Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The advent of new microprocessor chip architectures (e.g., GPUs, multi-core/many-core chips architectures), next generation large scale integrated problems such as datacenter applications points to the need for a comprehensive rethinking of the approach to architecture design, programming, and software design. The research proposed in this document will be concerned with the characteristic behavior of future applications, highlighted by the performance, scalability, and how computer systems (execution and architecture models, and compilers/runtime software technologies) can be appropriately targeted. This work will result in the characterization of the features and requirements of such applications, in the development of suitable execution and architecture models that match their needs, and in the development of a compilation technology and its associated tools that will work in coordination with the proposed architecture models for the targeted application domains. The outcome of the proposed research will be an in-depth understanding of the needs of future applications, the demonstration of new architecture ideas, as well as the design of compilation methods and tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1065448</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Guang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ggao@eecis.udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7941</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7942</Code>
      <Text>HIGH-PERFORMANCE COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
