<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research: Periods of Automorphic Forms and Applications to L- Functions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>286271</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tie Luo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project centers around the interactions between periods of automorphic forms, automorphic &lt;br/&gt;representations, and arithmetic algebraic geometry. In particular the PIs propose to work on several problems on the general derivative conjecture, analysis and arithmetic of Fourier coefficients on exceptional groups, bounds on heights, computational study of nontempered periods, averages/nonvanishing of derivatives of L-series. Recently the study of periods has yielded new results and proofs about L-functions, breakthroughs towards conjectures about algebraic cycles, and new perspectives on classical questions of representation theory. Combined with other tools, periods have also enhanced our understanding of equidistribution problems and topology on locally symmetric spaces. The PIs are at the forefront of these developments. The proposed framework presents an ambitious plan to work on and formulate conjectures incorporating/connecting the recent groundbreaking works in these areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research topic is central to several areas of mathematics (arithmetic geometry, automorphic representation theory, analytic number theory). A long range goal of the project is to establish a network of scientists working in automorphic representations, number theory, and arithmetic geometry. The PIs envision a group of PhD students and post-docs participating actively in the proposed Research Retreats and Annual Workshops. This group would include the 15 PhD students presently advised by the PIs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1065839</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shou-wu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shouwu@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1616</Code>
      <Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
