<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Inverse methods for tuning dynamics of complex fluids</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>281745</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Truskett, Thomas M.&lt;br/&gt;CBET-1065357&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Diffusing Probes of kT-scale Specific Protein-Protein and Protein-Carbohydrate Interactions&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is concerned with using Diffusing Colloidal Probe Microscopy (DCPM) to directly&lt;br/&gt;and nonintrusively measure kT and nanometer scale interactions of surface immobilized proteins and&lt;br/&gt;carbohydrates. Ensembles of freely diffusing colloids will be employed as ultra-sensitive probes to&lt;br/&gt;measure energy vs. separation dependent protein-protein and protein-carbohydrate potentials of mean&lt;br/&gt;force (PMF) between proteins/carbohydrates attached to colloids and planar surfaces. By using&lt;br/&gt;evanescent wave and video microscopy, DCPM will monitor three dimensional Brownian excursions of&lt;br/&gt;protein decorated colloids near homogeneous, heterogeneous, and patterned substrates with covalently&lt;br/&gt;attached and oriented proteins/carbohydrates. Because diffusing probes sample spatial positions according&lt;br/&gt;to their relative energies, statistical mechanical analyses of diffusing probes can be interpreted as net&lt;br/&gt;PMFs including superimposable non-specific (colloidal, macromolecular) and specific (residues,&lt;br/&gt;conformational) contributions. DCPM will interrogate protein and carbohydrate interactions by exploiting&lt;br/&gt;natural gauges accessible with diffusing colloidal probes including Brownian time scales (a2 /D), thermal&lt;br/&gt;energies (kT), and molecular length scales (nm) (and hence weak forces (~fN)).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed research is related to the fundamental and technological&lt;br/&gt;insights that will be gained into immobilized protein-protein and protein-carbohydrate interactions.&lt;br/&gt;Specific biomolecular interactions to be investigated include: (1) Ca2+ dependent homophilic and&lt;br/&gt;heterophilic cadherin interactions on supported lipid bilayers, (2) CD44-hyaluronic acid (HA) interactions&lt;br/&gt;in the presence of competing oligosaccharides. Cadherins are transmembrane proteins whose interactions&lt;br/&gt;play a critical role in determining cell adhesion in cellular processes including for example tissue&lt;br/&gt;morphogenesis, synaptic plasticity, apoptosis, and cancer metastasis. CD44 is the main cell surface&lt;br/&gt;signaling receptor for HA, which is an extracellular matrix component. As a result, CD44-HA interactions&lt;br/&gt;regulate cell-cell adhesion, cell migration, morphogenesis, cell proliferation, cell signaling via regulation&lt;br/&gt;of gene expression and RNA splicing, cell differentiation, and metastasis. Ultimately, measuring how&lt;br/&gt;immobilized cadherin-cadherin and CD44-HA interactions are influenced by physical, chemical, and&lt;br/&gt;biochemical variables is important to understanding fundamental biology and biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;The first task of the proposed work is to covalently attach/orient proteins and carbohydrates onto&lt;br/&gt;silica colloids and surfaces either with or without supported lipid bilayers. To allow for deconvolution of&lt;br/&gt;non-specific and specific contributions to net potentials, the second task is to measure how the&lt;br/&gt;interactions of covalently attached/oriented carbohydrates and proteins are influenced by varying solution&lt;br/&gt;chemistries (e.g. ions, small molecules), physical configuration (e.g. orientation, spatial organization),&lt;br/&gt;competitive interactions (e.g. antibodies, monosaccharides), and biochemical variations (e.g. different&lt;br/&gt;types, mutations). The last task is to measure non-specific and specific interactions on model arrays&lt;br/&gt;consisting of patterned regions of carbohydrates or covalently attached/oriented proteins. Successful&lt;br/&gt;completion of proposed objectives will demonstrate a conceptually new approach to directly and&lt;br/&gt;sensitively quantify kT-scale non-specific and specific interactions that control non-covalent, equilibrium&lt;br/&gt;binding of proteins and carbohydrates immobilized on particles and surfaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposed research include scientific and technological outcomes as&lt;br/&gt;well as integrated education and outreach activities. The ability to directly and sensitively measure weak&lt;br/&gt;interactions between proteins and carbohydrate on synthetic material surfaces provides information to&lt;br/&gt;enable many biomedical applications involving diagnostics, devices, therapeutics, drug delivery, and&lt;br/&gt;tissue engineering. Such understanding provides a basis to quantitatively design, control, and optimize&lt;br/&gt;(formally engineer) the properties and behavior of immobilized proteins and carbohydrates in biomedical&lt;br/&gt;applications and provide new insights beyond what is known from trial-and-error discovery. In terms of&lt;br/&gt;education, research images/videos will be incorporated into undergraduate thermo and graduate&lt;br/&gt;colloid/polymer elective courses and execution of the proposed research will involve training&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate and graduate students. In terms of outreach, content involving optical microscopy of&lt;br/&gt;colloids will be adapted for use in programs for 7-12 students and public museum presentations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1065357</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Truskett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>truskett@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
