<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TC: Medium: Collaborative Research: Random Number Generation and Use in Virtualized Environments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>749149</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Hypervisors and virtualization simplify application and system deployment. The many benefits of virtualization have resulted in a headlong rush into a world where virtualization is ubiquitous. However, virtualization can break assumptions that applications and operating systems make about the platform. This research investigates an important case: the intersection of virtualization and random-number generators (RNGs). Strong randomization is requisite in today's computer security tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Deployment of existing RNGs in virtualized settings introduces vulnerabilities. When RNGs fail, catastrophic attacks can be mounted on the the cryptographic services upon which modern information security relies. VM snapshots, which can be used to reset a VM and its contained applications, can cause RNGs to repeat outputs and break some encryption systems. Moreover, the environment presented by virtualization can degrade the quality of RNG outputs because entropy sources are virtual rather than physical hardware and hence lower quality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research develops the theoretical and architectural foundations for the next generation of RNG designs and RNG-using mechanisms. The investigators quantify the scope of VM-introduced vulnerabilities using dynamic and static analysis of program source code. They develop new, secure RNG systems for use in VMs. Finally, the reserearch advances cryptographic theory by extending provable security techniques to better account for the realities of RNG deployment and use in virtualized settings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work not only provides practical impact via stronger RNG systems but also opens up new directions in cryptographic theory in the important areas of generating and using randomness.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1065134</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ristenpart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ristenpart@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>03/26/2015</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swift</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swift@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swift</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swift@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>03/26/2015</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7795</Code>
      <Text>TRUSTWORTHY COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7795</Code>
      <Text>TRUSTWORTHY COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
