<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dynamics of Deformable Drops and Biomimetic Capsules in Microfluidic Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>305000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1066904&lt;br/&gt;PI: Osuji&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In recent years it has become clear that improved understanding of the hydrodynamics of highly-confined deformable particles is important for exploiting the full potential of microfluidic technology. Particularly promising is the development of microfluidic devices to assay the mechanical parameters of cell membranes for use in screening for certain diseases. In principle, such devices could be constructed using the current microfluidic fabrication techniques, yet they have not been developed, at least in part because of a lack of fundamental knowledge about the micro-hydrodynamics of deformable particles in typical micro&amp;#64258;uidic architectures and the absence of a suitable numerical formulation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to advance a fundamental understanding of the collective dynamics of deformable particles in micro&amp;#64258;uidic networks and to explore the feasibility of using micro&amp;#64258;uidic devices to differentiate particles based on their deformability. The investigation involves closely coupled experiments and numerical simulations. The specific objectives include: (1) to develop robust methods for controlled synthesis of vesicles, capsules, and drops with tailored deformation properties; to conduct experiments using these particles to explore the dependence of particle dynamics on deformation parameters; (2) to design and fabricate novel micro&amp;#64258;uidic devices to explore the feasibility of sorting vesicles and drops based on deformability parameters; and (3) to develop many-particle computer simulation of highly-confined deformable particles in micro&amp;#64258;uidic channels and at junctions between channels. &lt;br/&gt;Understanding the dynamics of deformable particles in microchannels has long been recognized an important aspect of diverse phenomena such as oil recovery and refining operations, environmental remediation, and blood flow in the microcirculation. A fundamental understanding of this problem is central to the development of microfluidic devices for bio-analytical applications that often involve flows of microscopic deformable particles. The proposed investigation will further a basic understanding of the collective dynamics of confined deformable particles. This project will thus advance a rational framework for the design and optimization of microfluidic devices for a broad class of applications. Moreover, this project may lead to new biomedical devices for sorting cells based on their mechanical properties as well as assaying cell populations for diseased states based on deformability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Graduate students involved in this study will acquire a broad engineering science and mathematics background. The proposed study will provide undergraduates with exposure to research through REU projects related to the project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1066904</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chinedum</FirstName>
      <LastName>Osuji</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chinedum.osuji@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Loewenberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael.loewenberg@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1415</Code>
      <Text>PARTICULATE &amp;MULTIPHASE PROCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>056E</Code>
      <Text>Multiphase flow</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
