<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Chinese Ways of Innovation: Strategic Directions of Research on Chinese Innovation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>58188</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Clive Woods</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a joint research workshop on Chinese ways of innovation, bringing together researchers from the U.S. and China. The workshop will address several key questions about the processes of technological innovation and economic development in China, promote new research collaborations in this area, and formulate a focused research agenda. The three key questions to be addressed are: (1) Does China present a new paradigm for successful innovation? (2) How does innovation occur in China? (3) How does the process of innovation differ from that in other developing and developed countries? The four-day workshop, to be held in Los Angeles in May 2011, will produce a white paper outlining promising approaches to research in this field that would be widely disseminated. &lt;br/&gt;Although the processes of innovation that occur in the U.S. and other developed countries have been studied and are relatively well understood, much less systematic research has been directed at the rapidly developing countries such as China. Creating a framework for such study and catalyzing collaborative research internationally to identify the key elements of innovation and development in China, the workshop will elucidate policy questions that can impact local and regional development. The outcomes of the workshop and subsequent research can be valuable to governments and industry leaders in guiding future development around the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1066036</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yifei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yifei.sun@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peilei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fanpeile@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The University Corporation, Northridge</Name>
      <CityName>Northridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>913308309</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8186772901</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>18111 Nordhoff Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
