<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research in High Energy Theoretical Physics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Keith R. Dienes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professor Carleton DeTar at the University of Utah.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the rapid growth of computing power over the past couple of decades and equally important improvements in computer algorithms, physicists are now able, with the aid of high-performance computing, to solve quantum chromodynamics (QCD), the theory of interacting quarks and gluons, to high precision. This capability has revolutionized this subfield of theoretical high energy physics and brought such studies to the precision frontier, just as the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) in Europe is advancing the energy frontier. In this research project, Professor DeTar and students will be using computer simulations to extract the most precise values to date of key constants in the Standard Model of the fundamental interactions. The results to be obtained will be essential for analyzing experimental measurements at national accelerator laboratories and at the LHC, as well as for testing the internal consistency of the Standard Model. Professor DeTar and his students will also continue studies of the high-temperature phase transition between confined matter and the quark-gluon plasma, and they will study the charm quark content of the plasma. This novel plasma occurred in the evolution of the early universe and has been shown to be produced in the laboratory in collisions of heavy ions at the RHIC accelerator at Brookhaven National Laboratory and at the LHC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research also has broader impacts. Valuable data files and effective codes are disseminated widely and used by other researchers throughout the world. Graduate students are trained, not only in physics, but also in state-of-the-art methods for solving general problems using high-performance computers. Research results also figure into classroom instruction, both undergraduate and graduate. Finally, this research activity enhances the local computing infrastructure and expertise at the University of Utah.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1067881</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carleton</FirstName>
      <LastName>DeTar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>detar@physics.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1286</Code>
      <Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
