<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Innovative Microfabricated Ionic Wind Pump Array for Thermal Management Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>286867</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PIs: Norman C. Tien, Alexis R. Abramson &lt;br/&gt;Proposal #: 1067159&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As microelectronics components continue to be miniaturized, power density is increasing substantially, and considerations for novel thermal management solutions are becoming critical. New technologies such as the proposed microfabricated ionic wind pump must offer a superior solution that meets industry requirements for heat removal effectiveness and is silent, contains no moving parts, and boasts a low weight and volume. In response to this need, the objective of this research is to model, design, fabricate and test an innovative, microfabricated ionic wind pump that ultimately outperforms a conventional CPU muffin fan. The ionic wind pump device works by applying a sufficiently high voltage between emitting and collecting electrodes, which causes nearby air molecules to be propelled from emitter to collector due to the presence of a high electric field, resulting in convective cooling. &lt;br/&gt;Methods and approaches employed for this work include: computational multiphysics modeling for device design optimization, particle image velocimetry for flow visualization, device microfabrication (including growth of carbon nanotubes as emitter tips) and device testing. The expected outcome of this work will be the development of an innovative ionic wind pump device that either alone or in conjunction with a thermal spreader, demonstrates enhanced heat removal capabilities as compared with conventional technologies. This "active heat sink" device will meet various industry requirements and will have the potential to replace existing cooling fan technologies used in laptops and other portable devices, making them more reliable, of smaller form factors and quieter.&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this proposal includes the systematic modeling, design, fabrication and testing of an ionic wind pump device, which will lead to the advancement of knowledge and understanding in the fields of electrohydrodynamics, thermal transport, fluid mechanics and microfabrication. Some preliminary data for this work has been collected including initial computational modeling, microfabrication of first generation test structures, flow visualization and experimental validation of the cooling phenomenon. This investigation is transformative because we are investigating at the intersection of electrohydrodynamics and thermal transport, wherein lies the potential for a unique and commercializable thermal management solution. The proposed program will leverage the respective strengths of the investigators, utilizing proven techniques available in the PI's laboratories and at multi-user facilities at CWRU.&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this proposal includes advancing the discovery and development of an innovative, microfabricated thermal management device to enable future progress in the high-speed electronics industry. All levels of students will be involved in this research project: at least one Ph.D. student, one Masters student, four undergraduate students and various high school students will be introduced to real-world problems associated with this work. A two week lesson on microfabrication/MEMS in Dr. Abramson's "Introduction to Nanotechnology" course will be developed. To promote high school participation, an exciting teaching module on the topic of thermal management will be tested at local high schools and publicly disseminated. Results from research will be further disseminated via conference presentations, journal papers and web site publication to enhance scientific and technological understanding.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1067159</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abramson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ara9@cwru.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jaikrishnan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kadambi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jrkadambi@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abramson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ara9@cwru.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/10/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tien</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>norman.tien@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/10/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>064E</Code>
      <Text>Convection heat and mass transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
