<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NDSO2015: National Data Science Organizers Workshop 2015</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>32073</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Chaitanya Baru</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Interest in Data Science has been increasing at a breathtaking pace, as a result of the vast amounts of data that are being generated and collected across all sectors of society and economy. Many Data Science Meetup groups have been created across the country, each with an active local membership and a vibrant set of community-driven activities. The objective of this workshop is to connect the rapidly growing number of participants in these Data Science Meetup groups, in order to take the best advantage of this wealth of data science talent across the nation in addressing some of the national priority goals, including the goal of creating a well-educated Data Science workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will result in data science meetup groups collaborating with local governments and non-profits to advance their impact and create data science solutions to national priority issues, including socioeconomic issues. The workshop will allow participants to network with their peers, including meetup organizers, nonprofits, government agencies, in order to create a national data science network. The meeting organizers have an established track record and extensive experience working with governments and non-profits on the use of data science techniques to address social issues, and have created several open source systems to address education, health, energy, and economic development problems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1600085</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rayid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghani</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rayid@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/27/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8083</Code>
      <Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8083</Code>
      <Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
