<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Dimensional touch: pressure-sensitive touchscreens for mobile applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The most common type of touchscreen - capacitive touchscreen - is capable of detecting the location of touch, but not the amount of force. The development of a pressure-sensitive touchscreen technology that can measure the location of touch as well as the amount of force applied is crucial for empowering next generation cell-phone and interactive electronics including advanced 3D navigation, graphic design, stylus operation, and medical care. This I-Corps team has developed a pressure sensitive touchscreen technology that can compete with capacitive technology on both cost and performance. The proposed touchscreen can detect where and how hard the user is touching, has the potential to replace the capacitive touchscreen while adding new features, and disrupt the touchscreen technology market. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Major cell phone manufacturers can sell up to 13 million units within the first three days of launch of a flagship device. Most recent generations of cell phones incorporate the "3D Touch" technology that allows two-level, force-based interaction with mobile apps, and variable range pressure sensitive touch screens are yet to be developed. The technology currently employed causes an increased display unit weight from 12 grams to 29 grams. The proposed technology provides variable range pressure sensitivity and additional functionality without increasing the display weight. The weight savings would lead to a reduction of shipping weight by about 200,000 kilograms for the first three days of sales, reducing transportation and energy costs, not to mention providing enhanced user experiences. Therefore, the proposed technology would allow "3D Touch" functionality that facilitates cheaper phone models and improved user-phone interaction. Additionally, this technology results in more ergonomic keyboards and reduces user fatigue. The application of the pressure sensitive touch screen extends well beyond cell phones to virtually any remote/touchscreen control that requires analog input of forces and pressures, including steering, medical, mechanical, and military domains. Through the NSF National I-Corps program, this I-Corps Team will interview 100 touchscreen industry contacts, including potential customers, partners, and advisors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1600329</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shadi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dayeh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sdayeh@ece.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
