<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometric Invariants of Rational Functions, with Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>70000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Polynomials, and more generally rational functions (meaning ratios between two polynomials), are used throughout science and engineering, since they are the functions that are best understood. It turns out that most rational functions of any given degree will behave similarly in almost every application. The goal of this research project is to determine the special rational functions whose behavior differs from this typical behavior. This will have important applications in various areas of mathematics, as well as in science and engineering. Much of the research will be carried out in collaboration with junior mathematicians ranging from high school students to postdoctoral researchers, thereby providing a rare opportunity for such junior mathematicians to play a significant role in the proofs of important results. Several of these junior mathematicians will be members of underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposed work is to determine all possibilities for the essential geometric data describing the "shape" of the function induced by a complex rational function, namely the monodromy group and ramification type. This problem has been studied by Hurwitz, Ritt, Zariski, Thompson, Guralnick, and other mathematicians, and it now seems possible to solve it in case the rational function is not the composition of lower-degree rational functions. A solution would resolve longstanding questions about diophantine equations, dynamical systems, value distribution of meromorphic functions, and several other topics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1601844</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zieve</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mzieve@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
