<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Midwestern Young Researchers Conference on Commutative Algebra and Related Disciplines: KUMUNU Jr 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy Hodges</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the 2016 KUMUNUJr meeting to be held at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln during April 23-24, 2016. KUMUNUJr is an annual conference series designed to promote interaction among junior researchers in commutative algebra and related disciplines (including homological algebra, algebraic geometry, K-theory, and coding theory) at Midwestern schools. The conference series is anchored by the Universities of Kansas (KU), Missouri - Columbia (MU), and Nebraska - Lincoln (NU). The gathering will provide an opportunity for young algebraists to interact and establish research connections with each other. This interaction will help to lay a foundation for fruitful research collaborations as the participants advance in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the conference are to foster collaboration among junior researchers in commutative algebra from Midwestern institutions, and to expose commutative algebra students and postdocs from Midwestern institutions to the current work being done in their fields at neighboring institutions. The conference will last for two days and will feature six talks by post-docs or senior graduate students and five talks by junior graduate students. The conference will be open to all interested graduate students and post-docs. Special efforts will be made to recruit women and underrepresented minorities. More information can be found at the conference web page: http://www.math.unl.edu/~ecanton2/KUMUNUjr/2016/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1601292</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mwalker5@math.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lutz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlutz3@math.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dailey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddailey2@math.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 Vine St, 151 Whittier</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
