<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>National Center for Supply Chain Automation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3999495</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David B. Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Supply Chain Automation is a new and fast-growing industry in the global market. Neither industry nor post-secondary education institutions have been primed for addressing the needs of this emerging sector, and both have struggled to adequately prepare existing and incoming workforce for the rapidly evolving technologies which drive the industry. The National Center for Supply Chain Automation is the formal medium for engaging both parties in a national dialog to ensure educators are preparing students for the rapid growth in this high technology job sector. The Center has the capacity to provide education and career pathways to thousands of Americans leading to living wage jobs. Within a six month training period, students enrolled in SCA Technician programs can earn national industry approved certifications leading to advanced certification and degree options for further career advancement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Norco College, with lead colleges and partners, will target services to the top 19 states with the greatest concentration of supply chain activity and employment. The National Center will (1) implement model 2+2 SCA career pathways through high school and community college partnerships to increase the number of skilled SCA Technicians entering the workforce; (2) convene supply chain automation stakeholders via a National Symposium to deliver professional development and establish a community of practice by engaging ATE Centers and projects focused on related disciplines; (3) increase the number of underrepresented participants entering the field; (4) disseminate information and product deliverables for secondary and post-secondary educators through conference presentations and participation in panel discussions, producing and publishing newsletters, videos, white papers, labor market studies and integrating social media channels with digital content; and, (5) establish and promote a stackable national industry certification for Supply Chain Automation Technician, validated and recognized by industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1601452</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fleming</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Kevin.Fleming@rcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sompolski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>somplski@oakton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ned</FirstName>
      <LastName>Young</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ned.young@sinclair.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Riverside Community College District/Norco Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Norco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>928602600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9513727015</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2001 Third Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
