<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Coupling Tribocharging and Hydrodynamics in Fliuidized Beds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>393037</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET - 1601986&lt;br/&gt;PI: Sundaresan, Sankaran&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tribocharging refers to the exchange of electric charge between two materials that make mechanical contact with each other. It is observed in many situations involving flows of particles suspended in a gas. One industrially important example is tribocharging in a fluidized bed chemical reactor. In this kind of reactor, gas flows through a bed of particles at such high rates that the particles become "fluidized," and the particles and gas behave as a fluid mixture. This project seeks to understand how tribocharging affects the fluid dynamics of gas-particle suspensions. Models will be developed to explain and predict how the dynamics of tribocharging and hydrodynamics of gas-particle suspensions are affected by material characteristics, humidity, and particle size. The research will be the first study that focuses specifically on the coupling between tribocharging and fluidization hydrodynamics. The results will be useful in a wide range of industrial processes involving gas-solid suspensions, because tribocharging can create significant hazards and reduce process efficiencies. The project will provide opportunities for students at various academic levels to participate in research, including high-school students who participate in Princeton's summer Laboratory Learning Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the project are to develop and validate a computational model that accounts for tribocharging and electrostatic forces in fluid-particle flow systems, to understand how electrostatics affect hydrodynamics, and to understand the transient rate of charging in these systems. The model will use an effective work function for triboelectric charging that captures charge transfer owing to differences in material of contacting particles, differences in overall charge of contacting particles, differences in sizes of the contacting particles and humidity. The effective work function will be incorporated into a model that combines a discrete element method for resolving particle contacts with computational fluid dynamics for resolving larger scales of the flow. Model parameters will be calibrated using vibrated bed experiments. Then, the model's predictions of fluidized bed dynamics will be tested against experiments in which particle material, size, humidity and the wall material of the fluidized bed are systematically varied. Results of the study will provide useful information for industrial practitioners to improve processes involving granular materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1601986</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sankaran</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sundaresan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sundar@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1415</Code>
      <Text>PARTICULATE &amp;MULTIPHASE PROCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
