<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>P2C2: Reconstruction and Dynamics of Interhemispheric Hydroclimate Variability between the Americas</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>626108</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020108</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David J. Verardo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The general goal of this project is to develop a pan-Pacific drought atlas using tree-ring records. This research specifically aims to explore: 1) drought occurrences and dynamics across the Americas; 2) inter-hemispheric regimes of decadal-to-centennial hydroclimate variability; 3) large-scale footprints and temporal properties of extreme events (including responses to volcanism, solar forcing and internal variability); and 4) past hydroclimatic drought events in reference to their underlying dynamics thereby offering insight into some of the most disruptive climatic events of the last millennium. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hydroclimate patterns will be analyzed for their associated dynamics and diagnosed for their connection to large-scale modes of variability and/or forced patterns of change. Multidecadal hydroclimate anomalies (e.g. megadroughts or pluvials) will be evaluated to determine if they arise from inter-hemispheric-scale climate regimes with coherence across continents or as more local continental-scale phenomena. Similarly, extremes in individual years will be assessed for their dynamic origins and probability of occurrence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Why this research? Characterizing and understanding large-scale hydroclimate variability during the last millennium is a critical means of evaluating and improving projections of future hydroclimate change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Why this research now? Two recent developments make the time ripe for significant advances in this area of research. First, fully pan-Pacific reconstructions of last-millennium hydroclimate variability are now within reach. Second, the large and growing ensemble of last-millennium simulations with fully-coupled climate models make dynamic investigations of past hydroclimate change possible thereby providing potentially improved assessments of projected future risks and impacts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will help improve the understanding of extreme climatic events climate and includes a substantive leveraging of international collaboration with South American colleagues in Argentina and Chile, creation of a user-friendly drought atlas, and public outreach on science and education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1602581</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seager</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>seager@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cook</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drdendro@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smerdon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jsmerdon@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>williams@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1530</Code>
      <Text>PALEOCLIMATE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5740</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7754</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY &amp; CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8070</Code>
      <Text>P2C2 Proposals</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
