<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for Active and Smart Matter: A New Frontier for Science and Engineering Conference; Syracuse University; June 20-23, 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daryl W. Hess</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Division of Materials Research, the Division of Physics, and the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems contribute funds to this award that provides support for an Institute of Complex and Adaptive Matter conference on active and smart matter to be held at Syracuse University in June of 2016. This conference brings together a diverse group of scientists from a wide variety of disciplines: physics, chemistry, biology, engineering, and medicine. The focus of the conference is on the merging of science and engineering using active and smart matter platforms. Examples of issues that will be addressed include how active and smart matter can help drive self-assembly to build self-replicating objects, and what physical interactions lead to observed patterns in systems whose constituents can communicate with each other. NSF support will enable the participation of 100 contributors, who might not otherwise be able to attend. Approximately one-third of the participants will be young researchers, graduate students and postdoctoral researchers, who will also benefit from mentorship activities during the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;he Division of Materials Research, the Division of Physics, and the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems contribute funds to this award that provides support for an Institute of Complex and Adaptive Matter conference on active and smart matter to be held at Syracuse University in June of 2016. This conference brings together a diverse group of scientists from a wide variety of disciplines: physics, chemistry, biology, engineering, and medicine. The focus of the conference is on the merging of science and engineering using active and smart matter platforms. Examples of issues that will be addressed include how active and smart matter can help drive self-assembly to build self-replicating objects, and what physical interactions lead to observed patterns in systems whose constituents can communicate with each other. NSF support will enable the participation of 100 contributors, who might not otherwise be able to attend. Approximately one-third of the participants will be young researchers, graduate students and postdoctoral researchers, who will also benefit from mentorship activities during the conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1602298</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paulsen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdpaulse@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schwarz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jschwarz@physics.syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>M. Cristina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marchetti</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcmarche@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Henderson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhhender@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1415</Code>
      <Text>PARTICULATE &amp;MULTIPHASE PROCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1765</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7246</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
