<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>INTRACELLULAR ELECTROCHEMISTRY WITH CARBON NANOTUBE-BASED SENSORS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>294103</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Schrlau, Michael &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1604893&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project proposes to create a very tiny biosensor for identifying and quantifying biomolecules inside a single living cell. The investigator proposes a novel way of performing selective measurement inside living cells, (instead of currently used methods of breaking open the cell), and after proving the approach plan is to quantify cellular metabolic state in real time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to create the ability to identify and quantify biomolecules inside a single living cell with minimal perturbation and over long periods of time using electrochemical techniques. Multifunctional nanoprobe will be constructed, capable of injecting fluids in order to conduct self-contained electrochemical measurements inside confined aqueous microenvironments. The nanoprobe is then utilized to inject a reaction-enabling substrate into the cell for selectively quantifying senescence-associated beta-galactosidase, a cytosolic enzyme, an indicator of many chronic diseases. It is proposed to use carbon nanotube (CNT) -based nanoprobes will provide the ability for selectively quantifying cell senescence in real-time. It is anticipated that at the conclusion of the project, there will be a new analytical tool and technique for quantifying electroactive biomolecules within single living cells. Simple, scalable template-based nanomanufacturing processes will be employed to integrate the nanoelectrodes into the tip of a pulled glass capillary without nanoassembly. The CNT-based nanoprobe is designed to readily fit standard cell physiology instruments, thus facilitating easy technological dissemination, broad utilization, and potential commercialization. The outcome of this proposal is likely to provide a first-in-class CNT-based tool for a novel minimally invasive analytical technique for gathering quantitative data from single living cells. The proposed efforts will generate new insights into fundamental cell physiology, which will ultimately help identify the early onset of diseases, facilitate drug development and improve therapeutic efficacy. More broadly, the development of intracellular electrochemistry will advance scientific knowledge in nanotechnology, materials science and engineering, electrochemistry, cell biology, and biomedicine. Further, the project will provide several high-impact research and educational opportunities for students at all levels as well as recruits and will support underrepresented groups in STEM.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1604893</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>KSV</FirstName>
      <LastName>Santhanam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksssch@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schrlau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mgseme@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
      <CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
