<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developing Active Artificial Hair Cell Sensors Inspired by the Cochlear Amplifier</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>333680</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Tarazaga, Pablo &lt;br/&gt;Proposal No: 1604360 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will develop a new approach for amplification of sound with potential applications to hearing impaired. The device will sense incident sound and amplify it in a new way such that lower threshold is detected, sharper frequency sensitivity and superior dynamic range are also expected. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of proposed research program is to develop piezoelectric-based, active artificial hair cells (AHCs) capable of mimicking the important aspects of nonlinear cochlear amplifier. They will possess a lower threshold of detection, sharper frequency sensitivity, and larger dynamic range than a traditional, passive transducer. The proposed work will examine a variety of feedback control schemes to achieve a cochlea-like response from piezoelectric-based, cantilever beam sensors. The work will explore using self-sensing methods to transition from lab experiments to practical sensors. Scalability analysis is expected to guide the design and fabrication of miniaturized active AHCs at scales suitable for use in practical applications. An array of active sensing elements for transducing multiple frequency signals will be built and tested. These sensors could also serve as a tool for auditory researchers to gain insight into a healthy cochlea. While the importance and general behavior of the cochlear amplifier is well established, there are unanswered questions over how this amplification arises. Various control laws can be tested on artificial hair cells to test different theories and develop insights into the functioning of biological cochlea. It is anticipated that this work will help establish improved cochlear implants, thereby improving the quality of life of over 30 million Americans who suffer from permanent hearing loss. Potentially the active artificial hair cells could lead to new cochlear prosthesis and restore hearing function. This research program will offer an excellent learning and education for underrepresented undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1604360</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pablo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tarazaga</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ptarazag@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Joyce</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bjoyce1@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
