<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Effect of free-stream disturbances on turbulent boundary layers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>277821</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Zaki, Tamer&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1605404&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a GOALI project that is focused on the computational investigation of the fundamental interactions between free turbulence and the turbulent boundary layer. The proposal will employ high fidelity direct numerical simulations and conditional sampling techniques. The industrial collaborator is at GE, and this collaboration can lead to a project that will be concerned with flow conditions that are relevant to practical applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work aims to fill a gap in current understanding and practice of designing engines with low emission goals. Currently, the design process is based on correlations that are extracted from studies of flows without accounting for background disturbances. Often efficiency is sacrificed in favor of reliability and safety. However, background disturbances can cause distortions that are not predictable. This GOALI proposal address this gap by providing the missing fundamental research that will enable more efficient and reliable designs and, in turn, better engine performance and cleaner operation. There is also a strong outreach plan that will leverage existing activities at Johns Hopkins, including activities for K-12 students. The graduate student involved in this project will benefit from the mentoring of the industrial co-PI and will spend time at GE.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1605404</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheung</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cheungl@stanfordalumni.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tamer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zaki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>t.zaki@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
