<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development and study of new generation of ultrabright fluorescent FRET-based sensing nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>476460</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1605405 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fluorescence is a powerful optical tool in biology and medicine. While the majority of fluorophores are used for imaging, some of them can also be utilized to detect the presence of particular ions. Fluorophores can also be functionalized to adhere to specific chemical structures. While being highly desirable, it is extremely difficult to create molecular fluorophores which can be functionalized and work as sensors. Fluorescent nanoparticles (NPs) offer a unique combination by having a fluorescent sensing core and a functionalizable surface. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to develop a new generation of bright fluorescent silica NPs that will work as sensors and be functionalizable with a variety of molecules. The proposed hybrid fluorescent nanoparticles (NPs) are novel and pioneered by the PI. The significantly improved brightness of the NPs could enable many applications that were previously impossible. The proposed super bright hybrid NPs would become a powerful tool for many biomedical applications that are not addressable with fluorescent dyes. The educational impact will include the direct exposure of the research to his graduate student and his post-doc on the grant, the PI has and will continue to involve undergraduates in the research. He will incorporate the research findings into existing courses he teaches and will maintain existing outreach efforts and public presentations in high schools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1605405</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Igor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sokolov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Igor.Sokolov@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>P. Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hoopes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>P.Jack.Hoopes@Dartmouth.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tufts University</Name>
      <CityName>Medford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021555807</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6176273417</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>20 Professors Row</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7236</Code>
      <Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
