<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Evaporation-driven Capillary Flow in Paper-Based Microfluidic Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>78096</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Martinez, Andres&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1605499&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposed research is to study fluid flow through the capillaries in microPADS (a special type of paper that can be used for analytic purposes in bio-related diagnostics in areas where complex hardware is not available.) A model for the process is proposed to be developed in collaboration with researchers at Princeton University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work focuses on the experimental study and modeling of evaporation-driven capillary flow (ECF) through paper-based microfluidic devices (microPADs) in order to use this type of fluid transport for the development of paper-based diagnostic devices capable of performing automated multi-step assays. The proposed work will result in an investigation of ECF in microPADs with infinite and finite fluid reservoirs; an investigation of the effects of the design of the microPAD on ECF; the development of mathematical models to describe ECF in microPADs, and the application of these models toward the design and development of prototype microPADs for conducting automated multi-step diagnostic assays, including an enzyme inhibition assay and an immuno-chromatographic assay with signal amplification. All the experimental work will be conducted by undergraduate student using relatively simple materials and fabrication methods. The proposed work will also serve to advance the general understanding of ECF, with implications for other systems such as plants and plasticbased microfluidic devices. The work with prototype diagnostic devices will elucidate mechanisms for developing more sophisticated point-of-care diagnostic assays that are still very simple to use. Finally, the project will enable the development of new assays that require at least two, timed, sequential steps, and that were previously not possible due to limitations with the current capabilities of microPADs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1605499</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andres</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martinez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>awmartin@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Polytechnic State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Luis Obispo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>934070830</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8057562982</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Grand Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
