<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research in High Energy Particle Physics at CMS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>430000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James T. Shank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This program of research aims to better understand the Universe at the smallest scales by probing nature's basic symmetries and their relation to the origin of mass. The 2012 discovery of a Higgs boson with mass close to 125 GeV represents both the crowning achievement of the standard model of particle physics and a hint beyond it - how can a light Higgs boson possibly survive huge, destabilizing quantum effects without new, undiscovered physics? Further, dark matter is known to exist from astronomical observations; however the particle properties of dark matter remain shrouded in mystery. The combined activities of the UIC group address those basic questions puzzling science - the origin of mass and the particle nature of dark matter - and have the potential for surprising discoveries that may change the way we understand our physical world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award also supports technological advances for high energy frontier experiments, in particular building and commissioning sophisticated high-speed electronics and silicon tracking systems for particle physics experiments. The challenges faced in advancing those technologies enhance the disciplinary knowledge in engineering fields. The data analyses and hardware projects supported by this award provide valuable experience and knowledge for students and post doctoral associates at UIC, enabling them to pursue successful careers in the private sector, academia, or research laboratories. The UIC group also fosters close collaboration between high school teachers and the UIC group members, strengthening teaching and learning in Chicago-area high schools. As these high schools serve predominantly minority students, this project aims to increase the number of students from historically underrepresented groups that major in STEM disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1606321</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>adams@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nikos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Varelas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>varelas@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cecilia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gerber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gerber@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cavanaugh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cavana@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1221</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
