<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a Biolog Semi Automated MicroStation System for Environmental Research and Education at Alabama A&amp;M University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>41370</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NSF funds will be used to acquire a Biolog Semi Automated MicroStation System for soil microbial analysis. Soil microorganisms play a crucial role in one of the most important ecological processes - the turnover of chemical element in an ecosystem. Soil microbes break down complex organic molecules and release inorganic molecules vital for life and environmental sustainability. The Biolog Semi Automated MicroStation System will promote understanding of environmental challenges in Alabama, fate of anthropogenic pollutants, and bioremediation of polluted areas. The instrument will promote STEM -related teaching and research training for underrepresented groups especially in an HBCU, generate 21st century minority professionals in sciences, and strengthen interdisciplinary collaborative interactions among faculty, staff, and students. The equipment will be integrated into undergraduate and graduate curricula including eleven (11) courses taught by the PIs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The equipment will expand faculty resources for soil and environment research and to improve research capability at Alabama Agricultural and Mechanical University (AAMU). The proposed instrumentation will have profound impact on faculty research and the quality of education and training at AAMU at various levels. The acquisition of this instrument will be an opportunity for students to integrate theoretical learning with hands-on practical skills, thus increasing their overall competitiveness in the demanding job markets which has seen tremendous growth in soil and environmental sector jobs. In addition to supporting the Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, this instrument also will benefit and impact other faculty and students from neighboring Oakwood University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1606426</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Regine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mankolo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>regine.mankolo@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Irenus</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tazisong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>irenus.tazisong@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Senwo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zachary.senwo@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leopold</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nyochembeng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leopold.nyochembeng@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Alabama A&amp;M University</Name>
      <CityName>Normal</CityName>
      <ZipCode>357620285</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2563728186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O BOX 411</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
