<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Theoretical Physics of Biological Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Krastan B. Blagoev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Theoretical physics is the search for concise mathematical models of Nature. It has had great success in dealing with the inanimate world: we can now predict in quantitative detail what the most sensitive experiments will observe inside the nucleus and in the cosmos at large. By contrast, even as our ability to observe and measure improves dramatically, the phenomena of life remain largely unpredictable, even in their most qualitative aspects. In this project, a group of theoretical physicists will engage with students and postdoctoral scholars in an effort to close this gap; in short, to construct a theoretical physics of biological systems. The proponents have explored phenomena that span the tree of life: from metabolism in bacteria, through the determination of cell fate in embryonic development, to coding and computation of sensory information in brain. They have identified broad theoretical problems which cut across the traditional biological divisions of organism and system: Do living organisms operate near the limits set by the laws of physics as they gather and process information? Can we learn the detailed microscopic "model" of an organism, its "wiring diagram", from the finite set of observations we can make on how it behaves? How do organisms set the parameters that govern their function (i.e. how do they learn from experience)? These questions can all be given a mathematical form which guides a search for answers in terms of general principles, in the tradition of physics that will apply across disparate biological domains. The time is right to bring the beautiful phenomena of life under the powerful predictive umbrella of theoretical physics. Just as cosmology has progressed, in roughly one generation, from wild speculation to a precise framework for analyzing a rapidly expanding set of observations, the proponents believe that the intimate interaction between theory and experiment can lead to a new and deeper physics of biological systems. It is the creation of this scientific culture, where theory and experiment are equal partners in the exploration of life that is the fundamental intellectual merit of the project. It is not just the boundaries of academic disciplines, but our view of ourselves, which is at stake. A very important aspect of this project will be the training of a new generation of physicists for whom the development of a theoretical understanding of biological systems is a central part of their discipline. The graduate students and postdoctoral scholars who pass through the group will learn by example how to pursue that goal in a way consistent with the intellectual rigor and traditions of physics. They will eventually move on to faculty positions of their own, where they will transmit this attitude to new generations of students. More broadly, all project personnel are deeply engaged with new educational initiatives, addressing levels from the first year of college to advanced PhD students, which provide a more complete guide to the evolving, multidisciplinary intellectual landscape.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The participants in the project will assemble into subgroups to attack instances of these problems. The individual projects will have unusual scope: as an example, the question whether we can capture the complex statistics of biological behavior in a learnable mathematical model can be asked in very similar terms both of spiking retinal neurons, and of the antibody sequence repertoire of individual zebrafish. If the answer is yes and the models have similar mathematical structure, one will have learned something novel and deep about what makes evolved, living, systems different from the inanimate world. Since these questions can only be answered in the light of accurate data, the work will involve a close partnership with many experimental groups in fields ranging from bacteriology to human perceptual psychology. The product of these interactions will be the design of novel experiments and the creation of novel data analysis methods in order to address clearly formulated mathematical questions of broad significance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly supported by the Physics of Living Systems program in the Division of Physics, the Cellular Cluster and the Systems and Synthetic Biology in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences, and the Neural Systems Cluster in the Division of Integrative Organismal Systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1607612</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Curtis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Callan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccallan@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bialek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wbialek@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ned</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wingreen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wingreen@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Machta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bmachta@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1114</Code>
      <Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7713</Code>
      <Text>ACTIVATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8011</Code>
      <Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1114</Code>
      <Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1757</Code>
      <Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7246</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7713</Code>
      <Text>ACTIVATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8091</Code>
      <Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
