<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Ophthalmic Cold Plasma Probe for Reduction of Corneal and Scleral Infections</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed project entails the commercialization of a device intended to reduce infections caused by surgical procedures of the eye. The significance of this device is its potential to address the problem of drug-resistant infections by using electric pulses at specific parameters to sterilize tissues of the eye without causing structural damage. Conventional antibiotic eye drops that are currently used in operative procedures fail to address this growing problem of drug-resistant infections and surgeons today are actively seeking alternative solutions. This I-Corps team's fundamental research results show the proposed device to be highly effective as an antimicrobial treatment and indicate promotion of wound healing as well. Introduction of the proposed device to the operating room could minimize the need for the conventional antibiotics and would provide significant cost savings while reducing the risk of further drug resistance development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to successfully introduce the proposed ophthalmic cold plasma probe to the market as an antibacterial treatment for the corneal and scleral regions of the eye. The team will accomplish this task by approaching surgical centers, hospitals, private practices, and ophthalmic instrument manufacturing companies. The team intends to demonstrate to these contacts that it has developed an instrument that shows potential to provide antibacterial treatment of ocular tissue for surgical procedures involving surgical cataract corneal wounds, retinal surgery scleral wounds, and intravitreal conjunctive-scleral injection sites. Successful completion of the proposed project will include a redesign of the proposed test bench prototype to present as a sophisticated surgical system and using the outcomes of the program as a basis of a provisional patent and SBIR proposal. The proposed project carries significant potential immediate contributions for reducing risk of ocular infections and addressing drug-resistant pathogens. This I-Corps team also expects this project to have long-term contributions in the design, development of novel plasma devices in the medical industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1608210</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fridman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gf33@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/25/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
