<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The new identity of galectin-3 as a glycosaminoglycan binding protein</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>420965</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David A. Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Glycan-binding proteins are crucial for a wide range of biological processes. They belong to two distinct groups: lectins and glycosaminoglycan (GAG)-binding proteins (GAGBPs). A member of one group rarely possesses the characteristics of both groups. The human lectin Galectin-3 (Gal-3) is a member of the first group. This project is based on the finding that Gal-3, a lectin, actually possesses characteristics of a GAGBP. The current study investigates these newly-discovered characteristics of Gal-3. The research is integrated with educational activities through an initiative called "From Bench to Blackboard." This initiative introduces glycobiology to high school students and K-12 teachers through lab- and web-based approaches. The anticipated results from the proposed work is revealing hitherto unknown properties of Gal-3 and will inspire new research activities involving Gal-3 and GAGs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Gal-3 is one of the most extensively studied human lectins but it has never been reported as a GAGBP. However, preliminary data for this study show that Gal-3 binds to sulfated GAGs and proteoglycans. The proposed research elucidates the detailed interactions of Gal-3 with GAGs and proteoglycans. The length and sulfation level of GAGs, that are optimal for binding by Gal-3, are determined by calorimetry and spectroscopy. The GAG binding site of Gal-3 is being delineated with the use of site directed mutagenesis. Various biophysical techniques are employed to study non-covalent cross-linking of Gal-3 by GAGs and proteoglycans. In addition, competitive cross-linking of Gal-3 by GAGs and glycoproteins is also being examined. Information obtained from this research is redefining the binding properties of Gal-3 and providing a foundation for discovering Gal-3 dependent cellular and extracellular functions of GAGs and proteoglycans.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1608537</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tarun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tkdam@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
      <CityName>Houghton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6883</Code>
      <Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
