<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on Symplectic Geometry and Topology at the International Center for Mathematical Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18183</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports travel for US-based participants in the conference "Symplectic Geometry and Topology" at the International Center for Mathematical Sciences (ICMS), Edinburgh, Scotland, UK, held July 25-29, 2016. Symplectic topology is a rapidly developing branch of mathematics, which originated as a geometric tool for understanding qualitative problems of classical mechanics and geometric optics. Since its inception in 1980s, it quickly became one of important branches of mathematics interrelated with topology, dynamics, complex analysis, algebraic geometry, algebra, and mathematical physics. This led to fascinating cross-fertilizations, making symplectic topology a centerpiece of many modern mathematical developments. The conference at ICMS will be concentrated on recent developments in the fields of symplectic geometry and topology. The meeting will allow students and young mathematicians to learn about new research and to interact with a senior outstanding mathematicians taking part in the conference. This award supports participation of US students, postdoctoral associates, and young mathematicians. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference focuses on four core topics: &lt;br/&gt;1. Holomorphic curves (algebraic structures and foundational problems); &lt;br/&gt;2. Groups of symplectic diffeomorphisms; &lt;br/&gt;3. Recent advances in symplectic packings; and&lt;br/&gt;4. Symplectic structures (new constructions and spaces of symplectic structures). &lt;br/&gt;The objective is to bring together specialists in symplectic topology and related areas to discuss recent progress in the field and to catalyze efforts for achieving further breakthroughs in these areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference website is http://www.icms.org.uk/workshops/symplectic</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1608194</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yakov</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eliashberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eliash@math.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
