<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Living Growth Synthesis of Metal Oxide Nanocrystals: Toward Enhanced Control of Composition, Size and Uniformity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Langell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nanocrystals, very small crystals with sizes on the order of 0.000001 millimeters (equal in size to 5-10 atoms), have interesting properties that can lead to novel chemistry. Metal oxide nanocrystals, the subject of this study, are promising next-generation materials for use as catalysts, energy storage materials, electronic device components, sensors, and diagnostic probes. Chemists need better ways to control the composition and structure of the nanocrystals at the atomic level in order to be able to harness the properties of these new materials. Dr. Hutchison is developing a new synthesis approach that grows nanocrystals in a highly controlled manner by the continuous, sequential addition of metal and oxygen atoms to the surface of a nanocrystal. Such a continuous growth process, referred to as "living growth", attaches atoms to the nanocrystals with high precision, permitting simultaneous control of size, uniformity, and composition. All of these properties are important for specific potential applications. The researchers are developing general approaches to the production of new nanomaterials to be used in industry as thin film, magnetic materials, and catalysts. Dr. Hutchison's research attracts a diverse, interdisciplinary group of undergraduate and graduate students, including underrepresented minorities. In addition to their scientific training, students develop and implement written professional development plans and receive training on innovation and entrepreneurship so that they can enhance the societal impact of their research. The results of the research are shared with the general public through the regional meetings. The students interact with scientists from industry at nanomaterial workshops offered at the University of Oregon's Center for Advanced Materials Characterization. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this research program, Dr. Hutchison of the University of Oregon is supported by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry (MSN) Program to investigate "living growth" syntheses of inorganic nanocrystals with the aim of gaining simultaneous control of core diameter and uniformity, core composition, doping levels and core-shell structures. Living growth synthesis works in much the same way that living polymerization yields polymers with controlled molecular weight, copolymer composition and block copolymer structures. Dr. Hutchison produces mixed metal oxide nanocrystals that have been difficult to synthesize by thermal decomposition or other high temperature methods. The research has established a general approach to producing new metal oxides with controlled atomic-level composition and size. The project builds fundamental understanding of the reactions producing these nanocrystals and supports new applications in thin film, magnetic and catalysis research. Dr. Hutchison actively engages a diverse team of undergraduate and graduate students in his research and augments their research training with targeted professional development activities such as training on innovation and entrepreneurship. The results of the research are disseminated through scientific publication, the regional meetings, graduate courses, and industry workshops.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1610675</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hutchison</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hutch@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
