<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Directed Self-Assembly of Linear and Star Block Copolymer Thin Films - Oriented Nanostructures with Reduced Feature Sizes via Raster Annealing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>119442</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research aims to address the challenge of manufacturing lower cost, more efficient, lighter weight, and smaller scale systems for applications ranging from information or data storage devices for digital media to portable biosensing arrays that could potentially screen and treat a myriad of diseases. The project integrates fundamental research with collaborative assistance from an industrial partner to generate nanoscale features (of order 1/1000th the width of a human hair) that have potential to be translated from the laboratory-scale to a widely available and useable platform. In undertaking this collaborative approach, the research team will use commercially-relevant polymers that are created to spontaneously form ultra-small features, whose shape and function can be dictated through processing conditions. By linking aspects of materials chemistry, materials properties, and processing, this project will aid in the cost-effective evaluation of polymer systems to generated efficient electronic devices. This project provides research opportunities to students (including underrepresented undergraduate and economically-disadvantaged high school students) in a vibrant and collaborative laboratory setting and exposes students of all levels to cutting-edge concepts for making new nanometer scale materials that could lead to lower cost and more energy-efficient fabrication of computer-related devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI and his industrial partner at DuPont collaborate to develop new nanotemplates from self-assembling macromolecules using commercially-relevant block copolymers. A particular goal of this work is to investigate star architectures (and variable block chemistries) in block copolymers as a viable means for generating "writeable" and oriented nanostructures with reduced feature sizes for nanotemplating applications. By accomplishing this goal, the University of Delaware and DuPont team will address key needs in the arena of nanotemplating and bit-patterned media, including the ability to rapidly generate thin film templates with well-defined features at low cost, with appropriate and addressable orientations and domains, with minimal defects, and approaching smaller feature sizes (&lt; 5 nm). To facilitate general understanding, the proposed activities combine 1) the examination of various block copolymer architectures and chemistries, 2) the development of a unique solvent vapor annealing approach (raster solvent vapor annealing with soft shear), and 3) the macromolecular design, synthesis, self-assembly, and characterization expertise of the University of Delaware and the nanoprocessing and materials expertise of DuPont. Specific research themes include: (1) investigating the differences between star and linear block copolymer directed self-assembly using both moderately-repulsive and highly-repulsive polymer-polymer interactions to reduce feature sizes, improve nanostructure ordering, and control nanostructure orientation; (2) utilizing a newly-developed directed and programmable solvent annealing process to directionally align nanostructures with minimal defects; (3) probing solvent partitioning between domains via neutron scattering techniques; (4) incorporating newly-proposed "flexible-blade" flow coating to simultaneously cast and align nanostructures.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1610134</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Qi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Kai.Qi@dupont.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Epps, III</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thepps@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8037</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
