<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2016 Frontiers of Engineering Symposia (Japan-America: Irvine, California, June 2016; U.S.: Houston, Texas, September 2016; and European Union-U.S.: October 2016)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Frontiers of Engineering (FOE) Symposia, organized by the National Academy of Engineering (NAE), provide emerging engineering leaders from academia, industry, and government laboratories the opportunity to share research insights to facilitate an interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge and research methodologies. The nature of emerging technologies and how they fit together to create products and processes that drive economic growth in an increasingly competitive environment have heightened the need for engineers to understand each other's disciplines and enhance the value in that interaction, particularly among those developing and using these new technologies. The symposia serve as a catalyst to spur engineering innovation and foster collaborative networks of researchers within the United States and between engineers from the United States and partnering countries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides partial support for three FOE Symposia, to be held in 2016, organized by the NAE for early career researchers: the 2016 Japan-America FOE Symposium (JAFOE) to be held on June 16-18, 2016, in Irvine, California; the 2016 U.S. FOE Symposium (USFOE) to be held on September 19-21, 2016, in Houston, Texas; and the 2016 European Union-U.S. FOE Symposium (EU-US FOE) to be held on October 17-19, 2016, in Helsinki, Finland. Each FOE symposium will focus on four topical areas. The four topics for the 2016 USFOE Symposium are scalable algorithms and software for high-fidelity graphics, technologies for eradicating cancer, water desalination and purification, and extreme engineering. The four topics for the 2016 JAFOE Symposium are advanced 3D printing; nanotechnology in energy generation, storage and efficiency; big data; and urban mobility efficiency. Finally, the four topics for the 2016 EU-US FOE Symposium are carbon capture, utilization, and storage; information and computer technologies for personal health; integrated photonics manufacturing; and intelligent transportation systems. About 100 outstanding young engineers for the US FOE Symposium and 30 from each country for the bilateral symposia will participate. Each two and one-half day symposium will include four formal sessions, technical tours, break-out sessions, and opportunities for developing collaborative research partnerships. Sessions will consist of presentations on cutting-edge research, innovations, and emerging research opportunities in engineering fields relevant to the symposium. Papers from the USFOE Symposium will be published in a volume available on the National Academies Press website at http://www.nap.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1611723</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hunziker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhunzike@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7633</Code>
      <Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
