<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Demonstration and Applications of Single Molecule Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy at Physiological Conditions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kelsey D. Cook</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging (CMI) and the Chemical Structure, Dynamics, &amp; Mechanisms - A (CSDM-A) Programs in the Division of Chemistry, Dr. Susumu Takahashi and his group at the University of Southern California are devising means of improving magnetic resonance (MR) techniques in order to enable application of these powerful characterization tools to study the structure and dynamics of biological molecules down to the level of single molecules. Dr. Takahashi is also developing educational/training programs and materials that will help explain these methods and the chemistry they help to explain to USC graduate and undergraduate students, as well as to high school and elementary school students in USC's neighborhood community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Magnetic resonance spectrometry techniques, such as nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR), can provide detailed information about molecular structure and dynamics, but are hampered by intrinsically low sensitivity. Recent technological advances, particularly those utilizing a single nitrogen-vacancy (NV) center in diamond as a sensor, have enabled detection of a single electron spin. Dr. Takahashi seeks to demonstrate MR analysis of a few molecules under physiological conditions using NV centers and high-frequency/high-field EPR. Success in the research work will provide a promising pathway to enable EPR investigation of single biological molecules containing either native electron spin centers or extrinsic spin labels.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1611134</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susumu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Takahashi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>susumuta@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9101</Code>
      <Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8990</Code>
      <Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
