<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Summer Research Conference in Statistics and Biostatistics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>21315</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Keith Crank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports graduate-student participation in the Summer Research Conference in Statistics and Biostatistics, held June 5-8, 2016 in Bentonville, Arkansas. The meeting, part of an annual research conference series sponsored by the Southern Regional Council on Statistics, is designed to encourage the interchange and mutual understanding of research ideas in statistics and biostatistics, and to give motivation and direction to further research progress, particularly for young researchers, in a manner not ordinarily possible at other meetings. The meeting is particularly valuable for graduate students and faculty from smaller regional schools in the South. Each year, the location of the conference is chosen to be within driving distance for researchers in the southern region, thus affording them the opportunity to participate and interact closely with internationally-known leaders in the field without the cost of travel to distant venues. Speakers present formal research talks with adequate time allowed for clarification, amplification, and further informal discussions in small groups. Senior participants make themselves accessible for informal discussions of their research as well.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This year's Summer Research Conference centers on five topical areas: Measurement Error Models, Visual Analytics, Alzheimer's Disease Modeling, Survival Analysis, and Big Data Prediction Modeling. In addition to two plenary speakers for the conference, each topical area features talks by one senior speaker and two junior speakers. A poster session for graduate students will be held on the second day. This award provides travel funding for graduate students who are making poster presentations and in need of support. For more information, see the conference web page: &lt;br/&gt;www.stat.missouri.edu/~srcos/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1613061</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arnold</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stromberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>astro@ms.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
