<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Water, Drought and Snowpack Monitoring in the United States Using the EarthScope Plate Boundary Observatory GPS Network</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>520000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dennis Geist</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Changes in water storage in aquifers, soils, lakes and glaciers cause the Earth to deform elastically in ways that can be detected using the Global Positioning System (GPS). We propose to study this water- related deformation at GPS stations in EarthScope?s Plate Boundary Observatory (PBO) and use these observations to estimate the variation of water loads over the continental United States. Given the longstanding importance of water and drought in the West, and the threat of climate change to water security across the entire USA, improvements in direct monitoring of the water cycle are of great social and economic relevance. By providing new data on water storage and the water cycle, this work has the potential to make a significant and positive impact on water management in the United States, in addition to improving the underlying science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this work is to combine GPS load estimates with mass change estimates from NASA's GRACE satellite mission and independent information about hydrological systems and their boundaries to develop improved models for water redistribution. This study puts special emphasis on the all- important snowpack estimates for the Sierra Nevada and Rocky Mountains, and drought impacts on groundwater changes in California?s Central Valley and other principal aquifers in the USA. Specifically, over the next three years, we will: 1) reprocess all daily GPS position data to generate reliable series of seasonal and nonseasonal displacements; 2) correct all time series for offsets, transient displacements, and known atmospheric/oceanic loads; 3) invert for the spatiotemporal water loading across the continental USA; 4) constrain GPS mass changes with lower-resolution data from the GRACE mission to develop better estimates of water fluxes; 5) investigate mass changes of vulnerable mountain snowpack and groundwater aquifer systems in response to the current western USA drought; and 5) publish the results of this work as a set of data products and accompanying methodology for use by scientists and for possible operational use by water managers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1614218</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Duncan Carr</FirstName>
      <LastName>Agnew</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dagnew@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borsa</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aborsa@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>017F</Code>
      <Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>017F</Code>
      <Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>007F</Code>
      <Text>EARTHSCOPE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
