<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: 3D Printing of Ceramic/Metal Composites for Aerospace and Automotive Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Additive manufacturing (AM), also known as 3D printing, has been the focus of research in the automotive and aerospace industries. Metal AM is advantageous for its ability to produce efficient and complex parts. However, the major drawback of AM is the lack of reproducibility and mechanical integrity, which conventional methods offer. In this project, the feasibility of embedded sensors in metal AM parts in order to monitor variations in mechanical properties will be investigated. This research will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Hyonkee Sohn, the project manager of the powder bed fusion metal printing group and a noted expert in laser materials processing, at the Korean Institute of Machinery and Materials (KIMM). This partnership will provide access to laser materials processing equipment and an original metal 3D printer designed by KIMM. Ultimately, this will initiate a global effort in the advancement of AM technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The integration of functional materials such as ferroelectrics and piezoelectrics into metal AM parts will enable sensing applications for in-situ monitoring. Despite the difficulty of depositing such ceramics onto metal substrates, preliminary results indicate that this can be achieved using industry-standard metal-organic solution deposition methods. In this research, ferroelectric thin films will be deposited onto metal substrates and further evaluated for its structural and electrical properties. Typical materials for ferroelectrics include: lead zirconate titanate (PZT), barium titanate (BT), and strontium bismute tantalate (SBT). As for the materials of choice for the substrate, additively manufactured Inconel 718, Ti-6Al-4V, and 17-4PH stainless steel will be considered. Different ceramic/metal combinations will be assessed for the best compatibility and performance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the National Research Foundation of Korea.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1614287</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tulsi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Patel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Patel Tulsi</Name>
      <CityName>Berlin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>06037</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5942</Code>
      <Text>KOREA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
