<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Computational Methods and Consistency for Dirichlet Graph Partitions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>46859</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will investigate theoretical properties, computational methods, and applications for a particular method of graph partitioning. Generally speaking, graph partitioning is the mathematical problem of subdividing a set into smaller components with desirable properties. This problem has diverse applications in image analysis (medical, satellite, and material), surveillance, social network analysis, and topic modeling, among many others. The results of this project could significantly impact these areas and due to the multidisciplinary nature of this activity, all involved parties will gain awareness and literacy outside their own respective fields. The project provides opportunities for the principal investigator to continue advising and mentoring students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will prove fundamental theoretical results and develop computational methods for the Dirichlet graph partitioning problem, formulated as minimizing the sum of the principle Laplace-Dirichlet eigenvalues for each partition component. This graph partitioning problem has rich and exploitable mathematical structure: it is motivated by a geometric problem and has both a variational characterization and an associated stochastic process. The project will have three goals. The first goal is to prove, via Gamma convergence with a suitable metric, the consistency result that Dirichlet partitions of geometric graphs, obtained by sampling from a probability space, converge to Dirichlet partitions of that probability space as the number of sampled points tends to infinity. This result will yield a better understanding of the relationship between the graph and continuum partitioning problems as well as possibly suggest subsampling strategies for extremely large datasets. The second goal addresses important computational aspects of the Dirichlet graph partitioning problem. Although two different relaxations of this problem have been identified, computational methods based on these relaxations necessarily have increased computational complexity. The PI will seek provably convergent new methods that combine variational arguments with ideas from geometry, partial differential equations, and Markov processes in order to extend and overcome these shortcomings. The third goal is to address concrete, real-world problems and to engage the developed algorithms in practical applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1619755</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Braxton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Osting</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>osting@math.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/07/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
