<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Strengthening the GEO REU Network and sharing best practices with the STEM REU community</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>96390</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Directorate of Geosciences supports approximately 60 Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) sites each year, and these sites provide research internships for over 600 students. These REU site programs are located at many different institutions across the county, and the scientists who run them are often the only faculty in their institution responsible for organizing this type of student research/professional development program. Although there is a general knowledge of how these programs should be managed, there has been limited sharing of ideas and best practices among the REU PIs. In the past, new PIs have had little support as they work through the details of developing and organizing a new REU program, and experienced PIs face a variety of challenges, including recruiting diverse students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funding to support the REU programs through professional networking efforts: (1) to connect PIs and managers running REU Sites, (2) to document and improve best practices, (3) to provide a support system for dealing with challenges and developments, and (4) to foster an understanding of how to integrate diversity approaches in all programmatic elements. The Principal Investigators (PIs) will formalize this support of REU managers in the geosciences by publishing handbooks for REU PIs, mentors and interns, and by organizing opportunities for REU PIs and REU interns to meet and exchange information. Ongoing networking activities will include hosting telecons and webinars on REU management, student recruitment, etc. and hosting and monitoring the GEO REU listserve. The goal is to develop a community of REU leaders and to increase the efficacy of REUs programs, allowing REU PIs to create a higher quality research experience for undergraduates. In addition, REU PIs will receive support for recruiting students from diverse backgrounds in order to increase participation by students who are from under-represented groups and community colleges or who are first-generation college students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Formalizing the networking activities and adding webinars, manuals, etc. will help the community run more effective programs and attract applications from a diverse set of students. The PI will provide support and leadership necessary to strengthen the REU programs that are funded by the Directorate of Geosciences. It will have a direct impact on the quality of research internship programs provided to more than 600 students each year. Improving the quality of these programs and the diversity of students who participate in them is likely to have an important impact on the future ocean sciences research community. The REU program is a major source of new graduate students since many of the students who participate in them go on to attend graduate school in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1619600</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Valerie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sloan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>valsloan9@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haacker-Santos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rhaacker@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3090 Center Green Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7699</Code>
      <Text>ICER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
