<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Next-Generation Relativistic Program for All-Order Treatment of Many-Electron Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The quantitative understanding of atomic and molecular structure and collisions represents one of the main areas of research in theoretical atomic and molecular physics. Results from this area of research form key input to fundamental theoretical and experimental studies in a broad range of basic and applied scientific fields, including astrophysics, plasma science, and quantum information. In addition, this research is relevant for important practical applications with important societal implications, such as the development of better clocks for GPS systems. To date success in this area has been primarily restricted to studies of the simpler atomic systems; comparable levels of understanding have not been achieved for more complex atoms in the Periodic Table. This project focuses on developing a high-precision theoretical and computational approach that seeks to bring the theoretical understanding of complicated atoms of transition metals to the same level of sophistication afforded presently only to much simpler atomic systems. If successful, the results could open up much of the Periodic Table to applications that heretofore could only be pursued with the simplest atoms. As such, this project provides ample opportunities for the training of students and post-doctoral fellows on topics at the leading edge of scientific research in physics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to develop a next-generation fully relativistic broadly applicable atomic code, based on the combination of large-scale configuration interaction and all-order linearized coupled-cluster method capable of predicting properties of open-shell atoms with precision of a few percent. The main feature of the code is to be able to treat systems where no accurate description of atomic properties is presently possible. While tremendous progress has been made recently in high-precision atomic calculations, treatment of correlation in d- and f-shell open systems present frontier challenges to AMO theory. This project will address the following short comings of current approaches needed for the treatment of correlations in d- and f-shell atomic open systems: omission of three-body interactions, limited choice of the starting potential, and the need for efficient selection of most important configurations for the construction of very large configuration spaces. The resulting code will be able to calculate a wide range of atomic properties including energies, g-factors, hyperfine constants, various transition matrix elements, electric-dipole and electric-quadrupole static and dynamic polarizabilities, long-range interaction potential parameters, various P(parity)-odd and T(time)-odd effects, sensitivity factors for tests of variation of the fine-structure constant and atomic tests of local Lorentz invariance. The performance of the new-generation code will be tested for systems with several valence electrons.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1620687</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marianna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Safronova</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>msafrono@physics.udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7244</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7569</Code>
      <Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8084</Code>
      <Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
