<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Seizure onset detection using tripolar Laplacian electroencephalography</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to increase the science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) instructional and research capacities of specific institutions of higher education that serve the Nation's indigenous students. Expanding the research capacity at these institutions expands the opportunities for students to pursue challenging, rewarding careers in STEM fields, provides for research studies in areas that may be locally relevant, and encourages a faculty community to look beyond the traditional classroom for intellectual and professional growth. This project aligns directly with that goal, and moreover will increase the body of knowledge on the efficacy of novel devices that may improve the detection of seizure onset.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dine' College will analyze datasets in order to validate a novel tripolar Laplacian electroencephalogram (tEEG) based seizure onset detection methodology using automatically detected high-frequency oscillations (HFOs) with better sensitivity (correct detection rate), selectivity (false positive detections per hour), and detection delay compared to the recent results of others obtained on large scalp encephalogram (EEG) datasets will constitute a positive output. This project will contribute to advancing quality postsecondary student learning and development through the inter-disciplinary Mathematics for Engineering Applications (MEA) research laboratory to be established at Diné College led by the PI of and funded by this proposal. Four undergraduate research assistant positions will be created in the MEA lab providing Diné College students with valuable cutting edge research experience. Moreover, talks and presentations by the MEA lab members and invited speakers collaborating with the lab will help further involve students into mathematics and engineering disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1622481</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oleksandr</FirstName>
      <LastName>Makeyev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>omakeyev@dinecollege.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Dine College</Name>
      <CityName>tsaile</CityName>
      <ZipCode>865560067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9287246670</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O Box 126</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
