<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2016 NSF-Germany IoT Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99901</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop brings together R&amp;D experts from the German and U.S. academic, government, and&lt;br/&gt;industry sectors to help spur discussion on research gaps, opportunities, and potential international&lt;br/&gt;collaborations and deployments in the areas of IoT (Internet of Things) and CPS. More specifically, the workshop&lt;br/&gt;will explore ongoing research and development activities in IoT/CPS, seek to identify future&lt;br/&gt;joint research opportunities, and establish a foundation for cooperative strategic progress&lt;br/&gt;in this important and rapidly growing area. The magnitude of research challenges and the urgency of addressing them require a strategic&lt;br/&gt;approach. Combining the specific strengths from the United States and from Germany is synergistic&lt;br/&gt;with the goal of accelerating progress in all aspects of research. The program of the meeting includes invited academic research and industry presentations about prospective research synergistic collaborations in the areas of IoT and CPS between the United&lt;br/&gt;States and Germany. Some topics that will be discussed are: 1) Architectures; 2) Development environments; 3) Foundations; 4) Inter-operability and Standardization. Funds from the workshop will support US researchers participating in the workshop. Significant efforts will be made to attract women and other under-represented minorities as workshop participants from both US and German sides. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ongoing fusion of information and communication technologies with engineering of physical&lt;br/&gt;systems has triggered tremendous changes in private and public sectors. These changes deeply&lt;br/&gt;influence the nature of systems we build, the technologies we use for development and manufacturing&lt;br/&gt;and the way we teach engineering. The resulting new generations of Cyber-Physical Systems&lt;br/&gt;(CPS) and their emerging platforms such as the Internet of Things (IoT) and Industrial Internet&lt;br/&gt;(II) require bringing together competences both from the information technologies and the&lt;br/&gt;engineering disciplines. As a result, academia, industry, and society will need to expand&lt;br/&gt;capacity in the area of creating CPS in a dependable way.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1622473</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sztipanovits</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Janos.Sztipanovits@Vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frankie</FirstName>
      <LastName>King</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>frankie.king@isis.vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
      <CityName>Nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7945</Code>
      <Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
