<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conferences: Southern California Geometric Analysis Seminar; Winter-2017; 2018; 2019; University of California-San Diego and University of California, Irvine</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>26000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Differential geometry studies the spatial properties of spaces, which includes the physical space-time in which the human beings live, by Einstein's theory of general relativity. These spatial properties have fundamental impact on all physical events happening. Many problems in science can also be formulated in terms of geometry. Geometric analysis uses the analysis and the partial differential equation as a tool to study analytic, geometric and topological properties of the spaces. It is an important part of modern mathematics and is related to many other branches of mathematics. It has solved a large number of problems in global geometry, topology, several complex variables and mathematical physics. The Southern California Geometric Analysis Seminar (SCGAS) is an annual two-day conference that rotates between the University of California - Irvine and the University of California - San Diego. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference features talks given by world leaders. The Seminar promotes interaction among mathematicians in Southern California who are interested in geometric analysis and related areas and to introduce graduate students and post-docs to some of the best works in geometric analysis. This funding award is geared towards supporting and encouraging the participation of graduate students and recent PhDs, especially women and under-represented minorities, by providing them the necessary travel support to attend the conference. Geometric analysis is an important area of modern mathematics and is related to many other branches of mathematics. Using the analysis and the partial differential equations as its main tools with differential geometry, topology, and algebraic geometry as foundations, geometric analysis has solved a large number of problems in global geometry, topology, several complex variables and mathematical physics. One example is the resolution of the celebrated Poincare conjecture via the study of the Ricci flow. As the success of the first twenty three meetings have demonstrated, the SCGAS conference has now become an important and anticipated event for the southern California region and has also attracted a substantial number of participants from the rest of the country each year. Indeed, it is the unique annual meeting of its kind in the southern California area, and continues to foster interests in geometric analysis at all levels. In the years past, interactions among the participants during the conference have led to a number of new collaborations and research projects. Web sites for the Southern California Geometric Analysis Seminar may be found at https://math.ucsd.edu/~scgas/ and http://www.math.uci.edu/~scgas/.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623782</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Li Sheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tseng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lstseng@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Streets</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jstreets@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhiqin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zlu@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schoen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rschoen@math.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ni</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lni@math.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1265</Code>
      <Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
