<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Upgrade of Computational Facilities for Geophysics Research and Student Training at Old Dominion University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15654</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1623816&lt;br/&gt;Georgen&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Division of Earth Sciences Instrumentation and Facilities Program grant supports acquisition of computational equipment to support research and research training in geophysics and geodynamics. Funding would allow for purchase of two Mac Pro desktops with 3.5 GHz six-core CPUs, 64 Gb RAM and dual GPUs each to support larger numerical model domains and smaller grid resolutions to better model geological processes with high spatial and temporal gradients, better handling of time-dependent solutions, and higher overall higher model throughput. This support is congruent with NSFs mission of promoting the progress of science and advancing the national health, prosperity and welfare given the importance of training the next generation scientific workforce in computational modeling techniques and the societal importance of understanding the impacts of changing climate and sea level on terrestrial hydrologic reservoirs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research will focus on modeling of geodynamics processed including mantle plume ? mid ocean ridge interactions, subduction zone dynamics and effects of sea level change on groundwater hydrology and submarine groundwater discharge along the eastern Mid-Atlantic shore.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623816</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Georgen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgeorgen@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
