<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conferences on Discrete Geometry and Algebraic Combinatorics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jacques Verstraete</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in two three-day conferences in the area of Discrete Geometry and Algebraic Combinatorics, held May 4-6, 2016 and in May 2017 in South Padre Island, TX. The conferences, eighth and ninth in a series, are devoted to a wide range of classical and modern problems in these active areas of mathematical research. The conferences bring together students and researchers in the region centered on the University of Texas - Rio Grande Valley. Due to the diverse composition of the student body, conference organizers expect to be able to attract a sizable fraction of attendees from among groups traditionally underrepresented in U.S. mathematics studies. The grant provides travel support for graduate students and early-career researchers, as well as non-local participants without other sources of support. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The two events represent the continuation of a successful series of conferences, the last of which was held in April 2015. The conference topics include: polytopes; packings, coverings, and tilings; rigidity and flexibility; geometric graph theory; topological combinatorics; incidence structures; lattices and discrete groups; geometric set partitioning and transversals; optimal configurations; spherical and Euclidean designs; distance sets; semidefinite programming in coding theory and discrete geometry; and strongly regular graphs. The conferences include an introduction of the research area through problems related to the topical areas and presentations of recent results by the leading experts in the field. More information is available at the conference web site:&lt;br/&gt;www.utrgv.edu/discgeo</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623600</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oleg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Musin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>oleg.musin@utrgv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Glazyrin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Alexey.Glazyrin@utrgv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alexey.garber@utrgv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley</Name>
      <CityName>Edinburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>785392909</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9566652889</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1201 West University Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7970</Code>
      <Text>Combinatorics</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
