<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Systems for Solar Fuels Generation Utilizing PV and Electrolysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory Rorrer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop on Systems for Solar Fuels Generation Utilizing PV and Electrolysis will be held at the University of Delaware on March 7-8, 2016. The purpose of this workshop is to bring academic, industry, and government researchers together to assess the potential of making hydrogen gas, a sustainable zero-carbon fuel, from the splitting of water into hydrogen and oxygen using electricity generated through solar energy. The expected outcome of this workshop is the formation of team that can advance both the science and practical development of integrated photovoltaic / electrolyzer (PV/EC) systems through coordinated efforts. The workshop will also include a Poster session highlighting student research and projects in this area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will cover two major topic areas underlying systems-level integration of PV/EC processes for potentially low-cost solar hydrogen fuel production. The first area is Systems Optimization, which will focus on identifying systems-driven approaches for scalable design, manufacture, assembly, and operation of large-scale PV/EC systems for solar fuels production. Topics discussed will include techno-economic analysis, minimization of coupling losses, power conditioning, and design implications for PV and electrolyzer components in an optimized system. The second topic area is Integration of Photovoltaic &amp; Electrolyzer Design, which will focus on identifying opportunities to improve system performance by redesigning both components for synergistic operation. Topics will include identification of low-cost/high-performance components, novel module and electrolyzer designs, membrane technologies, and catalyst development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623464</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Birkmire</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rwb@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/04/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>046E</Code>
      <Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
