<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Project: Data Science eXtension (DSX): Incorporating data science fundamentals in computing curriculum at Spelman and Morehouse Colleges</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399903</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue science, technology, engineering or mathematics (STEM) graduate programs and/or careers. The project at Spelman College and Morehouse College seeks to address the need for skilled data scientists through data science and big data training for faculty and students at both colleges in partnership with the College of Charleston's Data Science program. The activities and strategies are evidence-based and a strong plan for formative and summative evaluation is part of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has the specific goals to: train faculty on data science principles that are part of computing fundamentals and infuse the existing curriculum to showcase the data science principles; develop and implement a data science curriculum at the undergraduate level at both institutions; and broaden awareness of data science to students underrepresented in the discipline at the undergraduate level in preparation of graduate studies or corporate positions in data science. Two groups of ten faculty will be trained in data science principles, and these faculty will create, infuse and deliver data science modules to about 500 of their students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623362</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kinnis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gosha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kinnis.gosha@morehouse.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brandeis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marshall</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brandeis.marshall@spelman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Spelman College</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303144399</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4042705897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>350 Spelman Lane SW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
