<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Higher-Order Asymptotics and Post-Selection Inference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Keith Crank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Workshop on Higher-Order Asymptotics and Post-Selection Inference (WHOA-PSI) will be held on the campus of Washington University in St. Louis from September 30-October 2, 2016. (See http://www.math.wustl.edu/~kuffner/WHOA-PSI.html.) Post-selection inference is relevant to virtually all areas of statistical application. Higher-order asymptotics provides the tools and insights needed to refine basic large-sample results for post-selection inference procedures, and make them more accurate in the practically realistic setting of small to moderate sample sizes. WHOA-PSI seeks to merge these fields, foster collaboration and discussion, and push forward the post-selection inference research frontier in the direction of higher-order accuracy for inference procedures. NSF funding will provide travel support for junior researchers to attend this conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Washington University will host a workshop on higher order asymptotics and post-selection inference September 30 ? October 2, 206. Speakers include Brad Efron, Jianqing Fan, and Rob Tibshirani. This workshop attempts to address the needs of applied statisticians utilizing model selection procedures who also need extremely accurate inference procedures. The workshop will begin with tutorials on the main topics. This award provides funding for junior researchers to attend the conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1623028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuffner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kuffner@math.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
