<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAR-PF Whole-stream metabolism dependence on particulate organic carbon and microbes from urban point sources</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>184000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Jennifer Drummond has been granted an NSF EAR Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out research and education activities at the Center for Advance Studies in Blanes, Spain, and the Desert Research Institute in Reno, NV. The overall aim of the project is to examine how particulate organic carbon and microbes from wastewater treatment plant (WWTP) effluents influence the metabolism of recipient streams. This work will improve the understanding of the impacts of environmental alterations derived from urban activity on stream ecosystem functioning. The information can be used to guide management and policy decisions related to balancing human and environmental needs for sustainable water resources. The project addresses a worldwide issue of concern and the research results will be shared with multiple audiences in Spain, Europe, and the United States. The education plan will consist of contributions to a massive open on-line course and participation in MOVILAB. The MOVILAB travels to different villages and gives local kids and adults the opportunity to have hands-on experience while learning about current environmental topics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research plan will include experimental, field and laboratory work together with computational development and analysis. The project will result in a unique data set on the mechanisms underlying (i) transport and retention behavior of particulate organic carbon (POC) and microbes in urban channels and (ii) how this affects the metabolism of WWTP-influenced stream ecosystems. Furthermore, a computational model will be developed that combines transport and retention of solutes, POC, and microbes with the metabolic activity of the stream. This model can be used to link scales of solute and particle retention and examine the controlling mechanism of in-stream metabolism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award was supported with funding from the Office of International Science &amp; Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1624877</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Drummond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/27/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drummond Jennifer D</Name>
      <CityName>Lincolnshire</CityName>
      <ZipCode>600693067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5956</Code>
      <Text>IRFP</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5952</Code>
      <Text>SPAIN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
