<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Cryogen-Free, State-of-the-Art, Superconducting Quantum Interference Device (SQuID) Magnetometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>282697</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) and support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Program (CRIF), Professor Sarah Tolbert from the University of California Los Angeles and colleagues Louis Bouchard, Greg Carman, Jane Chang and Alexander Spokoyny have acquired a cryogen-free, state-of-the-art, superconducting quantum interference device (SQuID) magnetometer. This instrument consists of two superconductors separated by very thin insulating layers. Such a magnetometer is capable of detecting very small magnetic fields including those produced in living organisms. The magnetic flux is controlled by voltage variations using either direct (DC) or alternating voltages (AC). To be able to measure such small variations in magnetic fields, the instrument operates at very low temperatures achieved with the use of liquid helium, a limited resource. To avoid waste of such a valuable element, this instrument recycles the helium making it cryogen (coolant) free. This magnetometer is placed in a user facility and plays a role in the development of human resources in scientific research. It enriches the research experience of many graduate students, postdoctoral fellows and undergraduate researchers. It serves as a resource for users across the California State University System which is heavily populated by underrepresented students. In general, magnetometers have very diverse applications, ranging from locating submerged metal-containing ship wrecks and submarines to measuring Earth's magnetic fields to measuring tiny magnetic fields in the brain or heart.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels, especially in areas such as (a) understanding thermogravimetric materials for thermal energy harvesting; (b) studying magnetic states in condensed matter systems; (c) studying boron-rich clusters as building blocks for molecular and organic magnets; (d) exploring the use of multiferroic materials for spintronic devices; (e) studying single molecule magnets; (f) studying quantum anomalous half effect and topological superconductors, and (g) applying multiferroics as new materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1625776</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spokoyny</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spokoyny@chem.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpchang@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bouchard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bouchard@chem.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>carman@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tolbert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tolbert@chem.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8396</Code>
      <Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8609</Code>
      <Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
