<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Equipment to Establish Big Data Analytics Infrastructure for Research and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>198752</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project, acquiring an integrated high performance computing instrument for big data research and education, aims to fill the gap for big data analytics at a minority-serving institution in an EPSCoR state. The ability to perform network big data research and education adds assets to various basic research activities within the institution. The instrument will also become a critical asset for research groups currently involved in big data analysis and management. It strengthens educational training activities by enabling innovative cross disciplinary courses and promoting our education outreach activity with K-12 teachers and students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The instrumentation would initially support the following projects addressing issues of national priority critical for training graduate students in big data analytics: 1. Data-Bridge system development and deployment; 2. Community detection framework in large networks; and 3. Deep learning framework for big data analytics. These investigators are among the first few to systematically study sociometric systems for long tail science data collection to develop DataBridge indexing mechanism for scientific datasets. As scientific datasets by themselves provide very sparse information content for searching and discovery, the DataBridge will provide a rich set of tools for mining information and context. The research on community detection in large networks is expected to lead to new insights into community detection of large social and information networks, and new theoretical models for understanding such a community and algorithms to harness them. The research on deep learning library for big data analytics lays out a basic research program for tracking one of the fundamental challenges of developing the Actionable Intelligence Discovery and Exploitation (AIDE).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1625677</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laxmi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gewali</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>laxmi@cs.unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>justin.zhan@unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhang@physics.unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ge</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ge.kan@unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kazem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taghva</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kazem.taghva@unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nevada Las Vegas</Name>
      <CityName>LAS VEGAS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>891541055</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7028951357</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4505 MARYLAND PARKWAY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
