<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a Redeployable Spread Spectrum Multiple Input Multiple Output (MIMO) Meteor Radar</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>295496</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Meriwether</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding to construct a novel meteor radar instrument called Multistatic Spread Spectrum Meteor Radar (MSMR). The MSMR design is innovative in part because the electronics would be based upon commercial components that would avoid radio wave interference problems. The primary purpose of the application of this new instrument is to study the phenomena of mesospheric dynamics, ionospheric irregularities, and meteoroid influx deposition. The primary aim of the science application using this instrument would be to achieve the measurements of the winds in the mesosphere-lower thermosphere region from 75 to 110 km. Unlike other meteor radar systems, this instrument would be easily transportable, cheap to fabricate, with relatively low power required for any radio transmission. The broader impact of this award is that it would provide an excellent platform for young engineers to gain experience in working with a design structure largely centered around the collection of immense amounts of data that is analyzed on the fly to achieve intermediate data products. Summer students would be supported on this project as well as a postdoctoral scholar that would receive part time support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The radar system will consist of three transmitter antennas and two interferometric receiver antenna fields. A continuous pseudorandom phasecode unique to each transmitter would be utilized for transmission of the radar signals. Because pseudorandom waveforms do not correlate with external radio interference, the system has good rejection of external radio interference. An unqiue property of MSMR that is unlike any existing meteor radars is all of the transmitter antennas of MSMR can be operated on the same frequency band with minimal mutual interference. The radar system can also be used at a smaller peak power than current systems, while utilizing the same average power as a pulsed system. The new innovations make radio licensing easier, as a large radar network will only occupy a portion of the radio spectrum that is equivalent to a single mono-static radar. These new MSMR features allow construction of a dense meteor radar network that can be applied to studies of mesospheric wind fields and trajectories of ablating meteoroids using a significantly larger number of specular meteor echoes than ever before. The radar can also be used to allow observations of field aligned ionospheric irregularities (FAI) without the range-Doppler ambiguity that is an issue for existing pulsed systems. The radar system relies on modern software defined radio hardware, which greatly reduces the complexity of the radar system, with most of the features implemented in software.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1626041</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Juha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vierinen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jvierine@GMAIL.COM</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeast Radio Observatory Corp</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531975</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 Massachusetts Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4202</Code>
      <Text>UPPER ATMOSPHERIC FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
