<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Hybrid CPU/GPU High Performance Computing and Storage for STEM Research and Education at San Jose State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>900798</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is to acquire a state-of-the-art high-performance computing (HPC) facility at San Jose State University (SJSU). The HPC system will provide faculty and students regular access to a modern, on-campus computing facility for computational science and engineering research. As a key hub for STEM fields in the San Francisco Bay Area, this facility will promote the progress of science and engineering, as well as offer a wide diversity of experiences for our students through required laboratory courses and research opportunities. This multidisciplinary and collaborative project involves faculty and students from biological science, chemistry, computer science, aerospace engineering, computer engineering, meteorology and climate science, physics, astronomy, mathematics, and statistics. The HPC will further enhance SJSU?s capability as a focal point in training members of the biotechnology/ pharmaceutical and information technology workforce in the Bay Area. This facility will also contribute to attracting students from underrepresented groups as well as local community colleges into STEM fields at SJSU. It is anticipated that more than 200 students from SJSU each year in STEM related courses and activities will benefit from such an instrument.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Comprising a hybrid central processing unit (CPU)/graphics processing unit (GPU) HPC built using 1696 compute cores and a 1.0-petabyte High Performance Storage System (HPSS). This system will be used for computational analysis, data-intensive research, rich media, three-dimensional computer modeling, data mining, and large-scale simulation. The projects that are poised to commence include: on-demand numerical weather prediction, assimilation, and analysis (Atmospheric Science); dynamical modeling of orbits and dark matter in gas-poor galaxies (Physics and Astronomy); computational modeling of Tat peptide mutants binding to BIV TAR RNA and protein-protein interfaces (Biochemistry); quantum mechanical properties of materials in the atomic scale (Physics and Astronomy); guidance and trajectory optimization strategies in presence of wind, and spacecraft and orbital trajectory optimization (Aerospace Engineering); genomic assessment of adaptation, and pharmacological and evolutionary perspective on bioactive compounds in marine invertebrates (Biological Science); high-resolution simulations of weather phenomena, dust transport, and climate on Mars (Planetary Science); and efficient algorithms for modeling large amount of data in high dimensions (Mathematics and Statistics). The HPC infrastructure and associated user group will enable many further follow-up projects, including cross-disciplinary collaborations as well as participation from the wider SJSU community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1626645</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brooke</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lustig</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>blustig@science.sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ehsan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khatami</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ehsan.khatami@sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chiao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sen.chiao@sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Romanowsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aaron.romanowsky@sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kamran</FirstName>
      <LastName>Turkoglu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kamran.turkoglu@sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7476</Code>
      <Text>ETF</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
