<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an Advanced, Accelerated Computational System for Lattice QCD</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) is the theory of strong interactions, the fundamental force in Nature that binds quarks and gluons into subatomic particles (hadrons), such as protons and neutrons. The study of QCD properties is one of the central scientific challenges in nuclear physics. Nuclear physics scientists use computational methods and large-scale simulations to further the detailed understanding of hadronic structure. These simulations make use of state-of-the-art computational resources and researchers continue to improve their high-performance computing (HPC) methods to take advantage of the latest breakthrough in computer technology. This project will allow the acquisition of a parallel computer cluster incorporating the next-generation Intel multi-core processors (Knights Landing) and a high-performance communication network. The Knights Landing architecture has the potential to revolutionize scientific computing, by providing large computing resources at low cost and using significantly less power than conventional computer clusters. This computer cluster will be housed in a state-of-the-art computing center in the new Integrated Science Center at the College of William &amp; Mary and will form the centerpiece of high-performance computing on the W&amp;M campus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary scientific driver for the system is to use lattice QCD methods to build a solid foundation for nuclear physics based on the Standard Model of elementary particle physics. With increased computational power and recent algorithmic developments, the research carried out with this system will advance the Lattice QCD program. This system will be used as a test bed for the development of new algorithms for lattice QCD calculations. These algorithms will be designed in collaboration with computer scientists specifically for the modern multi-core architectures that are currently the trent in high-performance computing. Furthermore, this computer cluster will serve as the center of interdisciplinary research between computer scientists and physicists and will catalyze the integration of research and education through the training of students and postdoctoral researchers in the groups of the senior investigators and in the wider academic community at William and Mary.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project advances the objectives of the National Strategic Computing Initiative (NSCI), an effort aimed at sustaining and enhancing the U.S. scientific, technological, and economic leadership position in High-Performance Computing (HPC) research, development, and deployment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1626177</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kostas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Orginos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kostas@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>College of William and Mary</Name>
      <CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>231878795</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7572213966</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>026Z</Code>
      <Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
