<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Solid State Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectrometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>314930</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) and support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Program (CRIF), Professor Benjamin Keitz from the University of Texas Austin and colleague C. Grant Willson have acquired a 400 MHz NMR spectrometer equipped with solid state capabilities. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as the study of biologically relevant species. In general, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the study of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the changing interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. The results from these NMR studies have an impact in synthetic organic/inorganic chemistry, materials chemistry and biochemistry. This instrument is located a general user facility managed by highly qualified scientists as an integral part of research, research training and teaching. The improved research infrastructure further enriches the research experience for economically disadvantaged and underrepresented minority students at the institution. It is used in collaborations with non-Ph.D.-granting universities in the Austin metropolitan area. Specifically, faculty engages with students at St. Edwards University and Huston-Tillotson University as part of existing UT-Austin outreach programs. Such collaborations facilitate the development of interactions where faculty and students from these universities visit UT-Austin to use the spectrometer. Overall, the solid state NMR spectromater improves UT-Austin's many successful diversity initiatives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels, especially in: (a) gaining information on polymeric materials, (b) studying conjugated metallopolymers, (c) characterizing porous solids, (d) studying protein self-assembly in structured biomaterials, (e) enabling the design of surface-modified nanoparticles, (f) contributing to research in the geological sciences, and (g) helping prepare new pharmaceutical dosage forms.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1626211</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>C. Grant</FirstName>
      <LastName>Willson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>willson@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Keitz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>keitz@utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
