<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Orchestral Innovations in Science Education (OISE): An Experiment in Informal STEAM Learning</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299991</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alphonse T. DeSena</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Baltimore Symphony Orchestra (BSO), in collaboration with the Psychology Department of the University of Maryland Baltimore County (UMBC) and Octava (a technology company), are conducting a pilot exploratory research project to assess the effectiveness of delivering informal science learning (ISL) to adult audiences through live music in a concert hall environment. The first half of the study is being timed to coincide with the 2016 annual meeting in Baltimore of the League of American Orchestras. Audiences will be introduced to the core idea that symmetry is a central concept both in science and in music, and they will experience these ideas via the orchestral music of pieces such as Aaron Copland's Appalachian Spring and Beethoven's Symphony. No. 5. The project goals are: to test whether and the extent to which informal STEM learning can occur among adults (ages 18+) during live orchestral performances and how the science content may enhance the audience experience; and to develop assessment tools for measuring audience learning and retention of scientific concepts delivered in connection with live musical performances both through interactive technology and through traditional program notes. It is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program, which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. This includes providing multiple pathways for broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences, advancing innovative research on and assessment of STEM learning in informal environments, and developing understandings of deeper learning by participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The pilot study will investigate the interaction of key variables related to the audience composition, the learning formats (use of app technology, program notes, or not), and the science concepts. The tablet application technology, under continued development by Octava, presents unobtrusive program notes that act as a concert companion in real time as a concert proceeds. The mixed methods research methodology will produce quantitative and qualitative data using pre- and post-test instruments and focus group interviews. A follow-up questionnaire will be sent to participants six weeks after the performances to ascertain whether what was learned was retained over a period of time. Dissemination of project findings will be to professionals in science, science education and music fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1630154</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bogash</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbogash@bsomsuic.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/22/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jabel@bsomusic.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tonya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Robles</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tmrobles@bsomusic.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Baltimore Symphony Orchestra, Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212015545</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4107838095</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1212 Cathedral Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7259</Code>
      <Text>AISL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
