<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Group Travel Grant for the Doctoral Consortium of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>17050</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant partially supports the participation of students from US institutions in the Doctoral Consortium at the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) 2016. CVPR is the premier annual international conference in computer vision with about 2000 senior, junior, and student participants. The goal of the Doctoral Consortium is to highlight the work of senior PhD students who are within six months of receiving their degrees (including recent graduates), and to give these students an opportunity to discuss their research and career options with faculty and researchers who have relevant expertise and experience. The Doctoral Consortium supports the career development of some of the brightest junior researchers in computer vision, contributes to the research community in general by drawing attention to an important aspect of graduate student development, potentially increases the number of active researchers and educators in STEM, and ensures that the computer vision community, through its recent graduates, makes fast advances in solving problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF support covers some of the costs for 20 selected US-based graduate students to attend the CVPR 2016 conference and the Doctoral Consortium associated with it. Participants and recipients of travel support are selected by the 2016 CVPR organizing committee, with the logistics managed by the PI. The Doctoral Consortium provides opportunities for graduate students to receive advice on their research work and career plans from experts from different institutions, and with potentially different perspectives, is often not available internally at one's own institution. This year's Doctoral Consortium features two new components which aim to address comments from last year's participants. These components are a panel discussion and more interaction with mentors. The Doctoral Consortium helps graduating students in computer vision find the best career options for their talents and achieve their potential, thus benefiting the computer vision field and society as a whole.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1630019</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adriana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kovashka</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kovashka@cs.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
