<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI:BIC: RouteMe2 -A Cloud-Integrated Sensor Infrastructure for Assisted Public Transportation Services</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>992146</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will create a smart service system (RouteMe2) that will help passengers with special needs use public transit safely and confidently. This research addresses the needs of a large community of people who rely on public transportation for independent mobility, and yet face difficulties using it. For someone with poor vision or blindness, some level of cognitive impairment, or for a senior citizen, taking a bus on an unfamiliar route can become a challenge and a source of anxiety. The problem is often one of scarce access to relevant information such as which bus to catch, which platform to wait on for a train, when to exit the vehicle and how to negotiate a transfer. The smart service system will facilitate and promote use of mass transit systems as passengers, or their assistants, will be able to pre-register a trip, possibly involving multiple legs and different means of transportation from multiple agencies. It is envisioned that during the trip, passengers will receive context-aware information that will help ensure that they are waiting for a bus or a train in the right location; they are entering the desired bus vehicle or train car, and that they exit the vehicle at the correct stop or station. Importantly, authorized users (family members, friends, or assistants) will be able to monitor the user's trip remotely, and receive warnings when an unexpected situation occurs (e.g., when a user is waiting for a train in the wrong platform, enters the wrong bus, or is stuck at a certain location). Anonymized data about travelers can be relayed to the transit agency for enhanced service; for example, a bus driver can be informed that a blind passenger is waiting for the bus at a certain stop. RouteMe2 will promote increased travel independence, and thus increased opportunities for education, employment, socialization, participation, and leisure. It is expected that designing this type of human-centered technology with a clear societal benefit, and interacting with the participants in the user studies will be an inspirational and rewarding experience for the students involved in this research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This technology will rely on interconnected sensors that can track a passenger during a trip, and on services that can provide just-in-time information to passengers on smartphones. This project will develop and experiment with a sensor and information infrastructure specifically designed to assist individuals with special needs while taking public transportation. The RouteMe2 system will rely essentially on cloud services, complemented with location data from an infrastructure of economical, miniaturized sensors (iBeacons), as well as data from the smartphone carried by the user, such as data generated by its GPS and inertial sensors. Individuals from different communities of potential users of this system (senior citizens and people with visual or cognitive impairments) will contribute to system design by means of initial focus groups, and will test it with a series of carefully designed user studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is a partnership between the University of California, Santa Cruz (lead institution) with faculty and students from its departments of Computer Engineering, Computer Science, Computational Media and Environmental Studies with IBM Research as primary industrial partner (Almaden, CA; large business) participating with its Cloud, IoT &amp; Systems Lifecycle Analytics Group. Other broader context partners are Santa Clara Valley Transportation Authority (San Jose, CA; special purpose district) and the Vista Center the Blind and Visually Impaired (Palo Alto, CA; non-profit organization).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1632158</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>elm@cs.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kurniawan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>srikur@soe.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Millard-Ball</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>adammb@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roberto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Manduchi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>manduchi@soe.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1662</Code>
      <Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5342</Code>
      <Text>Gen &amp; Age Rel Disabilities Eng</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1662</Code>
      <Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
