<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Chemical treatment efficiency of point-of-use filters deployed in Flint, Michigan</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49992</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1633013&lt;br/&gt;McElmurry&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Changes in the source and treatment of Flint's drinking water have resulted in extensive corrosion and numerous violations to the Safe Drinking Water Act through elevated lead concentrations. As a measure of protection to consumers, faucet-mounted point-of-use filters are being deployed across the city at a scale not previously seen in the United States. The point-of-use filters distributed in Flint are rated for a maximum lead concentration of 150 ppb; however, concentrations of more than 40 times that were observed in January 2016. Therefore, there is an immediate need to rapidly evaluate the treatment efficiency of PoU filters. This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) grant provides a unique opportunity to advance fundamental scientific knowledge regarding physical-chemical process responsible for lead and DBP removal while simultaneously ensuring public health. Controlled laboratory experiments will be conducted to determine treatment efficiency under the range of conditions observed in Flint. These results will be compared to those obtained from filters in homes where filters are subjected to typical use conditions that often deviate significantly from conditions used to certify chemical removal efficiency.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Studies will be conducted to evaluate two hypotheses: (1) lead and copper removal by the ion exchange resin will be reduced by competition from other cations and dissolved organic matter present in Flint drinking water, and, (2) adsorption of trihalomethanes on the activated carbon filtration media will decrease with increasing disinfectant dosage. This work will advance the understanding of the removal of lead, copper and disinfection by-products under real world conditions where complex interactions with colloids and dissolved organic matter occur. The work will utilize controlled laboratory experiments, conducted in state-of-the-art facilities at two major research universities (Wayne State University and Michigan State University) with a strong commitment to collaborative and innovative research. The proposed study will help protect human health and improve the security of municipal water supplies. Laboratory experiments and field sampling will be done in collaboration with Michigan State University and University of Michigan, focused on microbial conditions within point-of-use filters. Results of this study will be disseminated with the assistance of another faculty at Wayne State University, whose research focuses on translating scientific information to the public. Graduate and undergraduate students from groups underrepresented in science and engineering will conduct experiments and collect field samples providing hands on training in the areas of water treatment, colloid chemistry, and disinfection processes. Skills these students obtain will be invaluable in advancing the protection of the nation's water supply. Additionally, the project team will develop and provide lectures and special programs on issues related to aging infrastructure and corrosion control that will be presented at regional meetings of the American Water Works Association.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1633013</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
      <LastName>McElmurry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>s.mcelmurry@wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/27/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wayne State University</Name>
      <CityName>Detroit</CityName>
      <ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5057 Woodward</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1440</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
