<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Do Cyanobacteria Drive Marine Hydrocarbon Biogeochemistry?</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>396911</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Miller</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>While the release of petroleum hydrocarbons into the ocean is recognized as an environmental and human hazard, a recent study has estimated that on an annual basis, the release of natural hydrocarbons by a single phytoplankton group (cyanobacteria) contributes at least ten times more total hydrocarbon to the surface ocean. This project will be the first in-depth study of the latent biogeochemical cycling of this huge pool of biogenic hydrocarbons. Using field studies, laboratory incubations of cyanobacteria, and state-of-the art chemical analysis, the researchers will examine the molecular structures, rates and mechanisms of production and removal, and the environmental conditions that control the cycling of this major pool of oceanic hydrocarbons. The results of this study will reveal significant new knowledge for improved understanding of a major carbon cycle in the ocean. Additionally, data could indicate a role for cyanobacterial hydrocarbons in preparing natural marine bacteria to respond to, and degrade petroleum spills, as well as a possible atmospheric impact (e.g. cloud formation) resulting from air-sea exchange of certain components of the hydrocarbon pool. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support undergraduate and graduate students, a postdoctoral investigator, and a new faculty member, and will engage participants from minority-serving institutions in California and North Carolina. Plans are also included to establish links with oil spill and biofuel researchers in order to evaluate additional practical applications for the data resulting from this study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The annual production of 308,000,000 - 771,000,000 tons of hydrocarbons by cyanobacteria has recently been reported and is a factor of 10 larger than marine petroleum hydrocarbon input from spills and natural seeps. Consequently, these biogenic hydrocarbons almost certainly have significant implications for the carbon cycle and the bacterial community composition in the ocean but have never been the subject of rigorous study. This project will investigate the distribution, partitioning, and cycling of biogenic hydrocarbons in the ocean, focusing on the abundance and molecular diversity of biogenic hydrocarbons in relation to cyanobacterial populations; the extent to which volatilization to the atmosphere acts as a sink for biogenic hydrocarbons; and the rate at which hydrocarbons are produced by cyanobacteria and consumed by hydrocarbon-degrading bacteria. Field studies across natural gradients in phytoplankton community structure and abundance will employ state of the art chemical analysis to evaluate the distribution of biogenic hydrocarbons, and together with incubation experiments will determine quantitative rates for biogenic hydrocarbons cycling in the surface ocean. Laboratory studies will augment field studies by assessing hydrocarbon production and loss mechanisms under carefully controlled laboratory conditions. Together, the project will obtain a quantitative understanding of this important component of the oceanic carbon cycle.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1634478</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reddy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>creddy@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1670</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1389</Code>
      <Text>CARBON CYCLE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
