<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integrating Directed Assembly and 3D Printing to Enable Advanced Nanomanufacturing Across Multiple Length Scales</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Access to nanomaterial building blocks with precisely controlled size, shape and composition has created a fertile opportunity space for emerging nanotechnologies. Prototype nanomaterial-enabled technologies spanning sensors, membranes, catalysis, data storage, electronics, displays, photovoltaics, energy storage, and thermoelectrics have generated high expectations for their commercialization. However, there is growing recognition that sustained progress towards the acclaimed promise of nanomaterial-enabled technologies depends critically on solving outstanding fabrication challenges; in particular the need to bridge the length-scale gap between millimeter scale devices and nanometer scale components. This research will develop spearheading nanomanufacturing capabilities to fabricate materials and devices with precisely programmed structure, composition, and function across six orders of magnitude in length scale. The research is driven by the vision that combined control over individual nanostructures (at atomistic length scales), programmable molecular assembly of micrometer superstructures and advanced manufacturing methods (spanning micrometer to meter) presents exciting prospects to manufacture new classes of materials and devices. Beyond the scientific and technological impact of advanced nanomanufacturing capabilities, the educational objectives of this project will focus research opportunities for undergraduates and minorities by developing interactive 3D printing learning modules. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The confluence of advances in directed assembly of nanomaterials and additive manufacturing technologies create powerful prospects to address critical challenges in scalable nanofabrication. On the one hand, technological applications of self-assembled nanostructures (e.g., nanoparticle superlattices) are limited by the lack of scalable fabrication methods. On the other hand, currently available 3D printing technologies are limited by speed, spatial resolution and material diversity. This project will explore synergies at the intersection of these two fields. The research team embraces the challenge of bridging this length scale gap as an opportunity to develop novel nanomanufacturing techniques that synergistically combine recent advances in molecular-level assembly and additive 3D printing. This project will explore the concept of continuous additive nanomanufacturing at Fluid Interfaces (CANFI). New knowledge from the project will establish the scientific and engineering foundation for advanced hierarchical nanomanufacturing techniques that span 6 orders of magnitude in length scale. Beyond the specific model systems at the focus of the work, the knowledge generated from this work is expected to have significant multiplying effects and will likely spur additional nanomanufacturing advances in related fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1635433</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tobias</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hanrath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>th358@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING &amp; CONST MACH EQP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>Nanomanufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
