<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Standard Proposal: Building a Culture of Responsible Research and Practice in STEM</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>335800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenda Bauchspies</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-technical: This award by the Cultivating Cultures for Ethical STEM program aims at situating responsible research and practice education within the research environment, and involving whole departments. This award is funded by the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences and cofounded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences. The approach will target both the organizational context in that it aims at modifications in the respective departments, and the peer environment in that it makes the discussion of ethical issues a regular part of research practice. The project will be an important component in building a more comprehensive bottom-up program of ethics education that will complement existing education tools addressing responsible conduct of research (RCR). The interactive exercises and discussions proposed in the guideline-development module will help to both reinforce and broaden the knowledge obtained in existing RCR courses and online training modules, as well as helping researchers to both recognize ethical issues and foster ethical practice in science, technology, engineering and mathematics. Furthermore, the project will provide ideas of how existing ethics codes can better consider responsible conduct and practice in laboratory environments and will suggest ways to modify current codes of ethics in order to better serve the needs of researchers working in laboratory settings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: The project will identify factors relevant to ethically responsible undertaking of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) and cultivate the building of an ethical research and practice culture in experimental laboratories through the bottom-up development of context specific ethical guidelines. The guidelines will address ethical issues specific to the organization for which they are developed and complement existing, more general codes of ethics and guidelines. In a process that involves research into existing discipline-specific codes and guidelines, exposure to ethical theory, and free discussion and interaction between stakeholders, the laboratory guidelines will be developed by groups of graduate students, discussed with students, faculty and staff, and ideally finally adopted within the respective departments. The process of developing these guidelines will cultivate a high level of ownership in participating students, and help make the guidelines an integral part of lab culture used in the orientation of new lab members. The approach has the potential to bring about lasting change in the ethical culture of experimental laboratories that can be passed on to future students entering the labs. An extensive assessment plan includes evaluation tools that monitor the rate of adoption and adherence levels and the influence on lab culture over time related to the proposed strategy within participating labs and departments. The inclusion of an ethnographic study in the project will bring to light the evolving process of cultural and ethical change. Based on the results obtained, a broadly applicable module that guides institutions in the bottom-up building of codes-of-ethics-based guidelines will be developed, refined and disseminated widely. The final guideline-development module will include a guide for measuring ethical lab culture, assessment of results, and strategies for continuing free discussions of this kind. It will be made available for other institutions including community colleges to use as part of lab orientation, workshops, or other formats.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1635661</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Laas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>laas@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elisabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hildt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ehildt@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brey@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cmille31@stuart.iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>019Y</Code>
      <Text>Cultivating Cultures of Ethica</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
