<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Public Service Provision and Pockets of Effectiveness</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11934</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES-1636972&lt;br/&gt;Ivan Ermakoff&lt;br/&gt;Michael Roll&lt;br/&gt;University of Wisconsin Madison&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The effective provision of basic public services is essential for reducing poverty in the developing world. In many countries, however, government agencies in charge of providing services like water, security, health services, and education are dysfunctional. Often, public sector reforms undertaken with international support have failed to remedy this situation. That is why the capacity of some government agencies to meet public service requirements in contexts marked by governmental ineffectiveness requires systematic attention. Focusing on subnational variation in organizational performance, this project examines why and how these organizations achieve satisfactory levels of performance. By exploring the micro-processes and mechanisms through which these pockets of effective public service provision emerge and become institutionalized, this project makes a theoretical contribution to understanding the origins of subnational institutional variation, institutional change, and development. The findings will also be of relevance to policymakers and international agencies working on corruption and public services. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using a matched pairs design, the project compares government agencies in Nigeria that differ substantially in terms of public service provision. Based on semi-structured interviews, focus group discussions, non-participant observation, surveys, and the analysis of administrative data, process tracing and within-case analysis will be employed for identifying the processes and mechanisms at work and cross-case analysis for added leverage.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1636972</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ermakoff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ermakoff@ssc.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roll</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mroll@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
