<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2016 International Indian Statistical Association conference `Statistical and Data Sciences: A Key to Healthy People, Planet and Prosperity'</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Keith Crank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 2016 meeting of the International Indian Statistical Association (IISA) will take place at Oregon State University, from August 18-21, 2016. (See http://blogs.oregonstate.edu/iisa/.) The main objective of the conference is to bring together both well established and emerging young researchers from around the world who are actively pursuing theoretical and methodological research in statistics and data science and their applications in various allied fields. The conference aims to provide a forum for leading experts and young researchers to discuss recent progress in statistical theory and applications and in data science, thereby providing new directions for statistical inference in various fields. It aims to promote education, research and application of statistics, probability and data science throughout the world with a special emphasis on the Indian subcontinent, foster the exchange of information and scholarly activities between various countries as well as among other national/international organizations for the development of statistical and data science, serve the needs of young statisticians and data scientists and encourage cooperative efforts among members in education, research, industry and business.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Oregon State University will host the 2016 meeting of the International Indian Statistical Association (IISA) from August 18-21, 2016. Plenary speakers will be Kanti Mardia (University of Leeds) and Xiao-Li Meng (Harvard University). Keynote speakers include Kathy Ensor (Rice University), Debashis Ghosh (University of Colorado, Denver), Kannan Natarajan (Novartis), and Ajit Tamhane (Northwestern University). Activities for junior researchers include a session on early career development and a student paper competition. This funding will assure the participation of junior researchers and graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1636648</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Debashis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mondal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mondald@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
