<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: The 10th Q-Bio Conference, July 27-30, Nashville, TN</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19776</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Q-Bio (Quantitative Biology) Conference brings together a community of researchers interested in developing a theory-driven and predictive understanding of biology. Such an understanding provides not only insight into basic biological phenomena, but is also a foundation for advances in biotechnology, agriculture and medicine. The conference will bring together researchers working in biology, mathematics, physics, chemistry, computer science and engineering, and broaden participation in this emerging area by supporting the attendance of early career researchers, women and members of groups under-represented in the field. Through encouragement and support of the attendance of junior researchers (including postdoctoral fellows and graduate students) the conference will provide opportunities for them to meet with senior, leading investigators to exchange ideas and information, thereby helping to train the next generation of researchers in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Conference will include keynote talks, oral presentations and opportunities for poster presentations; these will all be organized around a common set of themes. These themes will be: Cellular processes and signaling networks in prokaryotes and eukaryotes; Ecology and evolution of cellular collectives; Mechanisms of force sensing, transmission and generation and their relationship to signaling processes; Stochasticity in cellular signaling; Computational methods in the study of systems-level cellular processes; Metabolic processes and cellular signaling.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1636697</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lopez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c.lopez@Vanderbilt.Edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
      <CityName>Nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1114</Code>
      <Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8011</Code>
      <Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
