<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Magnitude, Extent, and Impact of a Pre-Historical Multi-Century Drought in the Western US</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sunil Narumalani</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project will investigate the causes of a multi-century drought in western North America during the Late Holocene Dry Period and will analyze its geographic extent and impact on Native Americans living in the immediate area. Droughts are a regular feature of climatic conditions in the western U.S., and global prediction models suggest that they will intensify in the future. Drought impacts society through agricultural losses, water restrictions, and a range of other damages to businesses, utilities, and industry. By analyzing paleoclimatic patterns, this project will enhance basic understanding of the ocean-atmosphere dynamics that create persistent droughts in the western United States. The project will provide new insights into strategies employed by prehistoric populations to cope with these harsh environmental changes. Given the devastating social, economic, and ecological impacts of droughts, this project will provide rich insights regarding drought dynamics and responses to drought. The project also will provide education and training opportunities for Native American undergraduate and graduate students through laboratory research experiences and fieldwork on tribal lands.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the western U.S., precipitation patterns during the Late Holocene Dry Period had a persistent dipolar pattern of a dry southwest and a wet northwest, similar to the pattern produced during the modern-day La Nina phases of the El Nino Southern Oscillation. Because of these similarities, the paleoclimatic record for the Late Holocene Dry Period offers insights into the temperature and precipitation profiles that caused long-duration, high-intensity droughts in the region. This project will focus on three core questions: (1) What were the spatial and temporal extents of the atmospheric circulation patterns that resulted in the dipolar conditions of very long-term drought in the southwest and wet climate in the northwest? (2) What was the precipitation and temperature regime during the Late Holocene Dry Period? (3) What was the nature and extent of human response to an extended period of environmental change? The investigators will analyze pollen from sediment cores collected from wet meadows along a north-south transect in Nevada and Idaho to reconstruct temporal changes in precipitation. Carbon and oxygen isotopes will be analyzed from remnant sagebrush wood to reconstruct seasonal patterns of precipitation and temperature. Curated collections from key archaeological sites will be re-dated using high-resolution accelerator mass spectrometry radiocarbon to identify small, short-lived organics for reconstructing the responses of Native American populations to periods of intense drought. Findings from this research will enhance capabilities to model future megadroughts and persistent drought conditions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1636519</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mensing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smensing@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kennett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>djk23@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rhode</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dave@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Csank</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>adam.csank@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1304</Code>
      <Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9278</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
