<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAP: Building a Cyberlearning Research Program: An Early Career Symposium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24573</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tatiana D. Korelsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Cyberlearning and Future Learning Technologies Program funds efforts that will help envision the next generation of learning technologies and advance what we know about how people learn in technology-rich environments. Cyberlearning CAP projects build capacity for research and development in the field of cyberlearning by improving technical infrastructure, human capital, and in other ways. The Annual Meeting of the Association for Educational Communications and Technology provides a forum for interchange of ideas around designing technological support for learning and training. This project supports an Early Career Symposium at the conference which allows early career scholars to receive mentoring from established cyberlearning researchers from both computer science and learning research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports travel for advanced graduate students and new faculty from U.S. universities to attend the Early Career Symposium at the AECT 2016 conference in Las Vegas, Nevada. Sessions during the Symposium are designed to help collaborators imagine forward-looking and viable technology-oriented research agendas, identify the types of collaborators who complement their strengths, and identify the funding agencies and programs that might support their work. An important goal of the Symposium is to add to the community of researchers interested in ways that technology can transform teaching and learning.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1639817</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ginger</FirstName>
      <LastName>Watson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>GSWatson@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8020</Code>
      <Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8045</Code>
      <Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8055</Code>
      <Text>Capacity-Building Projects</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
