<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CS 10K: The Tuskegee Partnership to Establish Computer Science Education in the Alabama Black Belt</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>999997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Janice E. Cuny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Tuskegee University is implementing the TU CS10K Project in partnership with Auburn University, the University of Alabama, A+ College Ready, the Alabama State Department of Education, the Black Belt Commission, the Exploring Computer Science Program, the Tuskegee University Computer Science Advisory Board, and 19 school districts in the 17 counties that traditionally constitute the historic Black Belt region of the state of Alabama. Computing impacts almost all aspects of our daily lives and its important that students get the opportunity to study computer science (CS) through formal course work in order to excite them about studies and career opportunities in CS. Yet, the vast majority of high school students in Alabama attend schools that do not offer rigorous CS curriculum. To address this, the TU CS10K Project aims to develop, implement, study and evaluate an ambitious project to establish the Exploring Computer Science (ECS) curricula in all 43 high schools of the historic Alabama Black Belt. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The TU-CS 10K Project will prepare 60 in-service teachers for ECS instruction in partnering high schools using the ECS model of teacher professional development (PD): a one-week comprehensive Summer Institute followed by face-to-face meetings during the school year, monthly virtual Google Hangouts, an online community of practice, and a follow-on Summer Institute, all of which are designed to prepare teachers for ECS course instruction, focusing both on content and instructional strategies. The PD will be provided by endorsed ECS PD facilitators and assisted by the PIs and CS graduate students; implementation support will be delivered to classroom teachers by teacher Professional Learning Communities. Additionally, recruitment and awareness activities will be carried-out to motivate high school students to take ECS, with the aim of involving 1,500 racially and ethnically diverse male and female 9th and 10th graders. The project's research agenda will advance knowledge in K-12 CS education in high-needs settings, and a rigorous evaluation plan will provide continuous guidance to the PIs to ensure that the project is on track to meet its goals and objectives.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1639971</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gray@cs.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mohammed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Qazi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maqazi@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hira</FirstName>
      <LastName>Narang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>narang@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Melody</FirstName>
      <LastName>Russell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>russeml@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cassandra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thomas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cthomas@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tuskegee University</Name>
      <CityName>Tuskegee Institute</CityName>
      <ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3347278233</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 W Montgomery Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>005Y</Code>
      <Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>023Z</Code>
      <Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7578</Code>
      <Text>CS 10K</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
