<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Support: 2016 Annual International Solid Freeform Fabrication Symposium; Austin, Texas; August 8-10, 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven R. Schmid</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports 83 graduate and undergraduate students studying at US institutions to participate in the 2016 Annual International Solid Freeform Fabrication Symposium - An Additive Manufacturing Conference. This conference will be held August 8 - 10, 2016, in Austin, Texas, hosted by The University of Texas in Austin. It is considered a globally-leading professional gathering in the additive manufacturing field. It brings together researchers from academia, industry, and national labs. The award provides student participants with opportunities to exchange ideas with leading researchers and engineers from worldwide industrial and governmental facilities, as well as with students and faculty from both domestic and international schools. In addition to nurturing a global additive manufacturing vision, participants will learn the latest research areas and results in additive manufacturing fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The support will cover the registration fees at $600 per student. The call for student support applications will be disseminated through posting on main conference website, promulgation through conference organizers, and direct communication with students involved in the poster session of the conference. The conference committee will select 83 students from these applications. The selection criteria include: (1) students must be from US institutions, and (2) students must be actively participating in the conference through presenting a paper or a poster. Priority will be given to students who have multiple technical papers accepted and students who present NSF-sponsored technical papers. After the conference, the list of students who receive the support will be posted at the main conference website and in the 2016 Solid Freeform Fabrication Symposium post-conference report.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1639406</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ihab</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ragai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ifr1@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bourell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbourell@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
