<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Second TMS Summit on Diversity in the Minerals, Metals, and Materials Professions (DMMM2); Evanston, Illinois; July 25-26, 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Numerous studies have demonstrated that a diverse talent pool increases productivity, competitiveness, and creativity. However, this diversity is often untapped among the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) professions, including the minerals, metals and materials community. To address this concern, The Minerals, Metals and Materials Society (TMS) will hold the Second TMS Summit on Diversity in the Minerals, Metals, and Materials Professions (DMMM2) in Evanston, Illinois, July 25-26, 2016. DMMM2 is part of a recurring summit series and will have a culminating emphasis on the development and implementation of skills and toolsets. Topics including communication and negotiation techniques to mentoring and support networks will be part of the event to help empower participants with skills they can use and share upon returning to their respective workplaces or classrooms to facilitate a more diverse workplace and community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Second TMS Summit on Diversity in the Minerals, Metals &amp; Materials Professions will primarily focus on three overarching topic areas to continue the themes initially raised during the first summit: (1) strategies for increasing under-represented minority engagement in STEM professions, (2) best practices for building a welcoming and inclusive workplace culture, and (3) addressing factors behind the self-induced glass ceiling in order to support new pathways to career fulfillment. This summit is intended to provide the tools and development of personnel skills to increase diversity in the minerals, metals and materials community. The audience will consist of at least 100 attendees who will hear from more than 40 invited speakers drawn from government, academia, and industry. This summit will be held over two days to include interactive panel discussions, lectures by key leaders in the field of diversity, and skill-building sessions intended to catalyze further tangible actions that actively address diversity and inclusion.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1641397</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jscott@tms.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beringer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lberinger@tms.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Minerals Metals &amp; Materials Society</Name>
      <CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>150867528</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7248143178</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>184 Thorn Hill RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7680</Code>
      <Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8092</Code>
      <Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1444</Code>
      <Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7680</Code>
      <Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8021</Code>
      <Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8022</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Infrastructure Materials</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8025</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
