<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US Ignite 2016 Application Summit</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>198545</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>To explore how advanced network technologies address important public benefit problems, US Ignite will gather teams working on these next-generation applications at the 2016 Application Summit, June 14- 15, 2016, in Austin Texas. Participants will demonstrate that advanced networking technologies such as software-defined networking, virtualized networks, gigabit to the end-user, and GENI racks can address societal problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of the 2016 Application Summit are to 1) create a collaborative venue to demonstrate applications that take advantage of next-generation network technology, 2) provide a public forum around gigabit applications, 3) convene current and potential future Smart Gigabit Community representatives, and 4) demonstrate the important role that advanced networks will play in the emerging smart city / Internet of Things ecosystem. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Summit hosts academic, research, commercial and community leaders who are experts in next-generation technologies that serve the public benefit. By providing thought-leadership as well as practical expertise in successful application of next-generation technologies, these experts help educate and engage industry labs, federal agencies, foundations, venture capitalists, entrepreneurs, open source developers, students and faculty. The Summit provides a collaborative environment wherein researchers, developers, students and faculty can share their work with and learn from one another.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1642580</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kochan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>joe.kochan@us-ignite.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/31/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>US Ignite, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200363846</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023659219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1150 18th Street NW, Suite 900</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>2890</Code>
      <Text>CISE RESEARCH RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
