<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2016 IEEE Global Communications Conference (IEEE GLOBECOM)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This travel grant will be used to support US based graduate students to attend IEEE GLOBECOM 2016, to be held in Washington, DC on December 4-8, 2016. IEEE GLOBECOM is one of two flagship conferences of the IEEE Communications Society (ComSoc). This conference offers not only technical paper presentations but also a wide range of other educational formats, including panels, tutorials, industry presentations, posters and keynote speeches by academic and industry leaders. Attending IEEE GLOBECOM is highly valuable for students. Not only will they be exposed to the state-of-the-art researches in the field of communications and networking, but also they can have the opportunity to interact with peers from institutions worldwide, meet with leading researchers from both industry and academia, and take part in discussions that may shape the future of the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant encourages participation by students who would normally find it difficult to attend. Recipients of the travel awards will be selected by a Travel Grants Committee, formed by the IEEE GLOBECOM 2016 student travel grant co-chairs. A total of 25 awardees will be selected. Award selection criteria include papers accepted into the conference and research interests in the conference topics as demonstrated by coursework and/or project experience. Women and minorities are given preference when other qualifications are similar. To avoid conflicts of interest, the students of the faculty in the selection committee will not be considered for this travel grant award. This student travel support will enable sharing scientific information and stimulating research interests for U.S. based students in the field of communications and networking.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1643335</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cheng@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
