<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Improving Model Parameterization of Energetic Fluxes in the Boundary Layer over Antarctica</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter J. Milne</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A joint NSF and DOE Atmospheric Radiation Measurement (ARM) West Antarctic Radiation Experiment (AWARE, PLR-1443549), is currently collecting a wide range of meteorological, radiation, and cloud microphysical data from McMurdo, Ross Island and also in part at the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) Divide field camp. These observational efforts will serve to better characterize Antarctic climate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award will additionally allow a US PI to participate in the French field program at Dome C entitled "Improving Model Parameterization of Energetic Fluxes in the Boundary Layer over Antarctica - CALVA." In addition to planned collaboration between the PI with her French colleagues from Laboratoire de Geophysique et Geophysique de l'Environnement (LGGE), there is expected to be a collaboration with the science teams for the joint AWARE and CALVA efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One AWARE objective is to observe the impact of long-range moisture transport from Southern Ocean storm tracks on cloud formation and microphysics, and ultimately to better understand the surface radiation and energy budget over Antarctic regions vulnerable to ice mass loss. Comparing AWARE measurement sets to the high terrain of East Antarctica, at Dome C, will allow conclusions as to the ice mass balance to be reached throughout the larger continental area. It is for this concurrency of data intensive measurement campaigns that a RAPID award is desirable and appropriate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1643304</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Veron</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dveron@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5113</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5113</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
