<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Southern California Number Theory Day Conferences at UC Irvine</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The first Southern California Number Theory Day funded through this grant will take place in October of 2016 at the University of California, Irvine, subsequent meetings funded by this award will take place in 2017,2018 and 2019. The Southern California Number Theory Day at UCI is a series of annual one-day conferences in number theory that brings together mathematicians from Southern California and beyond. The conferences will encourage interactions and collaborations among number theorists, giving the participants the opportunity to interact with scholars from other institutions, and giving graduate students and postdocs the opportunity to interact with senior mathematicians from other institutions in academia, government, or industry. A special effort will be made to include speakers from under-represented groups and to encourage participants from under-represented groups. Information about these meetings may be found at: http://www.math.uci.edu/~krubin/ntg/number_theory.html&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The lectures are research talks at the cutting edge of the field, given by international experts. The collaborations that are formed should lead to new ideas and useful research results in important areas of mathematics. The conferences bring together a critical mass of number theorists, in a way that each Southern California institution individually cannot do with its own seminars. The conferences also serve as a way to disseminate the latest research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1643328</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Silverberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>asilverb@math.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaplan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nckaplan@math.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498244768</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5171 California Avenue, Ste 150</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
