<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WiFiUS: Coordinating US-Finland Collaboration on Wireless Research through WiFiUS PI Meetings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>128099</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Internet of Things (IoT) is poised to create new economic opportunities and considerably enhance the quality of life of the general population. The proposed coordination project is aimed at bringing together a diverse body of expert researchers and scientists from the U.S. and Finland. This effort will result in identifying the best practices of IoT and push forward the state of the art, by leveraging unique skills and capabilities between the two countries. The project will facilitate collaboration by building on the previous successes of joint projects that have resulted in global innovations in the area of wireless networks and communication. The project is concerned with organizing meetings planned over the next three years that include technical workshops for researchers and two education-focused summer schools for students. Members from under-represented minority groups will be proactively included for all these meetings. This effort will directly link to several national-level objectives like enhancing data science and big data, climate change, disaster response, smart cities that have been prioritized within the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project builds upon and extends the solid foundation of the past successes achieved within the Wireless Innovation between Finland and U.S. (WiFiUS) program for building long-term research and education collaboration between the two world leaders in the field of wireless networking. The specific thrust of this project is on solving the wireless networking challenges for IoT, which has not been adequately covered in previous topic-focused WiFiUS calls. The topics of interest in the workshops and summer schools include IoT architectures and protocols, network functions with communication, computation, and storage, and security and privacy in IoT. It will also enable sharing of knowledge and cross-fertilization among the participants of various relevant international projects and expertise with respect to emerging experimental platforms, standards and wireless technology policies in the two countries with respect to IoT.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1644763</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kaushik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chowdhury</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krc@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8229</Code>
      <Text>WiFiUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
