<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Exploring a Taxonomy for Citizen Science Tools Database</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1645382&lt;br/&gt;Lande&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To help facilitate citizen science projects, an inventory of technologies used in citizen science projects is needed, as well as available technologies that have not yet been tapped which could provide opportunities for future citizen science efforts. Citizen science practitioners also need an easily understood reference/resource guide to evaluate available technologies. The types of technologies considered include standalone sensors, instrumentation available in smartphones such as cameras and global positioning systems, digital imaging devices, test strips, unconventional uses of standard devices, and digital and analog measurement tools. This project will build a foundation for increasing the capacity for future research into citizen science and informal science learning by increasing the frequency and efficacy of citizen science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main research question of this study is: how might greater awareness of, and better access to, citizen science tools help researchers meet the needs and grow interests in citizen scientists? The research objective of this project is to explore and understand what qualities and characteristics of tools for citizen science can help support high-quality data collection balanced with greater accessibility. The aim is to expand understanding of what citizen science tools are currently available, feasible, cost-effective, accessible and useful and to illustrate how a citizen science tools database may be adopted within the citizen science community. The PIs will use the repository of 1600+ citizen science projects within the SciStarter community to invite project leaders, researchers, and citizen scientists to help evaluate what criteria could be useful and desirable in a companion database for citizen science tools. SciStarter is a research affiliate of Arizona State University and receives support from the NSF to: 1) support participant engagement in one or multiple citizen science projects through GIS implementation so participants can find opportunities near them with local relevance; 2) increase the ability for participants to engage in multiple projects and track their projects, participation, and contributions to science; 3) create an online, personal dashboard for participants to track, share and save data, record interests in projects, create profiles, and find people and projects of interest to them. The database may serve as a reference guide to help Makers, developers, manufacturers, researchers, and funders understand the current landscape of citizen science tools to avoid duplication and identify gaps. The nature of the type of tools (cost, complexity, support, and additional categories) will be tested and evaluated through an iterative design-in-action process that will give multiple stakeholders opportunities for feedback. The project will increase the likelihood that more people will engage in projects by making it easier to both discover citizen science projects and access the tools required to get involved in the projects. This iterative process will lead to a sense of ownership of those participation in citizen science, by helping the participants to rate and review tools and track their use of the tools in their SciStarter engagement.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1645382</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Micah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lande</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>micah.lande@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Darlene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cavalier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>darlene.cavalier@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1440</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1642</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL INITIATIVES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>043Z</Code>
      <Text>PPSR- Public Participation in Scientific</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1638</Code>
      <Text>INFRAST MGMT &amp; EXTREME EVENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
