<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2016 ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (ACM SenSys)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SenSys, ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems, is a highly selective scientific forum that has successfully created fundamental knowledge and technologies to build the sensors and smart systems, from the wireless sensors in homes and offices to large-scale sensors, networks, and data analytics in smart infrastructures and cities. The conference brings together researchers from the fields of wireless communication and networking, embedded systems and hardware, energy harvesting and management, distributed systems and algorithms, data management, and applications and thus is an ideal venue for beginning researchers and PhD students to get to know the field from disciplinary and cross-disciplinary perspectives. The goal of this project is to provide funding for attending SenSys by PhD students who are enrolled in the US institutions of higher learning. The project will enable students who are not well-funded or who belong to underrepresented groups to attend SenSys. The students will not only gain exposure to the leading researchers in the field but also network with peers and start research collaborations as they take leadership roles in research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will enable approximately 16 Ph.D. from recognized US institution of higher education to attend SenSys. A grant selection committee will select the participants based on their financial need, research potential, and their ability to benefit from this attendance while increasing diversity among SenSys attendees. SenSys and the field of sensing and smart systems will benefit from this increased diversity and engagement from the US-based PhD students. The students will benefit from exposure to the leading researchers in the field and with increased networking and collaboration opportunities at SenSys.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1649762</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Omprakash</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gnawali</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gnawali@cs.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
