<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Science and Power, Science as Power: International Conference Travel</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15974</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>General Audience Summary &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support participation of US scholars in the international conference, "Science and Power, Science as Power," the 7th International Conference of the European Society for the History of Science, to be held at Charles University in Prague, Czech Republic. The goal of the conference is to bring international scholars together to advance scholarly efforts concerning two intertwining themes, how the nature of science and the nature of power have shifted historically, and how the relationship between science and power as itself changed over time. The outcomes of this conference will include promotion of international intellectual interchange, scholarship, and broad dissemination. The grant will promote US scholars' contributions in this exploration, with particular attention to supporting graduate students and independent scholars. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The grant will support eight US participants including three PhD students, an independent scholar, junior scholars, and scholars from underrepresented groups (including women). All of the participants and the principal investigator are scheduled to present in sessions at the conference. The conference theme focusing on power is intended to attract scholars from underrepresented groups in the fields of History of Science, Technology, and Medicine; this is particularly so for those who are situated in the European "periphery." With the cooperation of the international Commission on Women and Gender Studies, which is independent of European Society for History of Science, two conference sessions focusing on women, gender and science have successfully been included on the program, and several of the US participants are indeed participating in those sessions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1649769</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Opitz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dopitz@depaul.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>DePaul University</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606042287</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3123627595</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 East Jackson Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7603</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
