<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Workshop on Computational Network Biology: Modeling, Analysis, and Control (CNB-MAC 2016)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Third Workshop on Computational Network Biology: Modeling, Analysis, and Control (CNB-MAC 2016) will be held in Seattle, WA, October 2. The workshop will be organized in conjunction with the 7th ACM Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics (ACM-BCB 2016). CNB-MAC 2016 is a continuation of the first and second CNB-MAC workshops in 2014 and 2015, which have been successfully organized in conjunction with ACM-BCB 2014 (in Newport Beach, CA) and ACM-BCB 2015 (in Atlanta, GA), respectively. The continuing partnership with ACM-BCB will enhance the visibility of the workshop and attract researchers from various disciplines across engineering, computer science, statistics, biology, and medicine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CNB-MAC 2016 aims to provide an international scientific forum for presenting recent advances in computational network biology and boost the awareness of the importance of rigorous mathematical modeling in transforming big biomedical data into reproducible and meaningful scientific knowledge. One of the missions of CNB-MAC that is of foremost importance is to foster next-generation scientists in the emerging field of computational network biology. The workshop aims to offer keynote, tutorial, and research talks to provide future research directions for participating graduate students and post-doctoral researchers, especially women and minorities. CNB-MAC 2016 will provide travel awards to encourage graduate students to participate in the workshop and present their latest research findings. Specifically, the workshop plans to allocate a minimum of 20-30% of the awards to female and minority students to encourage their participation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1649426</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tamer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kahveci</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tamer@cise.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Byung-Jun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yoon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bjyoon@ece.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaoning</FirstName>
      <LastName>Qian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xiaoning.qian@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7796</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7931</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
