<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2017 Quality and Productivity Research Conference - Quality and Statistics: Path to a Better Life</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>21000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Yong Zeng</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 2017 Quality and Productivity Research Conference Quality (QPRC) and Statistics: Path to a Better Life is held during June 13-15, 2017, preceded on June 12 by a short course titled Computational Bayesian Methods for Big Data Problems. QPRC 2017 is an international conference which serve as the annual conference of the Quality and Productivity Section of the American Statistical Association (ASA) in bringing together academics and professionals to disseminate and discuss latest advances in statistical approaches relevant to quality and productivity. The conference and the short course will be especially valuable for research oriented graduate and undergraduate students, as well as junior researchers and professionals. In the long tradition of successful annual QPRCs, the goal of QPRC 2017 is to provide its participants - statisticians and inter-disciplinary professionals ? an opportunity to meet and exchange ideas related to a broad set of topics in the area of quality and productivity, especially on topics relevant to big data in various areas. The NSF supports the participation (registration, travel and accommodation) for about 30 research oriented students with special consideration to women and minority students - graduate students, or senior or junior undergraduate students - from US academic institutions. Participants receiving support are strongly encouraged to actively take part in the conference by presenting a poster, in addition to attending the short course and attending software demos to be provided by vendors. These students are expected to greatly benefit from participating in this conference and attending the short course, and additionally have an opportunity to disseminate their research and to develop strong collaborations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main objective of the conference is to bring together both well established and emerging young researchers from academia, industry and government, who are actively pursuing theoretical, methodological, and computational research in the areas of quality and productivity, in order to discuss their research and in particular, their applications in various related fields. The focus topics include, but are not limited to, Bayesian Methods and Computing, Data Mining, Dynamic Modeling, Experimental Design, Health Analytics, Nonparametric methods, Reliability, Stochastic Modeling, Time Series, Variable Selection, etc. There are three plenary sessions and several interesting invited and contributed talk sessions on these topics. The conference provides an opportunity for all attendees, and especially for junior faculty, graduate students, and undergraduate students to showcase their research, and to also benefit from interactions with senior researchers, leading to acceleration and enhancement of their research. A rapid round precedes the poster session, and each presenter has an opportunity to showcase his/her work in 3 minutes. The short course especially illustrates the importance of techniques that address modeling, methods, and computing for big data (both big n and big p problems). More details about the conference and the short course can be found at the conference website www.qprc2017.org.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1650520</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nalini</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ravishanker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nalini.ravishanker@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
