<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SAVI Belmont Forum International Collaboration: Community-driven strategy to deliver e-Infrastructures and Data Management for global environmental challenges</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/06/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>26544</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>ICER</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria L. Uhle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is designated as a Science Across Virtual Institutes (SAVI) award and is being co-funded by the NSF's Directorate for Geosciences, Directorate of Computer Information Science and Engineering's Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (ACI) Division and Office of International and Integrative Activities. The aim of this award is to deliver an e-infrastructure and data management roadmap and implementation plan for effective end-to-end (basic research to decision making) global environmental change research by facilitating collaboration among engineers, computer, natural, and social scientists from the United States and many countries across the globe through a Knowledge Hub. The funds will be used to support the collaboration between 14 US researchers and approximately 120 researchers from the 13 participating Belmont Forum countries and the coordination of the Knowledge Hub activities through a secretariat. Knowledge Hub activities such as virtual working groups and in-person workshops will focus on two thematic areas: governance and interoperability in architectures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The resulting e-Infrastructure and Data Management Strategy and Implementation Plan will serve as a clear roadmap to address and prioritize interoperability challenges across the globe and integrate national and international research efforts to promote more holistic environmental decision support systems for global environmental change research. A key outcome of these collaborative efforts will be enhanced interoperability among global environmental data that will help develop beneficial societal products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The development of this e-infrastructure and data management Knowledge Hub represents an extraordinary opportunity to bring together international leaders in interoperability, standards development, and various aspects of governance to seek a synoptic world vision. This virtual institute will create opportunities for enhancing the career trajectories of a new generation of researchers in the U.S. and across the globe. The Knowledge Hub will expose US early-career scientists to interdisciplinary, multi-institutional activities focused on environmental data and cyberinfrastructure where they can benefit not only from the US participants but also their counterparts from 13 other countries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1650664</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>M. Lee</FirstName>
      <LastName>Allison</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lee.allison@azgs.az.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/16/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tinal@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1679</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5920</Code>
      <Text>ITALY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5936</Code>
      <Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8058</Code>
      <Text>Science Across Virtual Instits</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1679</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7313</Code>
      <Text>REGIONAL INST FOR GLOBAL CHANG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
