<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TCS Academic Leadership Graduate Certificate Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>246553</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chicago School of Professional Psychology will build upon its existing offerings to develop and deliver a specialized focus in Academic Leadership, designed to address the compelling need for women faculty in the STEM disciplines at HBCUs to acquire leadership skills. The program will serve three cohorts of 15 participants each, each of whom will receive a Graduate Certificate in Academic Leadership.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;With the focus of this project on women STEM faculty in Historically African-American Colleges and Universities, this project will contribute significantly to increasing gender diversity in the leadership ranks at these institutions. By supporting women of color in STEM fields in realizing their leadership potential, this program will help ensure that students and faculty in these disciplines will benefit from the skills, wisdom, breadth of experience and unique perspectives that such women will provide. The model designed for the TCSPP Academic Leadership Graduate Certificate Program has promise for broad dissemination across its eastcoast, midwest, and westcoast campuses and their wide professional networks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1651417</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Orlando</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taylor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>research@fielding.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fielding Graduate University</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931053814</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2027535020</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2020 De la Vina Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
