<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Workshop in Advancing Research on Plant Biotic Interactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>45000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne Sylvester</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An interdisciplinary and international group of researchers will convene on September 19-21, 2016 in Washington DC to identify key challenges in research related to plant health. The goal of the workshop is to identify areas for collaboration and synergy among US and UK scientists in research focused on the understanding of biotic interactions of plants with pathogens or pests, or with symbionts or other beneficial organisms that associate with plants, the so-called phytobiome. Approximately 40 scientists will convene in Washington DC to discuss research and technology frontiers to move the discipline forward and identify pathways for applied outcomes. The workshop participants aim to identify partnerships that can address new and emerging plant diseases on a global scale. The workshop will conclude with the preparation of a whitepaper, or roadmap, to be shared broadly and designed to guide collaborative interactions and research over the coming years. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The collaborative workshop is designed to identify gaps in understanding of the biology of plant interactions with various pests and pathogens, including insects, fungi, microbiomes and other plants. Participation will include a diverse group of researchers of all career stages and backgrounds to discuss bottlenecks in research progress and to identify synergies and collaborative efforts among US and UK scientists. A particular emphasis is placed on leveraging recent advances in plant genomics and bioinformatics and integrating this information with diverse disciplines such as biochemistry, structural and cell biology, physiology and epidemiology. A goal will be to increase the use of quantitative, theoretical and systems approaches that will permit translating insights about biotic interactions from basic research to practical outcomes. The workshop will establish a clear understanding of current plant health research landscape in UK and US and will identify of areas of strengths and future prospects for collaboration to solve together a global problem.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1651224</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Michelmore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rwmichelmore@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7577</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH RESOURCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9109</Code>
      <Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
