<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Strengthening Solar Photovoltaic Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199892</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Southern California has a high density of solar energy businesses that require a technologically skilled workforce. Santa Monica College and its industry partners are further developing and improving an existing Solar Photovoltaic Installation program created in response to industry need. Through a multifaceted project that includes program improvement as well as curriculum and educational materials development, this project is creating and implementing strategies to bridge the gap between employer demand for qualified workers and student ability to acquire the skills necessary to match employment opportunities in the field, including on the job training and math and science understanding. This project focuses on three inter-related strategies for addressing workforce demand, including 1) expanded outreach to include K-12 and community based training programs; 2) the development of contextualized math and science modules to strengthen the solar photovoltaic curriculum and improve student success; and 3) the development of an internship course to provide on the job training for students while connecting them with potential employers. Through these activities, the college is improving the regional capacity to address the workforce demands of the solar industry. The project aims to increase student enrollment in the program by targeting high school students and first time freshmen, women, veterans, and underrepresented minorities so the program enrollment more closely resembles the general student population. It plans to improve student completion rates in courses by improving their math and science skills and increase student aptitude to attain employment by engaging students in internship opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a minority serving institution located in a highly diverse region, this project is impacting a diverse array of students, including many low-income, ethnically diverse, first generation college students, and providing them the opportunity to pursue viable careers in a new and emerging field. Employers are being provided a steady stream of skilled applicants for job openings that have both the hands on training and a strong background in math and science necessary to address immediate employer needs and advance in their careers. The educational materials developed to support the degree program are being thoroughly assessed for effectiveness and disseminated throughout California and the nation to assist other regions as they prepare a qualified workforce for the solar energy industry. An extensive evaluation is also assessing the effectiveness of the new strategies designed to increase the number of students who enter the Solar Industry workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advanced technological education in solar energy is part of a career path that begins in middle school and high school, continues through community college, and provides opportunities beyond the community college setting. This project, both its needs and its responses, is based on extensive conversations with students, faculty, and industry advisors both locally and throughout the state regarding the barriers to success both in the classroom and in the workplace. Strategies, specifically the development of contextualized math and science education and field-based learning experiences, are research-based and have demonstrated success in other industries. With these program improvements, students who pursue coursework through the Solar Photovoltaic Installation Program are completing their studies with the skills and knowledge that they need to enter the workforce or continue their education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1400689</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Paik_Steve@smc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stuart</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cooley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Cooley_Stuart@smc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Santa Monica College</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Monica</CityName>
      <ZipCode>904051628</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3104343718</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1900 Pico Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
