<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Molecular Organization and Transport in Synthetic and Biological Nanopores</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>386071</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL NO.: 1403058&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR: Szleifer, Igal&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION NAME: Northwestern University&lt;br/&gt;TITLE: Molecular Organization and Transport in Synthetic and Biological Nanopores&lt;br/&gt;NSF RECEIVE DATE: 10/29/2013&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Biological and synthetic pores and channels of nanoscale dimensions display unique ionic and protein transport behavior. Nanopores&lt;br/&gt;modified with supramolecular chemical species (such as polyelectrolyte brushes) have dimensions that are similar to the range of the&lt;br/&gt;electrostatic interactions, and also to the molecular size of the tethered macromolecules. In cells, Nuclear Pore Complexes (NPC)&lt;br/&gt;control the transport of species between the cytoplasm and the nucleus using disordered proteins as gate keepers. The competition&lt;br/&gt;between molecular and interaction length scales, as well as the geometry of the surfaces, creates interesting possibilities for the&lt;br/&gt;creation of stimuli responsive gates and ion channels and for the fundamental understanding of the interplay between molecular&lt;br/&gt;organization, charge, proteins and nanoparticle transport in nanoconfined environments. The proposed work involves the development&lt;br/&gt;and application of theoretical approaches that capture the coupling between molecular organization, physical interactions and chemical&lt;br/&gt;equilibrium in order to describe the behavior of the nanopores. Most of the theoretical work will be based on an equilibrium and&lt;br/&gt;kinetic molecular theory that has been developed in the group of the PI. Furthermore, comparing the predictions of the molecular&lt;br/&gt;theory with detailed molecular dynamics simulations (when possible) will check the range of applicability of the theory. The proposed&lt;br/&gt;work is separated into two main thrusts: 1) Synthetic nanopores. Understanding how responsive polymers, bulk solution conditions&lt;br/&gt;and the geometry of the nanopore affect the structure and transport of nanoparticles, proteins and small ions through the nanopores.&lt;br/&gt;The types of responsive polymers include: weak polyelectrolytes, hydrophobic polymers and pH sensitive zwitterionic polymers. 2)&lt;br/&gt;Nuclear Pore Complex. Systematic studies of the role that intrinsic proteins forming the NPC as well as adsorbed proteins have on the&lt;br/&gt;ability of the pores to gate transport of proteins across the pore. The proposed work is of fundamental importance in the understanding&lt;br/&gt;of interfacial properties of responsible materials as well as transport. Moreover, the proposed work will provide guidelines for the&lt;br/&gt;design of nanoconfined soft materials with a wide range of applications in biosensing, charge or proteins separations, chromatography,&lt;br/&gt;drug delivery and microfluidics among others.&lt;br/&gt;The understanding of responsive soft materials in confined environments requires multidisciplinary expertise at the interface between&lt;br/&gt;materials science, engineering, physics, chemistry and biology. The proposed work has the dual purpose of: i) fundamental&lt;br/&gt;understanding of the coupling between molecular organization, physical interactions and chemical state in confined soft matter and ii)&lt;br/&gt;the outcomes of these studies will be used for the molecular design of responsive coatings that lead to desired transport behavior. The&lt;br/&gt;study of these complex systems requires the understanding of equilibrium and time dependent properties. The time dependent behavior&lt;br/&gt;spans over many orders of magnitude in time. The proposed work, thus, combines molecular dynamics simulations that are excellent&lt;br/&gt;for short time scales with time dependent molecular theory that enables the study of very long times maintaining a molecular level&lt;br/&gt;description of the mixtures. The continued collaboration with the experimental group of Prof. Omar Azzaroni (UNLP, Argentina) and&lt;br/&gt;the theoretical group of Prof. Yitzhak Rabin (Bar-Ilan, Israel) will provide the theoretical work with realistic checks at all stages of the&lt;br/&gt;work.&lt;br/&gt;The work proposed here will include educational research experiences for graduate and undergraduate students. The PI plans to attract&lt;br/&gt;women and underrepresented minorities for this project, as he has been successful to do it in the past. The PI will use the resources&lt;br/&gt;from the REU programs administered by Northwestern MRSEC and by the Chemistry of Life Processes Institute. The main finding&lt;br/&gt;from this research will be included in the undergraduate and graduate courses taught by the PI. The findings from the research will be&lt;br/&gt;published in peer-reviewed journals and will be posted on the PI's web site. The software developed from this project to apply the&lt;br/&gt;molecular theory to complex soft materials will be available for download from the PI's web site and will be aimed for the use by&lt;br/&gt;non-expert due to the multidisciplinary nature of the potential applications of the proposed work</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1403058</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Igal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Szleifer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>igalsz@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1414</Code>
      <Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>051E</Code>
      <Text>Interfacial trans &amp; thermodynamic</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
