<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Experiences for Teacher Advancement In Nanotechnology (RETAIN)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>494220</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a three year standard award to support a Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) in Engineering and Computer Science Site program at Indiana University-Purdue University Indianapolis entitled, "Research Experiences for Teacher Advancement In Nanotechnology) for Green Energy and Technology (RETAIN)", under the direction of Dr. Maher E. Rizkalla.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Establishing an RET site at IUPUI will provide pedagogical training and assistance to STEM teachers within the school districts that comprise metro Indianapolis. Participation will enhance teacher development through graduate course credits and infuse STEM curricula with inquiry-based methodology in order to generate STEM interest among students. More importantly, due to the multidisciplinary nature of nanotechnology, trained teachers will be equipped to integrate multiple STEM subjects into their curriculum providing students with subject-to-subject connectivity comparable to real-world collaborative expectations. This program complements IUPUI's undergraduate nanotechnology-track, funded through an NSF Nanotechnology Undergraduate Education (NUE) award, by investing in Indiana's K-12 community to ultimately produce graduates with interest and college-ready skills for success in nanotechnology-related degree programs. The proposed framework provides a portable model that can be implemented at other institutions and teaching modules that can be implemented on a national level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Integrated Nanosystems Development Institute (INDI) at IUPUI proposes to establish RETAIN an immersive research and training program in the multidisciplinary field of nanotechnology for a total of 30 (10 per year) Indiana high school teachers from high needs, metropolitan school districts, for six weeks during the summer. RETAIN will offer participants: 1) knowledge of topics and careers in nanotechnology; 2) hands-on laboratory experiences in inquiry-based science; 3) participant-designed teaching modules developed to meet existing state and national science standards; 4) connection to a professional network of teachers and scientists as well as on-site RETAIN support during module implementation; and 5) professional development and college credit programming. Annually, five refined teaching modules will be disseminated on the Hoosier Association of Science Teachers, I-STEM Network, and TeachEngineering websites. The two major goals of RETAIN are: 1) Train 30 high school teachers (from high-needs metropolitan school districts) in inquiry and discovery-based science from hypothesis development and experimental design to data collection and dissemination of results, while introducing STEM concepts, applications, and careers options. 2) Integrate RETAIN content into high school classrooms by translating research experiences into 15 (five per year) inquiry-based, nanotechnology teaching modules designed to boost excitement and student interest in the STEM disciplines and careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1406995</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jomo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mutegi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmutegi@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Likun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>likzhu@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mangilal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Agarwal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>agarwal@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rizkalla</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mrizkall@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hess</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hessjl@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feldhaus</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cfeldhau@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/13/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1359</Code>
      <Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>115E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1359</Code>
      <Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
