<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Undergraduate Summer School in Supersymmetry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14905</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victoria Powers</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PIMS Undergraduate Workshop in Supersymmetry will be held at the Pacific Institute for the Mathematical Sciences at the University of British Columbia, on May 25-31, 2014. In physics, supersymmetry is a pairing between bosons and fermions appearing in theories of subatomic particles. One may study supersymmetry mathematically by using adinkra symbols, which are graphs with vertices representing the particles in a supersymmetric theory and edges corresponding to the supersymmetry pairings. The workshop will combine lectures on the mathematics of supersymmetry, emphasizing graph theory and algebraic structures, with problem-solving sessions. Sylvester James Gates of the University of Maryland, recipient of the National Medal of Science, will be the keynote speaker. The workshop's website is https://people.uwec.edu/whitchua/supersymmetry/ &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will have direct impact on undergraduate education, by introducing students to a thriving area of research outside the standard curriculum. Students will gain tools to choose and evaluate a graduate program and valuable skills in using computer algebra systems for mathematical experimentation. The speakers and problem session leaders will build a community of mathematicians interested in undergraduate research in supersymmetry; they will use this experience to enhance the undergraduate research program at their home institutions. This award defrays travel costs for eleven US-based undergraduate students participating in the workshop.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1406636</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ursula</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whitcher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whitchua@uwec.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Eau Claire</Name>
      <CityName>Eau Claire</CityName>
      <ZipCode>547024004</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7158362637</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>105 Garfield Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
