<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Very High Energy Particle Astrophysics with VERITAS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>366220</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jean Cottam Allen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Universe is host to myriad sources that emit electromagnetic radiation at gamma-ray energies. These very high energy photons are produced in processes involving particles with energies beyond the reach of any ground-based accelerator. Gamma-ray observations can therefore be used to study the highest energy phenomena in the Universe. With this award, the University of Minnesota group will continue their work with the VERITAS gamma-ray observatory. The activities funded through this award will contribute to maintaining the VERITAS capabilities and sensitivity. This work will also contribute to the study of known blazars and the discoveries of new blazars, a class of Active Galactic Nuclei. The scientific goals are to study the astrophysical processes that generate gamma-ray emission in blazars and the links to the origin of observed ultra-high energy cosmic rays. The University of Minnesota group will mentor undergraduate students through the university's Research Experiences for Undergraduates program. Members of the group will continue to present VERITAS science at local astronomy clubs, high schools and other public outreach events such as the weekly public observing nights at the campus observatory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The major objectives and methods to be employed by the University of Minnesota group include: (1) development of improved analysis techniques including implementation of a multivariate analysis toolkit and a new effort in better spectral reconstruction; (2) scientific analysis on Active Galactic Nuclei utilizing new spectral analysis techniques with a focus on locating the source of gamma-ray emission in blazars and understanding the origin of ultra-high energy cosmic rays; (3) coordination of multi-wavelength data campaigns in conjunction with VERITAS including efforts with Fermi, IceCube and HAWC; and (4) calibration and data quality monitoring tasks that include improvements on understanding of the instrument energy scale through a detailed study on the impact of atmospheric conditions on the reconstructed energy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1407326</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lucy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fortson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fortson@physics.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1643</Code>
      <Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
