<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanoantenna Optomechanics: Forces, Devices, and Sensors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>366619</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The planned research is to investigate various novel photonic devices based on the radiation pressure created by localized electric fields for development of high sensitivity optical sensors.The approach involves an integrated investigation of thermal-optical-mechanical forces for the development of reconfigurable devices. The analytic and experimental details are adequately addressed and may lead to useful devices as well as new optical science. The proposed effort has strong educational components including collaborative research interactions for underrepresented minorities, high school students and undergrad students. The PI intends to integrate the planned research with student education of nanotechnology and photonics to students at all levels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is based on integration of metallic nanoparticles that act as optical nano-antennae with micro-electro-mechanical systems for unique device functionality for sensing applications. The approach is to employ the plasmonic resonances in these nano-antennae arising from the oscillations of the conduction electrons in metals for making micromechanical resonators optically responsive at the desired wavelength range independent of the optical transparency of constituent mechanical resonator materials. This platform will enable the study of interaction between light and mechanical resonators through optically induced forces as well as the investigation of mechanically tunable optoelectronic devices. If successful, the proposed research could have a transformative impact on unique opto-electro-mechanical sensors with sensitivities far exceeding present-day technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1408139</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ertugrul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cubukcu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ecubukcu@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/13/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>094E</Code>
      <Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
