<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanoparticles with Stainless Interfaces: Void Symmetry Control and New Compositions for Applications in Energy Transfer Storage and Biotechnology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diana Farkas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is expected to overcome a number of challenges encountered by researchers synthesizing metal alloy nanostructures. Using a core/alloy approach, nanoparticles in the size range of 5 to 50 nm will be synthesized with stainless interfaces that are made up of iron, chromium, nickel, aluminum and titanium compositions. These nanomaterial alloys are expected to have unique phase behavior, oxidation properties, and void/defect morphologies. The ultimate goals of this project are to; develop new "wet-chemical" synthesis strategies to prepare the nanomaterials, to understand the resulting oxidation and phase behavior, and to control that behavior in order to construct novel structures that have utility in energy and biotechnology sectors. A postdoctoral fellow and multiple graduate and undergraduate chemistry students will be supported. The fellow will gain valuable professional development, and along with the students, will gain valuable experience and training in cutting edge nanomaterial science, materials chemistry and associated instrumental techniques. The PI will promote minority student involvement in the project, and continue his work in guiding women to professional STEM careers. The work will have a profound affect on the materials chemistry and nanoscience communities in the upstate Syracuse New York region through outreach events, enhancements to undergraduate and graduate course work and via hosting a regional workshop on nanoscience that brings together researchers with similar interests from the region. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project explores the hypothesis that alloy composition, phase behavior, and oxidation characteristics can be use to control the internal microstructure of nanomaterials. Over the years researchers have mastered the synthesis required for size and shape control of many nanostructures, and today focus is shifting towards being able to process the internal structure of these materials with great precision. To accomplish this goal, we will prepare new nano-alloy interfaces with stainless steel like compositions that will be used as a chemical tool to control interfacial oxidation rates, which in turn will alter Kirkendall diffusion of defects and vacancies. This will allow for the preparation of nanoparticles with morphologically defined void spaces, including asymmetric ones, which can be controlled with 1-5 nm fidelity. The goals of this project are to fabricate new non-noble metal nano alloys, to use alloy composition, phase behavior, and oxidation properties to manipulate the internal void structure, and to combine these technologies to tailor internal void symmetry and hierarchy. Moreover, through the course of the project, a number of novel nano-alloy interfaces will be attempted, including titanium and aluminum based medical and super-alloys. These new nanomaterials will have immediate applications ranging from the energy to biotechnology sectors, including; gas storage, heterogeneous catalysis and battery technologies, as well as medical alloy surfaces and coatings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1410569</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mathew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maye</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmmaye@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1771</Code>
      <Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
