<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SusChEM: Strained Core/Shell Nanoparticles with Non-precious Metal Core and Precious Metal Shell</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diana Farkas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Summary &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a novel type of nanoparticle composed of an abundant non-precious metal core and a precious metal shell. Novel approaches will be will be developed to prepare these nano- particles, and a combination of state of the art methods will be used to characterize them. The project will also contribute fundamental understanding of the properties of these structures and contribute to predicting the performance of these particles for catalysis applications. The ultimate goal of this research is to decrease the use of critical precious metals materials by novel design and fabrication of materials at the nanoscale. Considering the growing need for precious metal catalysts and their high cost and limited availability, this project will have great significance for the economy and for environmental sustainability. These novel materials will significantly reduce the use of scarce precious metals for these applications. The project also includes broad outreach to K-12 schools in the Baltimore area. Underrepresented students will be exposed to and engaged in the research frontiers of materials and energy research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a novel type of core/shell nanoparticles composed of a non-precious metal (core and a precious metal shell). A novel synthetic approach will be developed to prepare these composite nanostructures, and a combination of microscopic and spectroscopic methods will be used to characterize these materials. Insights into the structure-property relationship of strained surfaces&lt;br/&gt;and fundamental understanding of the impact of strain on heterogeneous catalytic processes will be developed, and this understanding will be further demonstrated to be capable of predicting the catalytic performance of strained core/shell catalysts for given chemical reactions. The ultimate goal of this research is to improve the using efficiency of rare and critical materials by novel design and fabrication of material architecture at the nanoscale. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The various NPM/PM core/shell nanoparticles developed in this project will have broad applications in chemical industry, manufacturing, and renewable energy technologies. The replacement of precious metals in the core by low-cost non-precious metals will not only substantially reduce the cost of precious metal catalysts, but also enhance the catalytic performance by finely tuning the surface properties through the strain effect. Considering the growing need for precious metal catalysts and their high cost and limited&lt;br/&gt;availability, the development of NPM/PM core/shell catalysts in this project will have great significance for the economy and for environmental sustainability. This research will also advance our fundamental understanding of strained nanostructures and in particular, the strain effect in heterogeneous catalysis. The combination of experimental and theoretical studies represents a persuasive approach&lt;br/&gt;towards rational design and synthesis of advanced functional nanomaterials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will also serve as a platform for graduate, undergraduate and high-school students to develop interests, and more important, participate in cutting-edge scientific research. High school students will be recruited to work on nanomaterial synthesis, characterization and catalytic studies at JHU, and be inspired to continue their studies in related areas in colleges or universities. Undergraduates participating in this project will be introduced to the creative and intuitive nature of scientific research, and encouraged to develop careers in science or engineering. Through the outreach programs at JHU's Center for Educational Outreach to K-12 schools in the Baltimore area, underrepresented students will be exposed to and engaged in the research frontiers of materials and energy research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1410175</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chaowang@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1712</Code>
      <Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1771</Code>
      <Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8248</Code>
      <Text>SusChEM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
