<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A STRATEGY TO OPTIMIZE THE U.S. OPTICAL/INFRARED SYSTEM IN THE ERA OF THE LARGE SYNOPTIC SURVEY TELESCOPE</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249088</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vernon Pankonin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Committee on Astronomy and Astrophysics (CAA) of the National Academy of Sciences will carry out a study for A Strategy to Optimize the U.S. Optical/Infrared System in the Era of The Large Synoptic Survey Telescope. Driven by discoveries, and enabled by leaps in technology and imagination, our understanding of the Universe has changed dramatically over the course of the last few decades. The fields of astronomy and astrophysics are making new connections to physics, chemistry, biology, and computer science. Realizing these scientific opportunities is contingent upon maintaining and strengthening the foundations of the research enterprise. Using the recent survey of astronomy and astrophysics, New Worlds, New Horizons in Astronomy and Astrophysics, and the NSF's Portfolio Review report, this study by a CAA committee will provide conclusions and recommendations to NSF which will help NSF achieve the best science for the investment in optical/infrared (OIR) resources and move the field forward.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The OIR system study committee will have a broad impact by acting as an established forum to bring together leading researchers from the scientific community and representatives from across the federal government to discuss research needs and issues relevant to the U.S. OIR system. The committee will engage the broad astronomy and astrophysics community through its work whereby members of the research community can share their expertise with the rest of the committee and with the public. These discussions can lead to new collaborations and insights into neighboring activities. By identifying cross-cutting issues and opportunities, the committee can enhance the research and education environment. The activities undertaken by the study committee will be disseminated broadly through distribution of reports, frequent updates to the committee's website, and at professional society meetings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1411382</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlancaster@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1798</Code>
      <Text></Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
