<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Implementation of High-Strength Materials in Structural Engineering Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Recents advancements now enable high-strength materials (HSM) to be used in structures. HSMs provide the option for equivalent column/beam strength while reducing the dimensions of the member. Reinforced concrete structures are widely used in many residential buildings and bridges throughout the world with the need for high-strength concrete (HSC) towards the base of high-rise buildings due to the large load from upper levels. A challenge associated with HSM is the brittle failure mode resulting in poor seismic performance. Although research on HSM is prevalent, there has been limited research on its seismic performance. Conducting this project in Taiwan provides the opportunity to use of the unique National Center for Research on Earthquake Engineering (NCREE) Laboratory in Taipei. Full-scale experimental tests of columns for building structures using HSM will be performed in the large lab under the supervision of Dr. Shyh-Jiann Hwang. This research will help determine if standard practice using normal-strength concrete will transition to high-strength concrete successfully. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Upon completion of the full-scale experimental tests, the results will be compared with similar tests using normal strength materials to understand the differences in mechanics of HSM columns under various loading patterns. A parametric study will be performed via analytical models to further knowledge and understanding. After results from experimental and numerical results are processed, these results will be used to determine refinements to the column design details. Possible refinements may include changes in reinforcement details for varying the confinement. Once the necessary refinements are determined, a final set of HSM column details will be generated and can be used to determine a detailed design code for HSM. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the National Science Council of Taiwan (Taiwan).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414981</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brett</FirstName>
      <LastName>Allen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/30/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Allen Brett M</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895122282</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5924</Code>
      <Text>TAIWAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
