<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Investigating the effectiveness of intergroup apologies on reducing negative intergroup attitudes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Negative acts committed by individuals from other nations, such as the tragic school shoot at Virginia Tech in 2007, often engender increased hostile and negative evaluations towards people from that nation. To mitigate these negative reactions, countries may issue an apology on behalf of the nation for the acts committed by their citizens. These apologies are defined as intergroup apologies, that is, apologies between two groups of individuals. The proposed project will investigate the role of intergroup apologies on ameliorating relationships and attitudes between groups. In addition, this study will advance our understanding of how cultural differences in group entitativity, that is, how strongly groups are viewed as cohesive, affect perceptions of intergroup apologies. This study will be conducted under the hypothesis that higher group entitativity will incite more of a need for group apologies as well as greater expectation for an apology, subsequently leading to more negative evaluations if no apology is given. This study will be carried out at Chungbuk National University in South Korea in collaboration with Dr. Sanghee Park. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participants from United States and South Korea will be recruited. This study will employ a 2 (United States or South Korea) x 2 (Apology or No-Apology) factorial design with dependent measures being scale items on outgroup attitudes and an Implicit Associations Test (IAT). Participants will be presented with a scenario depicting a negative intergroup event and then be randomly assigned to an apology or no apology condition. Following the apology, questionnaires will be given to assess perceptions of the apology, group entitativity, and outgroup attitudes. In addition, implicit negative associations towards South Koreans and Americans with the IAT will be assessed. Results from the IAT and explicit attitude measures will afford a test of whether apologies reduced negative intergroup attitudes. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the National Research Foundation of Korea.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414609</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Alt Nicholas</Name>
      <CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>231858795</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5942</Code>
      <Text>KOREA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
