<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Determining host seeking through olfaction in the nematode Parastrongyloides trichosuri</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Parasitic nematodes of humans, animals, and plants are major sources of economic loss and health-related hardship. The impact on human health alone is staggering. Current estimates suggest that nearly 1 billion people globally harbor a parasitic nematode infection. Despite their prevalence, our understanding of how parasitic nematodes find and infect their appropriate biological hosts remains poorly characterized. Olfaction is widely thought to be an important aspect of host seeking, since it is the sensory modality most likely to confer species-specificity. This project will elucidate the extent to which parasitic nematodes rely on host-emitted odors to find and infect a host. This research will be conducted at La Trobe University in Melbourne, Australia in collaboration with Dr. Warwick Grant, a global leader on nematode genetics. Dr. Grant also has unparalleled expertise with a unique parasitic nematode, Parastrongyloides trichosuri, whose native hosts are Australian possums. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research efforts in parasitic nematodes have been hampered by an inability to develop genetically tractable model species. The goal of this project is to develop Parastrongyloides trichosuri, a parasitic nematode of the Australian possum, as a model for odor-driven host seeking and the genetic analysis of olfactory neural circuits. Among parasitic nematodes, P. trichosuri is uniquely amenable to in vitro culturing, genetic manipulation, and transgenesis. This project will focus on conducting quantitative behavioral analysis, laser and genetic ablation analysis, and calcium imaging of P. trichosuri. The project aims to gain insight into the cellular and molecular mechanisms by which parasitic nematodes locate hosts to infect. By determining the host-specific odors that promote host seeking, and the underlying neural basis for the behavior, this study will facilitate development of new strategies to combat nematode infection. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Australian Academy of Science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414655</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Spencer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gang Spencer</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900247234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
