<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Cultural and age differences in the utilization of conflicting contextual cues in emotion perception</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Understanding how individuals perceive emotions through facial expressions can provide insight into how humans interact socially and form relationships. Successful emotion perception requires attention to both the emotion expressed on the face, and the context in which that emotion occurs. In daily life, people have access to multiple sources of contextual information. However, these various sources of contextual information may diverge. How the perceiver resolves these disagreements between context sources may be shaped by their life experiences, cognitive abilities, and culturally-specific way of thinking. The current research thus investigates how individuals in different age groups from various cultures use conflicting contextual information to identify emotional expressions in others. This research will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Sakiko Yoshikawa, a noted expert on emotion perception research, at the Kokoro Institute in Kyoto, Japan. Japan has the highest population of elderly, and the institute's expertise in aging research will greatly benefit this project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Emotion perception is affected by not only situational cues, but also knowledge about an individual's trait. Trait information can influence perception in a top-down manner, whereas visual attention to context, especially in older adults, has been found to be stimulus-driven. This effect might also be moderated by cultural differences in holistic and analytical cognition. This study will be the first to explore the effect of aging and culture on the integration of competing sources of contextual cues on emotion perception. Behavioral data from younger and older adults will be collected in both Japan and the U.S, and analyzed with mixed design analysis of variance. The topic of this project lies in the intersection of cognitive, affective, and gerontological sciences, and results will simultaneously advance knowledge in all these fields. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414649</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nhi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ngo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ngo Nhi</Name>
      <CityName>Boston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
