<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Evaluating the Interactions Among Species Selected for Assisted Colonization as a New Conservation Strategy for Chinese Orchids</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The moving of species beyond their natural ranges in response to a changing climate, also known as "assisted colonization", is a newly-emerged and controversial conservation measure. As a rare example of such an effort, dozens of species of wild orchids in southwestern China were moved to higher elevation sites in anticipation of the completion of the Longtan reservoir near the Yachang National Orchid Reserve in Guangxi Province. One important factor to consider when undertaking such actions is to understand the interaction of the moved species with other species in their new ranges. This project will examine the beneficial fungi associated with the roots of selected orchid species in both the current and new ranges. This project will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Gao Jiangyun, orchid ecologist and faculty at the Xishuangbanna Tropical Botanical Garden (XTBG) of the Chinese Academy of Sciences. The results will not only provide valuable insights into this debatable conservation strategy but will help promote research and science-based conservation of Chinese orchids.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under the context of climate change, understanding how range expansions can influence biotic relationships becomes more urgent since global changes may have the most impact on taxa that are heavily dependent on other taxa. Mycorrhizal fungi and plant interactions are among the most important of these vulnerable relationships. Using modern microbiological and DNA sequencing techniques, this project will identify the mycorrhiza associated with orchids that are part of the ongoing assisted colonization experiments at Yachang Reserve. After isolating and identifying the fungi in the root tissues, substrate samples will be collected to determine the distribution and abundance of compatible fungi in both the donor and recipient sites. The results of this project will be used to develop better protocols for this long-term project and will provide a critical evaluation on the role of biotic factors in the success of assisted colonization's. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414633</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
      <LastName>Downing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/02/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Downing Jason L</Name>
      <CityName>Miami Beach</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331397715</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
