<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Validation of Three-Dimensional Endoscopy System with Synthetic Vocal Fold Models</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Voice disorders affect many people in the United States but effective clinical treatment is limited by knowledge of the physics of voice production proper diagnosis and by challenges in diagnosis. Laryngoscopy, use of a specially designed endoscope to examine the vocal folds, is an important technique for vocal fold visualization in both clinical and research settings. However, the technique is limited to providing information regarding movement in two dimensions when the motion of vocal folds has been shown to be three-dimensional. Dr. Isao Tokuda at the Ritsumeikan University in Japan has developed a method for reconstructing three-dimensional vocal fold motion using a laryngoscope with two cameras, but the technique has not yet been extensively validated. In collaboration with Dr. Tokuda, this project will use synthetic vocal fold models, recently used in voice biomechanics research, to validate the stereo-endoscopy system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Synthetic vocal fold models have recently been used in voice biomechanics research and will be used in the proposed project because they offer more control, are more robust, and are easier to acquire than excised animal models. Multiple cameras and common computer vision techniques will be used to validate the stereo-endoscopy system by recording and reconstructing the vibrating surface of synthetic, self-oscillating vocal fold models with both the stereo-endoscopy and high speed systems and comparing the results. The validation of the stereo-endoscopy system will allow its use in clinical settings as well as for quantitative analysis of vocal fold motion, leading to improved understanding of the dynamics involved in phonation. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1414741</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stevens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/30/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stevens Kimberly</Name>
      <CityName>Provo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>846063368</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
