<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Improving the performance of extreme high frequency, radio amplifiers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With the rising demand placed by consumers upon computing technology in the form of massive volumes of video and multimedia information, the limitations placed upon communication systems within computers themselves has become a rising concern. As features of computing circuits become smaller, the speed of these systems becomes a greater problem for designers. Thus, while consumers want faster and smaller devices, making smaller devices may also impede the ability to make them faster. To alleviate some of these problems caused by miniaturization, wireless-networks-on-chip (WiNoC) have been proposed to remove long wires in devices and replace them with wireless transmitters. Currently, key performance of such systems is limited by the final amplifier used in the radios transmitter. This project will research the implementation of a Doherty amplifier, designed to dramatically improve the performance of all components in a WiNoC system. This research will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Youngoo Yang at Sungkyunkwan University in Korea. Dr. Yang is an expert in the design of high power, moderate frequency, Doherty amplifiers, and will provide invaluable insight and design assistance into the extension of design into higher frequencies, at lower power.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will push beyond current designs placed at multi-watt power output for cellular applications in the vicinity of 3GHz, towards lower power implementations in 65nm CMOS, targeted for use at and beyond 60GHz. The high linearity and efficiency of the Doherty amplifier will allow for the adoption of more sophisticated modulation schemes in WiNoC systems, reducing bandwidth, power consumption, and signal strength requirements. Performance of the amplifier will be analyzed through the use of the CAD tools Cadence, and electromagnetic simulations of on-chip passives through Ansys HFSS. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with National Research Foundation of Korea.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1415106</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luke</FirstName>
      <LastName>Renaud</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Renaud Luke P</Name>
      <CityName>Pullman</CityName>
      <ZipCode>991635095</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5942</Code>
      <Text>KOREA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
