<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Upgrade of community-orientated ICP-MS facilities for teaching and research at the University of Michigan</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>534820</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will provide funds to replace the 12 year old, collectively-owned, community-based High Resolution Inductively Coupled Plasma Mass Spectrometer (HR-ICP-MS). Updating the ICP-MS facilities at the University of Michigan will provide both traditional and novel tools to understanding surface geology, marine systems, environmental science, regional climate and subglacial processes, and will be a significant infrastructure improvement to the Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences. Continued infrastructure support to the University of Michigan will also be a resource to other local universities in the SE Michigan region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research projects supported by the updating and retooling of HR-ICP-MS capabilities include: trace element geochemistry of marine sediments and carbonate archives to determine past environments and anthropogenic influence including proxy records of droughts, floods, ocean-atmosphere dynamics and sea surface temperature; trace and REE geochemistry of terrestrial sediments, paleosols and ancient sedimentary units, to reconstruct paleo-redox, ancient atmospheric CO2, and basin environments; major and trace element concentrations to elucidate factors controlling spatial and temporal variations in chemical fluxes from glaciated terrains; radioactive heavy isotope concentrations to accurately determine the age of the deepest ice within ice sheets; radioactive isotope concentrations by isotope dilution, as part of the U-Th/He thermochronology method used to study young tectonic histories and climate-tectonic interactions; the geochemistry of biological material from fossils to proteins; and the biogeochemistry of trace metals, including the release, transport and bioaccumulation of metals within the environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1415543</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdblum@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ingrid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hendy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ihendy@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marinkc@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sheldon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsheldon@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aciego</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aciego@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
