<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Center for Accelerator Science and Education at Stony Brook University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>700000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vyacheslav S. Lukin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports advanced accelerator physics research and education program at the existing Stony Brook Center for Accelerator Science and Education (CASE) at Stony Brook University (SBU). It draws on CASEs ability to pursue cutting-edge, forward-looking explorations in accelerator physics to study the physics of advanced cooling for circular high-energy hadron and lepton colliders.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;This research is focused on developing the groundbreaking concept of Enhanced electron Cooling (EeC), a novel stochastic cooling techniques with bandwidth of ~(10)^17 Hz capable of cooling TeV-scale hadron and muon beams. The availability of such cooling technique would have a major impact on the discovery potential of future high-energy colliders. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;The success of this research will entail transformational advances in various branches of science, affording broad benefits to society. Cooling techniques would significantly impact both nuclear and particle physics through the enhanced capabilities of existing and future colliders. The process of enhanced bunching could bring about a new generation of compact but intense sources of incoherent radiation. Two students and one postdoc involved in the program will be immersed in an atmosphere of cutting-edge accelerator research and development. The group will work towards broadening the educational, outreach, and diversity programs at SBU and CASE.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1415252</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hemmick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hemmick@skipper.physics.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grannis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grannis@sbhep.physics.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Litvinenko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vladimir.litvinenko@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7243</Code>
      <Text>Accelerator Science</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
