<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>School for the Study of Earthquakes: nucleation, triggering, and relationships with aseismic processes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Luciana Astiz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests funds to help support a number of U.S. graduate students, and postdocs to attend the School of "Study of Earthquakes: nucleation, triggering, and relationships with aseismic processes" to be held at the Institut d'Etudes Scientifiques de Cargese in France, from November 3 to November 10, 2014. The conference website can be found at http://isterre.fr/annuaire/pages-web-du-personnel/david-marsan/article/cargese-earthquakes-2014?lang=fr&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This school aims to provide an intimate venue for a focused review of the current understanding of earthquake related processes in light of the recent advances in quality and quantity of data sets and in computational capabilities. The goal of the workshop is to bring together the leading experts in earthquake processes from around the world, and to provide back-to-back lectures with contrasting views on several of these processes in order to stimulate a broader discussion, to explore new datasets and ideas, to produce a much wider understanding of the issues, and ultimately build consensus thus improving earthquake preparedness and forecasting. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funds are requested to support living expenses during the school for 14 U.S. students and post-docs. The proposed funding will contribute to the development of the emerging earthquake seismologists by providing them with the opportunity to meet and interact with leading national and international researchers, gaining deeper understanding and broader perspective of the issues related to earthquake related processes, and forming the basis for future collaborations. All participants receiving support are required to bring a poster and prepare a short presentation. The US organizing committee will leverage over existing programs within the USGS, the American Geophysical Union, and the American Geoscience Institute in order to promote participations of underrepresented groups. Earthquake science questions to be discussed at this meeting have significant societal and economic implications, because of their implications for earthquake hazards.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1419886</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jean-Philippe</FirstName>
      <LastName>Avouac</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>avouac@gps.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1576</Code>
      <Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
