<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Reconstructing Prey Mobility Through Trace Element Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14934</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>For over two million years humans and their immediate ancestors lived as hunters and gatherers and basic elements characteristic of all human societies developed in this context. Understanding subsistence practices and the social organizations they fostered provides a valuable backdrop against which present day social practices may fruitfully be viewed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under the guidance of Dr. Leland Bement from the University of Oklahoma Ph.D Candidate Kristen Carlson will analyze the extent to which Paleoindian bison hunters focused on migratory herds as opposed to resident herds in large-scale bison hunting in North America. The Paleoindian time period of interest ranges from 10,800 to 9,000 years before present. Large-scale kill events conducted by hunters without the aid of horses or guns began during this time and continued until European colonization of North America. Large-scale bison kills enabled the procurement of multiple animals (at times over 30 individuals) in a single event. Large-scale bison hunting was an effective means of procuring resources for thousands of years and much remains to be discovered concerning the early methods of hunting large numbers of bison. This research focuses on the relationship between the hunters and their prey. The evidence required for the successful completion of this project will be obtained through new techniques in trace element analysis of bison teeth from three northern Plains bison kill sites and three southern Plains site. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this study is to test the 3rd molar or 4th premolar of bison found in kill sites in order to determine the range territory of the bison hunted. LA-ICP-MS is a high precision microscopic sampling technique that allows minimally destructive sampling at the microscopic level. Through this sampling an elemental signature is obtained informing specific time intervals in the animals life and representing the various places on the landscape visited by the bison. This cutting edge technique will provide information on bison migration patterns from 10,000 years ago. These data can then be integrated with what is known of archaeological sites to better understand the methods used by Paleoindian hunters and how they interacted with their social organization. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The examination of migration and movement patterns of prey species can further inform our understanding of prehistoric ways of life. Trace element analysis is used in biological settings as well, providing an opportunity for collaborative work between archaeologists and biologists. This project will also lead to the dissemination of information through scholarly works. In addition to the dissertation that will be completed with this data, refereed articles, and conference presentations will result. All findings will be published and made publically available. In addition to academic presentations, the University of Oklahoma promotes the education of the community through outreach programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1419245</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kristen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carlson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>K.Carlson@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leland</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bement</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Lbement@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
      <CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
