<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: 2014 Intrinsically Disordered Proteins Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar to be held on July 5-6, 2014 in Stonehill College Easton, MA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2014 Gordon Research Conference on IDPs will expand our knowledge of the structure, dynamics, and function of IDPs, will provide insights into the diverse biological processes that involve IDPs, and will drive new discoveries on the molecular mechanisms of IDPs in cell biology, and will provide a unique opportunity for the training of graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and early career investigators. There are a number of important challenges that must be met before we can develop a general picture of the dynamic structure, function, and evolution of IDPs/IDRs. Major challenges include developing new experimental and computational approaches to characterize structure and dynamics of IDPs/IDRs, understanding the expression patterns, molecular networks, and evolution of IDPs/IDRs and identifying fundamental principles of molecular recognition, regulation, folding, allostery, and mutational robustness for IDPs/IDRs. Speakers for the IDP GRC are directly addressing these challenges and making important contributions to developing solutions that will enhance our understanding of IDP structure, dynamics, function, and evolution. Addressing these challenges will have a profound impact on our understanding of (a) how IDPs/IDRs contribute to cellular function (b) how mutations in such regions can cause disease, and (c) how the distinct physico-chemical properties of IDPs/IDRs can be exploited for applications in various fields such as nanotechnology, material sciences and biotechnology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to advancing scientific knowledge in Molecular Biology, Structural Biology, Evolutionary Biology, Bioinformatics, Genetics, and Biophysics, the 2014 IDP GRC will provide a unique opportunity for the training of graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and early career investigators. For the first time in the meeting series, a Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) will precede the main conference. The IDP GRS is designed to further facilitate the participation of graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and early career investigators. Planned by and for the trainees, it will provide an opportunity for junior researchers to present seminars and posters in a supportive, interactive environment. It will act as an important springboard for the development of the future leaders in the field. The meeting will feature approximately 10 talks and 2 poster sessions. All attendees are expected to actively participate in the GRS either by giving an oral presentation or presenting a poster. The focus of the IDP GRS is to introduce the topic of IDPs to those just entering the field while motivating interest in key areas of IDP research. Topics covered will include: (i) what characteristics define an IDP, (ii) what experimental and computational tools can be used to study IDPs, and (iii) what roles IDPs play in vivo. The GRS will also include a career development session featuring a panel of scientists at different points in their career path who will offer career advice and answer questions on the academic job search from a variety of perspectives. Every effort has been made to include women and members of underrepresented groups in the conference. The goal is to have attendance in this area in the range of 25-30%, which is the percentage of women and members of underrepresented groups that are members of the IDP subgroup at the Biophysical Society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1421003</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Daughdrill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gdaughdrill@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
