<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SHF: Small: Cooperative Memory Expansion (COMEX) for Networked Computing Systems via Remote Direct Memory Access</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>476000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tao Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Legacy and emerging applications with large working sets and, when executed on commodity servers, &lt;br/&gt;may exhibit poor performance due to frequent page faults which rely on the slow disk swap partition. &lt;br/&gt;This research aims to establish immense memory collectively across nodes of a networked computing system for holding pages &lt;br/&gt;evicted from the main memory of any participating nodes during application runs with large working sets, &lt;br/&gt;realizing cooperative memory expansion (COMEX). It has a great promise to advance technical understanding &lt;br/&gt;and scientific frontiers of networked computing systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Given its wide adoption by operating systems and networking gear vendors nowadays, &lt;br/&gt;the remote direct memory access (RDMA) technology is adopted by COMEX for ultra-low latencies in page transfer &lt;br/&gt;between nodes whose OS kernel and CPU can be totally bypassed. &lt;br/&gt;This project deals with five technical challenges and the solution approaches to those challenges together &lt;br/&gt;will constitute the basis of the COMEX Handler, able to enhance execution performance and system throughput &lt;br/&gt;via better utilizing overall system DRAM memory on-demand. &lt;br/&gt;The project will also improve the research and educational activities on computer systems and distributed computing &lt;br/&gt;on the University of Louisiana at Lafayette campus, with its outcomes helping to integrate research and education for enriched teaching, &lt;br/&gt;training, and learning experience and to educate quality future workforce critical to the NSF mission, the state of Louisiana and the nation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1423302</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nian-Feng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tzeng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tzeng@louisiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Louisiana at Lafayette</Name>
      <CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>705032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3374826203</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 University Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7941</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
