<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Project: Enriching Security Curricula and Enhancing Awareness of Security in Computer Science and Beyond</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>146078</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is building our nation's capacity to develop a workforce well trained in computer security. Faculty from the University of Houston, University of Houston-Downtown and Texas Southern University, are developing interactive courseware and conducting workshops on the latest machine learning, data mining, natural language processing and statistics techniques as applied to computer security. Courseware on security-critical domains such as wireless sensor networks, and on key societal privacy and security concerns is also being developed. Workshops are being organized to cross-fertilize security curricula with related fields and topics and to develop a broad-based consensus on courseware contents. In addition to interactive courseware for security courses, materials are being developed to infuse security topics and increase awareness of information assurance in the broader computer science curriculum and, beyond computer science, in other STEM disciplines. A hypertextbook integrating the courseware is being implemented.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through faculty workshops, a community of information assurance education and research scholars is being created. This community will build bridges between information assurance professionals and professionals in related fields. The workshops are training diverse groups of faculty from different types of institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Courseware and other results are available in the National Science Digital Library as well as at a project-specific web site which also links to exemplary courseware developed elsewhere. Courseware and workshops are being rigorously evaluated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1423915</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ping.chen@umb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Boston</Name>
      <CityName>Dorchester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021253300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172875370</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 Morrissey Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
