<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NRI: Co-Robots to Engage Next Generation of Students in STEM Learning</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>359652</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Haury</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Robotic technologies are increasingly present in work spaces and homes. Maintaining investment in robotics research and education is vital to the 21st century US economy. Robotic technologies have the potential to transform not only the workplace and home, but also the classroom. This project by Michigan Technological University will introduce the use of two co-robots, robots that work cooperatively with people, as teaching tools. GUPPIE is an unmanned underwater glider that can monitor and inspect the environment and will be used to introduce students to the idea of robots as co-explorers in everyday life. Neu-pulator uses the electrical signals from a person's muscle to control its movement; without this human interaction it cannot operate. Neu-pulator will expose students to robotic assistive technologies that can enhance the capability of human beings, increase their mobility, and improve their general well-being. Both co-robots are low cost and their use is applicable in educational settings ranging from the 4th grade through graduate school. Use of both co-robots will be integrated into hands-on classroom and summer program activities for middle school students. These activities will also incorporate the concepts relevant to state standards for the middle school curriculum. The co-robot platforms are expected to utilize both right and left side thinking for students, encourage social interactions with team partners, and make explicit connections between engineering core concepts and the skills needed to solve today's most pressing problems. The project will investigate the hypothesis that application-based co-robotic activities will be of greater interest to some girls than the more prevalent mission-based robotics competition activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Next Generation Science Standards for Today's Students and Tomorrow's Workforce provides a curricular framework for using crosscutting concepts and disciplinary ideas in the classroom. The overall goal of this project is to develop and evaluate the use of two co-robotic platforms in learning contexts that are socially meaningful to students. Middle school students, particularly underrepresented students (female students from rural, low socioeconomic areas) will be the focus of this work. The specific objectives are to: 1) Optimize co-robotic platform designs for teaching STEM concepts, 2) Develop educational activities/curriculum utilizing co-robotic platforms, and 3) Investigate the co-robotic platforms effectiveness in engaging students in STEM learning. Taking advantage of 3D printing to make the parts for the robots will expand the range of possible designs that students can develop and reduce the amount of time necessary to do so. Hands-on activities using the co-robots in class, after school, or through summer programs will integrate science and engineering standards with core teaching concepts in the middle school curriculum. The dissemination of training modules and effective practices online will make the platforms accessible nationwide.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Evaluation will investigate the hypothesis that the interest and creativity of some girls will show greater increases with application-based co-robotic activities than with mission-based robotics competitions. Researchers will assess the complexity and creativity of student designs. The project will also review student work products from each robotics activity to assess student achievement of relevant standards.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1426989</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michele</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mhmiller@campbell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rastgaar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rastgaar@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mahmoudian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ninam@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
      <CityName>Houghton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7227</Code>
      <Text>ITEST</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8086</Code>
      <Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
