<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-China-Germany Planning Visits: Direct and Inverse Scattering Methods for Periodic Structures with Arbitrary Profiles and Defects</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36745</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lara Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Direct and Inverse Scattering Methods for Periodic Structures with Arbitrary Profiles and Defects&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Periodic structures have many applications, such as solar energy, semiconductors, photonic crystals, &lt;br/&gt;medical imaging, and diffraction gratings. In solar energy, the solar thermal collectors are periodic arrays.&lt;br/&gt;The surface of a diffraction grating is made up with a periodic array of grooves. Optical waveguides have &lt;br/&gt;many cells of the same structure. The main subject of the proposed international collaboration is to develop &lt;br/&gt;fast and rigorous numerical simulations and inverse scattering techniques for periodic structures with &lt;br/&gt;arbitrary profiles and defects. The research is important to the analysis, design, and optimization of periodic &lt;br/&gt;structures and has been an active area for many mathematicians, scientists and engineers. &lt;br/&gt;The proposed research activities will lead to important progress for computational methods and mathematical &lt;br/&gt;theory for direct and inverse scattering problems for periodic structures with arbitrary profiles and imbedded &lt;br/&gt;defects. The research outcome will provide physicists and engineers useful tools to treat practical problems&lt;br/&gt;such as effect of incidence angle and the shadowing phenomenon of diffraction gratings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first goal of the proposed research is to develop efficient and accurate numerical methods for wave propagation in periodic structures and bi-periodic structures with local defects. Due to the induced perturbed part of the scattered field by the defects, &lt;br/&gt;classic methods, such as the differential method, do not work in general. Based on the Limiting Absorption Principle, &lt;br/&gt;i.e., the solution for the periodic structure without absorption is the unique limit of the solutions as the absorption &lt;br/&gt;parameter tends to zero, the PI and his collaborators propose to employ an effective recursive doubling technique. &lt;br/&gt;Since the method can be further accelerated using super computers, it is realistic for practical industry applications &lt;br/&gt;with legions of identical cells for periodic structures.&lt;br/&gt;Detection of a compact inhomogeneity in a periodic structure has been a challenging problem, which is of interest by &lt;br/&gt;many engineers. For example, defects in memory chips and LCD electrodes have been a serious problem for years. &lt;br/&gt;Efficient and effective inverse scattering algorithms to detect/reconstruct defects are of great practical value. As the second goal, the PI plans to &lt;br/&gt;develop effective qualitative methods for the reconstruction of defects embedded in periodic structures.&lt;br/&gt;The qualitative methods avoid incorrect model assumptions and can provide extremely fast reconstruction. &lt;br/&gt;To the PI's knowledge, the proposed research is one the first attempts in the inverse scattering community&lt;br/&gt;to effectively reconstruct defects in periodic structures with arbitrary geometric profiles and physical properties.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1427665</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jiguang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jiguangs@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
      <CityName>Houghton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5936</Code>
      <Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
