<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-Singapore Workshop: Collaborative Research: Understand the World by Analyzing Many Video Streams</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>17985</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Fahmida N. Chowdhury</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NSF CNIC&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;US-Singapore Workshop: Collaborative Research: Understand the World by Analyzing Many Video Streams&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many thousands of network cameras provide near real-time view of the world. Valuable scientific information could be extracted by analyzing the large amounts of data. However, most of the data are never analyzed or archived. Analysis programs must be able to retrieve data from distributed sources, manage network accesses, schedule computation resources, allocate storage space, analyze the data, store the results, and present the results in formats that are easy to comprehend. Although the data are available, analyses today are limited due to the lack of a software framework to write and execute computer programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To harvest the knowledge from the data, the researchers from six universities are creating a system that can analyze the vast amount of visual data. The team will organize a workshop in December 2014 in Singapore. In this workshop, the team will share the information of the projects currently been conducted independently in the six universities. The researchers will present and demonstrate their projects, discuss and develop a plan for collaboration. The team includes Yung-Hsiang Lu (lead, Purdue University), Ketan Mayer-Patel (University of North Carolina), Cong Liu (University of Texas Dallas), Wei Tsang Ooi (National University of Singapore), Jason Gu (Singapore University of Technology and Design), Yonggang Wen (Nanyang Technological University).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1427808</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yung-Hsiang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yunglu@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5927</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA, OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
