<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of A Versatile High Resolution MS System for Determination of Small Molecules of Environmental and Health Concern</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>455000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Reckhow, David A.&lt;br/&gt;Proposal: 1428873&lt;br/&gt;Title: MRI: Acquisition of A Versatile High Resolution MS System for Determination of Small Molecules of Environmental and Health Concern&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Significance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is for the acquisition of a high resolution system for identifying and quantifying trace organic contaminants in water. The research group involved in this project has forged a strong link between environmental engineering and public health. Their proposed research projects have many applied objectives including potential translational benefits, such as discovery and then remediation of emerging contaminants in drinking water, and novel treatments for water and sanitation in Third World countries. The Xevo G2-S QTof is ideally suited for use by students from broad backgrounds due to its simple and intuitive interface. This instrument will be a centerpiece of an open resource (EEAP) available not only to those at UMass, but across the Northeast region. At UMass, it will serve the core researchers in Environmental Engineering, as well as an interdisciplinary group of researchers in various science disciplines and Public Health. Outside of UMass, it will be available for use by researchers in the 5-college consortium, and beyond, especially Universities and Colleges in New England and nearby states. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is for the acquisition of a high resolution system for identifying and quantifying trace organic contaminants in water. The Xevo G2-S QTof is a quadrupole time-of-flight instrument capable of rapidly switching between liquid (e.g., UPLC) and gas (e.g., GC) sources. This instrument will be a centerpiece of an open resource (EEAP) available not only to those at UMass, but across the Northeast region. This instrument will help connect engineering management and control technologies to the ultimate endpoints of public health. Examples include the role of watershed management and treatment technologies on bladder cancer caused by halobenzoqinones and related compounds in drinking water. Another touches upon the role of elevated bromide from industrial activities on cancer. A third pertains to nitrogenous organic compounds generated in surface waters from algal activity and photonitration reactions and human health endpoints. Others employ innovative mixed algal-bacterial granules to treat wastewater and produce biofuel, or bioelectrical systems to facilitate wastewater treatment in modern non-flush systems while producing electricity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1428873</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tobiason</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tobiason@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Park</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chulp@umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reckhow</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reckhow@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Caitlyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Butler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbutler@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>021E</Code>
      <Text>Water management</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>145E</Code>
      <Text>Water sustainability</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
