<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the ACM MobiCom 2014 Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ACM MobiCom conference is the leading international conference on mobile computing and wireless networking. It invites research contributions addressing the challenges in the area of mobile computing, from the perspective of networks, wireless and mobile systems, algorithms, and applications. The conference features a high-quality technical program, with an acceptance rate of around 10% out of around 250 submissions. It has a single-track session, which offers significant opportunities for individual and small groups that foster technical and social interactions among a diverse set of participants. MobiCom is also an international conference that stimulates exchanges between various international research communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will help increase the representation and participation of United States-based students at the conference by providing 20 or more travel grants limited to a maximum of $1000 each. By creating new opportunities for graduate students, especially those from under-represented groups, to attend a high-quality conference, this award will benefit the students by giving them an opportunity to interact with world-class researchers, inspire them to try new research directions, providing mentoring opportunities, as well as the chance to seek out internships and post-doctoral positions which will help the students advance in their research career.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1429953</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dimitrios</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koutsonikolas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dimitrio@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
      <CityName>Amherst</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
