<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Fundamental and Modeling Study of Cluster-Induced Turbulence in Particle-Laden Flows</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>222368</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of the proposed study is to develop multiphase turbulence models based on the kinetic theory for granular flows and utilizing high fidelity simulations. Areas of application of these flows include engines, industrial furnaces, fluidized beds for fossil and renewable energy conversion, and chemical plants (chemical reactors, cracking units, etc.), all of which are important for the competitiveness of the U.S. industry. The collaborating PIs propose to offer a full implementation of their models and code into commercial (Ansys Fluent) and public (OpenFOAM) platforms, as well as to make their comprehensive database of detailed simulation results available to the research community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently available models for multiphase turbulence are often based on phenomenological approaches requiring fine-tuning with experimental data. These models have limited predictive capability, preventing their adoption in industry or their generalization for research purposes. This proposal, however, aims at developing and validating a consistent Reynolds-averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS) model that is grounded on first principles, and, thus, generalizable. The exact RANS equations, as obtained from Kinetic Theory for granular flow, will be integrated to obtain a set of coupled macroscale hydrodynamic equations, which can then be averaged exactly. The terms that need to be approximated in order to close the system of equations will then be obtained with high fidelity Euler-Lagrange mesoscale simulations, already shown to predict accurately turbulent particle-laden flows.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award by the Fluid Dynamics Program of the CBET Division is co-funded by CIF 21 Software Reuse Venture Fund Program of the CISE/ACI Division.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1437865</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rodney</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fox</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rofox@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6892</Code>
      <Text>CI REUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>058E</Code>
      <Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6892</Code>
      <Text>CI REUSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
