<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Twitter and Informal Science Learning and Engagement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>215209</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Russell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project will develop a set of research instruments to assess and evaluate the role of social media micro-blogging platforms (e.g., Twitter) in fostering informal science learning. The Internet and social media are rapidly transforming the nature of public discourse and the ways in which adults learn about the changing world. Highly respected informal science institutions, such as museums, scientific foundations and societies, and government scientific agencies are trusted curators of science knowledge to whom the public looks for up-to-date information in their respective fields. These organizations are increasingly using social media tools, such as Twitter, to reach the public and disseminate information. To complement the highly quantitative and often market-driven perspectives of current research, the project will develop research tools to assess the role of Twitter in supporting informal science learning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop, pilot, and validate two instruments. The first is an informal science social engagement index or indices, based on a content analysis of social media comments. Researchers will extract online conversation threads constructed by media followers. The second measure will survey followers of the sites studied regarding motivations, objectives for their interest in science and for following these organizations, perceptions about their use of Twitter, and their perceptions about their use of Twitter. Twitter data will be gathered from several organizations, such as the National Geographic and the Field Museum of Natural History. The project will make available the two research tools for use in research on the role of Twitter in informal science education and will provide a foundation for future research on the topic.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1438898</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Light</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dlight@edc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Education Development Center</Name>
      <CityName>Waltham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024538313</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6176182227</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>43 Foundry Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7261</Code>
      <Text>PROGRAM EVALUATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
