<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Validating an Innovative Technology Classroom Observation Protocol (IT-COP) in High School Science Classrooms</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>265812</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Olga Pierrakos</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Integration of technology aligned with authentic science applications can help teachers address the focus on real-world science and engineering practices in the Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS) while also engaging students and enhancing their learning. However, few existing science classroom observation protocols examine the impact of this 'innovative' technology use in the classroom, and none measure the quality of technology implementation and its alignment with performance measures from the NGSS. Building on previous NSF-supported research, this study will develop the Innovative Technology Classroom Observation Protocol (IT-COP) to measure the impact of innovative technology integration on high school science teaching. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Co-led by an experienced team at Education Development Center and University of Maryland Center for Environmental Science, this study consists of designing and validating the IT-COP and creating a companion mobile app for data collection along with an online How-To Guide to support its use by other researchers and evaluators. The framework of the IT-COP centers on technology types (STEM workplace technologies not common in the classroom; ubiquitous technologies that are common in the classroom and beyond, and instructional classroom technologies); alignment with science, engineering and mathematical practices, pedagogical practices relevant to these standards; and authentic STEM contexts. The IT-COP will be piloted in classrooms that serve underrepresented students with a wide range of access to technology tools. This research and resulting tool will provide the foundation for future work on complementary measures of student learning aligned with high-quality integration of technology and may serve as a teacher professional development resource.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1438368</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cathlyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stylinski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cat@al.umces.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>216130775</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4102212014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 775</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7261</Code>
      <Text>PROGRAM EVALUATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
