<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>XPS: FULL: DSD: Collaborative Research: Moving the Abyss: Database Management on Future 1000-core Processors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350429</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Aidong Zhang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There are fundamental problems to speeding up CPUs beyond what is &lt;br/&gt;possible today. Because individual transistors are not getting any &lt;br/&gt;faster, manufacturers like Intel and AMD are no longer able to get &lt;br/&gt;massive performance improvements just by increasing clock speeds &lt;br/&gt;(e.g., going from 2GHz to 10GHz). To overcome this, future CPUs will &lt;br/&gt;contain hundreds to thousands of smaller computational cores on a &lt;br/&gt;single chip which will all run at the speed similar to current &lt;br/&gt;processors (e.g., 2GHz). This means that each single core will only be &lt;br/&gt;as powerful as current CPUs, but that the total aggregate power of all &lt;br/&gt;the cores will be significantly more than what is possible today. An &lt;br/&gt;important problem with the advent of these new CPUs is that the &lt;br/&gt;database systems that are used in all aspects of our society are &lt;br/&gt;ill-suited for this change. Such database systems are used to store &lt;br/&gt;and access data for a variety of applications, including on-line &lt;br/&gt;business (e.g., Google, Facebook), scientific instruments (e.g., &lt;br/&gt;astronomical telescopes), and medicine (e.g., MRI scanners). The &lt;br/&gt;reason that they are not ready to handle these new "many-core CPUs" is &lt;br/&gt;because most of them use ideas that were designed in the 1970s and &lt;br/&gt;1980s when processors only had a single core. Thus, the purpose of &lt;br/&gt;this project is to develop both software and hardware technologies &lt;br/&gt;that will allow database systems to utilize the full computational &lt;br/&gt;power of future CPU architectures. The results of this project will &lt;br/&gt;enable organizations to deploy future applications on fewer machines &lt;br/&gt;that use less energy than what is currently used today.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computer architectures are moving towards an era dominated by &lt;br/&gt;many-core machines with hundreds of cores on a single chip. This &lt;br/&gt;unprecedented level of on-chip parallelism introduces a new dimension &lt;br/&gt;to scalability that current database management systems (DBMSs) were &lt;br/&gt;not designed for. In particular, it becomes exceedingly difficult for &lt;br/&gt;the DBMS to perform concurrency control, logging, and indexing &lt;br/&gt;efficiently. With hundreds of threads running in parallel, the &lt;br/&gt;complexity of coordinating competing reads and writes to data &lt;br/&gt;diminishes the benefits of increased core counts. Thus, in this &lt;br/&gt;project the PIs propose to develop a software-hardware co-design approach &lt;br/&gt;for DBMSs in the many-core era. On the software side, rather than &lt;br/&gt;attempting to remove scalability bottlenecks of existing DBMS &lt;br/&gt;architectures through incremental improvements, the PIs seek a bottom-up &lt;br/&gt;approach where the architecture is designed to target many-core &lt;br/&gt;systems from inception. On the hardware side, instead of simply adding &lt;br/&gt;more cores to a single chip, the PIs will design new hardware components &lt;br/&gt;that can unburden the software system from computationally critical &lt;br/&gt;tasks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For further information see project web site at: &lt;br/&gt;http://db.cs.cmu.edu/projects/1000cores/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1438967</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Srini</FirstName>
      <LastName>Devadas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>devadas@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8283</Code>
      <Text>Exploiting Parallel&amp;Scalabilty</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
