<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I/UCRC Phase II: Center for the Integration of Composites into Infrastructure (CICI)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>774494</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Efficient infrastructure systems such as highways, bridges, buildings, pipelines, flood control systems and utilities are all necessary for a healthy economy and comfortable standard of living. Concrete, steel and timber are the backbones of physical infrastructure. High strength polymer composites have been used for aerospace structures for about five decades and their use in civil infrastructure spans about 20 years. To accelerate the adoption of polymer composites into infrastructure, the NSF I/UCRC Center of the Integration of Composites into Infrastructure (CICI) was established as a joint effort of West Virginia University (WVU), North Carolina State University (NCSU) and the University of Miami. Recently, NSF has awarded a travel grant to establish an additional CICI site at Nanjing University of Technology in China. The NSF I/UCRC program brings together universities, private companies and government agencies together to leverage the research dollars for all parties by engaging in highly cooperative research. CICI's work with civil infrastructure has a tremendous effect on daily life, thus the Nation as a whole benefits as composite and hybrid materials lead to infrastructure systems of higher safety, shorter construction times and longer life spans at a reduced overall cost and improved labor productivity with the creation of new and higher skilled job opportunities. Member companies and end users benefit from the interaction with others in their field including highly trained students, with over 100 students expected to pass through CICI in the next 5 years. CICI is prolific technology transfer machine, exceeding the output for most I/UCRCs through the publishing of journal articles and conference presentations to promote the scientific research and knowledge dissemination. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broadly speaking, the technical focus of CICI can be broken into four different areas. Initially, fundamental research projects are undertaken to broaden the knowledge base on infrastructure composites. This includes lifecycle performance, aging studies, evaluation of bond strength within a composite and as a substrate, and many others. From this on-going research, products are being developed that can be mass-implemented in infrastructure markets, including innovative hollow core or basalt fiber FRP rebar, waterway products that are noncorrosive or fabric reinforced cementitious composites for masonry wall strengthening and many others. The implementation of these products is the next focus area and is primarily accomplished through the development of codes and specifications. CICI has worked on the ASCE LRFD pultruded GFRP composites code, ASTM specifications, ACI building design and construction codes, the International Code Council and IIFC. Finally, CICI has an evaluation component based on IAB member feedback to ensure the composites that are implemented in the field are performing as designed as a part of our long-term performance program. Thus, through research, development, implementation and evaluation, CICI is involved in all facets of composite product evolution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1439688</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hota</FirstName>
      <LastName>GangaRao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Hota.Gangarao@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>West Virginia University Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>265066845</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3042933998</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 6845</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1359</Code>
      <Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>O273</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>P168</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>P338</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>p400</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>p410</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>p432</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>125E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>170E</Code>
      <Text>Interagency Agreements</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>115E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8037</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
