<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER-Collaborative: Exploring the feasibility of TIRF-based sensors for oceanographic research applications.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75554</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PIs propose to address the difficulty of developing a small, low power, highly sensitive molecular biology tool for oceanographic work with the novel implementation of a sensor technology known as Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence (TIRF). The TIRF provides rapid, sensitive, simultaneous, and cost-effective detection of multiple biochemical targets with minimal sample preparation. This EAGER proposal seeks funding to explore the feasibility of modifying an existing technology developed by MBio Diagnostics, Inc., consisting of a cartridge and reader system in order to achieve either a smaller form factor, an increased sample capacity, or both. This modified TIRF technology will be designed for integration with an AUV-based sample acquisition/processing module that will provide for underway generation of biological data in support of oceanographic applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The TIRF-based sensor is one of several emerging technologies that promise to transform ocean science by providing the ability to carry out interactive experiments and test hypotheses remotely at the molecular level. It has the potential for providing real or near-real time data revealing not only species? presence and abundance, but also the metabolic and physiological status of those organisms at the biochemical and molecular levels, can provide new insights into how populations are responding in situ to their environment over time as conditions change. This project will continue to build international collaborations with the UK and Ireland. It will include 4 undergraduate and 3 graduate student participation in both the US and Ireland. A workshop will be organized in Belfast as well as using these development experiences as part of an on-line module for a Masters in Diagnostics (University Arizona).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1440299</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lochhead</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mike.lochhead@mbiodx.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>MBio Diagnostics, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031377</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3039522810</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5603 Arapahoe Ave Suite 1</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1680</Code>
      <Text>OCEAN TECH &amp; INTERDISC COORDIN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
