<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CC*IIE Engineer: Campus Cyberinfrastructure Engineer for Arizona State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>398237</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports a large and diverse set of discipline specific researchers at Arizona State University (ASU) with data-intensive research programs. Example data-intensive use cases such as femtosecond nanocrystallography, biomass renewable energy, combustion for energy efficiency, the national EarthScope project, astrophysics, desert water flows, and genomics share a common need for low-latency transfer of ever-larger data sets with collaborators across ASU, Arizona, the Nation, and the world. This project leverages existing ASU investments in campus level dynamic network services to more efficiently enable a larger range of diverse and distributed research and educational data sets. ASU has significant network capability and a Science DMZ, but research groups often need specific assistance overcoming the challenges of optimally using this advanced infrastructure for their research. The campus infrastructure engineer supported by this two-year project bridges this gap by helping campus researchers make the best use of the advanced networking resources, advocating for the differing needs of research cyberinfrastructure within ASU, and engages national and international resources and organizations such as XSEDE and OSG. The campus infrastructure engineer thus strengthens network engineering and data-intensive discipline specific research across the University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1440600</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Steed</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jay.Steed@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Timmes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fxt44@mac.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wishon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Gordon.Wishon@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
