<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>North America-East Asia Workshop on Big Data Analytics for Infrastructure and Building Sustainability and Resilience (IBSR) Research Changsha, China - September 19-21, 2014.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>55000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1440504 (Chong). The focus of this workshop is to develop a knowledge framework and identify research needs for the application of big data analytics on infrastructure and building sustainability and resilience (IBSR) research. This is an area related directly to urban sustainability, of high interest in China due to rapid urbanization, and also in the U.S., since 80% of the U.S. population now lives in urban regions. The NSF funds will be used to support the travel and participation costs of the U.S. research delegation to the workshop. The workshop will develop a platform for attendees to connect with other researchers from around the world who share similar research interests, and layout the framework for such research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A website will be developed in the U.S. after the conference to (a) connect researchers from around the world and (b) disseminate the discussions, framework, research interests, and ideas from the workshop. The knowledge framework and research needs will also be published on the website. Workshop participants (including the PI) will assist in developing the framework and identifying research needs, while the PI will be responsible for developing the website in the U.S. and disseminating the findings gathered from the workshop. The workshop will be held in conjunction with ICSDEC 2014 (International Conference on Sustainable Design, Engineering and Construction 2014) at Changsha, Hunan, China between September 19th to 21st, 2014. ICSDEC 2014 will be chaired by Dr. Guangcai Gong, Professor of the Hunan University, Department of Building Environmental Engineering, Civil Engineering College. He is also the Head of the Lab of Building Environment at Hunan University. Dr. Wai Kiong (Oswald) Chong (Arizona State University) and Dr. Jae Chang (University of Kansas) will be co-chairing the conference. The workshop will be held in conjunction with the conference, with the conference chairs being co-chairs for the workshop. This grant is co-funded by NSF's International Science and Engineering section (ISE), through the ISE Program Officer Action Fund, as well as the Environmental Sustainability program in the CBET division of NSF's Engineering Directorate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1440504</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wai Kiong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ochong@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7643</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8020</Code>
      <Text>Green Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
