<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on computationally intensive modeling of dynamic social interaction November 7-8, 2014 in Tucson, Arizona</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kerry Marsh</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The ability to predict how people will behave during social interactions would have implications for a broad array of domains, ranging across close relationships, education, parenting, business management, work performance, health behaviors, and conflict resolution. A major barrier to progress is that behavioral scientists, who are experts at understanding social interaction, do not usually have advanced mathematical modeling capability. On the other hand, computational scientists, who have the mathematical and computational ability to model complex systems, usually are not experts on social interaction. To address this, Emily Butler (University of Arizona) and colleagues will host a cross-disciplinary, collaborative workshop to bring together behavioral and computational scientists with a shared interest in computationally intensive modeling of dynamic social interactions. The workshop will be attended by approximately 50 invited scientists and is designed to establish new cross-disciplinary collaborations, and the sharing of information and resources across disciplines. More broadly, the larger goal is to foster cumulative research that supports pragmatic applications. Information about social interaction is important for developing parenting classes, family counseling programs, interventions for health behaviors, managerial and negotiation training, reducing bullying in schools, and promoting constructive international relations. Thus the workshop has the potential to inform theory and practice across a diverse range of human experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1444761</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
      <LastName>Butler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eabutler@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1332</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1332</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
