<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GRC Biocatalysis 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT TITLE&lt;br/&gt;2014 Gordon Research Conference on Biocatalysis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;This award will partially cover the registration costs for some of the participants of the 2014 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Biocatalysis and associated Gordon Research Seminar (GRS), with preference given to post-doctoral associates, graduate students, and early career scientists. The GRC will be held on July 6-11, 2014, at Bryant University in Smithfield, Rhode Island. The meeting will be preceded by the second associated GRS on July 5-6, 2014, which follows up on the success of the first GRS in 2012. The PI for the award is Prof. Stefan Lutz of Emory University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mission of this joint GRS/GRC meeting is to provide a forum, in a highly interactive environment, to educate experienced researchers about the latest developments in fundamental and applied biocatalysis and to introduce students, postdoctoral fellows, and young investigators to current questions and challenges in the field. The agenda for the conference allows for extended discussions amongst the participants from academia, industry, and the national laboratories. Approximately a third of the participants are postdoctoral associates, graduate students, and early career scientists. The conference has a unique learning environment for early career participants because the format combines informal presentations and discussions, group meals, and external activities to encourage collaborative discussions between early career and advanced-career scientists in the field of biocatalysis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This 2014 GRC on Biocatalysis will continue the tradition of bringing together leading researchers from around the world to discuss their latest, most exciting work in biocatalysis and future directions for the field. The conferences sessions will cover core research areas in biocatalysis which have recently yielded exciting new discoveries. In addition, emerging areas in biocatalysis will be presented such as applications to new materials and the impact of disruptive technologies in advancing the field of biocatalysis.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1445636</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lutz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sal2@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
