<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop Support for Focused Technical Workshop on Improving Data Mobility &amp; Management for International Climate Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>44316</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Focused Technical Workshop on Improving Data Mobility &amp; Management for International Climate Science (FTW for Climate Science) will enable an active dialogue between climate scientists, climate data managers, and cyberinfrastructure engineers with the goal of setting longer-term relationship building in motion. The workshop also hopes to provide climate researchers with information about a set of broad, concrete, and immediately useful tools and resources for improved data transport and management. The FTW on Climate Science is sponsored by ESnet, Internet2, Indiana University (IU), National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), and National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) and will be hosted at the NOAA Boulder Labs, in Boulder, Colorado, in July 2014.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will bring together experts to discuss recent research technology advances and research techniques in data management for climate science. The format is being designed to encourage lively, interactive discussions with the goal of developing a set of tangible next steps for supporting this data-intensive science community. Participation key stakeholders from multiple agencies and programs provides the climate science community with the knowledge, tools, and partners necessary to improve data transfer performance as data scale continues to increase. This has the potential to have broad reaching effects in a science area that is critical to society. By increasing performance to match increased data scale, scientific productivity for this community is expected to increase. This workshop will leverage existing NSF supported projects, including work with EarthCube.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1445821</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schopf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmschopf@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
