<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium on Undergraduate Research to be held October 19-24, 2014 in Tucson Arizona.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides travel support for student participation in the 30th Conference on Laser Science to be held October 19-24, 2014 in Tucson, Arizona. Support is provided only for US students (students enrolled in US universities). This conference series is important to the vitality of atomic, molecular, and optical physics in the United States. The support of students through this award makes a substantial contribution to the education and training of future scientists. Students who graduate with a background in atomic, molecular, and optical physics acquire a broad range of knowledge and skills that enable them to contribute to progress in many areas of science and technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Conference is part of the Division of Laser Science (DLS) of the American Physical Society (APS) and offers an opportunity for students to present their research results and to interact with senior scientists primarily from the United States, but also the broader international community. A special undergraduate student symposium has been organized to allow students to present the results of their research and introduce them to cutting-edge topics in atomic, molecular, and optical physics. This Conference will be held jointly with the 98th Annual Meeting of the Optical Society of America.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1445398</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harold</FirstName>
      <LastName>Metcalf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>harold.metcalf@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1241</Code>
      <Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
