<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Defining, Measuring, &amp; Monitoring Adequate Instructional Time and Resources for Science in Grades K-5</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299700</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rebecca Kruse</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project addresses needs for research outlined in the 2013 National Research Council report, Monitoring Progress Toward Successful K-12 Education: A Nation Advancing?, which proposed indicators related to improving STEM education. Specifically, the project will address research on indicator 2, time allocated to teach science in grades K-5, and indicator 3, science-related learning opportunities in elementary schools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project, to be conducted by the University California, Berkeley, will address the issue of measuring instructional time and adequacy of resources for science education in grades K-5. The project will review existing evidence related to time, type, and substance of science learning experiences in elementary schools, conduct interviews and surveys of key informants, convene an expert panel in order to approach consensus related to measurement strategy and implementation recommendations, document research findings and expert recommendations, and lay groundwork for next steps regarding implementation of measurement systems. The project will advance the work of the Education &amp; Human Resources (EHR) directorate in fostering research on science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1445621</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dorph</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdorph@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ardice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hartry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hartry@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7261</Code>
      <Text>PROGRAM EVALUATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
