<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2nd International Sooting Flame Workshop in Livermore, CA on August 2-3, 2014</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruey-Hung Chen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Hai Wang&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: CBET 1445921&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The two-day workshop (August 2-3, 2014) will be held at the Sandia National Laboratory campus with experts from around the world and the country to address the research needs for basic combustion kinetics for soot formation and sooting flames. The dates have been selected to be in advance of the bi-annual 35th International Combustion Symposium, to be held in San Francisco, August 4-8, 2014, when experts from around the world will be congregate in the Bay area. The workshop's schedule takes advantage of the larger event resulting in cost reduction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop's key results have the potential of gaining knowledge that would make utilization of fossil fuels in energy production cleaner and more sustainable. The workshop also provides students a unique opportunity to be exposed to multidisciplinary science and the leading issues in sooting emission from combustion processes. Graduate students from US educational institutions are encouraged to attend the workshop, with NSF support to defray lodging costs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1445921</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haiwang@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/09/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
