<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Investigation of Best Practices and Lessons Learned from LSAMP Bride-to-the-Doctorate Programs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>476224</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dr. A. James Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Recent statistics show that very few US citizens pursue graduate studies in STEM fields. Of the US citizens that chose to pursue graduate studies in STEM fields a small percentage of these students are from historically underrepresented groups. Of those that chose to pursue graduate studies in STEM fields, there are many factors that enhance or inhibit successful matriculation through the graduate school process. Thus, researchers from the Center for Advancing Faculty Excellence(CAFE'), Florida A&amp;M University, and Prairie View A&amp;M University will work closely with LSAMP BD Program Sites to perform a descriptive research investigation aimed at identifying best practices and lessons learned strategies that can be employed within STEM graduate programs to broaden participation while ensuring student success. As a result of successfully completing this descriptive research investigation, a blueprint for designing and implementing various practices, procedures, and policies proven to ensure the success of broadening participation in STEM graduate education programs will be created. The creation of this blueprint describing best practices and lessons learned will allow valuable information to be shared among STEM graduate program faculty, staff, students, administrators, and other key stakeholders. It is envisioned that this resulting blueprint will become the conduit by which graduate programs can successfully produce the talent needed to fuel the STEM workforce of the future. Hence, this blueprint will serve as a valuable resource to the national STEM community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1446427</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lesia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crumpton-Young</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drcrumptonyoung@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tennessee State University</Name>
      <CityName>nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372091561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6159637631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3500 John A. Merritt Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9133</Code>
      <Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
