<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Doctoral Consortium at the 2014 ACM International Conference on Collaboration Across Boundaries (CABS 2014)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>23408</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ephraim P. Glinert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is funding to support participation by students and faculty based in U.S. educational institutions in a Doctoral Consortium (workshop) that will bring together promising doctoral students and distinguished researchers from academia and industry, to be held in conjunction with the 5th International ACM Conference on Collaboration Across Boundaries: Culture, Distance and Technology (CABS 2014), which will take place in Kyoto, Japan, on August 20-22. Sponsored by the Association for Computing Machinery's Special Interest Group on Computer-Human Interaction (SIGCHI), the annual CABS conference is a growing international forum for the presentation and discussion of research and practice focused on understanding and supporting intercultural communication and global teams. CABS serves as a gathering point for researchers who share a common interest in understanding how technology can be used to bridge people from multiple cultures. A fundamental premise of the conference is that the difficult problems of language and culture that arise in cross-cultural communication and collaboration can only be adequately addressed by multidisciplinary efforts. Thus, attendees come from diverse academic disciplines including computer science, engineering, management science, information science, communication, psychology, sociology, and anthropology. Attendees also span the globe, with participation from the United States, China, Japan, Korea, Israel, France, Denmark, Germany, the UK, and other countries. The conference solicits competitive paper, panel, demo and other submissions; peer-reviewed, archival papers and notes appear in the ACM Digital Library. More information about the conference may be found online at http://cabs.acm.org/2014/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CABS Doctoral Consortium is a research-focused meeting of a group of 10-12 selected PhD candidates and a panel of 4-5 distinguished researchers from academia and industry. The event, whose goal is to help launch the careers of outstanding researchers in the area of intercultural collaboration, will take place on August 20, with follow-up events during the conference's technical program on August 21-22. NSF funds will support participation by one senior researcher from the United States (the PI) and 8 students based in U.S. educational institutions. The full-day Doctoral Consortium will provide students with exposure to their research community, with an opportunity to present their work and receive constructive feedback from peers and senior researchers in the field, and with ample time to start building a professional support network of peers and mentors (e.g., during the organizational and working dinners). The feedback is geared toward helping student participants understand and articulate how their work is positioned relative to other CABS research, whether their topics are adequately focused for dissertation research projects, whether their methods are correctly chosen and applied, whether their results are being appropriately analyzed and presented, etc. The student participants will also present their work as posters, which they have prepared before arrival, during the CABS technical program. During the interactive poster session the students will be present to discuss their work with interested attendees, but the posters will be available for viewing throughout the entire three days of the conference. The students' work is thus showcased for conference attendees, and the students have the opportunity to get feedback from a larger audience. In addition, abstracts for all Doctoral Consortium attendee presentations will be printed as a packet to be distributed to all CABS attendees, and the full extended abstract for each presentation will be made available on the CABS 2014 website. The event organizers will make special efforts to promote participation from U.S. institutions and ethnic groups that have been traditionally underrepresented at CABS. They will also consider equitable gender balance in the mix of accepted students. To further increase diversity among the student participants, the organizers have committed to accepting no more than 1 student from any particular institution, except in the case that 2 qualified students of different genders apply in which case both may be accepted.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1446810</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Robertson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scott.robertson@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
