<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Use of Multimodal Interactive Storytelling to Create Interest in STEM in Prekindergarten and Kindergarten Children</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glenn H. Larsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I Project seeks to generate fundamental interest in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math (STEM) at a young age. According to the 2007 Trends in International Mathematics and Science Study (TIMSS), U.S. fourth grade students ranked eleventh in math and seventh in science out of 36 countries. A continued decrease in STEM interest is leading to a decrease in the awarding of STEM degrees. According to the 2008 National Math and Science Initiative, in 4% of US bachelor's degrees were awarded in engineering compared to 31% in China. Exacerbating the problem is a change in the fundamental nature of career development toward more technical skills requirements. This project aims to engage children at a younger age and create a foundation of interest in STEM education. This engagement reinforces the National Science Foundation's fundamental mission of education for all fields of science and engineering. On the micro level, the project aims to create software and creative development jobs in the US through the creation of the application and content. The project also aims to create a new generation of engaged young people with enthusiasm to pursue careers in STEM-related fields, thereby creating a more technical and science-minded workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I Project seeks to test the feasibility and commercialize a multimodal storytelling toy and software application to generate fundamental interest and augment learning in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math (STEM) at a young age. Although there are a number of toys and educational products on the market targeted toward children at an older age, a void exists for educational toys that provide a dedicated focus on STEM education for younger children. This project will involve the development of a curriculum along with a prototype application to promote early adoption of STEM education in a classroom environment. The application will feature academically sound stories centered on scientific concepts featuring the child along with a companion character to act as their guide through the stories. The toy character and story personalization aim to create an emotional connection between the child and the STEM concepts in the stories. In addition to the story itself, interactive elements will promote repeat use and retention of STEM concepts. The objective of this Phase I activity is to demonstrate that the platform can augment existing STEM curriculum and generate interest in basic science and engineering concepts in the prekindergarten and kindergarten classroom environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1447270</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scheinberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jeremy@mytrobo.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Skookoo LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Maitlando</CityName>
      <ZipCode>327940000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4697087626</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 948002</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8031</Code>
      <Text>Education Products</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8032</Code>
      <Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
