<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: A Unified system for low-cost, Scalable Projection Mapping</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be the creation of tools that democratize a new interactive medium called projection mapping. Projection mapping uses video projectors to overlay digital content (images, animations or video) onto 3D physical objects, allowing viewers to experience and interact with digital experiences in an entirely new way. These interactive displays will add value to a wide range of industries where dynamic, 3D presentations are needed to inform, educate, advertise or entertain. Applications include educational experiences at museums or schools, healthcare applications for rehabilitation and visualization, new training and simulation displays, as well as broad uses in advertising and entertainment. For example, a retail end aisle display could more easily attract customers by demonstrating product features with projected light directly on or around the physical product. Alternatively, an interactive diorama in a museum could allow visitors to learn history through an immersive visual experience. This project will bring projection mapping from high budget, niche markets into low budget, mainstream markets. Cost reductions will be realized through technological advances that decrease design, setup and calibration requirements, which in turn will advance technological capabilities and content authoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project proposes to develop a novel software and hardware system for authoring projection mapping content. The proposed system will greatly simplify a currently complex content authoring process, and will enable entirely new passive and interactive experiences which fuse digital content with the physical environment. The system is comprised of a content authoring software suite and a projector-depth camera hardware unit capable of high-resolution 3D scanning. Research objectives entail novel software algorithms in the areas of 1) automatic calibration of projector-camera systems, 2) optimized structured light scanning of 3D objects, 3) automatic, precise re-alignment and registration of the system in response to movement of the physical model, 4) intuitive authoring tools for creating passive and interactive projection mapping experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1448646</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Karsch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kevin@lumenous3d.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lumenous Co.</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941085029</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2179035826</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>251 Post St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8032</Code>
      <Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>163E</Code>
      <Text>SBIR Phase IB</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
