<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Novel Rare Earth Metal Oxysulfate (RE2O2SO4) for Upconversion</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tania Paskova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is co-funded by the Electronic and Photonic Materials Program (EPM) and the Ceramics Program (CER).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Description: This project focuses on an inorganic material system, oxysulfate (RE2O2SO4) doped with metal elements, in the form of nanometer spheres and explores its potential for converting low-frequency light to higher-frequency light (upconversion). Upconversion is used in various photonic applications including biological imaging. The project offers students the opportunity to acquire skills in nanoparticle synthesis, functionalization, structural characterizations, and optical property measurements. The research activities of this project are integrated with an educational mission in terms of course development and special seminars. As a Hispanic-Serving Institution, New Mexico State University offers significant opportunities for outreach and educational activities that involve K-12 students and underrepresented minorities including those at the NMSU community colleges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: Bulk glass and crystalline materials are usually used for upconversion, but bulk materials are often not suitable for certain applications such as biological imaging. Upconversion materials on nanometer scales are desirable. However, synthesis of small nanocrystals that exhibit high monodispersibility and excellent upconversion properties remains a challenge. The goal of this project is to establish a scientific basis for the design of small monodisperse rare-earth-metal-doped oxysulfate nanospheres for upconversion. The research team aims to develope an effective synthesis route, biomolecule-assisted hydrothermal method, to control the size and shape of nanospheres, as well as to tune the upconversion properties to enable their practical applications. The research activities are designed to develop a fundamental understanding of the formation mechanism of the nanospheres with controlled size and shape; to investigate the energy transfer mechanism between the sensitizer and the activator; and to reveal the relationship between the composition, particle size and shape, crystal structure, and luminescent properties.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1449035</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hongmei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Luo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hluo@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
      <CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
      <ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1774</Code>
      <Text>CERAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
