<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SNM: Roll-to-Roll Manufacturing of Films and Laminates Based on Cellulose Nanomaterials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1477970</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>While the potential applications of nanocomposites have stimulated much research, many practical barriers exist in production scale-up, and their environmental issues have raised significant concerns. These factors are driving a growing demand for nanomaterials that are produced from renewable sources that are also highly processable. Cellulose nanomaterials represent one promising class of materials. However, the scalable manufacture of these materials has yet to be established, due to scientific and engineering challenges that are unique to their dispersions. At present, cellulose nanomaterials based nanocomposite films are prepared by casting methods that can only produce small-area samples with limited quality control, or by press/filtration methods that produce sheets with a high density of structural defects. This Scalable NanoManufacturing (SNM) award will study continuous casting methods for the roll-to-roll fabrication of these films and laminates. The research will result in a capability of producing sufficiently large areas for practical vacuum- and thermo-forming applications. Breakthrough technologies and approaches to scaling up production of these films and laminates, large area continuous manufacturing, and new algorithms in process control can revolutionize many applications in packaging and structural materials. The interest expressed by industrial partners in this technology attest to the potential impact of the project in industrial innovation. Moreover developing scalable production of cellulose nanomaterial films and laminates will allow replacement of fossil fuel-derived materials, thus lowering environmental footprint and lead to a more sustainable economy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scalable production of cellulose nanomaterial enhanced laminate materials will be supported by sustainable and eco-friendly approaches for surface modification and particle dispersion, by fundamental advances in controlling the rheology of complex fluids for uniform film deposition, and by a cross-disciplinary approach toward process monitoring and control during continuous roll-to-toll nanomanufacturing. Multi-scale modeling of cellulose nanomaterial-polymer interfaces and process optimization will deepen our understanding of the interplay between structure and materials properties at different length scales. The simulation tools and computational models developed in the course of this project will be widely applicable to the development of other types of nanocomposites as well as continuous processes for film manufacturing. Specifically, the following barriers will be addressed: scalable production of cellulose nanomaterial-derived films and laminates, process monitoring and control, and understanding the effect of interfaces and microstructures on film processing and mechanical properties.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1449358</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wei</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alexwei@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pablo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zavattieri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zavattie@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chiu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gchiu@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Youngblood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpyoungb@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1674</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>081E</Code>
      <Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8037</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
