<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Advancing Direct Potable Reuse as a Sustainable Water Supply by Engaging the Environmental Community</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49973</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1450509&lt;br/&gt;Brown&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Workshop on Advancing Direct Potable Reuse as a Sustainable Water Supply by Engaging the Environmental Community&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The drought in Southern California and in fact the US Southwest has stimulated people to start to discuss alternative water supplies. One of the most sustainable supplies is the use of wastewater for direct potable reuse (DPR). DPR is the process of treating wastewater to drinkable standards and returning it into the potable supply. It is gaining attention as a supply alternative with multiple environmental benefits, particularly for arid and drought-ridden communities. However, DPR is not widely implemented in the U.S. due to gaps in technical knowledge and insufficient protocols for achieving public acceptance. The environmental community, which holds a prominent role in advocacy and public outreach, supports the development of safe, reliable, and cost effective water supply projects; however, they need more information to better understand DPR and approaches to support the implementation of DPR as a sustainable community resource. Armed with this knowledge, the environmental community can become a strong proponent of DPR within the broader community. The proposed workshop will provide an overview of current DPR research, address challenges, and recommend strategies for successful community outreach. The workshop will be held in the fall of 2015 in Southern California. Possible topic areas include DPR research and applications, regulatory issues, public health concerns, outreach challenges, and enhancing public acceptance. Invited speakers will include academics and water professionals with expertise and experience in these topic areas. Attendees will include executive directors and public outreach managers of environmental nonprofit organizations from arid states such as Arizona, California, Nevada and Texas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives and methods for the workshop include: (1) Organizing a forum for environmental groups to learn more about DPR and its role as a sustainable water supply; (2) Providing presentations by research experts on the technical and social aspects of DPR and representatives from regulatory agencies; (3) Dividing attendees into working groups to identify challenges, strategies, and solutions to help environmental groups support and advance DPR as a sustainable water supply; (4) Producing a final workshop report for dissemination among the environmental community, water agencies, and policy and decision makers. The workshop is designed to address the question, "What approaches can the environmental community implement to advance DPR as a sustainable water supply?" A final workshop report that includes summaries of the presentations, working group reports, and recommendations will be developed by Coastkeeper and NWRI and disseminated by the two groups to their respective networks within the environmental community and water industry. The workshop will bridge a gap between the scientific community (academic researchers), the engineering community (water treatment and supply agencies), the environmental community (nonprofit organizations), and policymakers. While there have been a number of recent outreach initiatives designed for academia and water professionals working in potable reuse, there has been a lack of resources designed to specifically address the environmental community's interest in sustainable communities and role in advancing DPR. The proposed workshop and final report, which will be disseminated to the environmental community, will enhance the technical and social understanding of DPR, giving practitioners and proponents the tools and knowledge necessary to achieve public acceptance and support appropriate policy measures. The societal benefits of DPR include providing a water supply resource that is locally controlled, requires less energy than other supply options (such as ocean desalination and imported deliveries), and protects oceanic and inland surface water quality by reducing wastewater discharge. The final report will enhance outreach, education, and advocacy efforts by the environmental community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1450509</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mosher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmosher@nwri-usa.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Garry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>trisha@coastkeeper.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Orange County Coastkeeper</Name>
      <CityName>Costa Mesa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926264621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7148501965</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3151 Airway Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
