<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Summer Course for Research Design in the Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences (SCRD)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>151726</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Josie S. Welkom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project runs a three-year series of summer courses called "Summer Course for Research Design in the Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences (SCRD). The SCRD brings together social science area experts and post-graduate participants from across the social, behavioral and economic sciences (SBE) for 1 week of intensive study of issues in research design in SBE disciplines with an emphasis on scientific proposal development. Participants, approximately 12 who already hold a PhD in any of the SBE disciplines, are selected from a competitive pool of applicants. Criteria for selection are based primarily on a participant's genuine interest in issues of research design in SBE research, demonstrated interest in research relevant to under-served populations and interests in advancing their proposal writing skills. Potential participants from under-represented groups are particularly encouraged to apply. This course should be of particular interest to individuals interested in the SPRF postdoctoral research fellowship initiative at NSF. Course content covers a broad spectrum of research design issues, but with a heavy emphasis on the link between theory and methods and its importance in writing well-conceived research proposals. This summer course provides PhDs in any of the SBE disciplines with the knowledge and tools to produce well-conceived research projects and proposals. In turn, participants will use the course to fashion fundable research agendas that could directly benefit under-served communities. Moreover, the knowledge and skills learned in the course can be used in the teaching of research design and proposal writing in their home institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program accomplishes a number of goals: 1) provides participants with a basic understanding of the link between theory and scientific methodology in the social sciences, 2) enhances a participant's ability to produce a well-conceived and written research proposal, and 3) provides participants with basic scientific research knowledge and skills for solving a variety of research design problems in the future. Topics include the link between theory and development of research designs (e.g., experimental, quasi-experimental, observational), research objectives, concepts, definitions, variables, measures, and hypotheses; the relationship between quantitative and qualitative approaches within the social sciences; the development of research plans in proposals including content on data collection procedures; probability and non-probability sampling; statistical analysis and models; human subjects concerns; introduction to data structures and management in both a qualitative and quantitative context; narrative and text analysis; and hypothesis testing to name a few.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1450520</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johnsonje@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCarty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ufchris@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8208</Code>
      <Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
