<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Elucidating conformational landscapes in proteins using high-sensitivity pulse EPR spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>637226</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kelsey D. Cook</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Measurement and Imaging program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Stefan Stoll of the University of Washington is developing high-sensitivity instrumentation and methodology for the determination of the nanoscale structure of flexible proteins. The flexibility of proteins is a prerequisite for their activity, but is difficult to quantify experimentally. The methods developed in this project provide tools to accurately probe fundamental chemical processes underlying life at the molecular level. The broader impacts include potential benefits to human health, as the molecular-level knowledge attainable through the methods developed in this project furthers our ability to rationally design new drugs and therapies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on instrumentation development of high-sensitivity pulse electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) spectroscopies for biostructural applications, specifically double electron-electron resonance (DEER) spectroscopy. DEER is a pulse EPR technique that can quantitatively determine protein conformational distributions and flexibility by measuring nanometer-scale distances between spin labels attached to proteins. The research approach consists of three thrusts: (1) Develop a pulse EPR spectrometer with improved sensitivity for DEER and related methods to be able to accurately measure conformational landscapes in proteins and complexes even at very low concentrations. (2) Quantify protein conformational change in a small soluble ligand-binding protein to benchmark the methodology and to gain insight into conformational dynamics and equilibria involved in ligand binding. (3) Elucidate the conformational landscape in fragments of a cardiac ion channel, in order to test and validate the methodology on a more complex membrane protein system.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1452967</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stoll</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stst@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
