<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Engineering Plasmonic Nanoantenna Architectures for Efficient Nuclear Delivery &amp; Advancing Awareness in Nanotechnology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500162</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This CAREER plan aims to develop configurable nanostructures for gene delivery. Gene therapy&lt;br/&gt;ultimately relies on corrected genes to be efficiently delivered across cell membranes and ultimately&lt;br/&gt;to the cell nucleus without exposing neighboring cells. This plan configures nanostructures to&lt;br/&gt;deliver genes efficiently and specifically to the cell nucleus. In particular, asymmetric&lt;br/&gt;configurations, displaying unique optical properties, will be developed to optically penetrate&lt;br/&gt;membranes, optically transport genes through the crowded intracellular space, and deliver genes&lt;br/&gt;directly to the nucleus. Efficient and specific delivery of corrected genes should lower required&lt;br/&gt;dosages and minimize unwanted side effects. This strategy also offers a new class of gene delivery&lt;br/&gt;systems which can be optically removed post-delivery, eliminating potential side effects from the&lt;br/&gt;gene delivery system itself. As part of broader impacts and outreach activities, this plan aims to&lt;br/&gt;advance awareness in nanotechnology, and to increase underrepresented participation in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;Drawing from this proposed research, laboratory course modules will be designed at the graduate&lt;br/&gt;level, research career series will be implemented at the undergraduate level, and nanotechnology&lt;br/&gt;capstone workshops will be designed to engage K-12 students in STEM. These combined activities&lt;br/&gt;serve to form a framework integrating research, education and outreach over the PI's career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER plan aims to address the challenge facing gene delivery systems to deliver genes&lt;br/&gt;efficiently and specifically to the cell nucleus. The proposed work will develop plasmonic&lt;br/&gt;nanoantenna architectures - consisting of asymmetrically configured nanoparticles - capable of&lt;br/&gt;optical transport, membrane penetration and nuclear gene release for efficient nuclear delivery. The&lt;br/&gt;intellectual merit of the proposed research lies in the configuration of plasmonic nanoantenna&lt;br/&gt;architectures, displaying high degrees of asymmetry and coupled longitudinal modes, to spectrally&lt;br/&gt;decouple the gradient force from the radiation pressure. Spectral decoupling of the gradient force&lt;br/&gt;from the radiation pressure allows, for the first time, optical forces at reasonable light irradiances,&lt;br/&gt;minimized photothermally induced Brownian motion, and multi-functional capabilities where&lt;br/&gt;optical transport is conducted at one wavelength and optical activation of gene release is conducted&lt;br/&gt;at another wavelength. The following tasks support the attainment of the research goal: (1) Identify&lt;br/&gt;operation conditions for optical transport of plasmonic nanoantenna architectures. (2) Assess&lt;br/&gt;whether optical force penetration compared to optical destabilization improves penetration&lt;br/&gt;efficiency. (3) Investigate whether spatial modulation of gene release modifies resulting gene&lt;br/&gt;expression. As part of broader impacts and outreach activities, this plan aims to advance awareness&lt;br/&gt;in nanotechnology and plasmonics at the K-12, undergraduate and graduate level, and to increase&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented participation in STEM. The following tasks support the attainment of the&lt;br/&gt;educational goal: (1) Lead capstone workshops to expose K-12 students to nanotechnology. (2)&lt;br/&gt;Implement research career seminar series to educate undergraduate students interested in research&lt;br/&gt;as a career path. (3) Expand plasmonics graduate course curriculum to include laboratory modules.&lt;br/&gt;These combined activities serve to form a framework integrating research, education and outreach&lt;br/&gt;over the PI's career.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1454188</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Somin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sleee@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
