<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Evolutionary genetics of a cosmopolitan generalist herbivore</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>437355</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leslie Rissler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>To counteract grazing by animal herbivores, plants use a large array of defenses that include the production of toxic compounds. In turn, herbivores exploit diverse strategies to overcome these plant defenses. As herbivores have profound impacts on natural plant communities, and are one of the major sources of crop loss in agriculture, understanding the genetic basis and strategies for how herbivores adapt to feed on plant hosts is of ecological and agricultural relevance. The objective of this research is to characterize the genetic underpinnings of the interaction between the two-spotted spider mite herbivore and different plant hosts. This mite species is well known as a generalist herbivore, meaning that it can feed on many plant species, including more than a hundred crop plants. The research will further our understanding of the extent to which given strains of generalist herbivores can persist equally well on diverse plant hosts, or alternatively may be specialized to more specific subsets of plant species. Furthermore, the research will characterize which genes and alleles, including ones that impact variation in gene expression regulation, are important for the life history of this generalist herbivore. Outcomes of the research will include specific insights into forces shaping genetic variation in generalist herbivores relevant to human welfare, and the work will more broadly inform studies in diverse organisms that aim to elucidate the genetic basis of adaptation to changing environments. The research will also train K-12, undergraduate, and graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To accomplish the research objectives, mite strains from diverse geographical locations and host plants will be collected. Using high-throughput DNA sequencing, the genomes of the strains will subsequently be determined to describe genetic variation. Molecular signatures of selection will then be assessed for genes associated with, for example, the metabolism of plant toxins. Complementing these studies of DNA variation, high-throughput transcriptome sequencing will also be performed to assess the possibility that variation in the regulation of these genes underlies establishment on different hosts. Finally, genetic crosses, followed by sequencing of resulting populations selected on different plant hosts, will be carried out to identify specific genes and alleles underlying host-plant adaptation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1457346</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clark@biology.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
