<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transfer Initiative for Engineering Scholars (TIES) - Phase II</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>620963</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Transfer Initiative for Engineering Scholars (TIES) project will increase opportunities for academically talented, 2- and 4- year students with financial need to transfer to programs in electrical or computer engineering at the Georgia Institute of Technology. The PI team will retain many of the strategies that were used in a first implementation of TIES; however, these have been further refined and will move TIES to a best practices blueprint for recruiting and retaining these transfer students. This project will address two of the major challenges faced by academically gifted students who are strong candidates for admission: financial need and academic support. The target population for this effort will include students at community colleges, and 2- and 4- year institutions that serve underrepresented groups. Approximately 115 scholarships will be award to 33 students over the five-year grant period. The TIES support structure will enable these students to perform at or above the level of traditional students. Since many of the TIES scholars will maintain strong ties to their home institutions, they can serve as role models and help create a pipeline for community college graduates who want to attend Georgia Tech or other top engineering programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The TIES program will be based on an analysis of successful paths taken by non-traditional students and generalizing them for a broader group of institutions. Using an approach and management team that have had success in a variety of outreach efforts for improving engineering enrollment and diversity, the PIs will build and expand upon those existing efforts to offer several support program options for such students and will include a mix of programs designed specifically for non-traditional junior-level transfers. Examination of these combinations of students and programs will advance the understanding of how to help non-traditional students. Several program details, such as active involvement with a cohesive student cohort and mentoring activities focused on research and career development, will keep students motivated to succeed. TIES will address important national and institutional concerns by providing financially limited students from 2- and 4- year colleges opportunities to graduate from a top-tier engineering school. This program will provide a best practices template for other departments and engineering schools that wish to recruit and graduate talented non-traditional students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1458632</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Michaels</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jemichaels@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elliot</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>em80@mail.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
      <LastName>Auerbach</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jill.auerbach@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
