<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Interfaces and Surfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Caro</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL PART: This project continues the Interfaces and Surfaces REU site at Clemson University focused on providing student researchers the opportunity to conduct research that will improve current scientific understanding of materials interfaces and surfaces. The research and program activities have been designed to help participants have a positive research experience, and to encourage them to pursue graduate studies and research oriented careers. The PIs will focus on recruiting a diverse group of students to apply for and participate in the program. Each accepted student will have an obtainable summer research goal that is embedded within their faculty mentor's established research program. All REU students will also participate in a workshop series designed to enhance their laboratory experience by focusing on professional skills and knowledge: navigation of scientific literature, laboratory documentation, and career path options.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL PART: The Interfaces and Surfaces REU site has four clearly defined programmatic goals: (1) providing students with the opportunity to conduct independent research with an obtainable summer research goal using state-of-the-art characterization tools and testing equipment commonly used in materials science graduate school and research careers, (2) improving student awareness of the importance of developing a research network and identifying career mentors, (3) providing students with the training and guidance to present their work in a professional manner at a well-attended poster session, and (4) encouraging students to consider research careers and find a graduate program that fits their interests and goals. Faculty mentors have been selected based on their technical research merit and their demonstrated commitment to mentoring undergraduate researchers. Program assessment will focus primarily on the program's impact on participants' career plans.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1460863</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Delphine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dean</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>finou@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kennedy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mskenne@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clemson University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7222</Code>
      <Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1711</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
