<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Additive Manufacturing- Advances and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>368405</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>BROADER SIGNIFICANCE OF THE PROJECT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU site renewal site advances applications of additive manufacturing has the powerful advantage of providing opportunities for interdisciplinary projects that culminate in excellent applied engineering research activities. The activities will help participants develop a passion for lifelong learning and will encourage entrepreneurship and global impact involving the useful "sometimes patentable" devices that will be created. The MSOE-REU Site will continue to be a research incubator for several first-generation and traditionally underrepresented students from all across the nation, especially from second tier/ non Ph.D. granting schools. To date, this program has provided 161 students with research opportunities. Of the 148 students who have completed their baccalaureate, 59% have completed or are pursuing advanced degrees, with several in faculty positions. The most recent award has served 21 students, of whom 67% are from other institutions, 38% minorities and others (14% African American), and 52% women. Of the 8 who have completed a baccalaureate, 75% are in graduate school. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commitment to diversity, strong mentoring environment, interdisciplinary nature of the program, and an established record of impact on participants' decisions to pursue graduate studies will continue to be major markers of the MSOE-REU. A new feature in the proposed site is to broaden the participants' role in diversity through 1) creation of five K-12 learning modules amidst interaction with teachers and students on campus during summer and 2) enablement of a global perspective among all participants and advisors while two students engage in laser-based materials research at the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research and the University of Johannesburg, South Africa during the middle six weeks of the 10-week REU program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PROJECT DESCRIPTION:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year summer REU renewal site at MSOE, funded by the National Science Foundation's Division of Engineering Education and Centers, will offer seven undergraduates annually opportunities to conduct research in advances (micro-, hybrid, laser-based metal) and applications (bio-nano) of additive manufacturing (AM). The range of new and functional AM applications and materials is growing rapidly and unprecedented technological advances in this field are affecting our daily lives. Also, the AM application, in addition to its unique features of accuracy, reduction in development and delivery time, and reliability, is becoming cost-effective because of the advancement of materials. The international component, with two participants conducting materials science research in a global setting during the middle six weeks of the program provides a new dynamic to all participants enriching their experience and bringing a global perspective besides the collaborative research accomplishments. These two participants will be typically MSOE juniors who have had exposure to AM on campus and have completed materials science course(s) with an adequate preparation to participate in advanced materials research at the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, South Africa and the University of Johannesburg. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The five participants conducting AM applications research on campus will be chosen among applicants from other institutions; they will create learning modules for K-12 outreach from their own research projects and will interact with Project Lead the Way teachers and students on the premises. Bi-weekly virtual meetings will be arranged for interaction among all participants. This ten-week program is geared to attract a broad mix of students, typically 50% women, 25% underrepresented minorities and more than 60% from other institutions. Participants will conduct research in a strongly mentored environment. Students will receive a career-enriching experience from a well-established and well-run program culminating in a final paper, a national conference presentation and a strong desire to pursue a graduate degree. Two additional participants under NSF Center for Compact and Efficient Fluid Power work alongside these students each year, making the team a rich cohort with excellent collaborative research interactions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1460183</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Subha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kumpaty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kumpaty@msoe.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Milwaukee School of Engineering</Name>
      <CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>532023109</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4142777300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1025 N. Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>115E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
