<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Biomolecular Nanophotonic Fabry-Perot Interferometry (BioNanoFPI)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>128356</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CAREER: Biomolecular Nanophotonic Fabry-Perot Interferometry (BioNanoFPI)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposes to design a Biomolecular Nanophotonic Fabry-Perot Interferometer (BioNanoFPI) platform that will allow scalable parallel detection of multiple bio-agents with concentrations in the femtomole range and ease-of-operation using a broadband white light source instead of a laser. The development of a polymer-based micromachined FPI (µFPI) with integrated nanostructures will enable a BioNanoFPI platform that allows for the creation of two-dimensional, highly-multiplexed, inexpensive arrays to conduct large-scale parallel screening of chemical and biomedical libraries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this CAREER project is to establish a significant advancement in biomolecular nanophotonics by theoretical modeling and interfacing liquid-state biopolymers to solid-state nanophotonic and micromachined devices. There are three main components of this career development plan. The scientific component of this project focuses on: (i) the theoretical modeling and understanding of and experimental confirmation of the signal enhancement mechanism of the nanopillar plasmonic substrates, and the interactions between the nanopillar-plasmonic substrates and micromachined Fabry-Perot Interferometry (µFPI); (ii) the theoretical modeling of the dielectric behavior of biopolymers and experimental elucidation of interactions of antibodies and antigens in the nanostructured Fabry-Perot cavity. The technological component of this project focuses on: (i) the development of an inexpensive nanofabrication process to construct a nanopillar array for plasmonic substrates; (ii) the precise control of sub100 nm nanostructure/nanopillar arrays in the µFPI cavity for highly sensitive label free bioassays, and a robust batch fabrication method of nanostructure-filled polymer-based µFPI arrays integrated with micro and nanofluidic networks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: This proposed research will help advance fundamental knowledge of signal enhancement mechanisms of the nanopillar plasmonic substrates and the BioNanoFPI micro/nanosystem. Understanding the fundamental physical mechanism of this micro/nanosystem might trigger other important ideas and innovations for bionanotechnology applications. This research has a broad range of applications to pathogen, disease detection, environmental monitoring and security. In addition, drug screening and discovery can benefit tremendously by using high throughput multiplexed label-free biosensing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: The PI proposes a coherent and comprehensive education, dissemination and outreach component that includes developing a new technical elective course ?Introduction to Nano-biophotonics,? integrating research results with existing nano and micro courses, mentoring graduate, undergraduate and underrepresented students and dissemination and outreach to the local community. A webpage will be designed especially to disseminate the outcomes of ?Introduction to Nano-biophotonics.? The proposed educational and outreach program will be accomplished through the NSF-sponsored REU program at Louisiana Tech to educate undergraduate students and through the NSF-sponsored NERO program to educate women and under-represented students in K-12, high school and prospective students from local small rural and small town schools. The overall educational goal is to help next-generation workforce development by training students to carry out research with sound theory and allowing them to gain hands-on laboratory skills for their advanced careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1461841</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Long</FirstName>
      <LastName>Que</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lque@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
