<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CRII:SHF: Enabling Technologies for Three Dimensional (3D) Millimeter-Wave Integrated Circuits: Through Silicon Via (TSV) Modeling and Design</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174902</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Millimeter-wave (mmW) communications is regarded as an emerging technology to resolve the spectrum shortage issues resulting from the exponential growth of mobile data traffic. This project addresses the fundamental scientific issues and advanced design challenges of the three-dimensional (3D) mmW integrated circuits (ICs) capable of handling very wide system bandwidth required for emerging communication systems. The project will facilitate further advances in 3D integration and broader adoption of this emerging technology in semiconductor manufacturing and electronic design community by offering fundamental understandings in circuit design for beyond ultra-high frequency (UHF) band wireless communications. In addition to technological impact, the PI will develop a broadening participation plan and an educational plan that will immerse students from the underrepresented groups in the field of electronic circuits. Tools and techniques developed in this research will be used for developing and teaching new courses. Outreach activities will span from the high school level up through the graduate level making full use of University Diversity Programs as well as Missouri-Iowa-Nebraska-Kansas Women in Computing Program. Furthermore, the PI will leverage the collaboration with several leading semiconductor companies to set up technical seminars and internship programs for both undergraduate and graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Three dimensional integration with Through Silicon Vias (TSVs) applied to the mmW mobile broadband wireless communications could offer miniaturization opportunities, performance improvement, and power consumption reduction. One of the most critical components and challenges in 3D ICs is the modeling and design of TSVs. In light of the great promise and design challenges of 3D mmW ICs, this project targets to introducing new ideas, developing system prototypes, as well as a new and transformative direction for the advancement of TSV design at all levels - circuits, systems, and computer-aided design (CAD). The proposed TSV modeling and analysis methodologies could be integrated with existing Electronics Design and Automation (EDA) tools. By investigating one of the key components of mmW ICs, this project attempts to lay a foundation for a practical design methodology for the mmW systems with higher reliability, lower power consumption, reduced delay, and increased system miniaturization.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1464424</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yangyi@ittc.ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/02/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7945</Code>
      <Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8228</Code>
      <Text>CISE Resrch Initiatn Initiatve</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
