<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: I/UCRC Phase II: Security and Software Engineering Research Center (S2ERC)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>953975</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dmitri Perkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Security and Software Engineering Research Center (S2ERC) is an Industry/University Cooperative Research Center devoted to applied and basic research addressing security and software engineering issues that plague both industrial (defense and commercial) companies and government agencies. Nearly all companies market products and services that involve software. The software is either a commercial product or a supporting technology for other products or services. Advances in software engineering are critical to the technical dominance and market performance not only of IT companies, but also of producers of products such as aircraft and their components, automobiles, medical devices, sensors, computer-aided diagnostics and robotics. Software developers and customers desire software that costs less, matches users needs, is secure, has credible defenses and fewer defects, executes faster, is easier to update and is completed on time. With societies growing dependence on software, it is important that software engineers build secure software cost-effectively and reliably. The investment in S2ERC has the potential to produce significant results given the expertise at the university sites, the many technical affiliate partners, and the importance of software to our national security and competitiveness. S2ERC researchers are focused on discovering unique solutions for security and software engineering issues which in turn benefits the whole of society as technology is properly constructed and managed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The S2ERC's technical goals are the creation and transfer of innovative software technologies and engineering skills to its affiliates and the training of both graduate and undergraduate students in promising research directions. The S2ERC research initiatives include intrusion detection, ad-hoc network security, wireless security, attack-tolerant systems, trustworthiness in cloud and mobile applications, security and vulnerability analyses, information protection, requirements capturing, software design, software metrics, software feature analysis, software testing, software reliability, user interface design, usability issues, global software development, migrating software to multi-core architectures, visualization environments, interactive collaborative environments, dynamic and static analyses, and testing and model checking for concurrent programs. As S2ERC partners with industry and federal agencies, it is expected that security and software engineering research will continue to integrate into broader programs and activities of national interest.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1464654</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wayne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zage</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wmzage@bsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dolores</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zage</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dzage@gw.bsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ball State University</Name>
      <CityName>Muncie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>473061022</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7652851600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2000 University Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>O214</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>O213</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>O215</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>O384</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>P146</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>P189</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>P280</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>P411</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>170E</Code>
      <Text>Interagency Agreements</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8032</Code>
      <Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8039</Code>
      <Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8237</Code>
      <Text>CISE Interagency Agreements</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
