<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: ELASTIC WAVE RESONATORS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>353004</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract:&lt;br/&gt; Current techniques used for metrology are plagued by slow measurement speed, susceptibility to surface interactions, and some techniques can even deform the measured surface due to tip wear on the surface. Development of new tools to address these challenges could spawn a new era in the area of nano-metrology, and nano-assembly of structures. Such systems can have significance in the area of electronics, optical, and biological applications. This integrated research and education GOALI proposal centers around the development of elastic wave resonators and integration of Ag2Ga nano-needles and photomechanical actuators to enable precise tools for nanomanipulation, nano-metrology and nano-assembly. The principle of elastic wave resonators is a method by which single and multidimensional standing waves propagate at a rate of kHz to MHz along a high aspect ratio micro-scale filament. The magnitude of energy contained within the "wave packet" compared to the flexibility and stiffness of the filament enable pronounced standing waves to be generated and sustained along the filament. The proposal objectives are to investigate the use of nanoscale standing wave probe resonators for metrology, understand the electro-mechanical limits and scaling issues of such resonators, develop mathematical models and develop applications in nano-assembly. The educational aspects of the proposal are utilizing research based undergraduate course in nano-mechanical resonators, internships at industrial sites, graduate level course on nano-mechanical resonators, and opportunities for underrepresented students in this exciting area.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1202190</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Balaji</FirstName>
      <LastName>Panchapakesan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bpanchapakesan@WPI.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Woody</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shane.woody@insitutec.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mehdi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yazdanpanah</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mehdi@nauganeedles.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Louisville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>402021959</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5028523788</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>The Nucleus</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>097E</Code>
      <Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
