<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSBR: Natural History Collections: RUI: Collection Improvement of Marshall University's WV Vertebrate Survey Museum: West Virginia Natural History Updated and Online</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>373256</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Roland Roberts</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal's goal is to save West Virginia's primary natural history collection which includes over 21,000 mammals, amphibians, and reptiles amassed over 70 years. Almost every species that has been described in West Virginia is included, even federally endangered species. This collection is larger than in any other museum nationally and as so is a unique resource and should be developed for training the next generation of biologists who can then study, maintain, and protect Appalachia's animals. However, it is in urgent need of new equipment and curation to ensure its survival. Additionally, once the database is developed it will be possible to make this collection nationally/globally accessible via the Web.&lt;br/&gt; Marshall University is a primarily undergraduate teaching institution in southwestern West Virginia. This collection has tremendous impact on its students and the local Appalachian community. It is used to train students in biology courses and students actively use the collections for research, presentations, and publications. The collections are also used for K-12 outreach focusing on local diversity and conservation ecology. Education outreach and early exposure to science is crucial for the development of a scientifically literate population in West Virginia, an educationally and socioeconomically challenged state.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1203304</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pauley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pauley@marshall.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suzanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strait</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>straitho@marshall.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Marshall University Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Huntington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>257550002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3046964837</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One John Marshall Dr.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1197</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
