<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integration of Natural and Synthetic Biomaterials with Organic Electronics 2012 Symposium Materials Research Society Spring Meeting (MRS) at San Francisco, CA on April 9-13, 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kaiming Ye</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;1205103, Bettinger&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The application of flexible and nonconventional electronics to biomedical engineering has the potential to transform both disciplines. First, flexible devices may be used to unlock mysteries of biological systems at various levels. This symposium provides a great opportunity for scientists and engineers from around the world, and from many different disciplines to share their results and insights in the field of nonconventional electronics with a specific focus on the application of these devices to biomedical engineering. As compared to other symposia on flexible electronics, this unique effort will focus on synergistic interactions with neural engineering and cellular phenomena to address unmet needs. Existing symposia are firmly grounded in either the field of biomaterials, organic electronics, or devices. However, this symposium aims to integrate all three through rich interactions. The NSF funding will increase the affordability of the meeting for oral and poster presenters, who consist mainly of young and emerging investigators in the field with a strong focus on participation by students and postdoctoral researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;This NSF funding will allow the student attendees to become familiar with state of the art in micro-systems, structures, and devices for modulating cell function and medical devices. Specifically, research groups across the country will be encouraged to support undergraduate participation in the poster sessions, as a means of exposing students to a high level of research at an early age. This symposium will also inform investigators at all levels about the unmet needs and emerging opportunities in the areas of research at the inter face between non conventional electronics and biomedical engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1205103</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bettinger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbetting@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Ardie Butch</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dillen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dillen@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
      <CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
