<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Early Career: Instrumentation and technical support for opening new frontiers in energy and environment research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>265542</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Early Career grant supports the acquisition of a GC-Isolink and two years of dedicated technician support in the new Stable Isotope Laboratory in the Department of Geology and Geography at West Virginia University (WVU). The instrument adds new capability of isotope analyses of individual compounds including hydrocarbons and dissolved natural gases. The instrument will be connected to the Delta V Advantage Isotope ratio mass spectrometer via the low flow outlet of Conflo IV device installed in the isotope laboratory. The award will help the WVU Isotope facility to become a core center for advancing research and training in the Earth Sciences with primary focus on the energy and environment topics targeted in the NSF?s Science, Engineering, and Education for Sustainability (SEES) program. Two areas of the PI?s research program that will specifically benefit from this grant include 1) biogeochemical controls on black shale deposition and environmental issues associated with shale gas extraction and, 2) gas-fluid-rock interactions in CO2 sequestration and enhanced geothermal systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will enhance PI?s ability to capitalize and meet goals of the Regional University Alliance (RUA) developed by the Department of Energy and the National Energy Technology Lab to address the emerging energy and environment issues. Acquisition of new instrumentation will greatly strengthen the ongoing research within the Marcellus Shale Initiative, Advanced Energy Initiative, and National Research Center for Coal and Energy; the three campus-wide programs established at WVU for advancing energy research in the region. Therefore, this award opens up new research frontiers across the state and the region. In addition, research programs of a very talented and diverse group of research faculty who are currently engaged and/or getting involved in stable isotope research at WVU will be benefited. The combined research, teaching and hands-on training will provide opportunities for students to develop a better understanding of the isotope basics and its application in several STEM disciplines while also contributing to the early career development of the PI.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1205596</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shikha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shikha.sharma@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>West Virginia University Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>265066845</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3042933998</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 6845</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7693</Code>
      <Text>CZO: CRITICAL ZONE OBSER SOLIC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
