<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>FRG: Structural Phase Transformations in Polymorphic Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>609981</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tania Paskova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Description: This project aims to understand the underlying mechanisms of crystalline-amorphous and polymorphic crystalline-crystalline phase transformations in phase-change nanostructure materials, particularly In2Se3 nanowires, and to understand the multi-level phase-change memory switching process. Specific tasks include (1) understanding the thermodynamics of phase transformations by constructing the temperature-pressure phase diagram; (2) investigating the phase transformation kinetics; (3) establishing the structure-property relation; and (4) elucidating the multiphysics process that underlies the multi-level memory switching. The approach combines experimental and theoretical investigations. The experimental approach utilizes a combination of transmission electron microscopy, Raman and infrared spectroscopy, x-ray diffraction, and multi-functional scanning probe microscopy techniques, with the capability to adjust the temperature and pressure in situ. Complementing the experimental aspect, the theory component based on first-principles calculations investigates the phase stability and its dependence on temperature and pressure, kinetic pathways of the phase transformation, and phase-specific electronic structures and physical properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Description: This project provides a fundamental insight into the structural phase transformation in a technologically important phase-change material. Compared to current mainstream non-volatile memory technologies, such as the Flash memory, phase-change memory offers faster random access time, higher endurance and scalability to the 10-nm range. The knowledge acquired in this study establishes a fundamental basis for developing next-generation non-volatile phase-change memory with multi-level storage capabilities in a single material system. This project provides training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, including those who are members of underrepresented groups. A new seminar course focusing on providing a coherent understanding of phase-change nanomaterials is developed and is team-taught by the PIs. The outreach to the general public is facilitated by developing visual materials, including images and movies, which are posted on YouTube. These materials are a part of the Explore Nano! exhibit in a local science museum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1206960</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wenguang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wzhu3@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yanfei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ygao7@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/21/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yigu@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCluskey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mattmcc@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington State University</Name>
      <CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1589</Code>
      <Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
