<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Singapore</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5836</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Katelyn Patricia Goetz of Wake Forest University to conduct a research project, entitled "Growing highly pure crystals of novel organic semiconductor materials," during the summer of 2012 at Nanyang Technological University in Singapore. The host scientist is Dr. Christian Kloc.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project lies in the creation of novel organic binary compounds composed of varying ratios of donor and acceptor semiconducting opto-electronic materials. These materials are expected to exhibit properties not present in the parent compounds, such as superconductivity, ambipolar charge transport, or metallic behavior. Such properties are technologically relevant because of the wide range of electronic devices they make possible, and interesting from the fundamental standpoint because of their ability to elucidate currently unknown mechanisms of charge transport in organic semiconductor materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209904</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katelyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goetz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Goetz Katelyn P</Name>
      <CityName>Winston Salem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>271063903</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5927</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA, OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
