<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in China</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Christian Lytle of the University of Arizona to conduct a research project, entitled "Development of an ultraviolet probe laser for a mercury-based optical atomic clock," during the summer of 2012 at East China Normal University in Shanghai. The host scientist is Long-Sheng Ma.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project is to improve the stability and accuracy of optical atomic frequency standards (clocks) by developing an ultraviolet laser which can probe a narrow linewidth transition in neutral mercury. This transition is an excellent candidate for achieving clock stabilities beyond that provided by the best ion-based optical clocks. Since the clock transition is in the UV, it has low susceptibility to background head radiation noise, giving it a significant advantage over other optical clocks. Development of more stable atomic clocks is important for many applications including tools to study the change of fundamental physical constants over time. These clocks can also have an impact on Global Positioning System (GPS) technology, as accurate timekeeping is critical to the reliability of the GPS satellite network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209958</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lytle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lytle Christian R</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857192656</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
