<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Australia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5954</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds David M. Hondula of the University of Virginia to conduct a research project, entitled "Forecasting Human Mortality during Extreme Heat Events" during the summer of 2012 at Queensland University of Technology in Brisbane, Queensland, Australia. The host scientist is Adrian Barnett.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research promises a forecasting framework to examine heat-health impacts on humans that is largely absent from the field to date. Previous results establish that human response to extreme heat varies over space and time, yet it remains unknown whether the severity, location, and timing of heat-related deaths can be reliably predicted and mitigated. Investigating the nature of local-scale heat-related mortality presents a significant opportunity to enhance knowledge of the geographic and temporal dimensions of adverse conditions on humans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts include of the potential to improve public health policy and increase capacity to minimize health risks associated with extreme heat through sharing research outcomes with a broad audience of stakeholders who can implement improved mitigation, intervention, education, and communication. Other broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1209837</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hondula</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hondula David M</Name>
      <CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>229034034</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
