<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Holes, Rings and Spiral Structure in the Milky Way</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>260792</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard E. Barvainis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will connect observable features such as spiral arms, rings, and holes in the disks of spiral galaxies to the physical processes that drive their formation and evolution, using a combination of state of art hydrodynamic simulations of galaxy evolution and multi-wavelength radiative transfer simulations. The primary goals are: (1) to identify the physical processes responsible for spiral structure, by comparing model predictions of infrared continuum, neutral hydrogen, and carbon monoxide emission with available data; (2) to explore the origins of multi-armed and few-armed spirals; (3) to determine the spiral pattern speeds and stellar velocity distributions in Milky-Way-sized disks and constrain the role of spiral arms in the dynamical heating and radial migration of stars; and (4) to assess the effects of impacts by satellite galaxies and dark matter clumps. The Principal Investigator and the graduate student supported by the project will produce an atlas of simulated galaxy images for comparison with multi-wavelength data. They will also create an educational website containing an interactive presentation of their simulation atlas and real images; and supplement the web presentation with images and videos for planetaria and museums.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1211258</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elena</FirstName>
      <LastName>D'Onghia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>donghia@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1217</Code>
      <Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1206</Code>
      <Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
