<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Center for Quantum Information and Control</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1330541</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexander Cronin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Quantum information science (QIS) is the interdisciplinary field that investigates how to use systems obeying the laws of quantum mechanics to perform information-processing tasks. This research project provides the core funding for the Center for Quantum Information and Control (CQuIC), based at the University of New Mexico (UNM), with a major component of experimental research at the University of Arizona (UA). CQuIC brings a quantum-information perspective to physics-based research. In particular, research within CQuIC applies the new ideas and techniques of QIS to the state-of-the-art laboratory tasks of controlling the behavior of quantum systems, so these systems can be engineered to do what scientists want them to do, instead of doing only what comes naturally, and of making high-precision, quantum-limited measurements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CQuIC specializes in the training of graduate students and postdoctoral fellows for research careers in QIS. Students at UNM and UA are exposed to a full range of courses and other activities, which provide an interdisciplinary integration of information-theoretic and physics perspectives. CQuIC partners with six external institutions: Sandia National Laboratories; Los Alamos National Laboratory; the Joint Quantum Institute at the University of Maryland, the Australian Centre for Engineered Quantum Systems, headquartered at the University of Queensland; Caltech's Institute for Quantum Information and Matter; and the Brazilian National Institute of Science and Technology for Quantum Information. These partnerships provide a two-way flow of ideas and people and thus expand the theoretical and experimental capabilities available to CQuIC and the partnering institutions. CQuIC is the administrative home for the Southwest Quantum Information and Technology (SQuInT) Network. A consortium of 22 node institutions, including research universities, undergraduate colleges, national and industrial laboratories, and international centers for QIS, SQuInT promotes QIS research at and collaborations among its node institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1212445</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Poul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jessen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>poul.jessen@optics.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Deutsch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ideutsch@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Caves</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccaves@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7281</Code>
      <Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7203</Code>
      <Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7281</Code>
      <Text>QUATM INFO &amp; REVOLUTIONARY COM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
