<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Interfacial Water-Mediated Structural Transformations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>432221</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, supported by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program (CSDM) of the Division of Chemistry, Prof. Dor Ben-Amotz of Purdue University and his graduate and undergraduate research students will use hydration-shell vibrational spectroscopy (especially Raman scattering spectroscopy), nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy (NMR) and other experimental, computer simulation, and theoretical modeling strategies to address key questions pertaining to water-mediated processes occurring molecular interfaces, including how solute molecules influence water structure and how such structure changes influence water-mediated chemical interactions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results will be use to better understand and predict how water participates in processes of relevance to the biological self-assembly as well as green chemical manufacturing, geological petroleum recovery, and environmental remediation. Besides the broad impact of the research on several areas of science, Prof. Ben-Amotz will continue to provide his research students with excellent training in the development and application of experimental and theoretical tools and innovation strategies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1213338</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ben-Amotz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bendor@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURE, DYNAMIC &amp; MECHANISM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
