<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Collaborative Research on Photodegradation of Oxygenated Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons on Environmental Interfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Environmental Chemical Sciences Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation supports Professors Krishna Foster of California State University- Los Angeles and Donald Dabdub of the University of California- Irvine in a collaborative effort that will investigate the chemical kinetics of oxy-polyaromatic hydrocarbons (oxy-PAH) in surrogates of particulate matter to elucidate the impact of this chemistry on the oxidizing capacity of the lower atmosphere. Photolytically excited oxy-PAH readily transfer energy to ground state molecular oxygen, producing the reactive oxygen species singlet molecular oxygen. This proposal is based on the premise that these reactions may take place on aged particulate matter, and consequently, impacts the oxidation capacity of the lower atmosphere. Innovative aspects of the proposal include the application of emerging quantitative HPLC/MS techniques for oxy-PAH to the discipline of chemical kinetics and MS analysis of gaseous mixtures. This is an interdisciplinary, collaborative project between a chemistry professor at a non-Ph.D. granting Hispanic Serving Institution and an engineering professor at a local Ph.D. granting institution. This model maximizes resources by advancing science and developing human resources simultaneously. Success of the proposed research will improve air quality models, and consequently, impact millions of people, especially those living in urban areas. The inclusion of undergraduates from groups underrepresented in the sciences, reflective of the California State University- Los Angeles population, will be a high priority. This project has the potential to increase the number of underrepresented students who select careers in the chemical sciences and pursue graduate education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1213639</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Krishna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Foster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kfoster@calstatela.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State L A University Auxiliary Services Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900324221</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3233434970</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5151 State University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6882</Code>
      <Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
