<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Structure and Dynamics of Heterogeneous Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>555000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sarah Stoll</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Steven L. Bernasek and his coworkers at Princeton University will investigate the fundamental mechanisms of heterogeneous reaction systems. The function of organic corrosion inhibitors in corrosive fluid environments will be examined using electrochemical methods and photoelectron spectroscopy. The structure and reactivity of self-assembled organic monolayer surfaces will be studied using scanning probe microscopy, with a focus on understanding the formation of chiral monolayers and nanopatterned surfaces. Plasmonic sensors based on ordered arrays of gold nanodots deposited on oxide substrates will be used to monitor surface reaction dynamics of catalytic oxidation reactions. This work will be carried out in close connection to measurements of the internal state distributions of the products of these catalytic oxidation reactions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will have broad impact on the education of graduate and undergraduate research students. The interdisciplinary nature of the work carried out in this project provides an excellent training ground for the development of capable researchers. Interactions with industrial collaborators expose research students to questions of commercial importance. The fundamental understanding obtained in this research will have important impact in the development of new corrosion inhibitors, in the understanding of self-assembly at surfaces, and in the clarification of the mechanisms of heterogeneous catalytic oxidation processes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1213216</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bernasek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sberna@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/13/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bocarsly</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bocarsly@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
