<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>"Photo-click" - Photocatalysis, Photopolymerization, and Photomodification via the Cu(I) Catalyzed Azide-Alkyne Reaction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Christopher Bowman of the University of Colorado will develop methodologies for photoinitiating the copper-catalyzed alkyne-azide cycloaddition (CuAAC) reaction. The approach to this research problem involves understanding and broadening the chemical mechanisms needed to photogenerate the copper(I) complex that ultimately initiates this reaction; scoping the capabilities of this process; elaborating techniques that enable the photopatterning of surfaces and 3D substrates with maximum precision and resolution; and developing simultaneous radical polymerization reactions that accompany the CuAAC reaction with independent control of the relative rates of the two processes. The broader impacts involve training and mentoring undergraduate and graduate students, broadly disseminating research results, and starting a "redshirt" program to enlarge the pool of students qualified for a Ph.D. program and thereby providing more opportunities to diversify the graduate student body in chemical sciences and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Polymers are found in many aspects of everyday life, including food packaging, structural materials for automotive and aerospace transportation, and lightweight electronic devices. This research may lead to the development of simple, robust reaction chemistries that are readily and cheaply implemented across a broad spectrum of polymer applications. By using light to control when and where the reaction proceeds, polymer networks can be formed with a great deal of three-dimensional precision. Such chemistry would impact a range of technologies including coatings, biomedical materials, and flexible electronics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1214109</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bowman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bowmanc@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1948</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
