<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Astrophysical Probes of Beyond Standard Model Physics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Keith R. Dienes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professor Manoj Kaplinghat at the University of California, Irvine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the next few years, astrophysical observations will play a pivotal role in the effort to detect dark matter through non-gravitational means. The focus in this project will be on two promising ways forward. One will be to use observations of gamma-rays towards the luminous satellites of the Milky Way in order to constrain or detect weak-scale thermal dark matter. Weak-scale thermal dark matter is the most widely studied dark-matter candidate and is motivated by particle-physics models at the high (electroweak-scale) energies currently being probed at the Large Hadron Collider. The other way forward will be to develop simplified models to describe dark-matter halo density profiles in the presence of significant self-interactions and compare to observations. As part of the project, the PI will provide a map between these preferred models and the underlying particle-physics models in which such phenomenology is realized. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is also envisioned to have significant broader impacts. The PI will develop a cosmology and particle-physics cluster for the California State Summer School for Mathematics and Science (i.e., the "COSMOS Program" at UC Irvine). COSMOS is a program for motivated high-school students and currently has a cluster in astronomy at UC Irvine but none in particle physics. Based on input from faculty teaching the astronomy cluster, it is envisioned that a particle physics and cosmology module will be highly subscribed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1214648</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Manoj</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaplinghat</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkapling@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1288</Code>
      <Text>Particle Astrophysics &amp; Cosmol</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
