<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Azulene-bridged Organometallics: New Platforms for Charge Delocalization and Transport at the Nanoscale</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Mikhail Barybin of the University of Kansas will study charge delocalization and transport within the 2,6-azulenic framework. The approach is to synthesize novel azulenic and bis-azulenic molecules linearly terminated with isocyano, mercapto, or cyano groups; to form and characterize self-assembled monolayer (SAM) films and nanografted patterns of these compounds on metal surfaces; to synthesize and study discrete metal complexes of these ligands to understand the ligand interactions with metal ions; and to probe the conductivity of the azulenic and bis-azulenic SAM films The broader impacts involve training undergraduate and graduate students in an interdisciplinary research environment, developing a new freshman honors course on the "Nanotech Revolution," and working with Northeastern State University (a predominantly Native American student institution) to bring students to the University of Kansas for undergraduate research experiences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computing using molecules has the potential to generate ultrasmall devices that use little power; however, many significant technical hurdles must be overcome to realize the benefits of molecular level devices. This work will further our understanding how molecules transport charges between two contacts and will afford novel platforms for developing advanced materials relevant to a variety of nanotechnological areas, including organic electronics. Such work could also impact the design of solar cells, molecular switches, and conducting polymers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1214102</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mikhail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barybin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbarybin@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1948</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
