<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: A Wafer-Scale Flat-Panel X-ray Source with Raster Control</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>148339</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to demonstrate key enabling technologies for a novel medical imaging x-­&amp;#8208;ray source. For over a century, medical imaging has relied on fundamentally the same approach to generate x-­&amp;#8208;rays: production in vacuum tubes, which are fragile, heavy, not portable, and expensive. This proposal presents a method that allows the x-­&amp;#8208;ray source to move from tubes to a robust flat-­&amp;#8208;panel system produced in much the same way as modern televisions; matching state-­&amp;#8208;of-­&amp;#8208;the-­&amp;#8208;art flat-­&amp;#8208;panel Digital Radiology (DR) detector and dramatically changing the economics and application profile of x-­&amp;#8208;ray devices. The anticipated outcome of Phase I is a proof-­&amp;#8208;of-­&amp;#8208;concept showing sufficient high-­&amp;#8208;quality x-­&amp;#8208;ray flux can be generated from the proposed portable flat-­&amp;#8208;panel source and that the array of emitters can be addressed (rastered). Simulations will also show that these devices will perform as expected and conform to the clinical needs and technical standards in radiology. Microfabrication will be used to produce a prototype system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is a dramatic shift in how medical imaging is delivered to the patient. The x-­&amp;#8208;ray source being developed under this proposal would be highly portable and robust. Such a device could be carried by first responders, but it would also improve portable x-­&amp;#8208; ray radiology within the hospital. Current equipment for use in the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) and Emergency Room (ER), where radiology must travel to the patient is bulky, cumbersome and uncomfortable in use. The device proposed would reduce the cost and discomfort associated with such equipment, as well as fundamentally changing the economics of the fixed radiology in hospitals. The proposed technology has the potential to reduce patient radiation exposure while maintaining image quality, and improve advanced imaging including dual energy x-­&amp;#8208;ray scans, mammography, tomosynthesis and fluoroscopy through Region of Interest selection: it can help save lives, provide healthcare to a wider population at lower costs, and in locations not previously accessible.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1215594</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schmiedehausen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Kristin@radius-health.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/17/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Radius Diagnostics Research</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900957227</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3104353970</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CNSI; Building 114; MC 722710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
