<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium: Growing the Next Generation in Plant Genomics, A Symposium to be held at Botany 2012; 7-11 July; Columbus, Ohio</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7462</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Ashley Egan (East Carolina University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Next generation sequencing techniques are becoming mainstream in life sciences research, providing new avenues for addressing novel and important questions. Only now, however, are the ramifications of these technological advances being seen for botanical science. This award will provide partial support of a symposium entitled "Growing the Next Generation in Plant Genomics", which will be held as part of the Botany 2012 Meeting at the Greater Columbus Convention Center in Columbus, Ohio, 7-11 July, 2012. This annual conference is spearheaded by the Botanical Society of America but also includes participation by a number of other societies including the American Bryological and Lichenological Society, the American Fern Society, the American Society of Plant Taxonomists, and the Canadian Botanical Association/L'Association Canadienne de Botanique. This symposium will bring together leading scientists to share research in which they have employed next generation sequencing methods and discuss how these techniques have opened up their research to new ideas and trajectories. The symposium will provide attendees with examples of how next generation sequencing methods can be used to address questions in plant biology. As such, the meeting will provide opportunities for students and young investigators to interact with leading scientists in the field, see how next generation sequencing methods can be applied to botanical questions, and establish collaborations to further learning and research development. NSF funding will be used to broaden participation of young scientists, particularly women and under-represented minorities, as speakers in the symposium.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1215885</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ashley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Egan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>egana@si.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>East Carolina University</Name>
      <CityName>Greenville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>278584353</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2523289540</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9109</Code>
      <Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
