<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Computational Framework for Non-asymptotic Homogenization with Applications to Metamaterials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>148426</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leland M. Jameson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project is aimed at developing a non-asymptotic homogenization&lt;br/&gt;theory of Maxwell's equations in artificial periodic composites&lt;br/&gt;(metamaterials). Currently, there is a consensus that sufficiently&lt;br/&gt;large lattice cell sizes are necessary for some nontrivial physical&lt;br/&gt;effects to occur in such structures. (The most intriguing of these&lt;br/&gt;effects is high-frequency magnetism.) Classical homogenization&lt;br/&gt;theories work well in the zero-cell-size limit but are difficult to&lt;br/&gt;apply to large metamaterial cells. In contrast, the proposed theory is&lt;br/&gt;non-asymptotic and does not involve any series expansions with respect&lt;br/&gt;to the cell size. The electromagnetic field in the material is&lt;br/&gt;approximated by a finite set of functions (modes) usually but not&lt;br/&gt;necessarily Trefftz functions such as Bloch waves. The coarse-grained&lt;br/&gt;fields and flux densities are defined via curl-conforming and&lt;br/&gt;div-conforming interpolations, respectively. A linear map between&lt;br/&gt;these interpolants is established and defines an extended material&lt;br/&gt;tensor. In a certain canonical basis, this extended tensor has a&lt;br/&gt;classical block of 36 local parameters and a novel block quantifying&lt;br/&gt;nonlocal effects. From the differential-geometric perspective, this&lt;br/&gt;constitutive relationship can be viewed as a realization of&lt;br/&gt;Bossavit-Hiptmair's discrete Hodge operators (linear maps between&lt;br/&gt;discretized 1-forms that correspond to vector fields and 2-forms that&lt;br/&gt;correspond to fluxes).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the last decade, metamaterials have attracted unprecedented&lt;br/&gt;attention due to a variety of potential applications that include&lt;br/&gt;superlensing, electromagnetic cloaking, electromagnetically-induced&lt;br/&gt;transparency, efficient antennas, and more. Experimental&lt;br/&gt;demonstrations of these effects have been limited to proofs of&lt;br/&gt;principle and at optical frequencies have so far been incomplete.&lt;br/&gt;Subwavelength optical imaging has been achieved only in the&lt;br/&gt;quasi-static (near-field) regime, standard for the more conventional&lt;br/&gt;near-field optics; the so-called "carpet cloak" conceals surface bumps&lt;br/&gt;rather than 3D objects, and so on. Moreover, applications that do not&lt;br/&gt;depend critically on the effective medium description of metamaterials&lt;br/&gt;appear to be more easily achievable than the ones that do. The latter&lt;br/&gt;group includes, notably, superlensing and cloaking. This suggests&lt;br/&gt;that, to make further progress, theoretical and mathematical issues at&lt;br/&gt;the heart of metamaterial science must be unambiguously resolved. The&lt;br/&gt;main problem can be stated as follows. Given the composition of a&lt;br/&gt;metamaterial cell and the operating frequency, determine whether this&lt;br/&gt;metamaterial can be reasonably described as a continuous medium with&lt;br/&gt;some effective parameters, just like any natural optical material; if&lt;br/&gt;the answer is positive, develop a rigorous methodology for such a&lt;br/&gt;description. The proposed research is aimed at solving this problem in&lt;br/&gt;the most difficult case when the cell size of the composite is an&lt;br/&gt;appreciable fraction of the wavelength of light. The methodology, once&lt;br/&gt;developed, will allow the scientific community to delineate the&lt;br/&gt;possible from the impossible in the field of metamaterials.&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed research is in the development&lt;br/&gt;of a new paradigm of non-asymptotic homogenization, of new&lt;br/&gt;computational methods related to it, and in the application of the&lt;br/&gt;proposed methodology to electromagnetic metamaterials, allowing one to&lt;br/&gt;gain a much deeper understanding of their properties and limitations.&lt;br/&gt;As a new area of research, non-asymptotic homogenization will also&lt;br/&gt;have a broader technical impact in other areas of applied physics and&lt;br/&gt;engineering, such as acoustics, heat transfer and possibly elasticity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1216970</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vadim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Markel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vmarkel@mail.med.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
