<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSR: Small: Rethinking the OS/Network Boundary</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>494353</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Operating systems and networks developed largely independently, due to&lt;br/&gt;the nature of their development -- operating systems were developed by&lt;br/&gt;groups within organizations/companies, while networking requiring&lt;br/&gt;interoperability was developed across organizations. As a result of&lt;br/&gt;this development history, the boundary between the networking&lt;br/&gt;subsystem and the rest of the operating system has remained largely&lt;br/&gt;opaque, with little information regarding the performance or progress&lt;br/&gt;of transfers being communicated to applications. This research&lt;br/&gt;addresses this limitation by exploring a richer boundary interface&lt;br/&gt;that allows programs to see the ongoing behavior of network transfers&lt;br/&gt;and to control their operation at a fine granularity. These interfaces&lt;br/&gt;would augment, rather than replace, the existing interfaces, so the&lt;br/&gt;portions of programs that are satisfied with the current interfaces&lt;br/&gt;could continue unmodified, and developers could change only the&lt;br/&gt;portions that can benefit from richer information. This research is&lt;br/&gt;largely experimental in nature, and will combine the design and&lt;br/&gt;implementation of new interface abstractions along with the&lt;br/&gt;development of new or modified programs to take advantage of these&lt;br/&gt;interfaces. In addition to the design work associated with the&lt;br/&gt;interfaces, additional criteria for success include examining the&lt;br/&gt;performance and delay behavior of modified applications, and the&lt;br/&gt;effort needed to modify such applications. The expected results from&lt;br/&gt;this work include applications that can more precisely control their&lt;br/&gt;networking behavior, reducing memory and processor usage, improving&lt;br/&gt;energy efficiency, and improving delay behavior. High-performance or&lt;br/&gt;time-sensitive applications, such as networked video, should benefit&lt;br/&gt;from this research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1217782</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vivek</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vivek@cs.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
