<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Conference on Ferromagnetic Shape Memory Alloys 2013; Boise, Idaho; June 2013 for 4 - 5 days</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diana Farkas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Ferromagnetic shape memory alloys are multifunctional materials that exhibit coupling between magnetic and structural order, producing very large magnetic-field-induced strains. The magnetic shape memory (MSM) effect arises through the magnetic-field-induced motion of twin boundaries. Compared to other technologies, MSM actuators offer several benefits. They are simple and reliable to construct; they provide a stroke that is 100 times longer than piezoelectric materials with a fast response time (0.1 ms); they generate a large work output, offer high position accuracy and dynamic range, and consume little power. Recent advances in the field of MSM alloys is the topic of the International Conference on Ferromagnetic Shape Memory Alloys (ICFSMA'13) to be held during the 2nd or 3rd week of June, 2013, in Boise, ID. This is the Fourth International Symposium on Ferromagnetic Shape Memory Alloys, the first of which was held in 2007. ICFSMA has become the preeminent conference for international researchers in the field of magnetic shape memory alloys. NSF funds will be used to offset the expenses of graduate students, postdoctoral associates, junior faculty, and selected invited speakers to attend the meeting. The funds will also be used to publicize and promote the conference via a web page. This conference will provide participants with an overview of MSM research from magneto-mechanics to more recently discovered properties and phenomena in a variety of material morphologies, including thin films, micro-systems, composites, foams and mats. Magneto-caloric and baro-caloric effects will also be covered. The participants will be expected to discuss the most current research in the field in order to advance the uses of these multifunctional materials between potential academic and industrial partners. Modeling and simulation, from the atomic to the microscale to inform theory, structure, and magnetism, will be emphasized. Interest among women will be especially encouraged in a field which is currently dominated largely by male researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1217842</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mullner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>petermullner@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Boise State University</Name>
      <CityName>Boise</CityName>
      <ZipCode>837250001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2084261574</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1910 University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Idaho</StateName>
      <StateCode>ID</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1771</Code>
      <Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
