<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AF: Small: Local Computation Algorithms</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Balasubramanian Kalyanasundaram</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The ubiquitousness of massive data sets presents&lt;br/&gt;great challenges. The difficulty of dealing with massive data&lt;br/&gt;sets is especially formidable when attempting to&lt;br/&gt;solve computational problems in which both the inputs&lt;br/&gt;and the outputs to the computation are large.&lt;br/&gt;In such a situation, it would be useful if one could find&lt;br/&gt;faster ways of computing just the portion of the output that is required&lt;br/&gt;by the user.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to study "local computation algorithms",&lt;br/&gt;namely algorithms that quickly compute only the portions of the&lt;br/&gt;output that are required by the user,&lt;br/&gt;without performing the full computation.&lt;br/&gt;In particular, local computation algorithms&lt;br/&gt;view only a miniscule portion of the input.&lt;br/&gt;The PI considers a broad based approach, studying the application of&lt;br/&gt;local computation algorithms to a range of problems and&lt;br/&gt;settings within algorithm design.&lt;br/&gt;The focus of this research is on the question of when local computations&lt;br/&gt;can be done in time that is sub-linear in the size of the input and output.&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will develop techniques for constructing&lt;br/&gt;such algorithms and for understanding when such algorithms are&lt;br/&gt;not possible.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will leverage known results from sub-linear time&lt;br/&gt;algorithms, which for the most part have focused on the somewhat&lt;br/&gt;different setting of computational&lt;br/&gt;problems in which the inputs are large but the outputs are small.&lt;br/&gt;In addition, the project will investigate well-studied&lt;br/&gt;classes of algorithmic techniques and focus on modifying them for&lt;br/&gt;use in this new setting. Such classes include algorithmic techniques&lt;br/&gt;first developed for parallel and distributed algorithms, as well as the&lt;br/&gt;extensively used greedy method.&lt;br/&gt;Problems from combinatorial optimization, graph theory and compressibility&lt;br/&gt;of strings will be studied.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1217423</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronitt</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rubinfeld</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ronitt@csail.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7796</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7926</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
