<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Statistical Analysis of Neural Data (SAND)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gabor J. Szekely</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop Statistical Analysis of Neural Data (SAND6) is planned for May 31-June 2, 2012 at the Center for the Neural Basis of Cognition, run jointly by Carnegie Mellon University and the University of Pittsburgh.&lt;br/&gt;SAND6 will bring together neurophysiologists, statisticians, physicists, and computer scientists who are interested in quantitative analysis of neuronal data. There will be 5 scientific sessions, at which 8 keynote investigators and 16 junior investigators will speak. There will also be a poster session. Authors will be encouraged to submit papers to the Journal of Computational Neuroscience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SAND6 is the sixth workshop in a series that began in 2002. The workshops are held in even years during the spring at the Center for the Neural Basis of Cognition, run jointly by Carnegie Mellon University and the University of Pittsburgh. The objectives of the workshop are to define important problems in neuronal data analysis and useful strategies for attacking them; foster communication between experimental neuroscientists and those trained in statistical and computational methods; and provide further dissemination of the findings presented at the workshop via a set of peer-reviewed articles. Secondary objectives are to encourage young researchers, including graduate students, to present their work; expose young researchers to important challenges and opportunities in this interdisciplinary domain, while providing a small meeting atmosphere to facilitate the interaction of young researchers with senior colleagues; and include as participants women, under-represented minorities and persons with disabilities who might benefit from the small workshop environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1219417</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kass</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kass@stat.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
