<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STEM Women of Color Conclave</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1995899</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Earnestine P. Easter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>GPRA Strategic Management, Inc. is developing a series of workshops to bring national attention to the issues related to minority women in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) fields in academia. The goal of the "STEM Women of Color Conclave" is to provide a national forum in which women of color in institutions of higher education can form the collective intelligence necessary for building a national network, harnessing a centralized body of knowledge and best practices related to women of color and promoting the personal and professional development of women of color in the academy. The participants have the opportunity to address the special challenges facing women of color in the academy in STEM fields where they are underrepresented at every faculty level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each workshop will inform and disseminate current research findings related specifically to the women of color research agenda; build strategic alliances across cultural and racial groups to encourage and support the advancement of women of color to institutional, national and global STEM leadership positions; develop and sustain a national network of mentors, role models and colleagues with similar personal and research interests; and promote national attention to the issues related to women of color in the academic STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1220582</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carmen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rivera</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crivera@gprasm.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>GPRA Strategic Management, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>White Plains</CityName>
      <ZipCode>206954428</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2405188667</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3929 Shaftsbury Court</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7568</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCE-PAID</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
