<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Examining the intersections of place-making and development in the Pribilof Islands, Alaska</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14962</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anna Kerttula de Echave</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed research focuses on developing a mixed methods approach to research into the complex social, economic and environmental issues facing the Pribilof Islands. The student, Lyons, proposes using a place-making approach to understanding community instead of a more standard development approach. Lyons is a NSF-funded Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship (IGERT) student at the University of Alaska-Fairbanks, and her research focuses on integrating ecological and anthropological data into tools that can inform fisheries and management decisions in the fishery-dependent communities of St. Paul and St. George in the Pribilof Islands of Alaska. With the use of a social-ecological system framework (that refers to complex interactions between the social and ecological environments) in which she highlights the notion of "place-making (in which a community establishes a coherent sense of place), this dissertation research attempts to develop techniques that can integrate the detailed ethnographic data collected by social scientists into management and policy decision-making.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1224181</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Courtney</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carothers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clcarothers@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5221</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5221</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
