<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for U.S. Participants at the 15th International Congress on Catalysis (July 1-6, 2012 / Munich, Germany)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George J. Antos</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1228024&lt;br/&gt;Wachs &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a continued and growing world interest in the role catalysts play in synthesis of petroleum- and renewable-based products for fuels, specialty chemicals, environmental controls and process efficiency. The importance of catalysis is reflected by the fact that 25-30% of all manufactured goods in the U.S. involve at least one catalytic step. Therefore, it is crucial for U.S. scientists to participate in activities that foster collaborations and new ideas in an area that impacts over a quarter of the U.S. economy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal requests partial travel support for 25 U.S. academic participants so they may participate in the 15th International Congress on Catalysis. The 15th International Congress on Catalysis which will be held in Munich, Germany on July 1-6, 2012, will bring together experts from around the world to discuss all the developments on the practical and new understanding in catalysis over the last four years. The scope of the 15th International Congress will include all types of catalysis (homogeneous, heterogeneous and others) related to innovative and current topics, with emphasis on prediction of catalyst performance and characteristics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the primary purposes of this travel grant is to provide support for junior faculty to participate, as well as to support women and underrepresented minority candidates. This is an ideal opportunity for these groups to establish international collaborations as well as to understand the cutting edge of catalytic science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1228024</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jingguang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgchen@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Israel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wachs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>iew0@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lehigh University</Name>
      <CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>044E</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
