<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>HCC: Doctoral Symposium at the Seventh International Conference on the Theory and Application of Diagrams</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20195</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ephraim P. Glinert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is funding to support a Doctoral Consortium (workshop) for approximately 12 graduate students, along with a panel of 4 distinguished research faculty mentors. The event will take place in conjunction with the Seventh International Conference on the Theory and Application of Diagrams (DIAGRAMS 2012), to be held July 2-6, 2012, on the campus of the University of Kent, UK. Diagrams are wide-ranging and open-ended representations that include sketches, drawings, charts, pictures, 2D and 3D geometric models, and maps. They are a vital tool in human communication in areas such as art and science, as well as commerce and industry. A better understanding of how effective diagrams can be generated and used has the potential to produce transformative advances in these areas. DIAGRAMS is a bi-annual, international conference series that covers all aspects of research on the theory and application of diagrams. The goals of the interdisciplinary conference are to present and discuss (a) state-of-the-art research on computational, cognitive and socio-cultural theories, models and techniques of reasoning with diagrammatic representations, and (b) cutting-edge intelligent and interactive information technologies for using diagrammatic representations in supporting human reasoning. Research topics include understanding diagrammatic reasoning in humans, understanding the use of diagrammatic representation for communication, developing techniques for automated diagrammatic reasoning, and designing tools for use of diagrammatic representations. DIAGRAMS is the only conference that provides a united forum for all areas that are concerned with the study of diagrams. The conference series is overseen by the Diagrams Steering Committee with a rotating membership; more information is available at the conference website http://www.diagrams-conference.org/2012. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of the DIAGRAMS 2012 Doctoral Consortium is to increase the exposure and visibility of young graduate student researchers in these areas. The workshop will be a research-focused day-long meeting that affords participants an opportunity to present their work and get feedback from established researchers in the field, who will be present to comment on the young researchers' presentations in an informal and constructive environment. Each invited participant will be asked to give a short talk, which will be followed by discussion and critiquing. For some students, this may be their first opportunity to give a research talk outside their home institutions, which will help prepare them for future scholarly discussions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: DIAGRAMS 2012 will significantly increase our understanding of diagrammatic reasoning in humans and machines, and will add momentum to the development of new information technologies for the use of diagrammatic representations in support of human reasoning. The conference will help develop human research capital by enabling interactions between senior and junior researchers and by catalyzing new collaborations. The doctoral consortium will increase the exposure and visibility of young graduate student researchers in these areas, and help train them by providing early input from senior researchers in the field in an interactive and constructive environment. The social network among this next generation of researchers, and the relationships with senior researchers, created by the workshop will play a critical role in their enculturation into the profession. The organizers will be proactive in order to ensure that both students and faculty are a diverse group across multiple dimensions including nationality, scientific discipline, gender, institutional affiliation, and under-represented minority status.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1228772</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nathaniel.miller@unco.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Northern Colorado</Name>
      <CityName>Greeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>806396900</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9703511932</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
