<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Institutional Settings and the Transmission of Social Scientific Knowledge</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>37001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda Layne</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Compared to understandings of the social causes of the creation and diffusion of biological and physical sciences, how social scientific knowledge is developed and deployed is less well understood. This study fills that gap by analyzing how training sessions transmit tacit and explicit knowledges, and how that transmission process feeds back to laboratory and other knowledge production settings. To do so, a team of interdisciplinary investigators examine a selection of over one thousand hours of training videos that seek to transmit psychological science to users. The findings provide new insights about how varied settings and modes of transmission shape the distribution and uptake of social science research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project enhances infrastructure for social science research and education by fostering collaborations between institutions, and training of undergraduate and graduate student researchers. It also creates an online database that is available to other analysts of the dynamics of the creation and deployment of psychological sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1229867</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miles</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>joemiles@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
