<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a High Resolution Mass Spectrometer for Small Molecule Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>315033</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) Program that is also co-funded by the Chemical Catalysis Program, Professor Charles Riordan from the University of Delaware and colleagues Donald Watson and Joel Rosenthal will acquire a high-resolution mass spectrometer (HRMS). The proposal is aimed at enhancing research training and education at all levels, especially in areas such as (a) reaction discovery and surface patterning; (b) bacterial activation of the innate immune system; (c) microbial energy metabolism; (d) catalytic upgrading of biomass-derived chemical intermediates;(e) nickel-oxygen chemistry; (f) solar fuels and renewable energy; (g) preparation, reactivity, and catalytic activity of low-valent chromium complexes; (h) development of transition metal catalyzed reactions; and (i) nickel- and copper-catalyzed reactions of acetals and carboxylates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A high resolution mass spectrometer analyzes samples by creating ions from it which are injected into the spectrometer where their mass/charge ratios are measured to high accuracy. The mass information that is obtained provides qualitative and quantitative information on the chemical composition of the sample. This instrument uses a variety of tools to inject the sample and ionize it, which will allow a broad range of small molecules to be analyzed from liquids to solids. The instrumentation provided by this award will provide faculty and students in several departments the opportunity to pursue research projects using state-of-the-art instrumentation. It will also be used in several laboratory courses to train undergraduate students in the use of this widely employed analytical tool. The mass spectrometer facility at the university of Delaware will partner and share the instrument with a number of institutions in the region including, Delaware State University, Lincoln University, Washington University, Bryn Mawr College and Drexel University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1229234</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rosenthal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>joelr@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Watson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dawatson@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Riordan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>riordan@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1108</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1982</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8650</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
