<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Trapped Microbubbles in Polymer MEMS Microcapsules as a Novel Pressure Sensing Principle Based on Electrochemical Impedance Transduction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>323451</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence S. Goldberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Meng, Ellis&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Southern California&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectrual Merit: The objective of this proposal is the investigation and development of novel microbubble-based pressure transducers enabled by polymer microelectromechanical systems and electrochemical impedance-based detection. The new microsensing modality is based on the principle that microbubbles can respond instantaneously to pressure variations. This approach addresses two major challenges in pressure sensing: (1) miniaturization and automation of microbubble-based pressure sensing, and (2) lack of safe and reliable implantable pressure sensors. Bubble-based sensing offers a unique set of advantages including operation in wet environments without specialized packaging, simple implementation, biocompatible construction, extremely small footprint, and low power operation. Fundamental factors that affect microbubble-based pressure sensor performance as well as microbubble response will be investigated and thereby demonstrate the potential of this transduction method for in vivo applications. New sensor structures, fabrication processes, and sensor arrays on flexible substrates will be achieved. Electrochemical and environmental conditions that affect sensor performance will be investigated. Instantaneous and real-time pressure measurement in wet environments simulating in vivo conditions will be demonstrated. These compact, low power sensors have the potential to provide advanced wireless health monitoring capability for telemedicine and remote patient monitoring and thus, thus chronic pressure sensing can inform evidenced-based care resulting in improved quality of life.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Successful demonstration of microbubble technology will provide a new pressure sensing modality and enable future innovative wireless applications such as monitoring of physiological pressures implicated as disease risk factors, providing immediate access to actionable pressure data to drive timely therapeutic interventions. This research effort will provide new research opportunities for both graduate and undergraduate students pertaining to polymer microfabrication, novel sensor technologies, and biomedical sensing applications. Emphasis is placed on the recruitment and involvement of underrepresented groups. Students at all levels will be trained to share research results through local and international conference presentations and write up their results in refereed journal publications. Students will also assist in the integration of research and education by generating laboratory demonstration modules and laboratory exercises suitable for a broad range of educational backgrounds based on the new sensing modality. Both live and digital formats will be used such that these educational products can be disseminated both locally and nationwide. These research products will be incorporated into an undergraduate course and a textbook on biomedical microdevices. This multifaceted research and educational program will provide multidisciplinary training to STEM students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1231994</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ellismen@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>104E</Code>
      <Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
