<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Structural, Climate, and Communication Dynamics of Innovative Inter-Organizational Project Teams</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>320855</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project assesses how communication behaviors and programs in inter-organizational project teams contribute to effective implementation of innovative practices and overall project quality. The project-based nature of the construction industry introduces many challenges, one of which is the collaboration process among key participants and their contracting organizations. This challenge is magnified in sustainable building projects where interdisciplinary collaboration is most needed. Accordingly, the project examines the introduction and use of integrated project delivery (IPD) in project teams as an innovation in the architecture, engineering, and construction industry. As an initial step, case studies are used to follow conventional theoretical models that consider the innovation's match to the organizations' structure, climate, and values. Then key communication behaviors of inter-organizational project team members, who not only serve as conduits in information flow and champions of working together, but also are creators of meaning and influencers of others' attitudes, will be examined. Consequently, the study will explore communication behaviors related to team dynamics, negotiation, and role change and their relationship to commitment to IPD and project outcomes across 20 inter-organizational project teams engaged in sustainable buildings projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The long-term goal is to develop an integrated organizational communication model for industry that fosters collaborative long-term relationships, product quality, and innovativeness. This research represents an important, continuing step toward enhancing sustainable building practices via effective coordination mechanisms and at the broader level, the identification of communication behaviors central to inter-organizational project teams. Results will contribute to interdisciplinary teaching modules and be widely disseminated. The research outcomes will be used to inspire graduate students; especially women in interdisciplinary research via CrossTalks to be given at Michigan State University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1231206</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vernon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vmiller@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sinem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Korkmaz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>korkmaz@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8031</Code>
      <Text>Science of Organizations</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>019Z</Code>
      <Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8031</Code>
      <Text>Education Products</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
