<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Long-Term Wind Engineering Research Needs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34018</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support for a workshop, jointly sponsored by the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) and the National Science Foundation (NSF), to be held in June 2012 in Reston, Virginia, to develop a research agenda (roadmap) for critically needed windstorm and coastal inundation impact reduction basic and applied (problem-focused) research. Of interest to the NSF-supported wind engineering research community will be the long-term research agenda, with broad strategic approach and objectives, for basic research needs for wind hazard mitigation for buildings, structures, and lifelines, including new and existing construction. Topics to be explored at the workshop include performance-based design; computational fluid dynamics; characterization of flood flow around buildings, including the influence of scour and flood-borne debris; and impact of research on loss reduction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will be led by an organizing steering committee and include experts from science and engineering disciplines related to wind hazard mitigation and community resilience research. Their interaction and synergy at the workshop will result in a rigorous set of recommendations that illuminates the most important research directions for the wind engineering field. The outcome of the workshop will be a report that outlines a five-to-ten year roadmap for basic wind engineering research. The report will be made available through the Applied Technology Council web site at https://www.atcouncil.org/.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1235689</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coulbourne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bcoulbourne@atcouncil.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Applied Technology Council</Name>
      <CityName>Redwood City</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940651191</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6505951542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Redwood Shores Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1637</Code>
      <Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>039E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>040E</Code>
      <Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
