<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Ultrahigh Brightness LED Luminaire Development for Commercial Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed effort in this Innovation-Corps project develops a LED-based product to replace fluorescent industrial lighting. The ubiquitous linear fluorescent T8 light bulb generates over 3300 lumens, while the brightest LED-based replacement generates less than 2500 lumens. However, customer desire for an adequate LED-based T8 replacement remains strong, and a bulb that can exceed the 3300 lumens brightness barrier and offer good light quality can capture much of the market. To address this market demand, the team proposes to experimentally validate a lighting architecture based on mercury-free, low-cost, off-the-shelf components that can exceed 3300 lumens brightness, match or improve upon the color temperature and color rendering index of current linear fluorescent lamps, while exhibiting a spatially uniform emission pattern. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team's proposed lighting architecture enables a LED-based, drop-in linear fluorescent replacement with greater power conversion efficiency across the entire visible spectrum compared to typical white LED technologies, while providing a more eye-pleasing light quality. Importantly, the proposed design utilizes commercially-available, highly efficient, and highly tunable luminescent dyes that enable unrivaled spectral engineering and adaptation for numerous specialized markets (e.g. hydroponics, museums, etc.), while allowing the component / supply stream to become completely independent from the fluctuations in the price and availability of rare earth elements.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1236998</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pei-Cheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ku</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peicheng@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
