<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: Exploring Frontiers in Synthetic Biology; to be held May 15-16, 2012 in Heidelberg, Germany</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49895</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susanne von Bodman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merits&lt;br/&gt;Synthetic biology is a relatively new field that sits at the intersection of biology and engineering, where practitioners use engineering tools and systems approaches to design novel biological systems, including genetic circuits and whole cells, with which to explore governing principles behind complex biological processes or to develop new functionality that can be exploited.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific objectives of the workshop are to bring together leading researchers in the field of synthetic biology to:&lt;br/&gt;1. Explore and identify areas of joint interests, needs, and opportunities associated with the rapidly emerging discipline of Synthetic Biology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Identify grand challenges and explore potential limits of the field from both biology and engineering perspectives.&lt;br/&gt;In addition, recognizing the future of science research will be increasingly transnational, this workshop seeks to establish new ties and collaborations between researchers in the United States and Germany.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will contribute to the enhancement and improvement of scientific, engineering and/or educational activities by bringing together a leading group of international researchers to define the frontiers in synthetic biology. In addition, this meeting will provide the foundation for international collaborations between researchers in the US and Germany. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The meeting sponsors will produce a report of the meeting that will be distributed to the participants and sponsoring organizations (NSF and DFG) and will also be posted for the public on sys-bio.org. We will also explore publishing a meeting report in peer-reviewed journal such as ACS Synthetic Biology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop's organizers will ensure that workshop includes attendees from underrepresent groups in Science and Technology and also attendees who are at early stages of their career.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1236974</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cvrao@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1491</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8011</Code>
      <Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
