<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Operando Molecular Spectroscopy during Catalytic Biomass Pyrolysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>311993</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory Rorrer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Wachs, Israel&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1236716&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Lehigh University&lt;br/&gt;Title: Operando Molecular Spectroscopy during Catalytic Biomass Pyrolysis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Biomass pyrolysis to produce bio-oil is emerging as an attractive technology to produce renewable liquid fuel. However, a major obstacle in the development of this technology is the catalytic pyrolysis of the biomass to bio-oils - - the first and most critical catalytic reaction step. Very little attention, however, has been paid so far to the catalyst and catalytic reaction mechanisms of biomass pyrolysis. The hypothesis of this proposal is that a fundamental molecular level of understanding of the catalyst, surface reaction intermediates and reaction pathways during biomass pyrolysis will guide the rational design of advanced catalysts that will yield improved bio-oils and fuels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will focus on the molecular events taking place on the surface of solid acid catalysts during biomass pyrolysis since recent biomass pyrolysis studies have only investigated pyrolysis product yield and bio-oil composition under various reaction conditions. In order to elucidate the molecular events taking place on the catalyst surface, cutting edge in situ and operando spectroscopic characterization studies during the catalytic biomass pyrolysis reaction will initially be undertaken with representative model biomass compounds of cellulose, hemicellulose and lignin before the investigation of pyrolysis of natural biomass. This modern approach to catalysis will allow for unprecedented insight into the fundamentals of biomass pyrolysis over solid acid mixed oxide catalysts. The fundamental studies during pyrolysis with well-defined mixed oxide catalysts and model biomass compounds will unravel the fundamental structure-activity relationships for catalytic biomass pyrolysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research program has the potential to significantly advance the fundamental catalysis aspects of biomass pyrolysis and also showcase the modern approach to heterogeneous catalysis research. The new fundamental insights that will be generated for biomass pyrolysis metathesis by solid acid mixed oxide have the potential to also influence applied biomass pyrolysis research by stimulating the development of advanced catalysts for biomass conversion to bio- oils. The modern, molecular level approach that will be developed and applied to the proposed research program will also be applicable to other areas of cutting edge heterogeneous catalysis research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This multidisciplinary project will broadly educate both graduate and undergraduate students. Specifically, this project focuses on several key technology areas including nanotechnology, material synthesis, spectroscopy, surface chemistry of carbohydrates, reaction kinetics and problem solving of cutting edge energy issues. The students involved in the proposed research project will be mentored to develop their critical thinking skills, experimental design and data analyses approaches, and effective oral and written communications skills. An emphasis of the proposed program is to provide the participating students an international research experience that will broaden their educational and cultural experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1236716</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Israel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wachs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>iew0@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lehigh University</Name>
      <CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>002E</Code>
      <Text>Bio-energy</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
