<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Integrated On-Board SiC-based Level-3 Charging for Plug-In Electric Vehicles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>95498</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Radhakisan S. Baheti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Research Objectives and Approaches: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to investigate, design, and develop an integrated on-board silicon carbide (SiC) based level-3 charger, compatible with level-1 and level-2 charging, using the propulsion machine and its inverter for next generation of plug-in electric vehicles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The approach is to conduct a comprehensive propulsion motor and inverter analyses to propose a rectifier/charger topology to charge the battery. The research will investigate the possibility of eliminating power factor correction inductors for both single-phase and three-phase charging by utilizing the propulsion machine windings, without producing torque.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will achieve breakthroughs in control, modeling and design of power electronic interfaces for electric vehicles. It will be fundamental research for scientific understanding of motor-integrated inverter/chargers. This important work will (a) lead to generic methodologies for obtaining optimal design of level-3 chargers and introducing control strategies to prevent torque generation during three-phase charging; and (b) involve multidisciplinary research in power electronics, adjustable speed drives, control, and power management. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The projected outcome of this research will promote widespread adoption of EVs through enabling EV owners to take longer trips and refuel along the way, similar to a gas station visit. The highest quality integrated education and research will be ensured to meet the emerging workforce and educational needs of U.S. energy industry by educating young and talented students. The results will be disseminated broadly to enhance scientific and educational achievements. Efforts will be made to engage students from underrepresented groups in the project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1238985</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alireza</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khaligh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>khaligh@ece.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7607</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY,POWER,ADAPTIVE SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>099E</Code>
      <Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7423</Code>
      <Text>Energy collection &amp; storage</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
