<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2012 Rock Deformation Gordon Research Conference: Feedback Processes in Rock Deformation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>22505</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030103</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Fountain</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project provides funding for travel and registration support to U.S. based early-career professionals and students to attend the Gordon Research Conference " Feedback Processes in Rock Deformation", which will be held in Andover, NH from August 19-24, 2012. The Rock Deformation conference series highlights the latest research and future trends in brittle and ductile rock mechanics, with experimental, field and theoretical contributions. The broad goals are to assess the understanding of the nature and controls on rock strength, fracture, friction, ductile deformation, and both fluid and melt flow during natural tectonic loading. This particular conference focuses on feedback mechanisms, which are very important in controlling the rates and mechanisms of rock deformation. Positive feedbacks lead to accelerating rates, and commonly to spatial focusing whereas negative feedbacks commonly cause decelerating, spatially distributed deformation and reaction. Major topics addressed at this conference include: (1) mechanisms of failure in geological materials at high confining pressure; (2) fluid-assisted slip, earthquakes and fracture; (3) reaction-driven cracking; (4) localized fluid transport (feedbacks involving chemical reaction; mechanical feedbacks); and (5) dynamic triggering of earthquakes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference addresses many cutting-edge frontier research topics in tectonics, geophysics, and related fields. The conference theme has special relevance for extraction of unconventional hydrocarbon resources, implementation of enhanced geothermal systems, geological carbon capture and storage, and understanding seismic hazards. The conference would promote the participation of students, early career scientists, and researchers from underrepresented groups in the earth sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1238362</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kelemen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peterk@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
