<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Ultra High-speed Bandwidth for Performance Improvements in Radar Networks for Weather and Aircraft Surveillance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>289029</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Min Song</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project demonstrates the benefits of connecting radars to ultra high-speed networks to improve hazardous weather warning and response and the identification and tracking of small, low-flying aircraft by developing new detection algorithms that operate directly on uncompressed, high-bandwidth radar data. Although radar networks are a critical part of the nation's infrastructure for weather observation and aircraft surveillance, today's best-effort Internet is used to transport data from radars to a variety of end users for decision-making. To allow for real-time delivery, the radar data are compressed and important information can be lost during this process. Transmitting uncompressed radar data over ultra high-speed networks could enable advanced, very geographically precise detection and prediction of weather hazards resulting in benefits to public safety and the economy. In addition, the ability to track, small low-flying aircraft is important for drug enforcement and for tracking Unmanned Aircraft Systems used for homeland security and law enforcement that are expected to be prevalent in urban areas in the near future. The project will be conducted using a test bed of high resolution, low-cost radar located in the Dallas Fort Worth Metroplex linked to users such as emergency managers and National Weather Service forecasters. To manage the increased demand for processing and networking resources from the usage of high-bandwidth data techniques related to the usage of on-demand networks (SDN) and compute resources (cloud computing) are studied.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1238485</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zink</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zink@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brenda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Philips</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bphilips@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8002</Code>
      <Text>CISE Research Resources</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
