<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Targeted Infusion Project Grant: Innovative Learning Experiences in Astronomy for Undergraduate Students at NC A&amp;T</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350486</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Targeted Infusion Project entitled - Innovative Learning Experiences in Astronomy for Undergraduate Students at NC A&amp;T - proposes a partnership with the University of North Carolina Chapel Hill (UNC-CH). The goals of the partnership are two-fold: (1) to incorporate UNC-CH's successful introductory astronomy curriculum into North Carolina A&amp;T University's (NC A&amp;T) existing space science curriculum, and to provide NC A&amp;T's space science faculty with the training and the tools to deliver the lecture and laboratory courses; and (2) to recruit talented NC A&amp;T undergraduate students as research fellows, who will work with telescopes at professional observatories, engage in astronomical research at both NC A&amp;T and UNC-CH, present their work at conferences, publish their findings in observing reports, conference proceedings, and journal articles, and in doing these things be inspired to pursue graduate studies and/or careers in STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;UNC-CH has recently developed a new introductory astronomy curriculum that leverages access to the robotic telescopes in Chile and Australia. Through this collaboration NC A&amp;T will adopt this curriculum, NC A&amp;T faculty will receive training on how to deliver the curriculum and on how to make effective classroom use of the tools that were developed such that even first-year, non-majors can use remote telescopes and analyze the resulting images. Furthermore, NC A&amp;T will gain permanent, guaranteed access to observing time on the new PROMPT telescopes in Chile and Australia, and on the 20-meter diameter radio telescope in West Virginia.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1238809</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abebe</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kebede</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gutaye@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reichart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reichart@physics.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University</Name>
      <CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1601 E. Market Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
