<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER Collaborative Research: Towards Wireless Nano-Electrostimulation of Ion Channels in Mammalian Cells.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>46889</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this exploratory research is to develop a technique for remote stimulation of mammalian cells using nanoscale electric fields. This new concept takes advantage of magnetoelectric properties of multiferroic nanoparticles which can generate local electric fields in the proximity of cell membranes when subjected to external magnetic field pulses. These fields are expected to control functions of voltage-gated ion channels, which are voltage-sensitive macromolecules, responsible for transport of Na+, K+ ions across cell membranes. To elucidate feasibility of this new approach PI will use computer simulations and thin film technology at the Advanced Materials Research Institute of the University of New Orleans to design and fabricate nanoelectrodes and patterned arrays of multiferroic particles to generate nanoscale electric fields. The response of the ion channels to the nano-electrostimulation will be measured by Co-PI in his Biophysics Laboratory at Loyola University New Orleans using modified patch-clamp technique. Since future in-vivo applications of the new method will involve use of multiferroic nanocomposites of magnetic and ferroelectric nanoparticles, The Co-PI will also devise methods of delivery of the ferroelectric nanoparticles and will determine their toxicity and binding to mammalian cells. This collaborative research will efficiently use resources and expertise in physics, materials science and biophysics available at the University of New Orleans and Loyola University New Orleans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is an attempt to utilize magnetoelectric properties of multiferroic nanoparticles as wireless probes to electrostimulate mammalian cells. The effects of external nanoscale electric fields on ion transport in mammalian cells have not been studied and this research will provide better understanding of fundamental functions of the cells. Although there have been extensive studies on applications of magnetic nanoparticles in biological systems, little is known about the interactions of ferroelectric nanoparticles with mammalian cells and proposed research will shed light on feasibility of biomedical applications of ferroelectric materials and their composites. New methods will be developed for intracellular and extracellular delivery of the nanoparticles, and patch-clamp technique will be modified to test responses of the ion-channels in living cells to applied magnetic fields with the frequency up to 5 kHz. The sequences of the pulses, as well as properties of the nanoparticles will be tuned to detetermine control of ion currents. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The outcome of this research on is expected to have profound effect on several disciplines, such as biology, medicine, biotechnology and bionics. Successful control of ion transport using magnetic field pulses offers alternative noninvasive method to treat ion-channel related diseases, such as cystic fibrosis, diabetes, cardiac arrhythmias, neurologic and psychiatric diseases, gastrointestinal disorders, cardiovascular diseases and hypertension. Since voltage-gated ion channels are responsible for triggering and propagation of action potentials in neurons the new mechanism of stimulation of ion channels can be used to treat pain and psychiatric diseases. Ultimately, electric fields from magnetoelectric nanoparticles can be used to interface neurons with bionic devices which can remotely control their action potentials. &lt;br/&gt;This project will greatly benefit undergraduate and graduate students participating in this research through extensive training in modern technologies, hands on experiment experience and communication skills gained through participation in meetings and conferences that will impact their future professional careers in academia or industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1239912</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leszek</FirstName>
      <LastName>Malkinski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lmalkins@uno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Orleans</Name>
      <CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
      <ZipCode>701480001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5042806836</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2000 Lakeshore Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>107E</Code>
      <Text>Magnetics and spin electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>108E</Code>
      <Text>Bioelectronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
