<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Teachers for a New Tomorrow (TNT)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1199282</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sandra Richardson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>To combat the urgent local need for improvements in mathematics and science education, the University of Mississippi (UM) Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program, Teachers for a New Tomorrow (TNT), provides the support to expand and enhance the efforts of UM's Center for Mathematics and Science Education (CMSE) in addressing this issue. Through the TNT program, the CMSE provides unique opportunities for STEM majors to pursue a career in mathematics or science education, thus increasing the number of certified teachers prepared to teach science and mathematics in secondary schools. Thirty STEM majors are obtaining teacher certification in science or mathematics by enrolling as a double major (in STEM and STEM Education) or by enrolling in the School of Education's Master of Arts in Curriculum and Instruction (MACI) program. In addition to meeting course requirements, TNT scholars enrich their pedagogical knowledge by participating in the TNT Preparation Program by enrolling in CMSE's enrichment programs. These events and activities are designed to train pre-service teachers with additional education activities created specifically for TNT scholars. Once certified, TNT scholarship graduates fulfill their commitment by teaching in a partnered high-need school district at least two years for each year a Noyce scholarship award was received. The project's formative and summative evaluation processes ensure that the program maintains a focus of improving mathematics and science education in Mississippi. This program is a multifaceted endeavor that includes diversity in the partnering districts and in participants with focus on areas of greatest economic need.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1240085</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Haver</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johaver@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Steimle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>asteimle@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Mississippi</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>386771848</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6629157482</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 BARR HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
