<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EFRI-ODISSEI: Multi-scale Origami for Novel Photonics, Energy Conversion</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2006613</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation (EFRI) Origami Design for the Integration of Self-assembling Systems for Engineering Innovation (ODISSEI) award is to study how the folding of planar sheets can produce novel, three-dimensional, functional structures ranging from millimeters to nanometers in size. Special "nanostructured paper" will be created, comprising thin films and membranes containing a variety of functional nanoscale objects (e.g. carbon nanotubes, semiconductor and metal nanoparticles, etc.); the nano-paper will be etched and perforated to facilitate controlled folding into more complex shapes, which can be programmed to respond to impulses and pre-determined conditions such as local and global changes in temperature, humidity, and light. The research will examine how folding can be triggered by mechanical strain, external electrical or magnetic fields, and local laser heating. Using a combination of experiments and computer modeling, the fundamental principles governing the creation and transformation of sheets into three-dimensional (3D) objects will be studied, in particular focusing on how the size of the object influences the folding dynamics. This knowledge should help resolve significant challenges of materials integration into complex and robust 3D structures for, e.g., the control of light propagation in energy conversion devices, scalable fabrication of optical and electromagnetic metamaterials, and engineering of reconfigurable "smart" surfaces powered by changes in ambient conditions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research can address broader technological and societal challenges, including those in the areas of renewable energy harvesting, energy efficiency, water purification, environmentally benign microfabrication, etc. Specifically, this work may result in novel approaches to the design and deployment of focal plane arrays, beam steering, dynamic control of radar signatures, thermal management, and other applications. Paper folding techniques (www.mattshlian.com) will be used as a means of inspiration, realization, and visualization of structures at larger scales, and will provide design principles for scale-independent miniaturization. Special sessions on ?origami electronics? will be conducted at the scientific conferences attended by the investigators. The visual and hands-on nature of the research is likely to resonate with a wide range of students and audiences, which will be reached through summer workshops on origami and its technological applications. Further outreach activities will include exhibiting at the world-renowned Ann Arbor Art Fair, the Ann Arbor Hands-On Museum, and presentations at various arts / design / interdisciplinary conferences (e.g. Siggraph, ARS Electronica), as well as at traditional gallery venues for the arts (e.g. Detroit Institute of Arts, Cranbrook Academy, Urban Institute for Contemporary Art).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported in part by funds from the Air Force Office of Scientific Research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1240264</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kotov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kotov@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Glotzer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sglotzer@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Max</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shtein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mshtein@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pei-Cheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ku</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peicheng@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anastasios John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ajhart@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>L563</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7633</Code>
      <Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>067E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>073E</Code>
      <Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>080E</Code>
      <Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1444</Code>
      <Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7633</Code>
      <Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7715</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8021</Code>
      <Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
