<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RESEARCH INITIATION GRANT: Impact of Interactive Web-based Activities on Mechanics Self-Efficacy and Achievement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149953</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This engineering education research initiation grant seeks to understand how on-line learning affects students' self-efficacy and later achievement in an engineering degree program. The research will investigate how different types of web-based activities impact student learning and their self-efficacy, or belief that they can accomplish a given task. By looking longitudinally the study will help instructors understand how to effectively integrate web-based learning into mechanics courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project will be to inform best practices in the rapidly growing area of on-line learning. The study will be conducted in an introductory mechanics course, common to most engineering programs, and thus can widely inform practice. This project overlaps with NSF's strategic goals of transforming the frontiers through preparation of an engineering workforce with new capabilities and expertise. Additionally NSF's goal of innovating for society is enabled by creating results and research that are useful for society by informing educational policy and practices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1240367</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sheri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sheppard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sheppard@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Billington</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>billington@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
