<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Initiation Grant: Examining the Impact of Situated Learning on Undergraduate Student Cognitive Complexity and Motivation to Learn</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This engineering education research initiation grant makes a comparative study of situated learning between the two professions of nursing and engineering. Situated learning takes place when learners are placed in an authentic context such as engineering internships. The researchers plan to study how situated learning impacts students ability to construct complex ideas and how it motivates them to continue in their chosen discipline. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project will be to inform other programs on the effects of situated learning, which is increasingly used in engineering degree programs. By understanding the effects of situated learning, it will be possible to better transition students from degree programs into the workforce. This project overlaps with NSF's strategic goals of transforming the frontiers through preparation of an engineering workforce with new capabilities and expertise. Additionally NSF's goal of innovating for society is enabled by creating results and research that are useful for society by informing educational policy and practices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1240316</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
      <LastName>McComb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sara@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kirkpatrick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmkirk@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
