<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EFRI-PSBR: Cyanobacterial Biorefineries</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2394999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Impacts-&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A useful long term vision of the chemical industry integrates the use of modern biotechnology and chemical catalysis to engineer systems where everyday fuels and chemicals are produced from renewable resources. The vision of this award, made to Professors Brian F. Pfleger, Christos Maravelias, Katherine D. McMahon, Thatcher W. Root and Andrew Greenberg of the University of Wisconsin-Madison is to develop and evaluate a biorefinery strategy using cyanobacteria to produce compounds that support a chemical industry based on photosynthesis. It will demonstrate methods for producing high-value commodity chemicals from CO2 and sunlight that will replace current petrochemical-based processes. Key fundamental questions that will guide the establishment of such a sustainable chemical economy based on photosynthetic cyanobacteria include: 1) What chemicals, i.e. final products or intermediates of value, should be made by living systems to optimize a chemical industry based on photosynthesis? 2) At what rate and fraction of theoretical yield can cyanobacteria produce target compounds? &lt;br/&gt;3) What process parameters are critical to effectively scale up photosynthetic bioreactors from the laboratory to industrial size? Is there a limit to the feasible size of a photosynthetic biorefinery? 4) Can a photosynthetic biorefinery be integrated with waste remediation (e.g. municipal wastewater treatment) to simultaneously meet sustainability and environmental objectives? This award details a number of key features in the fundamental science and technology supporting their photosynthetic biorefinery vision, and is made through the Emerging Frontiers in Research and Innovation Program at NSF. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts- &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the long term the proposed work will contribute to restructuring the chemical industry away from fossil fuels and towards renewable carbon sources. In addition establishing photosynthetic biorefineries is a route for achieving energy security and maintaining national defense. Deployment of successful, commercial photosynthetic biorefineries could generate a sustainable source of fuels and chemicals without altering current agricultural practices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Impact on education and outreach has many individual strategies proposed by the PIs, including a)Integrating technoeconomic analysis and LCA into CBE process design and lab courses; b)Providing independent study and research experiences for undergraduates in the university labs; c) Mentoring an interdisciplinary undergraduate synthetic biology research team (iGEM); d) Providing summer research experiences for high-school students and teachers; and e) Recruiting students from underrepresented groups through successful, existing UW-Madison programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1240268</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thatcher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Root</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thatcher@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pfleger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pfleger@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maravelias</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>christos@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>McMahon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tmcmahon@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7633</Code>
      <Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7487</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
