<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Security Injections: Promoting Responsible Coding and Building a Community of Security Ambassadors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>451879</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Information Assurance (IA) requires pervasive action to prepare all computing graduates to meet the current and future cybersecurity challenges. The challenges to this are significant: instructors who are untrained in computer security, lack of teaching resources, and introductory classes overloaded with course material. The Security Injections@Towson project includes over 40 security injection modules that target key security concepts including integer overflow, buffer overflow, and input validation to be used in introductory computer science courses. Research results show that these security injection modules lead to an increase in the ability of students to remember, comprehend, and apply secure coding principles. This project builds on the success of the security injection modules. The project team and its partners (from the ACM Committee for Computing Education in Community Colleges, three NSF Advanced Technological Education (ATE) centers, and several diverse institutions) focus on community building and effective national dissemination to reach more students and faculty. Community building efforts include 1) a Security Ambassadors program with faculty who teach and encourage others to teach responsible coding, 2) a Build-A-Lab program to grow teaching resources and increase faculty engagement, knowledge, and sense of ownership, and 3) Short IA pedagogy courses at ATE centers and educational conferences. Project dissemination is synergistic with community building efforts, using short courses at conferences, workshops, outreach through ATE centers, and the security ambassadors to facilitate module adoption at two and four year institutions. All resources will also be submitted to the NSDL Computing Pathway - Ensemble and other venues. The community-building and disseminating strategy uses discrete one-time workshops (short courses), long-range professional development (Build-A-Lab), and the involvement faculty as the source of change through the Security Ambassador program. The team brings strengths in undergraduate curriculum development, education research, capacity-building experience, and the perspective of diverse institutions, including a historically-black university and community colleges.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1241738</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Blair</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taylor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>btaylor@towson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hawthorne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ehawthorne@acm.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Siddharth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaza</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>skaza@towson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Towson University</Name>
      <CityName>Towson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212520001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4107042236</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8000 York Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
