<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research CRPA: ResearchLink: Spotlight on Solar Technologies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>35000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul W. Jennings</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This CRPA award will address the science behind solar energy, its capture, measurements, and uses. It is a collaborative effort between scientists at Portland State University (PSU) and the Oregon Museum of Science and Industry (OMSI). Materials for the OMSI staff will be prepared by the scientists and the OMSI staff will work with the scientists on making presentations to the public. OMSI will translate information from the exhibits, displays, and presentations into Spanish to engage the Hispanic population. Scientific café?s will be part of this engagement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI and OMSI museum have had a working relationship for some time adding to the potential success of the project. The PI and his colleagues at PSU have a major effort going in research on photonic science suggesting that this engagement can continue to be updated as the time goes on.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will be evaluated by the well established evaluation group at OMSI. Further, Spanish speaking public will be embraced with this material as will rural residents from traveling exhibits and displays.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1241353</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wamser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wamserc@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Portland State University</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
