<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Chemical Design for Controlling Electronic Properties of Organic Semiconductors and Molecules via Edge-On Gating</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This EAGER project, supported by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry and Electronic and Photonic Materials Programs in the Division of Materials Research, is aimed at investigating the edge-on chemical gating effect on electronic properties of semiconducting molecules and materials. The molecular system proposed resembles a field effect transistor, but allows using ultrafast spectroscopic techniques to investigate the gating effect. Extensive synthetic efforts are proposed to prepare a series of new compounds with different gating moieties. Electron transfer rate constants (corresponding to conductance) will be correlated with linear free energy Hammett parameters. If the synthetic approach is proved feasible, numerous kinds of molecular materials will be developed based on the chemically edge-on gating concept. This research effort will impact the design and development of new solid state materials and molecular electronics. It is possible that after a short period of research, this EAGER project will find firm footing for expanding into a full scale research effort.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Moore's law in microelectronics is rapidly approaching its limitation. This EAGER project is aimed at developing and investigating molecular-scale field effect transistors, the smallest possible electronic devices. The PI will investigate a new concept to control charge transport in single molecules, namely an edge-on gating effect. The proposed work involves synthetic efforts to create prototype molecules that allow gating-control and spectroscopic studies to determine electron transfer rate constants (corresponding to conductance). This project will provide basic knowledge for controlling the charge transport process in organic semiconducting materials and lead to development of new semiconducting molecules, materials and new molecular transistors. It will also provide a new perspective on solid state assembly and structure/property relationships in these materials. New materials generated will have impact on sustainable energy and electronics industries. It offers a broad spectrum of research and educational opportunities for students who will be well prepared to be future leaders in the area of organic/material chemistry and organic electronic materials. This EAGER proposal will financially support 2 graduate students and involve 2 undergraduate summer research students through the University of Chicago's Leadership Alliance's Summer Research Early Identification Program (SR-EIP) targeting underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1242729</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lupingyu@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
