<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Drug-eluting Sutures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Errol Arkilic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There are many applications where a drug-eluting suture can prevent infection and ultimately save lives. The team's initial target application is a cervical cerclage (suture), which is utilized to prevent premature birth by bolstering the strength of a mother's weak (incompetent) cervix from the beginning of their third trimester. Despite closing the cervix with a cerclage, devastating infections are known to occur from bacteria that migrate through the cervix and infect the fetus. Typically oral antimicrobials or vaginal pessaries are prescribed to prevent infection. However, the oral route may adversely affect healthy stomach bacteria, and both methods rely on patient compliance. By incorporating a localized drug delivery for the full three month duration needed to bring the fetus to term this new technology can usurp current treatments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In 3% of all surgical and traumatic wounds a patient develops an infection, necessitating an average 6.5-day hospital stay, adding $35-40 billion in expenses in the United States alone. While orally-administered antibiotics have an established efficacy towards preventing infection, they come with inherent risks. Instead, the technology developed in this effort delivers the minimally-effective dose of a powerful broad-spectrum antimicrobial directly from a suture, minimizing side effects. Further, administration of the antimicrobial from the suture ensures 100% patient compliance with the drug regimen. At the end of the project, the team will have a woven, prototype suture that has been examined more thoroughly for drug release and strength and has gone through preliminary in vivo animal trials at the Medical University of South Carolina. The team will also have a go/no go decision with regard to potential commercialization of the technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1242516</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hirt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hirtd@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cody</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reynolds</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>REYNOLD@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clemson University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
