<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshops on Big Data and Urban Informatics: e-Infrastructure for Social Science Research on Sustainable Urban Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>137280</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William J. Badecker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project will establish a multi-disciplinary research community to generate decadal-scale data-intensive research questions on how Big Data can be leveraged for Urban Informatics. Pervasive sensing, social media, location-aware technologies and vast numbers of sensors in the urban infrastructure will lead to massive amounts of Big Data on cities. Urban Informatics is the design and analysis of Big Data to create the next generation of tools and services for improved social science research on urban decision-making and citizen engagement. These tools will enable urban systems of the future to be designed, planned, managed and used more sustainably, efficiently and equitably.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research community will be organized around creating an Urban Informatics e-Infrastructure (UIE) for social science research. The UIE will consist of three components--a Big Data resource, Urban Informatics Analysis Tools to enable social science research on urban systems and Emerging Technologies to facilitate the use of the e-infrastructure by researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By interweaving these components from a multi-disciplinary perspective, data-intensive research on urban modeling, data mining and knowledge discovery to explore urban dynamics will be stimulated. Agent-Based Modeling, large-scale simulations and research on unique data management and multi-sensor sensor fusion that arises with urban Big Data will be encouraged. Innovations in urban sensing and new directions in community-based information generation will inspire questions on participatory urban planning and models of community engagement as well as on sustainable choices regarding transportation, urban ecology, green infrastructure, land development and water use. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will support two workshops on the topic. The overall goal of the workshops will be to present advances in such activities and to stimulate discussion on research and applications to be built using the e-infrastructure.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1244769</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Piyushimita</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thakuriah</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vonu-pt@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/27/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Piyushimita</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thakuriah</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vonu-pt@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Moira</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zellner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mzellner@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nebiyou</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tilahun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ntilahun@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/27/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nebiyou</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tilahun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ntilahun@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8068</Code>
      <Text>Data Infrastructure</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
