<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Fuel Analyzer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will develop a Fuel Analyzer for the cement industry. The cement market is predominantly powered by fossil fuel and in many cases they can benefit from knowing the exact composition, moisture level, and BTU of the fuel. By accurately analyzing and characterizing the composition of the fuel, it is possible to run the kiln and operations more efficiently, while both lowering costs and reducing emissions. This SBIR project seeks to develop technology that can be used to accurately and fully characterize cement fuel. Phase I will involve the design of a new type of analyzer designed to measure the full composition of the fuel. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact /commercial potential of the project is a result of a better characterization of the composition of the fuel so that the fuel can be used more efficiently. More efficient use of the fuel, which is the largest cost in a cement plan, can result in lower cost and more efficient operations. Another benefit of using the equipment is to lower overall emissions. The impact of this technology goes beyond just cement operations. Any operation burning extensive amount of fossil fuels can benefit from this technology due to the impact on cost, efficiently, and emissions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1248933</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chaur-Ming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shyu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chaurming_shyu@xrsciences.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>XRSciences LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Encinitas</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920246830</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7604028663</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1031 Olive Crest Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
