<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Simulation Studies of Plasmaspheric Plume Density Structure/Ion Composition and Plume Plasma Transport to Dayside Magnetopause and Polar Cap</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>310419</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carrie E. Black</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A plasmaspheric plume is a region of dense cold ionospheric plasma extending outward into the magnetosphere from the nominal location of the plasmapause. It has a limited width in azimuth. This study will use and improve the dynamic-fluid-kinetic-plasmasphere-ionosphere (DyFKPI) model. This model combines self-consistently a fluid based model of the ionosphere with a particle based model of the plasmasphere. It will be used to determine the density distributions of electrons and ions (H+, He+, and O+) along plume magnetic field lines and provide formulas that can be used to determine the density along the flux tube. The second part of this study will quantify the plasmaspheric plasma mass delivered to the dayside magnetospause as a function of magnetospheric activity. This research will investigate how plasmaspheric plumes deliver plasma to the polar cap and contribute to magnetospheric plasma circulation. IMAGE RPI data will be used in this study and compared with simulation derived density distributions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While the research is rather narrowly focused on the structure and impact of the plasma plumes the resulting formulas will be valuable in other studies of magnetospheric physics. The grant will support a graduate student.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1248242</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jiannan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jiannan_Tu@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/17/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Lowell</Name>
      <CityName>Lowell</CityName>
      <ZipCode>018543643</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9789344170</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>600 Suffolk Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5750</Code>
      <Text>MAGNETOSPHERIC PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
