<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: A Radio p-Chip for Intracellular Sensing and Communication</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149989</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims at developing a Radio p-Chip, the first microchip with a sensor that can be injected into live cells, and transmit information from within without a physical connection. The design combines elements of laser light-activation of the p-Chip, a novel device that transmits the chip's serial number via radio signals, with enhancements to monitor events by adding a sensor. The target dimensions for the Radio p-Chip are suitable for investigations of large cells. The on-board sensor will gather information about real-time physiological conditions in the cell and transmit it along with the serial number identifying the cell itself. The information will be transmitted to a reading station that will collect data related to the identity of the cell, as well as the reported conditions from the sensor. The main goals of the Phase I project are to 1) design, build and test the fully functional prototype of the Radio p-Chip; 2) implant the device into a living mammalian cell and demonstrate its function; and 3) build and test components of a future version of the chip. The device envisioned is one part of a system incorporating, in addition to the chip, a custom-designed receiver and antenna system, the stimulus apparatus, devices to implant the chip into cells, and associated firmware and application software. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will be felt in a wide variety of applications, including the readout of key physiological characteristics, ID-tagging of individual cells and tracking their history, tagging embryos, flow cytometry and process monitoring. All research to date with living cells relies upon indirect or intrusive methods that almost always effect what is being measured. The Radio p-Chip will be superior in both performance and cost and will have a wide commercial impact. The development of a Radio p-Chip will provide a powerful new tool for cell biology and in particular for the in vivo studying of a wide variety of human diseases and have implications for drug discovery and in vitro diagnostics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1248465</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wlodek</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mandecki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mandecki@pharmaseq.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>PharmaSeq, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Monmouth Jct.</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088521923</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7323550100</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11 Deer Park Dr.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
