<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Dynamic Thermal Interface Material for Cooling Medium and High Power Electronics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149886</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project has the objective of demonstrating thermal interface material (D-TIM paste) at least twice as effective in use in packaging electronics with medium and high power loads as prior material. A major focus is on enabling novel mode of heat transfer at the walls of a thermal stack and within the thermal paste, while fulfilling other technical requirements for a TIM, such as minimal thermal contact (interfacial) resistance and compatible coefficient of thermal expansion. The TIM concept investigated has a built-in performance enhancement as demands on the material increase. Improved interfacial performance is the key to turning this interesting and promising material into product of commercial value. The team has scientific and business experience appropriate to the task; it has identified measurement strategies and materials composition experiments likely to lead to TIM with low contact thermal impedance. A balance of in-house resources and out-sourcing ensures successful completion of the work. The work builds on the body of work of the last two decades in nanocarbon composite materials and exploitation of nonlinear responses of materials to selected stimulae.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is the consequence of a breakthrough solution to fill the need for fast thermal transport through thermal stacks for high speed, densely-packed, or high power electronics. The results of this project will refine understanding and performance of its proprietary materials to the point that commercialization becomes feasible. This woman-owned company will supply unique thermal interface products and license intellectual property for use in computing devices, servers, telecommunications, motor control, and many diverse Industrial/military applications such as semiconductor, energy conversion, transportation, chemical manufacturing, and space satellite/probe thermal management. Improved heat dissipation is of environmental significance, as better thermal performance improves device lifetime, reduces material consumption, and allows greater device speed for a fixed-size heat sink. Portable electronics reduces the need to move materials or people between locations, thus reducing fuel consumption and attendant pollution. The TIM is likely to be useful for stationary heat transfer problems as well, such as solid state power supplies, fuel cells, power inverters, thermo-electric coolers, and motors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1248614</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ewa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kirkor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>conductor@anchorscience.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Anchor Science LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Branford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>064053127</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2032316181</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>37 Victoria Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
