<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Ultra High Efficiency Top-emitting Quantum Dot light-emitting Display Incorporating Microlens Array</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179996</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project seeks to demonstrate ultra high efficiency quantum dot light-emitting diodes (QD-LEDs) using a top-emitting structure and micro-lens array for display applications. Two key challenges will be addressed. First, a novel top-emitting structure will be explored based on the previous efficient bottom-emitting QD-LEDs. Use of top-emitting structure removes light trapped through the wave-guide mode within the glass substrate, which improves light out-coupling. A micro-lens array will be applied on top of the QD-LEDs to further enhance the light extraction. The project will focus on a number of innovative approaches. Micro-lens arrays will be fabricated using a novel stamp printing method. A small size micro-lens along with a top-emitting structure will minimize the pixel blurring effect induced by the conventional out-coupling micro-lens. Secondly, high refractive index material will be used to fabricate a micro-lens to match the refractive index of the transparent electrode, hence improving light extraction efficiency. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project lies is to enable the commercialization of QD-LED displays, solid-state lighting and other applications. QD-LEDs provide intrinsically higher color purity compared to LCD or organic light-emitting diode (OLED) technology and are suitable for display applications. However, current QD-LED solutions suffer from lower efficiency compared to LCD and OLED. The company?s innovative nanomaterials and device architecture has enabled very efficient bottom-emitting QD-LEDs with high external quantum efficiency. Additionally, the multi-layer structure in the company?s QD-LED are deposited through solution processing, which reduces the cost significantly. It is expected that a better performing and substantially less expensive QD-LED will quickly gain considerable market share in a $60B market that ships over 1.5B units a year.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1248863</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yixing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yixing.yang@nanophotonica.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ying</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ying.zheng@nanophotonica.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/29/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NanoPhotonica</Name>
      <CityName>Orlando</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328193310</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3522942719</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5036 Dr. Phillips Blvd. #319</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>091E</Code>
      <Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>123E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
