<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAR-PF: An Investigation of Continental Rift-Parallel Deformation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. D. Sarah Stamps has been awarded an NSF Earth Science Postdoctoral Fellowship to conduct research and develop a GPS geodesy education program while at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. This project aims to confirm and elucidate the origin of the dynamic processes driving rift-parallel surface deformation observed along the East African Rift, an archetype continental rift system. Dr. Stamps will (1) occupy geodetic benchmarks with Global Positioning System (GPS) instruments at previously measured sites along the Western Branch and Rukwa Rift where rift-parallel deformation is indicated, and (2) test candidate mechanisms for rift-parallel deformation using an adaptive finite element technique that can solve viscoelastic and time-dependent problems at various spatial scales. Verifying the existence of rift-parallel deformation along the East African Rift and determining the responsible mechanism(s) will provide a more complete understanding of rifting processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The use of GPS as a tool for monitoring active deformation is vital for advancing knowledge of seismic and volcanic hazards. This project supports the development of a GPS geodesy training program aimed at educating university students to observe millimeter precision surface motions with GPS. The pilot program will be implemented at the University of Antananarivo, Madagascar and documented for future GPS geodesy capacity building efforts in developing countries and within the US.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1249295</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dorothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stamps</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stamps, Dorothy S</Name>
      <CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479011499</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
