<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Does Genomic Imprinting and DNA Methylation Modulate Nasonia Behavior?</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>79999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle M. Elekonich</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>How do changes in the activity of genes in the brain contribute to behavioral flexibility? One epigenetic mechanism, DNA methylation, creates temporary changes in gene expression. DNA methylation can also lead to changes in gene activity that are passed from parent to offspring called genomic imprinting. The role of genomic imprinting and DNA methylation in modulating behavior will be investigated using Nasonia, a parasitoid insect used widely in biological control of pests and an emerging model system for behavioral genetics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; A wide range of behaviors will be examined for imprinting, including activity level, dispersal, aggression, courtship and host choice. Using high throughput sequencing differences in methylation and gene activity (expression) between brain and body will be measured for the entire set of genes of the organism. Experiments will also test whether partial "knockdown" of the activity of genes that cause DNA methylation leads to changes in behavior and behavioral gene activity within and across generations. Finally, controlled genetic crosses will test whether parents influence the behavior of their offspring through DNA modifications passed through egg and sperm. By comparison to the few other studies on focusing on one behavior, this study on a more typical insect species group and multiple behaviors will allow us to determine how frequently DNA methylation is a common method of modulating behavior in different organisms across a wide variety of taxa, how variable the role of methylation in behavioral flexibility is and how often these effects carry across generations. To advance discovery based learning, the project will be integrated into an undergraduate course on research methods in behavioral genetics. Because parasitoids kill pest insects, the project could lead to improved methods of biological pest control due to a better understanding of how behavior is regulated in these important insects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1250790</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Werren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>werr@mail.rochester.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Rochester</Name>
      <CityName>Rochester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>518 HYLAN, RC BOX 270140</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7659</Code>
      <Text>ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
