<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Renewable Polymers and Composites Derived from Hydrocarbon-Rich Natural Rosin</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research program seeks to explore potentially transformative concepts to lessen the dependence on petroleum by seeking novel monomers and polymers from natural sources. One of the major hurdles to increasing the share of renewable polymers in the commercial market is their high cost and inferior performance compared with synthetic polymers produced from petroleum chemicals. This CAREER project at the University of South Carolina is focused on the use of low cost hydrocarbon-rich natural resources as a building block of polymeric materials with tailored properties and controlled structures. The overall goal of the proposed research is to integrate bulky hydrophenanthrene-based rosin into polymeric framework to increase glass transition temperature and hydrophobicity in thermoplastics, biodegradable resins and biocomposites. This program includes the development of new synthetic protocols for making rosin-derived monomers and polymers through highly efficient click chemistry and a variety of controlled polymerization techniques, and through parallel efforts to combine rosin-based feedstock with (1) biodegradable polylactide, (2) polymers based on renewable fatty acids, and (3) biocomposites based on lignin and cellulose nanowhiskers. This project also aims to investigate how macromolecular compositions and architecture dictate thermal, surface and mechanical properties of these materials and to establish a clear structure-property relationship. The proposed efforts may ultimately lead the PI to achieve macroscopic processability and physical properties resembling those polymers made from petroleum chemicals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Synthetic plastics account for consumption of ~7% of fossil fuels worldwide. Energy shortage and environmental concerns prompt opportunities to seek developing renewable resources for manufacturing of "green" plastics. Molecularly engineered rosin-derived polymers and composites are viable alternative materials to broaden value-added renewable plastics, which will result in a decrease in demand of petroleum chemicals. This program will provide training opportunities to graduate students and undergraduate students in polymer synthesis and characterization. An important component of this program involves several integrated educational activities for high school, undergraduate and graduate students to stimulate their interest in science and technology with enhanced global research and education training opportunities. All students will be trained on a number of facilities, participate in local and national meetings, and interact closely with collaborators in the process of performing the research. An International Outreach Program for the Education in Sustainable Materials and Nanotechnologies will be developed to facilitate global cooperation/network in addressing renewable materials and environmental impact, and will strengthen the global competence and competitiveness of US students. One direct outcome of this program would be the development of prototype renewable polymers for educational demonstration. Furthermore, a Project Seed Program will be supported to allow high school students from economically disadvantaged families to carry out summer research. Underrepresented students will be an important part of all educational activities. This program would also serve as an integrated educational experience for graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1252611</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chuanbing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tang4@mailbox.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/09/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8249</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Materials</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
