<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER:Systems analysis of the cardiac hypertrophy signaling network</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>436000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michele Grimm</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1252854&lt;br/&gt;Saucerman&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A python's heart grows by a remarkable 40% a mere 48 hours after feeding, returning to normal&lt;br/&gt;size on a similar timescale. But in humans and other mammals, exposure to pathological&lt;br/&gt;stress such as myocardial infarction (heart attack) leads to a detrimental and irreversible form of&lt;br/&gt;heart growth that ultimately leads to heart failure. Because postnatal cardiac myocytes generally&lt;br/&gt;do not proliferate, heart growth is due to an enlargement of existing cells, termed hypertrophy.&lt;br/&gt;The myocyte hypertrophy response is controlled by a complex web of biochemical signaling&lt;br/&gt;pathways, triggered by a range of neurotransmitters, hormones, cytokines and mechanical&lt;br/&gt;stimuli. While many individual pieces of this network have been discovered, major advances&lt;br/&gt;are required to achieve a quantitative understanding of how these molecular circuits work and&lt;br/&gt;how they may be controlled therapeutically. Thus there is an urgent need for new&lt;br/&gt;approaches, both theoretical and experimental, that allow such integrative understanding.&lt;br/&gt;Yet systems biology approaches to date have been most focused on more tractable model&lt;br/&gt;organisms and cell lines, with much less work done on biochemical networks&lt;br/&gt;regulating the heart.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Here, new computational and experimental systems approaches will be developed to&lt;br/&gt;understand how extracellular signals drive physiological and pathological myocyte remodeling.&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Saucerman's lab has adapted techniques from image processing to perform the first highthroughput&lt;br/&gt;microscopy of cardiac myocyte morphology, identifying distinct forms of hypertrophy&lt;br/&gt;depending on the stimulated receptor. In parallel, they have developed the first largescale&lt;br/&gt;computational model of the hypertrophy signaling network, predicting that PI3K and Ras&lt;br/&gt;are key network decision points. The research objective of this proposal is to test the&lt;br/&gt;overall hypothesis that the balance of PI3K and Ras signaling determines how diverse&lt;br/&gt;receptors induce distinct forms of cardiac myocyte hypertrophy. This hypothesis will be&lt;br/&gt;tested by 1) experimentally measuring and perturbing PI3K and Ras signaling to determine their&lt;br/&gt;distinct regulation of myocyte size, shape and sarcomeric organization; 2) training a&lt;br/&gt;computational model of hypertrophy signaling based on biochemical and morphological data;&lt;br/&gt;and 3) applying the model to predict and then experimentally validate signaling mechanisms&lt;br/&gt;that mediate the distinct roles for PI3K and Ras in hypertrophy signaling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The training of individuals ranging from high school students through postdoctoral&lt;br/&gt;researchers is highly integrated into this program. Specific educational aims include: 1)&lt;br/&gt;mentoring of undergraduate students in graduate-level research; and 2) outreach to high school&lt;br/&gt;students from underrepresented populations, particularly in developing original computational&lt;br/&gt;models of cardiac signaling networks. This training is aided by user-friendly network modeling&lt;br/&gt;software and accompanying problem-based learning curricular materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This research will integrate new computational and experimental approaches&lt;br/&gt;to identify PI3K and Ras as network decision points for myocyte size, shape, and sarcomeric&lt;br/&gt;organization. The educational program is innovative in graduate-level research by&lt;br/&gt;undergraduates and in problem-based learning of systems biology with high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This research is expected to identify new potential therapeutic targets for&lt;br/&gt;cardiac hypertrophy. The educational program will provide mentoring for underrepresented high&lt;br/&gt;school students and undergraduates, enhancing their career development. Modeling software&lt;br/&gt;and curricular materials will make these approaches accessible to a much larger community.&lt;br/&gt;Further impact will ultimately be achieved by the scientific achievements and career successes&lt;br/&gt;of diverse trainees.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1252854</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Saucerman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jjs3g@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7334</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7454</Code>
      <Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>004E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>017E</Code>
      <Text>Cellular and Tissue Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>138E</Code>
      <Text>Stem cells/regenerative medicine</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
