<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Young Mathematicians Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179975</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal provides support for the Young Mathematicians Conference (YMC) to be held at Ohio State University each year for three years, with the first conference scheduled to be held on August 9-11, 2013. The YMC showcases undergraduate research in mathematics at the national level, providing a venue for up to 70 undergraduate students to present their results in an authentic research conference experience and discuss mathematics with their peers and with senior researchers. Invitations to YMC are selective, and applications are evaluated by a panel of faculty referees. Each conference has three plenary talks given by world class researchers on diverse topics of high impact and innovative research of current interest. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Young Mathematicians Conference is a national opportunity for bright undergraduates to present their research, to gather new ideas and insights. The conference aims to support the undergraduate research community in mathematics on the national level, serve as a focal point for research groups, to inspire and sustain the enthusiasm and momentum necessary for students to seek and pursue challenging graduate programs in mathematics. Involvement of mentors into discussions about generating research projects and supervising students provides support and stimulation for new directions in undergraduate research. The plenary talks are engaging, and are disseminated via online video streams, introducing students, researchers, and the general public into exciting and original areas of mathematical research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1252904</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rodica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Costin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rcostin@math.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Caceres</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>luis.caceres1@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bart</FirstName>
      <LastName>Snapp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>snapp.14@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jackson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chjackso@owu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
