<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Evaluating the Impacts of River Engineering and Stream Restoration Projects on the Ecosystem Service of Floodwave Attenuation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>403847</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;1254569 (Stone). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research goal of this CAREER award is to discover the degree to which river engineering, watershed management, and stream restoration efforts impact the ecosystem service of floodwave attenuation. To accomplish this goal, the following three research objectives will be pursued: (1) improve conceptual and numerical models of the process of floodwave attenuation with an emphasis on the influence of channel-floodplain interactions on flood hydrodynamics; (2) evaluate the impacts of historical river engineering and watershed management activities on the ecosystem service of floodwave attenuation within the Middle Rio Grande (MRG); and (3) assess the potential to enhance floodwave attenuation within the MRG through restoration. Flume experiments and field observations will be used to test and refine a conceptual model of the physical processes controlling channel-floodplain interactions. The improved understanding of flood hydrodynamics will be incorporated into hydraulic models to more accurately represent floodwave propagation. Using historical reconstructions of river conditions, models will be used to investigate changes in floodwave attenuation in the MRG as a result of human activities. Finally, using alternative future restoration scenarios, the potential for enhancing floodwave attenuation through MRG restoration activities will be evaluated. The long-term education goal is to advance water resources engineering training in the U.S. towards more holistic and sustainable practices while increasing participation by underrepresented students. In pursuit of this goal, the educational objectives of this CAREER award are to: (1) create an integrated research and educational program focused on sustainable management of rivers and their floodplains; and (2) increase participation of underrepresented students in engineering and science programs at the University of New Mexico. These goals will be pursued through an education plan that includes: (1) outreach to underserved K-12 students through hands-on learning activities to teach them about watersheds and human interactions with the Rio Grande; (2) collaboration with faculty and Native American students at the Southwest Indian Polytechnic Institute on both educational and research components of this project; and (3) involvement of graduate and undergraduate students in all aspects of the project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1254569</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stone@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7643</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8020</Code>
      <Text>Green Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
