<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Quantum Information Science with Single Defects in ZnO</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Miriam Deutsch</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Description: The research aim of this CAREER project is to understand the photo-physics and spin-physics of single point defects in ZnO as a platform for quantum information science and quantum-enhanced metrology. While quantum information science promises fundamentally new technological capabilities, implementation of these theoretical ideas in a physical system is very challenging. Single point defects in semiconductor crystals are promising quantum systems with potential for scalability through integration with conventional computing technology and other quantum systems. This research project studies point defects in ZnO using a "single-molecule" approach, combining confocal fluorescence microscopy, time-resolved single-photon counting, and magnetic resonance to understand the structure and dynamics of this individually addressable quantum system. Emphasis is on understanding spin and photo dynamics with an eye toward controlling the quantum states of electronic and nuclear spins, and on the generation of high-quality single photon sources. In addition, ZnO growth is studied, both in the principle investigator's laboratory and through collaboration, to understand and control the formation of defects and how they interact with the electronic and photonic properties of ZnO.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Description: This project examines the optical and magnetic behavior of single atom-scale defects. An example is a single missing atom within the array of atoms that form a crystal. Such defects can behave like single atoms, even at room temperature, within a solid-state environment. Understanding and controlling these point defects could lead to new technology for computing and communication because their behavior is governed by quantum mechanics. The research team studies a single defect through its optical signature by detecting the individual photons it emits under different experimental conditions and in samples grown using different methods. Graduate and undergraduate students working on this project benefit from research experience in a stimulating and interdisciplinary environment. The principal investigator (PI) also develops hands-on science lessons, including equipment and supplies that may be borrowed by teachers through the Cornell Center for Materials Research lending library. The PI works with teachers on the development of these kits, and brings teachers into the laboratory so they can experience scientific research and share it with their students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1254530</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fuchs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gdf9@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7203</Code>
      <Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
