<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Early Career: Acquisition of an Accelerated Solvent Extractor and a Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometer for Lipid Analyses in Organic Geochemistry Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>160602</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Early Career: Acquisition of an Accelerated Solvent Extractor and a Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometer for Lipid Analyses in Organic Geochemistry Research&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funding to acquire an Accelerated Solvent Extractor (ASE) and a Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometer (GC-MS) at University of Alabama (UA). These two instruments are essential for reliable lipid analysis, which is the core research tool utilized by the PI to understand organic matter cycling in aquatic environments. Lipids are important tracers indicating sources, quality and preservation of organic matter in contemporary and paleo-ecosystems. Examples of application from the PI's past and on-going research projects include: reconstructing environmental changes in the Lake Erie during the development and remediation of its cultural eutrophication; understanding the effects of human development in watershed on organic matter cycling within aquatic environments; and developing biomarkers for sulfide-tolerate microbes that inhabited oceans during past periods of anaerobicity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The instrumentation provides state-of-the-art technological support for research and education in Earth Sciences at UA. It enables the PI, an early career organic geochemist, to develop an independent research program, establish cross-disciplinary and inter-institutional collaboration and attract quality graduate students. The instruments further enhance the research capacity of a research consortium at UA investigating past climatic and environmental changes, which comprises a group of diverse and talented faculty members and students. This enhanced infrastructure allows more effective integration of research, teaching and student training. A variety of courses in geological and environmental sciences will benefit from hands-on activities, such as analyzing environmental pollutants or identifying compounds indicating activities of past organisms. Currently, 12 students (5 undergraduates and 7 graduates) are conducting research projects requiring the use of the requested instruments. Most importantly, the research topics supported by the new instrumentation have important society values, including understanding distribution and metabolism of organic pollutants, and elucidating factors governing climate changes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1255724</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuehan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yuehan.lu@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Findlay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rfindlay@biology.as.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
