<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The evolution of gene expression and functional specialization in Siphonophora (Cnidaria)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>700000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Different species have different degrees of specialization between their cells, genes, and organs. Understanding the evolutionary origins and genomic underpinning of this functional specialization is critical to understanding the diversity of life on Earth and the implications of division of labor for complex systems. This project will investigate functional specialization in a group of marine invertebrate species with some of the most extreme divisions of labor, the siphonophores. Siphonophores are made up of hundreds of specialized bodies that each perform particular tasks, such as feeding or defense. The investigators will measure gene activity in multiple types of specialized bodies in twelve species of siphonophores, and characterize the anatomical differences between these bodies. Evolutionary analyses will indicate which genes have shifts in activity that are associated with shifts in the division of labor.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will test general hypotheses about the evolution and impact of the division of labor in complex, integrated organisms. It will also develop new statistical methods and computational tools that will enable evolutionary analyses of gene activity in other species. In addition, this grant provides support to produce new animations that communicate findings to a broad audience (posted at http://creaturecast.org).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1256695</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Casey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>casey_dunn@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
