<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Society for Economic Anthropology Conference Proposal</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12120</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award to the Society for Economic Anthropology will support a conference in which cutting-edge research on the theme of 'Inequality' will be presented, discussed, and disseminated. The award will support ten students to attend the conference, providing an opportunity for them to present their research, interact with senior scholars, and attend a roundtable session on field research methods in economic anthropology. The conference will contribute original, empirical research to further understanding of the origins and perpetuation of inequality across societies globally. Themes to be explored include the cultural manifestations of inequality in diverse societies, processes through which relatively egalitarian societies become more hierarchical over time, ways in which inequality is measured and studied, and the impact of current economic crises on inequality globally. The conference provides a forum for scholars, students, and others in attendance to engage with recent research on the issue of inequality which is a growing social concern in the United States and elsewhere. In particular, the active participation of students, both undergraduate and graduate, in the conference will contribute to their academic training and professional development. A special roundtable session on anthropological research methods and student research presentations contribute to this goal. Finally, products from the conference, including an edited volume or journal issue as well as online posting of conference abstracts and posters, will further disseminate research findings to the scholarly community as well as the general public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1256174</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cliggett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Lisa.Cliggett@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lesorogol</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clesorogol@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cohen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cohen.319@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1390</Code>
      <Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1390</Code>
      <Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
