<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Stimulus-induced neural networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>764374</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sridhar Raghavachari</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project's central hypothesis is that brain networks may be much more flexible than generally appreciated, perhaps to the point of altering their functional organization moment-to-moment to optimize stimulus processing. This hypothesis will be tested by using fast voltage sensitive dyes to image the firing activity of networks of over 100 neurons in two different molluscan species as they respond to sensory input, generate behavioral motor programs, and store memory. State-of-the-art analysis methods will be applied to track all recorded neurons as they shift allegiances among network communities in real time. The project will have three areas of scientific and broader impacts. First, the anticipated findings will significantly extend our current understanding of how brain networks are affected by the very information that they process. Second, the recording and analysis tools being developed by this project will be of great use to many other laboratories. Finally, the broader impacts of this project are designed to inspire and educate future scientists, both undergraduate biology majors from neighboring 4 year colleges, as well as high school students from two predominantly Hispanic Waukegan-area high schools. These educational outreach activities aim to increase the excitement and satisfaction of underrepresented individuals for careers in scientific research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1257923</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Frost</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>William.Frost@rosalindfranklin.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>ROSALIND FRANKLIN UNIVERSITY OF MEDICINE AND SCIENCE</Name>
      <CityName>North Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>600643037</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8475788524</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3333 Greenbay Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7713</Code>
      <Text>ACTIVATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1096</Code>
      <Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
