<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Brockport Physics, Mathematics and Computer Science (BPMACS) Scholars Program - Completing Their Degrees</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ron Buckmire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Brockport Physics, Mathematics and Computer Science (BPMACS) Scholars Program - Completing Their Degrees provides 28 to 32 scholarships of up to $5400 each year to juniors, seniors and Master's degree students in the fields of physics, mathematics and computer science. An important emphasis of the program is to ensure that BPMACS scholars complete their degrees in a timely fashion. Scholars in the current BPMACS program have achieved 98% college-wide retention and on-time graduation rates, and it is the goal of the new program to match this success rate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A cadre of STEM professionals from the three participating departments of Mathematics, Computer Science and Physics administers the program, supported with the full backing of an involved administration. The seven academic members of the Program Board are committed to recruit a diverse applicant pool for the program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the program is strengthened by strong academic programs of the three STEM departments involved and by the requirement that student awardees are maintain a 3.0 GPA out of 4.0 in their major and overall each semester. The team administering the program consists of two mathematicians, three computer scientists, and two physicists and includes the chairs of all three participating departments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The program achieves broader impacts through the large number (85 - 90) of STEM scholars it anticipates to graduate, its collaborative relationship with the Empire State STEM Hub, its focus on minority and female recruitment and awardees, its financial support for student research presentations at regional and national professional meetings and its interface to college/industry forums through its series of invited STEM lectures.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1257849</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stanley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Radford</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sradford@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lucas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlucas@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mihail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barbosu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbarbosu@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kadathur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lakshmanan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>klakshma@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sanford</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smiller@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY College at Brockport</Name>
      <CityName>Brockport</CityName>
      <ZipCode>144202932</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5853952444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Foundation of SUNY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
