<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Scholarships-Creating Opportunities for Applying Mathematics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>605931</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stephanie August</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Scholarships Creating Opportunities for Applying Mathematics (S-COAM) project at Indiana University of Pennsylvania establishes supportive connections between Master's students and undergraduates through various cohort activities, while increasing numbers of students pursuing mathematics degrees, improving retention, and enhancing recruitment from regional community colleges. Scholarships support ten students seeking the Master's of Science degree in Applied Mathematics, and 18 undergraduates seeking a major in a mathematical area or minor in mathematics with another science-related major; at least 49 students are supported over three years. Effectiveness is assessed by student surveys and an outside evaluator.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The highlights of S-COAM include the formation of a supportive cohort of students focused on applied mathematics, mentoring and leadership opportunities for participating Master's students and undergraduates, expectations of students doing research or internships and attendance of STEM-related presentations by visiting scholars. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;S-COAM expands career options of women, minorities, first-generation, economically disadvantaged, rural, and others by providing support to pursue advanced mathematics coursework and providing workforce-ready graduates trained on industry standard software. S-COAM builds university and student connections in the region through internship and job placement with local businesses as well recruitment visits to and research presentations at local educational institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1259860</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yu-Ju</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yjkuo@iup.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/04/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adkins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fadkins@iup.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/04/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Indiana</CityName>
      <ZipCode>157051048</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7243572244</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Stright Hall, Room 129</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
