<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Broadening Opportunities for Interdisciplinary Computational Science and Engineering Research Training (ICSERT)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>618792</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dawn Rickey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Computational Science Research Center at San Diego State University (SDSU) is awarding $10,000 per year scholarships to 26 graduate students in interdisciplinary computational science and engineering areas. Over the course of this 4 year project, SDSU is awarding support to 16 PhD students, in unique cohorts of four to six students, during their first two years of study, and these doctoral candidates are being supported as research assistants in subsequent years. In addition, 10 Master's students, in unique cohorts of 3 or 4 students per year, are supported each year of their two-year degree program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is ensuring the development of a future workforce with high level problem solving skills and experience to work on interdisciplinary computational science and engineering problems in team settings. The project is engaging and training the cohorts of graduate students in 'discovery teams' which include professors, research staff, graduate and undergraduate students, working interactively to solve practical problems. S-STEM scholars are being supported through to degree completion via strategic academic and career counseling, appropriate and timely course support as needed, guidance on seeking additional graduate study financial support, networking opportunities with researchers from academia, national laboratories, and industry, and enhanced teaching, outreach, and leadership training.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is increasing the diversity of graduate students in interdisciplinary computational science graduate program and is increasing the number of women and socioeconomically disadvantaged students who complete graduate level STEM-programs and obtain private sector or academic appointments in interdisciplinary computational science and engineering fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1259951</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Castillo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jcastillo@sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paolini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ppaolini@sunstroke.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edwards</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>redwards@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Satchi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Venkataraman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>satchi@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
