<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Denver Metro Chem Scholars</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>620309</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Higgins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Denver Metro Chem Scholars (DMCS) program is providing financial assistance, effective student supports, and academic experiences leading to student degree completion. DMCS graduates are entering the STEM workforce or continuing their formal STEM education in graduate school. The project is supporting approximately 24 students spread across three cohorts, during their sophomore, junior and senior years, as they pursue Bachelor's degrees in Chemistry. The DMCS program, led by a team of Chemistry faculty, is focused on retention and reducing the time-to-degree by augmenting existing student support services with peer mentoring, supplemental instruction, faculty-guided undergraduate research, enhanced academic advising, and workshops on post-graduation opportunities. Additional program features include collaborative cohort activities, a focus on science literacy, and professionalization into the scientific community through scholarly journal groups, conference participation, and engagement with student chapters of professional societies. Metropolitan State University Denver, with a total enrollment of over 23,000 and 94% from the metro area, serves more students of color (31.6% of the student population) than any other university or college in Colorado and is designated as an emerging Hispanic Serving Institution. Due to the diverse population served, the DMCS program is enabling students from underrepresented groups to persist, graduate, and pursue graduate education or enter the STEM workforce. Because all DMCS activities are open to all students, the project is leading to improved retention and graduation rates, and to an increase in the number of students pursuing undergraduate research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1259336</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rosemarie</FirstName>
      <LastName>DePoy Walker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>walkerr@msudenver.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Derrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haynes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haynesd@mscd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bonham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abonham@msudenver.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Metropolitan State University of Denver</Name>
      <CityName>Denver</CityName>
      <ZipCode>802173362</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3035563484</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 173362</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
