<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Trace Metal Deposition And Cycling In The North Atlantic On The 2013 CLIVAR/Repeat Hydrography A16N Expedition</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>211008</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henrietta N. Edmonds</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Joseph Resing of the Joint Institute for the Study of the Atmosphere and the Ocean, Pacific Marine Environmental Laboratory, University of Washington and Dr. William Landing of Florida State University have proposed an ambitous field study to conduct trace metal sampling on the CLIVAR/CO2 Repeat Hydrography section A16N in the Atlantic Ocean in 2013. This field program will provide a valuable opportunity to elucidate aerosol-water column coupling, and possible decadal variability, for selected trace metals (Fe, Al, and others) and biogenic calcium carbonate. In addition to examining important questions regarding the nature of the response of trace element distributions in the water column to external dust input, these invetigators will gain further insight into the issue of temporal and spatial changes in trace metal distributions through comparison with other field programs, most notably the international GEOTRACES program. With regard to the broader significance of this study, results from this large expedition will generate multiple national and international collaborations, contribute positively to the education and training of a graduate student and a postdoctoral fellow, and be of broad interest to the ocean sciences community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1260376</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Resing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>resing@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1670</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9156</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
