<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on QIS in Computer and Natural Sciences, hosted by Joint Quantum Institute, University of Maryland, College Park, MD. September 28-29, 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ann Orel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop on Quantum Information Science in Computer and Natural Sciences is being organized by the Physics Frontier Center at the Joint Quantum Institute of the University of Maryland to help the Computer and Natural Sciences community become aware of the possibilities of developments in Quantum Information Science. This is in connection with the recent program solicitation from the National Science Foundation NSF 12-540 CISE-MPS Interdisciplinary Faculty Program in Quantum Information Science. The workshop plans to have about 65 participants from academic institutions of the United States including 15 speakers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of this workshop stems from the potential to connect people in the computer sciences and other areas of MPS with leading researches in Quantum Information in a favorable environment to foster collaboration, including spending sabbaticals at the QI primary centers in the United States. This will help fulfill the United States National Science and Technology Council report A Federal Vision for Quantum Information Science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of this activity include the multiplicative effect that the participants, when returning to their institutions, will have for the expansion of Quantum Information Science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1261307</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Orozco</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lorozco@physics.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
