<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Ecosystem Studies in the Maquenque National Wildlife Refuge (MNWLR) of Costa Rica</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>290185</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Research Experience For Undergraduates (REU) Site award has been made to Kean University, providing international experience and training for 8 students per year for 10 weeks (5 weeks in Costa Rica and 5 weeks in New Jersey) during the summer of 2013-2015. This REU project will have students conduct research as part of an international team of scientists from Kean University, the Centro Cientifico Tropical and Instituto Biologica Nacional to study the vegetation, invertebrate, primate, soil microbial community structures, biogeochemical, and/or ecological characteristics within a variety of undamaged, damaged, or at-risk habitats in Maquenque National Wildlife Refuge (MNWLR), a new conservation area, in the Northern Zone of Costa Rica. Students will assess if patterns/indicators of change in ecosystem conditions can be observed by habitat, management strategy, and/or atmospheric condition, adding to Costa Rica's natural resource database as students study the differences across different trophic communities within a continuum of habitats in the MNWLR, where little research has been conducted. Students will develop an understanding of the connections between land use, biodiversity and ecosystem function; present their work at a regional ESA conference and submit manuscripts to journals; and have a value-added cultural experience working with the local community in the village of Boca Tapada in their elementary school. Students will receive enhancement activities concerning research methods, data analysis, communicating science, publishing their work in journals, the ethics in scientific investigations and responsible conduct of research, and other support mechanisms to enhance the students' pursuit of graduate programs in ecological/environmental sciences. The PIs will use the NSF REU common assessment tool to assess students' scientific and intellectual gains, and will also track student progress and activities for 3 years post-REU experience. Students will be chosen based on a more holistic perspective that includes transcripts, GPA, an essay on why they want to work in the program, their goals as future scientists, how they think they will benefit from this program, what other research opportunities may exist at their home institution, and 2 letters of recommendation. For more information, please contact Dr. Bill Eaton (weaton@kean.edu) or Dr. Daniela Shebitz (dshebitz@kean.edu).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1262907</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniela</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shebitz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dshebitz@kean.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/13/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniela</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shebitz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dshebitz@kean.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/13/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eaton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weaton@pace.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/13/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eaton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weaton@pace.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/13/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kean University</Name>
      <CityName>Union</CityName>
      <ZipCode>070837131</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9087373461</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Morris Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
