<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU SITE: ASSET: Research Experiences for Undergraduates in Advanced Secured Sensor Enabling Technologies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award renews a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU)Site focused on secured sensor technologies at Florida International University. Undergraduates will work with faculty on research projects to explore new technologies and solutions utilizing sensor networking as well as software and hardware solutions essential to the advancement and practical proliferation of new technologies. The site includes a range of research projects including trajectory privacy preservation in sensor networks, secure social sensor networks, on-chip switch architectures for sensors, software for visualizing large-scale sensor network applications, resource management for security, and surveillance over sensor networks and game theoretic approaches to self-configuring non-cooperative mobile sensors. The objective of the program is to nurture students into computer and communications research fields through an intense, interdisciplinary, collaborative research environment. The program serves as an excellent opportunity for students to participate in many aspects of a scientific research program through a set of well-planned and focused activities that will ramp up student research skills and knowledge in emerging technologies. All activities ensure development of student-faculty and student-student communication to enhance and accelerate the students' research skills and learning in the field. The program will spark an interest in continuing relevant research careers. The goal is to build human capacity in computing and communications research and knowledge. This site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project brings together fields of sensing, computing and communications to pioneer new core technologies along with supportive methods, architectures and toolkits sensor enabling technologies. This effort is based upon an existing and highly successful undergraduate research experience site where diverse group of undergraduates is learning how to conduct research and is becoming prepared to pursue graduate studies. The topics are timely and focus on emerging research with that has the potential to contribute to the research frontiers of the field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The goal of this project is to build human capacity in computing and communications research and knowledge. The program will provide an unparalleled scientific and cross-cultural experience to motivated underrepresented undergraduate students. It aims to influence their choices about further education and future careers and continue to give them confidence to pursue these choices. With specific recruiting efforts that target underrepresented groups such as women, minorities and persons with disabilities, this REU program also aims to increase the size and diversity of the scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1263124</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Niki</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pissinou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pissinou@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sitharama</FirstName>
      <LastName>Iyengar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>iyengar@cis.fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida International University</Name>
      <CityName>Miami</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>L644</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>N532</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7736</Code>
      <Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
