<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU site: Computational Biology Summer Program at Rutgers-Camden</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>320970</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Center for Computational and Integrative Biology (CCIB) at Rutgers University - Camden, will provide research training for 10 students, for 10 weeks during the summers of 2013- 2015 under a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site award. The program focuses on an interdisciplinary approach to research in computational biology and will include integrating experimental biology and computational modeling in fields such as ecology, animal group movement, plant physiology and synthetic engineering of biofuels. The CCIB has faculty from five departments who will serve as mentors and graduate students who will act as near-peer mentors. Participating students are expected to do full-time lab research as well as participate in seminars and workshops, such as publishing, insights on global issues and societal needs, regulatory issues, licensing, and entrepreneurship. The project will introduce students to research in computational biology; encourage students to pursue a major in STEM disciplines and/or a career in scientific research; develop tangible academic, professional, and personal skills; foster a collaborative environment that encourages discovery and innovation; expose students to areas of relevance related to scientific R&amp;D such as ethics and responsible conduct of research, technology transfer; and finally, equip participants to make well informed decisions on their academic and professional career. The REU Site will recruit students that would not otherwise have any access to a research experience. Moreover, the students targeted are expected to be at a critical stage where they are deciding whether to change academic focus, follow a new career path, and/or re-engage in academic study. Students will be recruited in collaboration with a number of New Jersey community colleges and the Joint Base McGuire-Dix-Lakehurst (JBMDL), the nation?s first tri-service military installation. Students are tracked to determine their continued academic interests, their career paths, and the lasting influences of the research experience. The program encourages students to stay connected to their REU experience by participating as "alumni" of the program during orientation of subsequent years. Information about the program will be assessed by various means, including use of an REU common assessment tool. More information is available by visiting http://ccib.camden.rutgers.edu/reu.html , or by contacting the PI (Dr. Benedetto Piccoli at piccoli@camden.rutgers.edu).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1263163</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benedetto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Piccoli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>piccoli@camden.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jomartin@camden.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/17/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University Camden</Name>
      <CityName>Camden</CityName>
      <ZipCode>081021400</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8562252949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>311 N. 5th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
