<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Participant Travel for Workshop on Advanced Power Plant Cooling at the ASME IMECE 2012 Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11638</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruey-Hung Chen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal: 1264886&lt;br/&gt;PI: Garimella &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop proposal will bring together experts in power plant cooling to address a critical issue, that of using clean water in condensers and cooling towers in power plants. The awareness of limited clean water supply has raised focus on this issue since a significant fraction of the water is used in power generation industry. This is part of the Energy-Water nexus issue that has been brought to the forefront recently. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The workshop will include a review of the state of the art in current technology, operating conditions and requirements, related emerging technologies being developed for other industries, and the advances needed in these areas. Leading experts from industry and academia will present these reviews. This will be followed by breakout sessions in selected topics to discuss and identify high impact directions. It is anticipated that a roadmap for future work in cooling technology will come from this workshop. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A motivation for pursuing research in this area is "the increased concern regarding the availability of water and the impact of the cooling water consumption and withdrawal on the environment." The current cooling technology uses condensers that utilize either once-through cooling (where water extracted from a large body such as the sea or lake is used), or cooling towers, or air-cooling to condense the steam discharge from the turbine. The workshop will help identify technologies and challenges towards reducing water consumption in energy generation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1264886</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Srinivas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garimella</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>srinivas.garimella@me.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>064E</Code>
      <Text>Convection heat and mass transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>150E</Code>
      <Text>Conduction/Diffusion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
