<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Processing of Electroactive Polymers in Nanostructured Energy Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>325975</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Triantafillos Mountziaris</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Lau, Kenneth K.S.&lt;br/&gt;Institutions: Drexel University&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1264487&lt;br/&gt;Title: Synthesis and Processing of Electroactive Polymers in Nanostructured Energy Devices&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Energy storage is a key component in the energy conservation equation, especially when considering&lt;br/&gt;sustainable energies like solar and wind, which are more variable and intermittent in nature depending on&lt;br/&gt;the time of day, season of the year, and geographical location. Similarly, the ability to store energy and&lt;br/&gt;use it when demanded will provide a more seamless operation of electric vehicles whether during&lt;br/&gt;acceleration/deceleration or in cruise mode. Among different energy storage technologies, supercapacitors&lt;br/&gt;or electrochemical capacitors are emerging as an attractive option for delivering much higher power (rate&lt;br/&gt;of energy transfer) than alternative options like the lithium ion battery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Supercapacitors that store charge through electrochemical double layers possess higher power density but&lt;br/&gt;lack sufficient energy density. By incorporating electroactive polymers, which undergo relatively fast&lt;br/&gt;redox reactions, further pseudocapacitance can be added to enhance energy density. However, as the&lt;br/&gt;supercapacitor electrodes are typically highly porous nanostructures, there remains significant synthesis&lt;br/&gt;and processing challenges in adding the electroactive polymers onto the surfaces of pores inside these&lt;br/&gt;nanostructures without sacrificing surface area or pore access. The PI plans an oxidative&lt;br/&gt;chemical vapor deposition (oCVD) approach that will address many of the challenges by enabling the&lt;br/&gt;conformal, uniform growth of thin films of electroactive polymers inside porous nanostructured materials.&lt;br/&gt;The central hypothesis is that the liquid-free, vapor-to-solid polymerization reactions will lead to surface&lt;br/&gt;confined polymer growth and ultrathin films that do not significantly alter the underlying pore structure&lt;br/&gt;while adding appreciable pseudocapacitance. This work will involve (1) synthesis of&lt;br/&gt;electroactive polymer thin films in porous nanostructures, (2) understanding the effect of processing on&lt;br/&gt;polymer structure and properties, and (3) assembly and electrochemical analysis of pseudocapacitors that&lt;br/&gt;make use of oCVD to incorporate the electroactive polymers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work is expected to deliver enhanced supercapacitors with significantly&lt;br/&gt;higher specific capacitance, energy density, power density and cycle stability, making them viable for use&lt;br/&gt;in electric and hybrid vehicles as well as in the development of greener energy systems that include solar&lt;br/&gt;cells and fuel cells. Fundamentally, the work is expected to provide an effective synthesis and&lt;br/&gt;processing methodology for conformally coating porous nanostructures that will have broader utility in&lt;br/&gt;other nanoscale devices, including electronics, sensors, solar cells, fuel cells, transistors and organic light-emitting diodes (OLEDs). Integrated with the research is an education program, which aims to train graduate and undergraduate&lt;br/&gt;students as well as to engage high school students in polymers for energy. Minority and underrepresented&lt;br/&gt;students will be actively recruited to participate in the project. In addition, outreach will be&lt;br/&gt;made to schools in Philadelphia and inner city Camden, NJ to promote STEM involvement and learning&lt;br/&gt;early on.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1264487</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth K.S.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>klau@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1403</Code>
      <Text>PROCESS &amp; REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>047E</Code>
      <Text>REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
