<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Logistical Planning for Scientific Drilling in Lake Towuti, Indonesia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>39982</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The overarching goal of this project is to develop new records of terrestrial climate and&lt;br/&gt;environmental change in central Indonesia spanning multiple glacial-interglacial cycles over the late Pleistocene through continental scientific drilling in Lake Towuti, the largest lake in Indonesia. Lake Towuti has long been recognized as a priority drilling site for a global lake drilling program due to its location in the climatically-important Indo-Pacific region, its extraordinarily high rates of biodiversity and biological endemism, and its location within the East Sulawesi Ophiolite, giving rise to important biogeochemical cycles of carbon, iron, chromium, and other metals. Recent geophysical and piston coring surveys, combined with an international workshop, have developed the scientific rationale and hypotheses behind the Towuti Drilling Project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning grant will provide funds to conduct site visits to Lake Towuti with drilling engineers and personnel to develop a logistically feasible drilling plan for Towuti, and to develop a budget that is both realistic and cost-effective for drilling proposals to be submitted in 2013. In particular, this award will provide funds for two trips to Lake Towuti for the lead PI and DOSECC Exploration Services (DES) staff to:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) Identify sites on Lake Towuti for constructing, deploying, and recovering a drilling barge, to identify local contractors for site improvements related to barge deployment (e.g. dock construction), and to develop a budget for these activities;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2) Develop a concrete plan and budget for housing the drilling barge crew near Lake Towuti;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3) Finalize agreements with PT Vale Indonesia Tbk, a local mining company, for logistical support in the areas of shipping, import/export, supplies, and other local needs;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;4) Identify local contractors for heavy equipment supply, fuel supply, and other services, and obtain price quotes for those services;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;5) Obtain up-to-date information on permitting procedures for large, international projects such as the Towuti Drilling Project;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;6) Finalize and verify a budget for the Towuti Drilling Project for drilling proposal submission to the International Continental Drilling Program, the NSF, and other national agencies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1265296</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Russell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james_russell@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/05/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
