<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Highly Sensitive Multiple Biomarker Biosensor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Researchers plan to further develop a biosensor prototype device in order to prepare it for possible future use in medical and research fields. This prototype is an Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay based biosensor that is capable of simultaneously detecting very low concentrations of various biomarkers with minimal false positives and false negatives. If successful, this will lay the foundation for early detection and monitoring of colorectal cancer that can potentially save lives and improve healthcare. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Further development of the biosensor could lead to impacts in the pharmaceutical and biotechnological fields through advanced technologies of drug development and therapeutics. Additionally, if successful, the biosensor will demonstrate the effectiveness of nanotechnology approaches to overcome diagnostic challenges. This technology could aid medical professionals by furthering their knowledge on how to address low sensitivity and high specificity detection of diseases in their early stages.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1265141</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ahmed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Busnaina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>busnaina@coe.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
