<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Planning Grant: I/UCRC for e-Design: IT Enabled Design and Realization of Engineered Products and Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14380</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence A. Hornak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A new site is to be planned at Oregon State University for the Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) for e-Design. The I/UCRC for e-Design conducts research that supports a new design paradigm for the development of engineered products and systems that allows customer driven design and product realization and virtual simulation and prototyping that encompasses the entire product life cycle. The planned Oregon State site will complement the existing center?s activities through focus in the following areas: 1) optimization of products and systems, 2) failure, reliability, and robustness analysis; 3) early stage design theories and methodologies, 4) manufacturing and lifecycle analysis, 5) cost and choice modeling; 6) design for sustainability; 7) computational design; and 8) design innovation education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The e-Design center addresses an area central to the competitiveness of U.S. manufacturing. The center site at Oregon State University has the potential to further expand the diversity of member companies in the overall center and expose all member firms to a broader base of discovery in the e-Design area. Results of the site?s research efforts will be integrated into the educational curriculum in design, modeling and simulation, decision analysis, and optimization. Student engagement in center work will include laboratory and field studies, attendance of and presentations at interdisciplinary conferences and workshops, a design colloquium series, participation in interdisciplinary activities and journal publications, as well as training in the ethical conduct of research. The addition of Oregon State University to the Center contributes to the diversity of the Center, with the leadership team and 30% of participating faculty being women, typically underrepresented in engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1265970</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Irem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tumer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>irem.tumer@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rstone@engr.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8043</Code>
      <Text>System Design and Simulation</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
