<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Core Support for the Institute for Laboratory Animal Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>304778</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Edda (Floh) Thiels</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An award is made to the National Academy of Sciences to support the Institute for Laboratory Research (ILAR) to: 1) convene annual meetings of the ILAR Council advisory body; 2) support staff time to develop topics for new studies and projects and perform tasks related to completed studies; and 3) support staff time to produce the ILAR Journal. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mission of Institute for Laboratory Animal Research (ILAR) is to evaluate and report on the scientific, technological, and ethical use of animals and related biological resources and of non-animal alternatives in non-food settings, such as research, testing, education, and production of pharmaceuticals. ILAR seeks to identify practices that provide for excellence in the welfare of animals used for these purposes, recognizing their moral value while achieving high-quality science. ILAR also evaluates and encourages the use, development, and validation of non-animal alternatives. By engaging the expertise residing in the laboratory animal science, veterinary, and broader biological research communities, ILAR formulates and disseminates guidelines and standards for humane and scientifically sound animal care and use and provides independent and objective advice on developments and key research opportunities in laboratory animal science and medicine to the U.S. federal government, the international biological research community, and the public. More information can be found at: http://dels.nas.edu/ilar/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1265238</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frances</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharples</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fsharples@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1165</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
