<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I/UCRC: New Site of I/UCRC Safety, Security, and Rescue Research Center</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>160000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of North Carolina at Charlotte's site for the Safety, Security and Rescue Research I/UCRC intends to contribute to the mission of the existing center to conduct integrative, multi-disciplinary research in autonomous systems to improve homeland security and emergency response. The site plans to extend the scope of SSR to healthcare, energy, material handling, and manufacturing, by focusing on human safety, injury prevention, and patient care. The new SSR I/UCRC site intends to address areas including autonomous and guided robot actions for both sensing and manipulation under high-level human control, multi-agent, integration of real-time multi-modal sensory data, secure real-time computational analysis of safety critical SSR scenarios.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SSR Technologies are having world-wide impact in both the private and government sector. Moreover, application of these technologies is having impact that touches individual citizens. The University of North Carolina at Charlotte's Site of the SSR I/UCRC intends to extend the research outcomes it brings to the center to a new set of industries both regionally and nationally not currently represented in the center drawing upon complementary research domains. The site intends to leverage its I/UCRC site and strong NSF-funded programs on broadening participation in computing (e.g., the STARS Alliance) and REU Site by providing opportunities to engage undergraduate students from underrepresented groups and encourage them to enter graduate study.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1266162</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xiao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xiao@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Srinivas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Akella</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sakella@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8039</Code>
      <Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
