<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Algebra Extravaganza</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24949</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy Hodges</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the conference Algebra Extravaganza which will take place on the main campus of Temple University on July 24-28, 2017. Algebra is a very broad and vital part of mathematics which involves everything from the study of solutions of polynomial equations to the study of subtle abstract algebraic structures. It lays the necessary foundation for other branches of mathematics such as algebraic geometry, number theory, representation theory and algebraic topology. This conference is devoted to the recent research activities on the interplay between Noncommutative Algebra with Invariant Theory, Representation Theory, and Algebraic Geometry. Many recent conferences in these areas of algebra have focused on parts of these connections, but this conference will be unique in that it will feature talks on a large variety of topics. The conference will feature over 20 lectures from world-renowned experts, and should attract around 75-100 participants from the international mathematics community. In addition to regular talks by experts, the conference will feature a poster session as a networking opportunity for junior participants. Funding will be prioritized for junior participants and for women and underrepresented minorities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference will bring together research leaders in Noncommutative Algebra, whose expertise have connections to Invariant Theory, Representation Theory, and Algebraic Geometry. Focus topic areas include: algebraic deformation theory; cluster algebras and cluster categories; Hopf algebras and their actions on algebras; noncommutative invariant theory; noncommutative projective algebraic geometry; noncommutative resolutions of singularities; and Poisson algebras and Calabi-Yau algebras. Further information can be found at the conference website: https://math.temple.edu/events/conferences/k-l/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1712663</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vasiliy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dolgushev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vald@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chelsea</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>notlaw@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Temple University</Name>
      <CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191405104</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2157077379</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3340 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
