<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Long Term Spatiotemporal Control to Investigate Dynamics in Xenopus Laevis Embryonic Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>144333</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This collaborative research project will develop a system for investigating embryonic development. Specifically the team will develop a system for controlling the chemical environment of nearly microscopic (~1/20th of an inch) samples of embryonic tissues, such as from the African clawed frog, Xenopus laevis, frequently used by biologists. By controlling the region of the tissue that is exposed to different chemicals, and the time for which it is exposed, the research team can gain unprecedented insight into the embryonic development process. Our system will employ sophisticated independent control of five inlet-ports supplying three different fluidic streams. This system will have a wide range of applications for manipulation of the complex chemical environment of engineered tissues. Deliverables include (1) the development of micro-fluidic systems and control systems capable of regulating complex 2D and 3D flow patterns, (2) a novel control algorithm design methodology for dealing with uncertain dynamics, and (3) fluorescent biosensor tools for evaluating control over the microfluidic environment of embryonic tissues. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide tools for tissue engineers to precisely control chemical stimulation that may be useful for creating new tissues for long term future clinical application. The work will combine techniques that previously have been successfully implemented in microfabrication and automatic control of disk drives. These tools may be used to create complex patterns of chemical stimulation to growing cells for manufacturing of engineered tissues. Dissemination of our results will also lead to new devices with increased accuracies, reliability, and functionality for commercial and basic science applications. In addition, this project will train undergraduate and graduate students to become leaders in science and industry in transdisciplinary fields including dynamic systems/controls, biology, microtechnology, and engineering. The team will also reach out to underrepresented K-12 students in academically challenged neighborhoods to build their knowledge and their interest in STEM.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1100515</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lance</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davidson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lad43@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1632</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>030E</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
