<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Random Structures and Algorithms Conference - 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 15th International Conference on Random Structures &amp; Algorithms&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 15th International Conference on Random Structures &amp; Algorithms &lt;br/&gt;will take place at Emory University in Atlanta, May 24 - 28, 2011. &lt;br/&gt;This is a biennial meeting, initiated in 1983 by the Faculty of Mathematics, Adam Mickiewicz University, in Poznan, Poland. The aims of these conferences are to present recent research results and to identify and explore directions for further research in random discrete structures, randomized algorithms and broad areas of applications of probabilistic methods in discrete mathematics, computer science, and related fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference is established as a key locus for the exposition of trends and breakthroughs in the development of probabilistic methods and their application in discrete mathematics and CS theory.&lt;br/&gt;The choice of the plenary speakers highlights important themes ranging from classical topics such as Ramsey theory, phase transitions in random graphs, and the regularity lemma, which have seen recent exciting progress, to modern ones including message passing algorithms, unique games related hardness of approximation for optimization problems, internet related mechanism design, auctions, and computational game theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A main feature of the conferences is the mix of researchers from discrete mathematics, theoretical CS and optimization, attracted by a common interest in probabilistic tools and their application. Holding the meeting in Atlanta is intended to attract more involvement from the CS theory community, which is arguably best-developed in this country. Conference activities will be widely disseminated by the conference proceedings in Random Structures &amp; Algorithms, a leading research journal, on the conference website, and through archived and/or streaming video of selected lectures. We hope to attract, and support, a large number of students and postdoctoral researchers, and participants from groups under-represented in the community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1101623</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dwight</FirstName>
      <LastName>Duffus</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dwight@mathcs.emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vojtech</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rodl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rodl@mathcs.emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Prasad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tetali</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tetali@math.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrzej</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rucinski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>andrzej@mathcs.emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Emory University</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
