<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Streaming Ultracold Neutral Plasmas</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven J Gitomer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In plasmas, charged particles move together in concert to produce density or velocity patterns that oscillate in time in what are called collective modes. Collective modes often dominate the properties of plasmas, such as their stability, so it is crucial to understand them. This work will study ion collective modes in ultracold neutral plasmas for the first time. Ultracold neutral plasmas are created by laser ionization of clouds of atoms that have been cooled to temperatures as low as 1/1000th of a degree above absolute zero. In addition to expanding our fundamental understanding of an exotic regime of nature, these experiments may shed light on the physics of dense plasmas in thermonuclear devices or the cores of gas giant planets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this proposal starts with the training of graduate students for careers in science and technology. It is augmented by the diversity of Rice's physics program and strength of Rice's geographical location for attracting minority students to the program. One third of the students who have worked on these projects in the past have been women, and one third have been under-represented minorities. An additional goal of the project is to attract and retain more students in science and engineering through involvement of undergraduate students. These experiments are ideal for this purpose because concepts are accessible and lasers capture students' imaginations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1102516</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Killian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>killian@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1242</Code>
      <Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1062</Code>
      <Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
