<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>139200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henrietta N. Edmonds</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Arctic climate change is resulting in rising temperatures and decreasing sea ice extent. Interactions between sea ice and the atmosphere lead to unique halogen chemistry, resulting in significant losses of atmospheric ozone and mercury. However, significant uncertainty remains in our understanding of the spatial distribution and conditions associated with Arctic ozone depletion events, due to measurement challenges. This research project involves analysis of in-situ ozone and BrO data from long-term O-buoy measurements across the Arctic Ocean, as well as field campaign measurements in Barrow, Alaska. O-buoy data will enable development and evaluation of both simple (zero- and one-dimensional) air-sea ice models, as well as regional atmospheric chemistry models to examine the oxidation pathways in the Arctic. This will improve our ability to predict the impacts of future climate and sea ice changes on the Arctic atmosphere. This integrated understanding is essential to better inform decision-makers about future Arctic system changes. Given the importance of educating the public about science, and climate change in particular, public outreach activities will be integrated into this research in the form of elementary school activities and through the Purdue Climate Change Research Center.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1103423</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kerri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pratt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>08/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pratt Kerri A</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479061043</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5247</Code>
      <Text>POST DOC/TRAVEL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
