<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Gromov-Witten theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300100</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-1103368&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Yongbin Ruan&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During the past twenty years, there has been a great deal of&lt;br/&gt;interaction between mathematic and physics. Various&lt;br/&gt;correspondences or dualities arising from physics have had a&lt;br/&gt;great impact on mathematics. One of these correspondences is the&lt;br/&gt;Landau-Ginzburg/Calabi-Yau correspondence. This proposal offers a&lt;br/&gt;comprehensive program to establish this correspondence in&lt;br/&gt;mathematics with mathematical rigor. There is a wide range of&lt;br/&gt;applications such as global mirror symmetry, the computation of&lt;br/&gt;Gromov-Witten invariants of compact Calabi-Yau manifolds, and to&lt;br/&gt;modular forms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since the era of Newton, mathematics has been a key tool in&lt;br/&gt;helping us to comprehend the universe. An example is&lt;br/&gt;differential geometry via Einstein's theory of general&lt;br/&gt;relativity. During the last twenty years there has been a great&lt;br/&gt;deal of activity in building so-called string-theoretic models of&lt;br/&gt;the universe. The string-theoretic model of the universe is&lt;br/&gt;ten-dimensional, our usual 4-dimensional space-time togeher with&lt;br/&gt;a very small 6-dimensional space called a Calabi-Yau manifold.&lt;br/&gt;Such a small internal space will affect our space-time through&lt;br/&gt;certain mathematical quantities such as Gromov-Witten&lt;br/&gt;invariants. The computation of these invariants has been a&lt;br/&gt;central problem in geometry and physics. This is the area in&lt;br/&gt;which mathematical tools can be very useful. The current&lt;br/&gt;proposal envisages a theoretical framework as well as developing&lt;br/&gt;technical tools to compute Gromov-Witten invariants</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1103368</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yongbin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ruan@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
