<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology for FY 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>189000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Vanni</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2011, Broadening Participation. The fellowship supports a research and training plan in a host laboratory for the Fellow who also presents a plan to broaden participation in biology. The title of the research and training plan for this fellowship to Shermin DeSilva is "Social stratification and leadership in elephants." The host institution for this fellowship is the Colorado State University, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. George Wittemyer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Socioecology explores how social and ecological factors structure animal societies. This research builds much-needed bridges between theory and empirical observation in the study of social evolution. It poses three inter-related questions: 1) How does resource availability influence social cohesion? 2) What effect does this have on dominance and leadership behavior? 3) How do individuals adjust to social disruption? Theoretical predictions are tested by comparing the social behavior of wild Asian and African elephants, sister species that experience different ecological pressures. It examines how the spatial arrangement and abundance of resources shape social relationships via individual movement decisions, whether this in turn drives the emergence of leadership and dominance hierarchies, and ultimately how individuals cope with changes such as the loss of a companion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Training objectives include acquiring experience working with a diverse array of data ranging from animal movements, to satellite imagery, and social networks. It also offers a comparative perspective on research and conservation in the African context relative to the Asian, with direct implications for wildlife management. Both field sites host local and foreign students at the undergraduate and graduate level, including those from the U.S. and Europe, encouraging collaboration and exchange of expertise. Researchers also oversee community-based education and sustainable livelihood programs seeking to reduce conflict between people and elephants. Long-term goals are not only to further the study of behavior, but also to address the challenges people and wildlife face in living together through participatory science-based conservation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1103468</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shermin</FirstName>
      <LastName>deSilva</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/11/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>deSilva Shermin</Name>
      <CityName>Concord</CityName>
      <ZipCode>945182908</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1157</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY POSTDOC RSRCH FLW-NEW</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1036</Code>
      <Text>BIO MINORITY POSTDOC RESEARCH FELLOW PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
