<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-Egypt Cooperative Research: Managing Grid Integration of Large-Scale Wind Power Parks using Energy Storage Technology and Demand Response</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>169899</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lara Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1104023 &lt;br/&gt;This project supports a cooperative research project by Dr. Saifur Rahman at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (VA Tech) and Dr. Mohamed El-Sobki, Cairo University, Cairo, Egypt. They plan to study the management of grid integration of large scale wind power parks. As large wind power parks, or wind farms, rapidly expand around the world, electric power systems operators face new challenges. While it is desirable to use the zero-emission wind energy, managing large wind parks integration is difficult due to the intermittency and fluctuation of their power production. Therefore, it is of the interest of the United States, Egypt, and other countries with wind generation to seek solutions for integration of large wind farms without compromising their power grid stability and reliability. This research involves using an energy storage technology and demand response techniques for managing the grid integration of large wind parks. Specifically, it aims to develop novel sizing, scheduling and control methods to enable an application based on compressed-air energy storage (CAES) technology for partial smoothing of the high-rate fluctuations of multiple wind parks output. Furthermore, it develops a new operation scheme for combining the load regulation capability of demand response techniques with the energy storage to increase wind power utilization and thereby reduce wind curtailment. The application is also designed with added functions to provide real and reactive power support for stabilizing the power grid and coping with grid emergency situations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will develop novel sizing, scheduling and control methods for compressed-air energy storage technology (CAES), which are applied to wind power integration applications at utility scale. It will also develop a new operation scheme for combining the load regulation capability of demand response techniques with CAES. The research outcome will contribute a set of analytical tools, which are needed for managing the integration of large-scale wind power parks into power systems while ensuring the safe operation of the power grids.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The research outcome will fill in the need for high-efficiency solutions to manage wind power on a large scale. The resulted application based on CAES technology and demand response will improve the integration and conservation of wind energy, which benefit both electric utilities and wind developers. Increased wind energy integration helps utilities meet their renewable mandates and enhances revenues for wind investors. This international collaborative project creates a valuable opportunity for U.S.&lt;br/&gt;researchers and students to work with Egyptian researchers on the technical problems for mutual benefit.&lt;br/&gt;Overall, the joint research contributes innovative tools to ensure safe operation of power grids, increase wind energy usage thereby reducing carbon emissions and helping protect the environment. These factors foster the sustainable economic development of Egypt and the United States. The US team includes two women scientists at Virginia Tech, Dr. Ha Thu Le, a postdoctoral researcher and Dr. Manisa Pipattanasomporn, a junior scientist.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1104023</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Saifur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rahman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Srahman@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7680</Code>
      <Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5944</Code>
      <Text>EGYPT (COOP SCIENCE)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5976</Code>
      <Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
