<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI/FRG: Layered Systems with Dynamically Evolving Structure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1966681</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: Mounting concerns about the availability, environmental impact and cost of energy on the economic health and well being of society provide strong motivation for substantial improvements in the efficiency of propulsion and power generation systems. Crucial to these improvements are material systems capable of higher temperature operation, epitomized by multi-layer engineered surfaces in gas turbine engines. An interdisciplinary academic/industry team aims to develop the scientific understanding needed to meet the challenge and guide progress in this critical technology. Emphasis is on (i) the science-based discovery of materials with the requisite performance and durability in the unprecedented conditions expected in future engines, and (ii) establishing the relationships between materials chemistry, structure and properties to enable materials design and implementation. By collaborating closely with a leading engine manufacturer, the outcomes of the scientific research have a direct and more immediate impact on technology and its design infrastructure. The project builds on established relationships between the academic and industrial participants and a network of international collaborators that create an exceptional educational environment where students (i) work on scientifically challenging problems with substantial potential for technological impact, (ii) are mentored by an interdisciplinary team of academic and industrial experts in the field, and (iii) have opportunities for research internships at industrial laboratories and international institutions. The team has an established record of promoting the participation of undergraduates, women and members of underrepresented groups in research projects and international experiences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS: The overarching objective of this project is to establish a science-based framework for underpinning the conceptual design of new materials systems for gas turbine engines with substantially improved efficiency. The aims of the research are (i) to understand the limitations of current materials to meet the temperature/performance targets of advanced engine technology, (ii) to explore new directions in materials design, and (iii) to develop the science base needed for implementation. Key elements of the strategy include (i) an interdisciplinary, systems-based approach, (ii) the use of multiphase constituent layers designed to evolve readily into a desirable configuration and retain functionality over the life of the system, and (iii) the development of modeling approaches that allow efficient assessment of concepts and guide their experimental validation. Because of the chemical and morphological complexity of the layered architectures, novel computational tools are needed to capture and integrate the dynamics of the system and the individual layers. Simulations are coupled with a strong experimental activity to identify and solve the critical challenges in design, synthesis/processing, and characterization of the structures and their constitutive behavior. Scientific advances are envisaged within the following themes: (i) constitutive behavior of multiphase oxides and alloys, as well as their interfaces, at relevant temperatures (ii) synthesis of metastable structures and their evolution into phase assemblages with the desired attributes, (iii) the thermodynamics, diffusion and phase transformation mechanisms/kinetics underpinning said evolution, (iv) the role of stresses arising from the internal system dynamics and/or imposed thermal/mechanical stimuli on the structural stability and evolution of damage, (v) approaches to probe the state of the system and its properties at various stages in the evolution. The project offers unique educational experiences for students and post-doctoral scholars by (i) learning first-hand how to work within an interdisciplinary research group focused on a scientific theme in the context of a critical technology; (ii) acquiring knowledge of industrial research-team protocols by combining well designed internships with co-supervision by the industrial team members; and (iii) participating in international research exchanges with foreign institutions (in Australia, Japan, Germany and the UK) and in topical workshops. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;FUNDING: This National Science Foundation project is co-funded by two of the Office of International Science and Engineering (OISE)'s Programs: (1) East Asia and Pacific, and (2) Europe and Eurasia; the Engineering Directorate and the Mathematical and Physical Sciences Directorate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1105672</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Levi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>levic@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van der Ven</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>avdv@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tresa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pollock</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pollock@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Begley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>begley@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Don</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lipkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lipkin@ge.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1771</Code>
      <Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1774</Code>
      <Text>CERAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1589</Code>
      <Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5936</Code>
      <Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9165</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY-INDUSTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
