<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Shaping Colloids for Self Assembly</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Sokol</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will explore and develop the role of particle shape in the self assembly of colloids. Until recently, the basic shapes used in colloidal self assembly have been limited to spheres and rods, which has limited colloidal structures to fcc, bcc, and a few simple variants. The inability to achieve the same richness of structures observed for atomic and molecular crystals in colloidal crystals has been brought into sharp relief by the challenge of making photonic colloidal crystals with the diamond or similar symmetries, as such crystals should exhibit full photonic band gaps. This project will focus on developing two new colloidal systems: (1) lock-and-key colloids and (2) cubic colloids. Both sets of colloids represent a significant departure from existing colloids and lead to new structures and new kinds of phase transitions. The aim is to explore the various kinds of structures that can be made using these new building blocks and to develop models that capture the basic physics controlling their formation. The depletion interaction will be used as the primary means of controlling the strength and range of the interaction. The anisotropic shapes of the particles will be exploited to generate directional and specific interactions, both of which are relatively new to colloidal science. A related goal is to develop mechanisms for precise control of the relative placement of colloids made from disparate materials, thus increasing their potential for making useful new materials, including photonic crystals, catalysts, and solar cells. The research will support the education of a PhD student in interdisciplinary science involving physics, chemistry, and materials science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A central goal of 21st century materials science is to fabricate nanomaterials from the "bottom up" rather than relying on the traditional the "top down" approach. Thus, instead of imprinting small structures on large objects, as is typically done in top-down approaches for making computer chips, the idea is to make nanoscale components that assemble themselves from the bottom up into complex useful materials. In this bottom up approach, the small nanoscale components carry with them the information required for them to assemble into the desired structures. This project will explore strategies for bottom-up self-assembly of nanoscale objects using particle shape as the mechanism by which particles recognize each other and fit into a larger structural design, much as jigsaw puzzle pieces fit together to form a large picture. The challenge is two-fold in that new techniques to make particles with complex shapes will be developed along with design schemes for directing their assembly. These methods should be useful in developing new materials for optical switching and circuitry as well as for solar cells. This project will support the education of a graduate student in these advance techniques for careers in advanced science and technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1105455</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pine</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pine@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1710</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
