<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Russian Indigenous and Environmental Collaboration to Promote Sustainable Use of the Arctic</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49449</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anna Kerttula de Echave</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a small workshop project to support the participation of Arctic indigenous scholars and students in a discussion of Arctic sustainability. The workshop is to be held in Krasnoyarsk, Russia following the larger international conference, "Arctic: A Territory of Dialogue." The main theme of interest from this conference to be discussed at the Krasnoyarsk workshop is: How science and communities can collaborate on topics crucial to the vision of Arctic sustainability - key topics to be discussed are: how short lived climate forcers impact climate change; impacts of seismic exploration on marine mammals, fisheries and other subsistence resources; the observed changes in Pacific walrus populations in relationship to climate change; the broader Russian national vision of the Arctic, e.g., resource development in a changing Arctic and the cross boarder national Beringia park, to name a few. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Pacific Environment will facilitate the participation of over 40 scientists, indigenous leaders, policy experts, and students in the workshop. Following the workshop PE will continue web-based communication forums among the participants and implement a "Young Leaders'" program that continues to facilitate indigenous youth participation in future workshops on key issues affecting their communities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1106857</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Galina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Angarova</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gangarova@pacificenvironment.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pacific Environment and Resources Center</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941084530</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4153998850</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>251 Kearny Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
