<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Curriculum and Assessment Partnership Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>135119</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patricia S. Wilson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Consortium for Mathematics and Its Applications is engaged in an effort to bring together members of the community of mathematics curriculum developers and experts in assessment, including representatives and stakeholders from the two assessment consortia recently funded by the US Department of Education. The primary goal of the meeting is to discuss issues and recommend actions regarding assessment design and production that arise in an environment of Common Core State Standards (CCSS). The format will allow information exchange and resource sharing in the service of states and districts as they work to effectively implement the CCSS. Participants will include representatives from the governing states as well as from the leadership teams of the assessment consortia along with experts in curriculum development, standards implementation and assessment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work is being carried out with the support and cooperation of the National Council of Teachers of Mathematics, the National Council of Supervisors of Mathematics, the Association of Mathematics Teacher Educators, and the Association of State Supervisors of Mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1108723</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Solomon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garfunkel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sol@comap.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/03/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Consortium For Mathematics &amp; Its Applications Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Bedford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>017300000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7818627878</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>175 Middlesex Turnpike Suite 3b</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
