<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multidimensional Incoherent Spectroscopy for Measuring Condensed-Phase Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>427000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemical Measurement and Imaging program in the Division of Chemistry, Prof. Mark Berg and his group at the University of South Carolina are developing and applying new methods to assess the rates of chemical processes (including peptide conformational dynamics) in heterogeneous materials. Traditional "one-dimensional" spectroscopic methods use a single excitation source and measure rates over a single time period. Prof. Berg is developing multidimensional methods that use more than one excitation source and measure rates over multiple periods. By using three excitation pulses, both the distribution and rates of conformational change will be measured. Multidimensional methods are also being broadened to include light pulses of variable polarization and thereby measure the distribution of local viscosities within bulk polymers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Kinetic measurements are used throughout chemistry, biology, physics and engineering. The fundamentally new approaches to kinetics developed in this program will provide new tools to all these areas. Training in advanced spectroscopy will be done at the University of South Carolina, which is both geographically underserved and has a large population of students from underrepresented groups. In addition, Prof. Berg is collaborating with Prof. Peter Chen of Spelman College, an HBCU for women, to adapt the technological development from this project to an undergraduate research environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1111530</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>berg@sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6880</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
