<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Developing an Adaptive Compact Fuel Reformer with an Ultra-Fine Homogenous Atomizer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruth M. Shuman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project will investigate the merits and&lt;br/&gt;feasibility of an Adaptive Compact Fuel Reformer (ACFR) using an Ultra-Fine Homogeneous&lt;br/&gt;Atomizer based on an autothermal process. Diesel reformer is the key to provide syngas (H2+CO) for&lt;br/&gt;fuel cell auxiliary power unit (APU) which can significantly reduce engine idling fuel cost. Hydrogen&lt;br/&gt;rich syngas with EGR is effective for simultaneously reducing engine NOx and PM emissions.&lt;br/&gt;However, most diesel reformers face challenges of auto-ignition control, coking and fuel slip, size&lt;br/&gt;and weight reduction, and durability issues, etc. The key innovation of the adaptive compact fuel&lt;br/&gt;reformer is an ultra-fine atomizer, which has an innovative micro-circular orifice coupling ultra-thin&lt;br/&gt;layer of fuel spray, steam and air flow simultaneously. The atomizer can produce very small fuel&lt;br/&gt;droplets (~10 micron) and homogenous mixture, which can be quickly vaporized and converted into&lt;br/&gt;syngas in a small space without auto-ignition, coking and slip. The Phase I work will complete the&lt;br/&gt;key design work for the fuel reformer and conduct lab bench scale testing for key components.&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impacts of this research are significant potential benefits for US&lt;br/&gt;energy security and environment protection. The potential customers include engine OEMs and auto&lt;br/&gt;makers. The industry-university collaborated research will help graduate students carry on&lt;br/&gt;fundamental research while providing deeper understanding of diesel fuel reformation for commercial&lt;br/&gt;applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1113660</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deyang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dalianqlc@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>QuantLogic Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Sugar Land</CityName>
      <ZipCode>774793809</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2819807288</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5111 Avondale Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
