<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI: Establishing an Open Forum for Innovation in Advanced Fluorescent Microspectroscopy Technology for Molecular Imaging in Living Cells</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>570543</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Partnerships for Innovation project from the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (UWM) focuses on innovation in the area of fast-acquisition-speed spectrally resolved two-photon microscopy (SR-TPM) and identification of biomarkers and labeled antibodies for use in research, diagnostics, and drug screening applications. As part of the PFI project, an Open Forum for Innovation (OFI) will be established to develop and guide proof-of-concept experiments in several areas related to SR-TPM technology development and applications: (1) high-spectral resolution and high-acquisition speed imaging scanners, (2) fiber laser alternatives to current solid-state lasers, and (3) novel biomarkers and labeled antibodies for detecting transient interactions between proteins in vivo, identifying rare cell types (such as circulating cancer cells) in body fluids, and developing living cell assays for cell signaling pathways to be used for drug screening. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this research are (1) expansion of the SR-TPM customer base, currently represented by cellular biologists, to include both biochemists and drug researchers; (2) introduction of fiber laser products more broadly to the microscopy market; and (3) expansion of applications of fast-acquisition speed spectrally resolved fluorescence microscopy to include development of targeted diagnostics and therapeutics. This team's ability to address such needs would significantly expand the U.S. presence in the scanning fluorescent microscope market, by providing product capabilities that exceed those of existing products. Proof-of-concept experiments to be conducted will directly involve graduate, undergraduate students, and postdoctoral researchers who will work alongside consultants and lab scientists from the&lt;br/&gt;knowledge-enhancement partner companies. To add to the university's innovation capacity and create a cadre of UWM-grown scientist-entrepreneurs during the performance period of this project, OFI will evolve into a UWM University-Small Businesses Collaboratory (UWM-USBC), which will offer resources and networking opportunities to its member investigators, establish a gateway for businesses to UWM-developed technology, and promote the PFI project leaders as role models for knowledge transfer within UWM, in the Southeast Wisconsin area, and in the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partners at the inception of the project include the Knowledge Enhancement Partnership (KEP) unit, consisting of UWM (College of Letters and Science (through its Department of Physics) and the Graduate School at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee), and three small businesses: Aurora Spectral Technologies, LLC (Milwaukee, WI), NeoClone Biotechnology International, LLC (Madison, WI), and PolarOnyx, Inc. (San Jose, CA). In addition, there are other core partners. These include private sector organizations: Brandt Innovative Technologies, Inc. (Pewaukee, WI) and the UWM Research Foundation, Inc. (UWMRF, Milwaukee, WI). In addition, two industrial collaborators and potential end users: MetriTrack, LLC (Hillside, IL) and AndroBioSys, Inc. (Buffalo, NY)], as well as academic collaborators and potential end users from the University of Toronto and University of Wisconsin-Madison, have already expressed strong interest in participating in the OFI.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1114305</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scanes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scanes@uwm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/04/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Valerica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Raicu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vraicu@uwm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lovell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mlovell@uwm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/30/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee</Name>
      <CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4142294853</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O BOX 340</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
