<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support: 7th International Symposium on Bioinformatics Research and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant will provide partial travel support for US graduate students, post-doctoral scholars, and keynote speakers attending the International Symposium on Bioinformatics Research and Applications to be held on May 27-29, 2011 at Central South University in Changsha, China. The symposium aims to bring together faculty, students, junior and senior researchers, including women and members of underrepresented groups, for three days of scholarly communication on latest advances in all aspects of bioinformatics and computational biology and their applications. A main objective of the 2011 symposium is to promote communication between researchers in the US and China and particularly engagement of life scientists, statisticians, and computer scientists in cross-disciplinary transnational collaborations. The Chinese participation will be supported by the National Science Foundation of China (pending approval).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to contributed abstracts, the technical program will include tutorials, panel discussions, and poster sessions, and will feature invited keynote talks by distinguished researchers in the field. The program will provide ample opportunities for interaction between researchers with complementary expertise and foster joint US-China research projects and scientific collaborations after the symposium in all areas of bioinformatics research, ranging from comparative genomics and population genetics to structure prediction and protein-protein interaction networks. Participation in the symposium will be particularly beneficial to US graduate students and post-doctoral scholars, by providing them with a critical formative experience and preparing them to become future leaders in the field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1116001</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yipan@gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aleksandr</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zelikovskiy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alexz@cs.gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ion</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mandoiu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ion@engr.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303023999</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4044133500</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>G76Dahlberg Hall 30 Courtland St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
