<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CIF: Small: Compressive Network Analytics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>phillip regalia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The rich information generated by computer and human networks creates exciting opportunities for network analytics, namely, the process of gaining knowledge and insights by mining a large amount of network data collected by a diverse set of monitors. To enable effective network analytics, several significant challenges must be addressed:&lt;br/&gt;--- (i) Scalability. The enormous scale of computer and human networks makes it challenging to analyze massive network datasets in a scalable fashion. &lt;br/&gt;--- (ii) Complexity. Real-world network datasets are complex and often violate the operational conditions of existing analysis techniques. &lt;br/&gt;--- (iii) Robustness. Anomalies and imperfections are common in real-world network datasets. &lt;br/&gt;--- (iv) Diversity. Network analytics often requires mining information from diverse data sources with different characteristics and data quality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses the above challenges by developing a series of novel compressive sensing techniques to effectively exploit the presence of structure and redundancy in real-world network datasets, including:&lt;br/&gt;--- (i) clustered spectral graph embedding, a novel technique for reducing a massive graph to a much smaller graph while preserving essential clustering and spectral information of the original graph,&lt;br/&gt;--- (ii) LENS decomposition, a novel method for accurately decomposing a network data matrix into a Low-rank matrix, an Error term, a Noise matrix, and a Sparse matrix, and &lt;br/&gt;--- (iii) multi-source spectral learning, a novel framework for effectively integrating information from diverse data sources. The research promises to significantly enhance the ability to analyze massive network datasets. &lt;br/&gt;The resulting tools and techniques have potential applications in business, information technology, networking and cyber security. Finally, the research includes a significant education and training component. The research results will be integrated into both undergraduate and graduate curricula as well as outreach activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1117009</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lili</FirstName>
      <LastName>Qiu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lili@cs.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yzhang@cs.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7797</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
