<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Mathematical Study of Smectic Liquid Crystals</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>85852</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Joo&lt;br/&gt;DMS-0908538&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator and her colleague study mathematically the&lt;br/&gt;interaction of smectic liquid crystals with external electric or&lt;br/&gt;magnetic fields. Typical liquid crystals are nematic and smectic&lt;br/&gt;liquid crystals, consisting of rod-like molecules that tend to&lt;br/&gt;align themselves lengthwise along a common axis, called the&lt;br/&gt;director. The local orientation of a nematic liquid crystal is&lt;br/&gt;described by the director field. However, in smectic phases the&lt;br/&gt;molecules of the liquid crystal also tend to lie in layers. To&lt;br/&gt;describe the local orientation, a smectic order parameter must be&lt;br/&gt;introduced in addition to the director field. The free energy of&lt;br/&gt;smectic liquid crystals has a resemblance to the Ginzburg-Landau&lt;br/&gt;energy for superconductivity, and it is a nonlinear, nonconvex&lt;br/&gt;second order energy. While nematic phases are rather well&lt;br/&gt;understood, the mathematical theory of smectic phases is&lt;br/&gt;comparatively underdeveloped. This study consists of two main&lt;br/&gt;projects. In the first project, the investigators advance the&lt;br/&gt;mathematical understanding of smectic liquid crystals in the area&lt;br/&gt;of instabilities driven by external magnetic fields, by means of&lt;br/&gt;mathematical analysis and numerical simulations. Partial&lt;br/&gt;differential equation methods for phase transition, calculus of&lt;br/&gt;variations, Gamma convergence theory, and bifurcation theory are&lt;br/&gt;employed. In the second project, the investigators study&lt;br/&gt;ferroelectric liquid crystals such as smectic C* and bent-core&lt;br/&gt;phases, which are named after the bent or banana-shaped&lt;br/&gt;molecules. The response time of bent-core liquid crystals is&lt;br/&gt;only in the range of microseconds and thus this material offers&lt;br/&gt;huge potential for many applications. The investigator studies&lt;br/&gt;an electrodynamic model of the molecular reorientation of&lt;br/&gt;ferroelectric liquid crystals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Liquid crystals are used in many different applications such&lt;br/&gt;as optical switching devices and temperature sensors. Nematic&lt;br/&gt;liquid crystal materials have been widely studied because of&lt;br/&gt;their applications to flat panel displays. However, it is known&lt;br/&gt;that ferroelectric liquid crystals such as smectic C phases with&lt;br/&gt;chiral molecules exhibit much faster switching times. Thus&lt;br/&gt;understanding the features of smectic liquid crystals such as&lt;br/&gt;defect structures and switching dynamics is a very important&lt;br/&gt;issue in practical applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/26/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1120637</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sookyung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Joo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sjoo@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
