<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for travel to the 18th International Botanical Congress- to be held July 23 - 30, 2011 in Melbourne, Australia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maureen M. Kearney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Botanical Congress (IBC) is the largest international conference in plant biology and extends the broadest disciplinary coverage of any such conference. The IBC is held every six years and will take place in Melbourne, Australia, in 2011. This grant will support travel for graduate students, postdocs, and early career faculty (within three years of first appointment), who are presenting the results of their research, to attend the upcoming IBC. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IBC serves a critical role in international communication within and across disciplines in plant biology, as well as a valuable opportunity to establish international collaborations. Participation is particularly valuable for young scientists as they establish their careers. The opportunity to reach so many scientists within any individual discipline creates an unequaled opportunity for exposure by a young scientist. The once-in-six-years frequency of the Congresses means that for most young scientists, who are about to complete Ph.D.s, find a job, or compete for tenure in their academic institutions, there is only one opportunity to participate in an IBC during these critical stages of professional development. For the young scientists supported by these travel awards, connections made here will be career-altering and will create life-long collaborations that will enhance their development as scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1120802</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Olmstead</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>olmstead@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Botanical Society of America</Name>
      <CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631103201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3145779566</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4475 Castleman Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7374</Code>
      <Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7377</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7657</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Ecologi Physiology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
