<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Folding of Dihydrofolate Reductase and the Response Regulators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>706861</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to test the hypothesis that the interplay between chain connectivity and hydrophobic clusters of branched aliphatic side chains in two members of the very common Rossmann-fold family of proteins, CheY and dihydrofolate reductase (DHFR), dictates their folding free energy surfaces. Available evidence on both proteins suggests that locally-connected clusters of isoleucine, leucine and valine side chains rapidly collapse via subdomains that can enhance or impede subsequent folding reactions leading to the native conformation. A battery of spectroscopic methods, at equilibrium and interfaced to ultra-rapid mixing systems, will probe the size, shape and pair-wise distances in the chemically-denatured state and in partially-folded states that appear in the microsecond time range after dilution to native-favoring conditions for CheY, complementing previous findings on DHFR. Chemical shift index and paramagnetic relaxation enhancement NMR measurements will probe for nonrandom structure in the chemically denatured state. Complementary pulse-quench hydrogen exchange experiments on CheY will probe the formation of secondary structure at the peptide and the site-specific level in the early intermediates. Mutational analysis will test the role of local and nonlocal ILV clusters in driving these early folding reactions, and permutations of the sequences will test the role of the connectivity of the polypeptide chain in driving the formation of these clusters and the N- and C-terminal subdomains. Appropriate permuted variants of CheY will be subjected to single molecule pulling experiments to study the effect of subdomain connectivity and the ILV cluster integrity on the cooperativity of the unfolding reaction and reveal the stabilization of partially-folded states. The experimental data will be used to validate course-grained MD simulations of the folding reactions of CheY and DHFR, and high-resolution simulations on CheY. It is anticipated that the combined application of experimental and computational methods on the same target will substantially enhance the value of both approaches and expedite the solution of the protein folding problem.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The protein folding problem remains as one of the outstanding challenges in molecular biophysics, and its solution would have a major impact on biology and the biotechnology industry. To expedite a solution to the folding problem, a collaborative network of investigators has been established to generate a comprehensive experimental data set on a single protein target that will validate companion coarse-grained and high-resolution MD simulations of its folding reaction. This collaborative approach will serve as a paradigm for the solution of other complex problems in biology. A micro-channel mixing system has been developed over the course of this work that allows access to microsecond folding reactions and that can be interfaced to a variety of spectroscopic methods. This technology has been shared with colleagues at other institutions, and its dissemination in the open literature has enabled others to study the early folding events in their target systems. Pursuit of these research objectives will also provide training opportunities for high school students, undergraduates, graduate students and postdoctoral fellows, and the scientific advances are being incorporated into a graduate molecular biophysics course.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1121942</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Osman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bilsel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>osman.bilsel@umassmed.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>C Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matthews</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c.robert.matthews@umassmed.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Medical School</Name>
      <CityName>Worcester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>016550002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5088562119</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>55 Lake Avenue North</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1144</Code>
      <Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
