<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Support for Travel Expenses for US Participants in ACS Symposium "Controlled Living Radical Polymerization" to be held in Denver, CO August 28-31, 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Freddy A. Khoury</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Synthesis and characterization of new materials with precisely controlled macromolecular dimensions, functionalities and composition as well as with well-defined topologies is the ultimate goal of contemporary polymer science. For many years control of molecular architecture and functionalities in radical polymerization was very difficult. However, recently controlled/living polymerizations have been extended to radical systems which are not only commercially the most important but also have the largest potential due to availability of polymerizable monomers, facile copolymerization and undemanding reaction conditions. Therefore, controlled/living radical polymerization of vinyl monomers expands and enhances fundamental knowledge. This proposal requests support for 3 US assistant professors, 3 postdoctoral fellows and 3 graduate students to participate in the Symposium on "Controlled/Living Radical Polymerization" at the National Meeting of the American Chemical Society in Denver, CO, August 28-31, 2011. The Symposium will cover recent advances in controlled/living systems. Three general approaches to controlled radical polymerization will be highlighted. This includes use of nitroxides and other organic stable radicals, application of metal catalyzed polymerization such as atom transfer radical polymerization, and techniques employing chain transfer and addition-fragmentation chemistry, including inifers. The lectures will cover mechanisms, synthesis and characterization of materials with novel molecular architectures, functionalities&lt;br/&gt;and composition. The symposium will include one tutorial and 7 regular sessions with approximately eighty lectures and 6 poster sessions. The meeting will allow to exchange and disseminate information among researchers from various countries and many US academic (including graduate students and postdoctoral fellows), governmental and industrial laboratories.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Controlled radical polymerization is among the most rapidly developing areas of polymer and materials science. It impacts many advanced technologies enabling unprecedented advances in biomedical materials, optoelectronics, environmentally related areas and other areas such as coatings, lubricants, adhesives, additives, surfactants, dispersants and health and beauty products. Thus, knowledge generated during the 2011 Denver Symposium on "Controlled/Living Radical Polymerization" will benefit many participants, including undergraduate and graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, their advisors as well researchers from governmental and industrial laboratories. As in the case of the previous 2008 ACS Symposium on "Controlled/Living Radical Polymerization" held in Philadelphia, the PI plans to publish proceedings with the major lectures presented at the meeting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1122575</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Krzysztof</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matyjaszewski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>km3b@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
