<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Cognitive, computational, and neural processing--Constraints on theories of language production -New York University - July 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>23189</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William J. Badecker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Language production is a remarkably complex cognitive ability which requires the successful integration of multiple levels of cognitive/neural processing. Research on the mechanisms underlying language production is performed from a variety of disciplinary perspectives, including psycholinguistics, neurolinguistics, theoretical linguistics, computational linguistics, cognitive neuropsychology, and communication sciences and disorders. However, a complete understanding of language production requires situating our findings in a broader context that addresses the constraints that are placed on theories of language production by general cognitive, neural and computational processing principles. This award provides support for a special workshop session addressing cognitive, computational and neural constraints on theories of language production. The session will be part of the July 2012 meeting of the International Workshop on Language Production at New York University (NYU). The special session will consist of presentations by five leading scientists whose research on cognitive, neural and computational processes can directly constrain theories of language production. Over the past seven years, the International Workshop on Language Production has become the premier meeting focused solely on language production, and is thus the ideal venue to hold a special session of lectures and discussions addressing constraints on language production theories. This special session will inform language production researchers about state-of-the-art findings on the constraints on language production theories, which they can incorporate into their research, and will also provide opportunities to form collaborations between researchers who focus on language production with others who focus on more general cognitive, neural and computational issues.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1124124</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buchwald</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abb6@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Poeppel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.poeppel@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alec</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marantz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marantz@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1311</Code>
      <Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1311</Code>
      <Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
