<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>INQUA Congress Travel Fellowship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria L. Uhle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests funds to partially support the participation of US early career scientists (within 7 years of earning a Ph.D.) and graduate students at the XVIII International Union for Quaternary Research Congress. The participants supported by this grant will be provided the opportunity to present their research at the Congress, to develop international collaborations, and gain knowledge of global research initiatives. The proposal presents a clear plan for advertisement of this funding opportunity, including outreach to a wide range of disciplines and institutions and members of under-represented groups. Proposal sets out clear criteria on which to select the award recipients.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The United States is a world leader in Quaternary research and continued participation by young U.S. scientists it is vital to sustain this leadership. The XVIII INQUA Congress is a key multidisciplinary forum for the exchange of scientific information and ideas and based on feedback from previous travel award recipients, this is an effective venue to inspire and encourage U.S. students and early career scientists to effectively address problems with global impact. Effective U.S. participation in this congress will build international science partnerships and foster future international collaborations to address problems that are far greater than the United States can address on its own. This proposal will contribute to the advancement of science in Quaternary Research and will promote the professional development of US early career scientists in an international forum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1125215</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bailey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kbailey@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>A. Ester</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sztein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esztein@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1679</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1679</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
