<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Field-Emission Scanning Electron Microscope for a Primarily Undergraduate Consortium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>546273</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We request the purchase of a field-emission scanning electron microscope (FE-SEM) for use in the Claremont Colleges consortuim, a major academic community of 5,500 students. The instrument will be used daily by undergraduate research students across a broad range of disciplines with time allocated by an online reservation system and without user fees. We have chosen to focus on the three main areas in the description below:&lt;br/&gt;(1) Materials for Energy and the Environment. In this area, the proposed instrument would support important imaging in several projects: Dye-Sensitized Solar Cells with Porphyrin Sensitizers on Zinc Oxide Nanotubes, Low-cost, High-Stability Polymer Solar Cells, Inorganic/Organic Composite Gas Separation Membranes for Low-Energy Separations, and Environmental Monitoring (combinatorial materials research for chemical microsensor and microanalytical system development).&lt;br/&gt;(2) Bioengineering. Amongst other projects in this area, the instrument would support projects on Tissue Engineering a Cornea, and Chitosan Nanoparticle Synthesis.&lt;br/&gt;(3) Geology. Two major projects in this area include Igneous and Metamorphic Petrology and Geomicrobiology and Sedimentary Geology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary purpose of the requested instrument is for undergraduate research and research training. Our management plan is based on our success over the past 7 years with the current facility built around a used FE-SEM, which is now over 13 years old. In the past four years, more than 150 users, almost all undergraduates, have used the current FE-SEM for a total of 1070 sessions. Providing undergraduate students with the opportunity to work with sophisticated instrumentation provides motivation to discuss a variety of specialized topics and can be a key factor in encouraging students to pursue further scientific research, graduate studies or industrial research positions. The facility will be featured in outreach programs across the consortium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Claremont Colleges consortuim, a major academic community of 5,500 students has submitted a proposal to the National Science Foundation for the purchase of a field-emission scanning electron microscope. This type of microscope is able to routinely image analyze fibers, cells, particles, minerals, new materials, and devices at size scales ranging from inches to nanometers, corresponding to magnifications from ten times to one million times, and significantly better than any tradition optical microscope. The microscope will be used daily by undergraduate research students across a broad range of projects including novel materials for new energy sources such as new types of solar cells, sensors for environmental monitoring, bioengineering of artificial corneas, and for analysis of geologic samples that help scientists understand mechanisms through which the most basic forms of life interact with the Earth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While most field-emission scanning electron microscopes are located in large research universities and high tech industrial settings, the primary purpose of the requested instrument is for undergraduate research and research training. The proposal is based on the success over the past 7 years with the current microscope facility built around a used microscope, which is now over 13 years old. In the past four years, more than 150 users, almost all undergraduates, have used the current microscope for over a thousand research sessions. Providing undergraduate students with the opportunity to work with sophisticated instrumentation provides motivation to discuss a variety of specialized topics and can be a key factor in encouraging students to pursue further scientific research, graduate studies or industrial research positions. The facility will be featured in outreach programs for the public, especially with school children and teachers in grades 1-12. The proposal was written by a team of professors from Pomona College and Harvey Mudd College, both amongst the most selective colleges in the country with strong records of undergraduate research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1126080</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van Ryswyk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Hal_VanRyswyk@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tanenbaum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dtanenbaum@pomona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taylor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ctaylor@pomona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Orwin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Elizabeth_Orwin@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lape</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nancy_lape@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pomona College</Name>
      <CityName>Claremont</CityName>
      <ZipCode>917114434</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9096218328</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Alexander Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
