<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel for Magnetism Summer School to attend the 2011 INternational IEEE Nagentics Society Summer School being held in New Orleans on May 22-28, 2011.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funds are requested to provide travel and subsistence support for 12 U.S. graduates&lt;br/&gt;students to attend the 2011 International IEEE Magnetics Society Summer School in New&lt;br/&gt;Orleans. The International Magnetism Summer School is the IEEE Magnetics Society?s main&lt;br/&gt;outreach effort to promote education in the field of magnetism and attract more young scientists&lt;br/&gt;to choose a research career in magnetism and related areas. The one-week Magnetism Summer&lt;br/&gt;School is designed for graduate students studying magnetism and related areas. It will consist of&lt;br/&gt;lectures by international experts and will include poster presentations by participating graduate&lt;br/&gt;students. The program will cover fundamentals and advanced topics in magnetism. The summer&lt;br/&gt;school is a unique opportunity for young scientists to meet leaders in their field in a relaxed and&lt;br/&gt;collegial atmosphere and to begin establishing a network of colleagues in the research&lt;br/&gt;community.&lt;br/&gt;The Magnetics Society has allocated $106,000 which will be used primarily to provide&lt;br/&gt;with free room and board and reimburse for most of the travel expenses for 65 students from all&lt;br/&gt;over the world including the United States. The funds requested from NSF will allow additional&lt;br/&gt;U.S. graduate students to attend the Summer School and interact with peers internationally.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The Summer School provides a forum for exchange of information in the field of&lt;br/&gt;magnetics research. In addition to formal lectures, each participating student is required to&lt;br/&gt;present a poster about their current research. These topics are discussed amongst the students and&lt;br/&gt;lecturers during poster sessions.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the Summer School lies in the education of young scientists and&lt;br/&gt;researchers in a fast-moving and economically important field. Participants will learn both&lt;br/&gt;fundamental as well as advanced topics through lectures delivered by internationally-renowned&lt;br/&gt;experts. In addition, there is a degree of cultural education, teaching young scientists to interact&lt;br/&gt;with and respect their colleagues from other countries. The students will be co-housed with peers&lt;br/&gt;from different nationalities fostering interaction and cultural exchange.&lt;br/&gt;The organizers of the Summer School particularly encourage women and&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented minorities to apply. The program committee also strives for diversity in the&lt;br/&gt;lecturers selected for the summer school to provide role models for female and minority students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1127901</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spinu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>LSpinu@uno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Albrecht</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jander@eecs.orst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Orleans</Name>
      <CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
      <ZipCode>701480001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5042806836</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2000 Lakeshore Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>107E</Code>
      <Text>Magnetics and spin electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
