<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ERC - Small Business: Walking Robot Based Ground Penetrating Radar Sensor for Mine and IED Detection</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Deborah J. Jackson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This effort is a collaboration between the Gordon Center for Subsurface Sensing and Imaging Systems (CenSSIS), an NSF Engineering Research Center (ERC) at Northwestern University since 2000, and Square One, a small business partner of the ERC. Square One has been developing a walking robot and research at the CenSSIS ERC has developed ground penetrating radar systems (GPR). This effort integrates the GPR systems of CenSSIS into the walking robot of Square One. Square One's walking robot has been specifically designed to step over obstacles and move efficiently across rugged terrain. CenSSIS's GPR will be adapted for the robot with the radar antennae on the robot?s legs to put them in close contact with the ground and eliminate ground clutter interference. The system should be able to detect all land mines including the plastic mines having no metal and thus invisible to conventional magnetic mine detectors. Deployment of the system will eliminate thousands of land mines worldwide, with the ensuing reduction of death and personal injury.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this joint effort will be to develop and test a high resolution, self-propelled GPR unit.&lt;br/&gt;CenSSIS will computationally model the electromagnetic wave propagation and scattering characteristics of candidate GPR configurations, optimize radar signal performance relative to the configuration of the robot, and design geometry-specific algorithms for subsurface image reconstruction. Square One will create an application-specific version of the robot geometrically optimized for GPR use and integrated with impulse radar hardware and antennae. Additionally, Square One will draw on its ongoing SBIR Phase II effort to equip the robot with essential navigational software and sensors. The project will conclude with a series of comparative field tests aimed at conclusively establishing the superior performance of the combined system. The intellectual merit lies in the adaptation and integration of known engineering sciences to form a new system with a wide variety of applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The U.S. State Department estimates that more than 200 million mines are in place throughout the world. These mines are a constant threat in many parts of the developing world. Military units, non-governmental agencies and commercial contractors work together to ameliorate the threat posed by landmines and other unexploded ordnance. However, the technique of using hand-held detectors to locate mines is essentially unchanged since World War II and demining operations remain slow and exceedingly dangerous. Given the vast areas of land that remain to be cleared, faster and safer methods of locating and neutralizing mines must be introduced. This effort addresses both the safety, cost and speed of mine detection. At Northeastern University several civil engineering undergraduates will continue to pursue interdisciplinary research on radar sensing; and a graduate IGERT student will direct her current electromagnetic modeling research toward the specific mine detection application. While demining operations will continue to be the main commercial market for the robot, numerous other markets will be attracted to the technology. In addition to the Department of Defense, demining contractors, oil companies, and construction firms have interests in ensuring safe terrain.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1128541</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rappaport</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rappaport@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martinez-Lorenzo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmartine@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
