<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ERC - Small Business: Remote chemical sensing instrumentation based on chirped laser dispersion spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Deborah J. Jackson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a collaborative project between an NSF Engineering Research Center for Technologies for Health and the Environment (MIRTHE) and Physical Sciences Inc. (PSI), a company that is a world-renowned leader in the research and development of laser chemical sensing technologies. The proposal focuses on developing a new, compact, cryogen-free mid-infrared hard-target LIDAR (laser detection and ranging) technology for remote spectroscopic chemical sensing that will target atmospheric methane. The proposed system will be based on a new chirped laser dispersion spectroscopy (CLaDS) technique, recently invented by the PI, who is a researcher at the MIRTHE ERC. The proposal will develop a new remote sensing technology that is capable of atmospheric CH4 monitoring and will provide significant improvements over the current state-of-the-art. Present concentration in North America range from 1600 to 2200 parts per billion by volume (ppbv). Unfortunately, it is difficult to fully quantify its emission rates and location of sources and sinks using existing methane monitoring instrumentation. Thus technologies that enable remote sensing of natural and anthropogenic methane emissions are needed for accurate source and sink assessments of this important greenhouse gas. The new sensor system, CLaDS, is based on measurement of resonant molecular dispersion and provides unique capabilities for remote chemical detection (i.e. immunity to optical power fluctuations). The proposed instrumentation will also take advantage of another core MIRTHE technology; quantum cascade lasers (QCLs). QCLs give an access to the mid-infrared region of electromagnetic spectrum between ~3 and 16 ìm where most chemical compounds in the gas phase (including methane) possess their strongest fundamental ro-vibrational absorption features. As a result, detection at mid-IR wavelengths enables ultra-high sensitivity detection of trace-gases. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ultra-sensitive, fast, in-situ molecular remote detection has a large number of applications in environmental studies, industrial emission monitoring and security. Therefore new discoveries and scientific advancements in this field integrated with a comprehensive educational program will provide an excellent training for the new generation of scientists and engineers as well as have a strong impact on the well being of society. The versatility of the project provides a full spectrum of education and training opportunities integrated with the research goals and specifically addresses career development goals at each academic level from high school students to post-doctoral researchers. Participation of a graduate student and a post-doc is planned within the budget of this project. The engagement of undergraduate students will be provided through other programs including a strong MIRTHE Research Experience for Undergraduate (REU) Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1128282</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wysocki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gwysocki@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
