<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: How Collaboration Affects Group Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saylor Breckenridge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES - 1129584&lt;br/&gt;Michael Lovaglia (PI)&lt;br/&gt;Shane Soboroff (co-PI)&lt;br/&gt;University of Iowa&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Doctoral Dissertation Research Proposal: How Collaboration Affects Group Dynamics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;How does group size affect group member trust and cohesion? In unstructured task groups, cohesion and performance begin to decline when the group has taken on too many members. Yet group size can also be an advantage, because it adds diverse skill sets to groups working on shared tasks. As group size increases, the problem of coordination often results in bureaucracy, which in turn can create new problems for effective collaboration. Investigating the maximum number of members for effective, unstructured task groups is important for understanding both how teams work together to achieve goals and how bureaucracy becomes attractive as a strategy for solving problems of collaboration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project examines how the maximum effective size of unstructured task groups is affected by the degree to which individual contributions are central to task completion, a phenomenon known as "task jointness." The study involves a set of laboratory experiments involving face-to-face groups, in which group size and task jointness are systematically varied. The following hypotheses derived from social psychological theory are tested: 1) Members of groups working on joint tasks will report higher trust than members of groups working on additive tasks and members of groups having a purely social interaction. 2) Groups with seven and eight persons working on joint tasks will report higher trust and cohesion than similar groups working on additive tasks, or than groups engaging in purely social interaction. 3) Members of groups working on joint tasks will be less likely to choose to leave their group as group size increases than members of additive task groups or purely social groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts &lt;br/&gt;The results of this study on the determinants of effective team work are of interest to people in business and complex organizations, both in the profit and non-profit and governmental sectors. Results seek to inform organizational design, as well as workflow and related workplace activities. Research will be conducted at a nationally known center for small-group research. The study will generate experimental and qualitative data that can serve as the basis for future research, theory development, and graduate student training in data analysis. The P.I.s will train undergraduate researchers in experimental methods, data collection, and analysis. Results will be disseminated at a multi-disciplinary conference on small-group research and prepared for publication in an appropriate academic journal.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1129584</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lovaglia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael-lovaglia@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Soboroff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shane-soboroff@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Iowa</Name>
      <CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
