<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SFS: An Information and Systems Assurance Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1529703</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Ira A. Fulton School of Engineering at Arizona State University is supporting three cohorts of undergraduate and graduate students in Information Assurance (IA) via a Federal Cyber Service: Scholarship for Service (SFS) program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Arizona State University has developed a strong cybersecurity curriculum with ten IA courses in computer science and engineering (CSE) and an additional six courses in other disciplines, including electrical engineering, industrial engineering, mathematics, and information systems in ASU's Business School. ASU's IA Research Center has been designated as a National Center of Academic Excellence in both Information Assurance Education (CAEIAE) and Research (CAE-R) by the National Security Agency and the Department of Homeland Security. Its main educational and research programs focus on trustworthy information systems and the quality of information being stored, processed or transmitted. The main strengths of this project include: (a) SFS students are provided with effective mentoring and support to successfully place them in Federal jobs. (b) In addition to a rigorous academic program emphasizing both theory and practice, all SFS students participate in IA research as part of their capstone projects, theses or dissertations. (c) The program promotes leadership, collaboration and communication skills of SFS scholarship recipients through their participation in community service, student organizations, collaborative projects, IA workshops and IA seminars. (d) Students gain hands-on experiences with various IA areas through ISU's state-of-the-art IA Instructional Laboratory, cloud-based virtualized IA laboratory, and IA research facilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is having an immediate impact on the Information Assurance and Computer Security capabilities of the federal workforce by providing highly qualified information technology and engineering professionals trained in information assurance. In order to help increase the diversity of IA professionals in the Federal workforce, this scholarship program is placing special emphasis on recruiting and graduating outstanding female students and members of other underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1129561</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yau@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gail-Joon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ahn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gahn@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dijiang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dijiang@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7434</Code>
      <Text>CNCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
