<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Modular Curriculum for Embedded Systems Security</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>114475</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this project at Florida Gulf Coast University is to improve the quality of teaching security for embedded systems in computer science and software engineering. Embedded systems are ubiquitous in our everyday lives in microwave ovens, garage door openers, cars, cell phones, and point-of-sale credit card transactions to name a few. However, the explosive growth in embedded technology has not been accompanied by substantial educational activities particularly in the area of the security of embedded systems. The issues in the security of embedded systems are substantially different from those in traditional enterprise systems and desktop computing. First, embedded systems are highly distributed and essentially unattended, which makes them vulnerable; and second, embedded applications involve the use of sensors and actuators, which are themselves computerized and thus subject to security breaches if not protected properly. The diversity of potential threats makes it difficult to provide general countermeasures to protect embedded devices and, consequently, teach protection techniques. The embedded systems curriculum at Florida Gulf Coast University involves junior and senior level courses on Embedded Systems Programming, Data Acquisition and Control, Computer Network Programming and Senior Software Engineering Projects. In this curriculum, students work on real life projects, designing and implementing embedded systems using microprocessors, microcontrollers and FPGA circuits. The project is developing course materials with the following goals: 1) studying and learning professional issues in embedded systems security; 2) developing eight learning modules on the subject; 3) presenting them as web-based lectures; 4) creating lab exercises for practical applications; 5) evaluating the project results by two professional evaluators; and 6) assessing the project's effectiveness and impact in the classroom by the students. The broader impact of this project lies in exposing undergraduate students to the security aspects of embedded systems, which is rarely covered at the undergraduate level. Development and dissemination of comprehensive learning modules is helping to create a knowledgeable workforce in an area that is critical to U.S. national security.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1129437</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janusz</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zalewski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zalewski@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Gulf Coast University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort MYERS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>339656565</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2395907022</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10501 FGCU Blvd. South</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
