<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference Support: 19th International Symposium on Transportation and Traffic Theory; Berkeley Hill, California; July 18-20, 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49970</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Konstantinos Triantis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides participant support funds for the 19th International Symposium on Transportation and Traffic Theory (ISTTT) to be held July 18-20, 2011 in Berkeley, California. The symposium will showcase 35 original papers drawn from a pool of over 500 submissions from around the world. Selections were made via a rigorous, multi-stage peer-review process. The 35 selected papers will be presented in plenary sessions. To disseminate their findings, all papers will be published in i) hard-copy proceedings; ii) Elsevier's on-line Procedia series; and iii) the prestigious archival journal series Transportation Research. A special workshop session will be held to explore additional ways of placing the symposium findings into professional practice. The funds from NSF will support key elements of the symposium. Part of the funds will cover fellowships to foster participation from a select set of advanced graduate students from underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since its inception, the ISTTT has been the premier gathering of transport theorists. The coming Berkeley Symposium promises to build on that tradition: the papers accepted for the event represent breakthrough research from around the world. These papers have the potential to challenge current thinking about transport science, and perhaps even to transform the field. And the papers address a variety of pressing topics in transportation: they include ideas for promoting greener, more sustainable travel modes, and for transporting people and goods in emergency situations. Given the role that transportation plays in the world and in the lives of her people, the ideas unveiled in the coming symposium are expected to be of real significance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1132456</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cassidy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cassidy@ce.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
