<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Canada Colloborative Research: Dissecting behavioral isolation in nature: mate choice and the among-population divergence of signal traits and mate preferences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49562</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jessica H. Robin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this international collaborative project researchers from U.S. and Canada will perform experiments to study the role of cuticular hydrocarbons (CHC) in species recognition and the maintenance of boundaries between two closely related species of mushroom-feeding flies, Drosophila subquinaria and Drosophila recens. Male contact pheromones consist of a suite of CHCs, and preliminary data suggests that these differ between the two species. Three specific aims will be pursued to test the hypothesis that male CHCs are the key signal traits that are used by females during mate choice and that underlie species discrimination, and that these traits and the female preferences for them have diverged among populations in response to reinforcing selection generated by the presence of the other species. The results of these studies will lay the groundwork for a long-term collaborative research program that will shed light on how behaviors diverge to generate reproductive isolation and ultimately speciation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Knowledge of the male signals and female preferences will inform hypotheses about whether the genetic basis of within vs. between species female discrimination is the same, and how simple vs. complex we expect these traits to be at the genetic level. The genetic basis of female discrimination and evolutionary genomics of species differentiation in these fly species might be more generally applicable to an understanding of the behavior, ecology, and genetics of reproductive isolation. The data resources will be made available to the community. This project will provide the opportunity to develop a long-term collaboration between early career researchers in the U.S. and Canada and will involve training of students in both laboratories, including women and ethnic minorities. Involvement of junior researchers, especially from groups underrepresented in science, in collaborative international activities is a major goal of OISE.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1132807</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kdyer@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5977</Code>
      <Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7561</Code>
      <Text>CANADA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
