<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EDGE Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>117604</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The EDGE Program is a comprehensive mentoring and training program designed to support the academic development and research activities of women in mathematics. The program targets women in five targeted groups from new PhD students to senior faculty. The program includes a summer session, with workshops in real analysis, alge-bra and other topics at a graduate level, as well as support for collaborative research. The program also supports regional mentoring clusters, research symposia, mentor training, an annual conference, travel support for research collaborations, travel support for research talks and other open-ended mentoring activities for each targeted participant group. The EDGE program provides support for the implementation of successful recruitment and retention practices by a broad spectrum of mathematics departments. By ensuring success in Ph.D. programs, we can transform the mathematics community by increasing the number of women, particularly from minority groups who assume lea-dership roles in academia, industry, and government. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the EDGE Program are to increase the number of women PhDs in the ma-thematical sciences, especially those from underrepresented groups; and to place more women in visible leadership roles in the mathematics community. Increased diversity in the mathematics community will ultimately strengthen U.S. competitiveness in mathe-matics and science and allow people from all backgrounds and cultures to thrive, ad-vance, and contribute to the profession. &lt;br/&gt;To accomplish these goals, the current EDGE program will continue the development and articulation of successful and replicable paradigms for the retention and success of women and minorities in the mathematical sciences. Our summer program, along with sustained mentoring and research activities provide practical manifestations of these paradigms. We support the implementation of these practices by a broad spectrum of mathematics departments, thereby transforming the mathematics community by in-creasing the number of women, particularly from minority groups who assume leader-ship roles in academia, industry, and government.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136296</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ulrica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ulrica_wilson@icerm.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Morehouse College</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4046812800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>830 Westview Drive S W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
