<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Phase-I: Internships and Scholarships to Promote Technological Pedagogical Content Knowledge in Teacher Education at SUNY College at Brockport's Science Education Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The State University of New York at Brockport is developing and implementing resources and methodologies to improve technological pedagogical content knowledge in teacher education. The project is using resources and computational mathematics, science, and technology (C-MST) courses, developed under previous grants, to improve teacher education. It emphasizes the recently developed conceptual framework, technological pedagogical content knowledge that has now put both science educators and computational scientists on the same path to utilize an interdisciplinary approach to STEM and teacher education. Strong content knowledge (via a STEM degree), extensive field experience (150 hours), student teaching, dual certification (science and special education), computational pedagogy courses, monetary support in the form of internships and scholarships, and a capstone summer institute construct a set of coherent strategies to attract, prepare, and retain a new cadre of 40 secondary school science teachers. The project is informed by a formative evaluation to enable frequent reviews and mid-course corrections and is disseminating its findings and resources through articles, conference papers and the project's website. The curriculum framework and learning modules are shared with national digital library collections contributing to teacher education nationwide.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136332</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maliekal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmalieka@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Osman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yasar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>oyasar@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Veronesi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pverones@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY College at Brockport</Name>
      <CityName>Brockport</CityName>
      <ZipCode>144202932</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5853952444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Foundation of SUNY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
