<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The molecular evolution of a blind cichlid endemic to the Democratic Republic of Congo, and the democratization of DNA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Edward Murdy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This international dissertation enhancement grant supports the research of Jacob Lowenstein (Columbia University) under the supervision of Dr. Melanie Stiassy (American Museum of Natural History/ Columbia University). The research examines the evolutionary genetics of the blind cichlid, Lamprologus lethops found in the Congo River and will be carried out in collaboration with researchers at the University of Kinshasa and the Institut de Développement Rural, Université Marien Ngouabi, Brazzaville.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cichlid fishes have fascinated biologists for years due to their unrivaled capacity to evolve into new species. Many scientists believe their visual acuity underlies this propensity to speciate, and enables them to choose mates and habitats with great selectivity. The genetics underlying the evolution of the cichlid visual and pigment system is becoming documented in a number of cichlids. The species studied in this research, which is also depigmented, provides many opportunities then to understand the genetics underlying speciation through comparative biology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Mexican Tetra is an unrelated species used as a model for evolutionary development research. Like this Congo River cichlid, blind individuals of this fish are depigmented and have enlarged jaws. Thus, there is great future potential for L. lethops to lend insight into gene functioning bridging these two important study systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will further refine genetic techniques for species identification helping to test and build a gene library being developed for Lower Congo River fishes. Once complete, this resource may assist non-specialists to monitor trade or conduct epidemiology studies on previously unknown samples.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136895</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Melanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stiassny</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mljs@amnh.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lowenstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhl2122@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
