<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Undergraduate Training at NSF Teragrid XD RDAV Center</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>28120</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Chadduck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>As scientists continue to produce data from experiments, sensors, and simulations, the next&lt;br/&gt;challenge is in analyzing and visualizing the results. Addressing this issue is not just a&lt;br/&gt;problem of technology nor of simply deploying larger computers and data storage devices; (future)&lt;br/&gt;scientists need to develop the skills to effectively take advantage of the latest resources&lt;br/&gt;for advancing scientific discoveries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Remote Data Analysis and Visualization Center (RDAV) is well-situated to address&lt;br/&gt;essential issues in workforce development by developing and providing a robust learning opportunity for undergraduate students. RDAV students work on developing software to address computational problems stemming from active projects in science and engineering and proposed by researchers who have been allocated computation time on RDAV?s Nautilus hardware. Experience with these hardware and software resources are each, separately, uncommon skills that undergraduates seldom encounter; the combination is extremely rare. These projects integrate experience working with high performance computing hardware as well as the specialized software tools used in scientific domains. Students gain important applicable skills in computational science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136246</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>huangj@eecs.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ahern</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ahern@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
