<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Group Travel Grant for the Doctoral Consortium at the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14525</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This travel grant supports students who are near graduation, or have recently graduated, to take part in a doctoral consortium at the 2011 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR). The doctoral consortium highlights the work of these up and coming researchers, and pairs each student with a senior member of the computer vision community who serves as their mentor. The mentorship process provides each student with valuable feedback on their research, as well as meaningful career advice as the students move on to the next phase of their professional development. The doctoral consortium event aims to have representation from a diverse group of participants (in terms of gender, ethnic background, academic institution and geographic location). The travel grant ensures participation from a broad range of institutions across the country and gives visibility to a diverse population of students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136370</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Walter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scheirer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wscheire@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Colorado Springs</Name>
      <CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>809183733</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7192553153</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1420, Austin Bluffs Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
