<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CREST:Center for Functional Nanoscale Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4950000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor A. Santiago</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Center for Functional Nanoscale Materials was established in 2006 as a NSF Phase I CREST. The Phase II award will enable the Center further to increase the capacity of Clark Atlanta University to train talented minority scientists in the area of the physical sciences and will advance human understanding of nanoscale materials science. The Center will continue to play a major role in mitigating the Nation's technical workforce needs, will make significant contributions to the technical knowledge base that has kept the U.S. competitive on the world stage, and will continue to enable talented and well-prepared Center alumni and alumnae to assume leadership roles in industry, government and academia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;In Phase II the Center will implement its five year plan (2011 to 2016) to build on the expertise, experience, resources, connections and partnerships that have been firmly established by the Center?s work during Phase One. Three research subprojects form the foundation of the Center?s research and educational activities. The subprojects are: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;* The Development of Carbon Nanotube-Based Multicomponent Nanohybrids, &lt;br/&gt;* The Design of Nanophase Inorganic Oxides Derivatives as Oxidation Catalysts and for the Synthesis of Organic Molecules and Structures, and &lt;br/&gt;* Functional Nanomaterials for Biosensors and Drugs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of these studies can potentially be translated into new energy storage technologies to fully utilize the intermittent forms of energy such as solar and wind. Studies will also result in the development of novel nanoscale functional materials to serve as detectors in sensors for single molecule detection and thus contribute advances in nanomedicine The Center's educational programs thoroughly integrates into these research programs with the goal of stimulating the development of a cadre of talented and well-prepared minority scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: &lt;br/&gt;This NSF CREST funded Center will continue to function as an effective agent for change within the University by providing support for students, administrative and technical support for faculty and upgrades to and acquisition of new equipment. The Center will provide summer research opportunities for students attending other universities through its summer programs. The Center will continue to work with area middle and high schools by providing training in new instructional methodologies, creation of new instructional materials and sponsoring graduate student-teacher teams that work in local classrooms. Through its diverse activities, the Center will continue to provide top quality graduate and undergraduate training that is holistic and will produce individuals who will be well prepared to assume leadership roles in their fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1137751</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reed</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jreed@cau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ishrat</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ikhan@cau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdwms@cau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clark Atlanta University</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303144358</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048806990</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>223 James P. Brawley Dr. S.W.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9131</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
