<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Forensic Analysis of Eccentrically Braced Frame Fracture during the February 2011 Christchurch, New Zealand Earthquake</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>26000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The principal research objective of this Rapid Response Research (RAPID) award is to identify and understand the conditions that could cause an earthquake-induced fracture in eccentrically braced frame (EBF) steel buildings. For this purpose, multi-scale forensic analysis of the first earthquake failure worldwide of an EBF structure will be conducted. Such a failure occurred in the Christchurch Hospital during the February 2011 Christchurch, New Zealand earthquake. The perishable data to be collected under this RAPID are material specimens from the failed frame before repairs begin. The forensic analysis involves simulations encompassing several scales (from building scale to micromechanical fracture), and will feature mechanical and chemical material tests from the failed frame. The research, if successful, will result in the discovery of new failure modes of EBFs with direct implications for design safety. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broad significance of this research will include the discovery of new failure modes and the consequent enhancement of design considerations, resulting in safer buildings. Outside the immediate discipline of structural engineering, a significant impact is the modeling of a comprehensive end-to-end simulation (encompassing several scales) of an observed field failure. In addition to revealing deficiencies in such end-to-end simulation methodologies, and thus spawning new research, this will have high educational and training value across various levels of academic accomplishment, including technology transfer to industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1138634</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amit</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kanvinde</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kanvinde@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1637</Code>
      <Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>038E</Code>
      <Text>FOUNDATION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>039E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>040E</Code>
      <Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>043E</Code>
      <Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1576</Code>
      <Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5941</Code>
      <Text>NEW ZEALAND</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8016</Code>
      <Text>Japan Earthquake 2011</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
