<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transition: Arecibo Operations and Maintenance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>456020</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ralph A. Gaume Jr.</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SRI and its partners, the Universities Space Research Association (USRA) and the Universidad &lt;br/&gt;Metropolitana (UMET), collectively the Arecibo Managing Partners (AMP), will provide on-site staff at &lt;br/&gt;Arecibo during the transition period and will cooperate fully with the present Cornell University &lt;br/&gt;management team to ensure a graceful transition, including: continuity of the scientific observation &lt;br/&gt;program; seamless operation of the Education and Public Outreach (EPO) program; clear, fair, and timely &lt;br/&gt;transition of employee compensation and benefits; stewardship of maintenance, safety, and &lt;br/&gt;environmental duties; efficient initiation of new business systems; and, importantly, &lt;br/&gt;resolving uncertainties of the incumbent staff, user communities, and other stakeholders. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Transition Plan is divided into two overlapping phases to ensure that all necessary functions are &lt;br/&gt;completed in a timely manner and with minimal impact on AO operations. The first phase covers the &lt;br/&gt;formal four-month transfer period while the second is an ongoing process of integration and adjustment, &lt;br/&gt;which will continue throughout the first year of the new Cooperative Agreement. An important feature of &lt;br/&gt;the transition process is the immediate appointment and relocation of the Director-designate/PI as the on- &lt;br/&gt;site transition manager to provide clear responsibility and accountability for transition implementation,&lt;br/&gt;and collaborative alignment with the incumbent, NSF, NASA, and the staff.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1141342</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kelly</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kelly@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kerr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rkerr@naic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SRI International</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508592651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
