<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: GreenSC: Characterizing and Modeling Energy Use in Social Computing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299982</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Social networks link behavioral and social activities with a myriad of infrastructural networks that support relationships between individuals. These infrastructural networks include the Internet, telephone systems and transportation networks, all of which are in turn tied to power and fuel-supply networks, such as electricity grids. Social networks play a powerful shaping role on underlying infrastructural networks, placing great demands on their capacity and helping determine how they evolve through use. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An initial set of analyses suggests that there are significant opportunities for improving energy use by analyzing and optimizing the energy required to build and sustain social networks. This project seeks to quantify the energy requirements of social networks and identify strategies for optimizing their energy use by: assessing the ecology of technologies used in social networks through surveys and crowdsourced data; modeling and empirically measuring the power consumed in communication technologies; and developing a social sustainability composite indicator that will be integrated into a tool to help users make more sustainable choices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit This project will lead to an improved understanding of the behavior and dynamics of complex, socio-technical networks so that future networks can be better designed. The project seeks to build an understanding of how different communication technologies are used together in social networks and to use this model to address how energy use accumulates in technical networks that support relationships. Finally, the project seeks to link large-scale problems with the actions and behaviors of individuals, which is critical for promoting behavioral change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts The questions answered in this project are critical to informed optimization and innovation of energy use in the context of social networks and social life. A better understanding of the energy cost of social networks and social computing technologies promises to have impact in climate change, information technology for development and operational efficiency. Additionally, the project?s findings will be distributed through a number of national programs for training and curriculum development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1141517</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Finholt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>finholt@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hofer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ehofer@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
