<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Geochemical Study of the Nature and Evolution of Mantle Upwelling Beneath Ross Island and its Relationship to Tectonics in the West Antarctica Rift System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>276068</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael E. Jackson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;Existing petrologic and geochemical data for Ross Island volcanic centers are sparse and outdated, with the exception of the well-studied Mt. Erebus stratovolcano. Therefore, understanding of the genesis, evolution and tectonic context of alkaline magmatism on Ross Island is extremely limited. The PIs propose to conduct a field and laboratory based geochemical, isotopic, and petrologic study to investigate alkaline volcanism across the entirety of Ross Island. This study will provide: state-of-the-art isotopic abundances of Nd, Sr, Hf and Pb; pre-eruptive volatile concentrations as determined in melt inclusion studies; petrological and mineralogical information, and major and trace element concentrations for samples from Mt. Terror, Mt.Bird and Hut Point Peninsula. When combined with the published compositional and isotopic data from Mount Erebus, and the published Ar-Ar ages from Ross Island, these data will provide essential information on the nature of the mantle source and the processes and causes of magma genesis beneath Ross Island.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: &lt;br/&gt;This proposal will train two PhD students, broaden the participation of underrepresented groups, promote and enhance secondary educational experiences in a formal class room setting, and encourage new investigators to become involved in USAP. The proposed research includes a collaboration with ENS, Lyon, France. This study will also establish a suite of well-described and geochemically well-characterized samples available to other researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1141534</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kyle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>philipkyle1@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Socorro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>878014681</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5758355915</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 Leroy Place</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5112</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC EARTH SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
