<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: Cognition and signaling in songbirds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>187000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research will examine associations between communication signals and cognitive ability in two species of songbirds. Song in these species is learned: males memorize external models early in life, and then use these memories to shape their own production when they begin to sing many months later. Because song development involves learning and memory, it is logical to hypothesize an association between song and other aspects of cognition. To test that hypothesis, cognitive ability will be measured in a series of laboratory tasks, for example a novel motor task, in which subjects learn to remove lids from the wells of a foraging grid to obtain food, a color association task, in which subjects learn to associate food with lids of a particular color, and a spatial task, in which subjects learn that food can be found only in certain locations. These cognitive measures will then be related to aspects of song that are the outcome of learning, such as the accuracy with which song models are copied during development and the frequency of sharing of song types with others in the local population. Vocal learning in songbirds shows a series of striking parallels with speech development in humans, and therefore results on the tie between vocal development and cognition in songbirds will have implications for the relationship between cognition and speech in humans. Results from the study will be disseminated not only in scientific outlets but also in workshops for high school biology teachers designed to demonstrate how the study of animal behavior can be used to teach the scientific method.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1144995</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Searcy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wsearcy@miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami</Name>
      <CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7659</Code>
      <Text>ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
