<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshops on Basic Research Needs for Biofuel Production from Photosynthetic Microorganisms; Fall 2011, Washington D.C.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34994</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory Rorrer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal ID: 1144433&lt;br/&gt;PI: Reardon&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The production of biofuels from photosynthetic microorganisms has significant potential, but also has considerable scientific and technological challenges for scale up, including water and nutrient use, cost-efficient cultivation and harvesting, and development of microorganisms that are robust and productive at process scale. Due the recently revived interest in the potential of algae for the production of renewable liquid transportation fuels, a variety of research, development, and demonstration activities are now underway by the private sector. Although these efforts provide an important stimulus toward the development of an algal biofuels industry, they largely have short term commercialization goals. Basic research at the level of the biochemistry, biophysics, ecology, metabolic engineering, and synthetic biology of these microorganisms, as well as complimentary bioprocess engineering research, has the potential to resolve scientific and technological barriers to productivity and scalability, and hence accelerate the drive to commercialization. Furthermore, there are parallel research and development activities underway in several countries around the world, and the facilitation of new collaborations would enable synergism with respect to both basic and applied research in this area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will identify the current research gaps underlying the scalable production of biofuels from photosynthetic microorganisms, primarily microalgae and cyanobacteria, from the perspective of fundamental bioscience and bioprocess engineering. The workshop will engage 12 scientific experts in topics fundamental to the use of algae and cyanobacteria for biofuels production. The complimentary follow-up workshop in Germany with 4 US participants will provide an international perspective. These workshops will also suggest research priorities that have the potential to make the greatest impact for advancing the fundamental science and engineering needed to facilitate the nascent algal biofuels industry, and nurture the development of future photosynthetic biorefineries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A report will be submitted to NSF summarizing the conclusions and high priority research needs for algal and cyanobacterial biofuels. In addition, a manuscript on these workshop outcomes will be submitted for publication in a research journal. It is anticipated that new networks and partnerships will arise from the activities associated with both workshops, many of them multidisciplinary and some involving teams of German and US researchers. Travel support will be offered to four junior researchers to benefit their professional development. Efforts will be made to attract applications for these travel grants from members of underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1144433</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reardon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reardon@engr.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>002E</Code>
      <Text>Bio-energy</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
