<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Beyond Virtual Hardware: VMM/OS Co-Design for Lightweight, Flexible Virtualization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>412896</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Virtualization is an increasingly popular strategy for users to run applications designed for one platform on another platform---the holy grail of write once, run anywhere. The caveat for virtualization is that 'anywhere' has to be a powerful system with resources to spare. In a virtual machine, users can bundle an application with all of its operating system dependences in an easily-migrated environment---as long as users are willing to drag along duplicate networking stacks, CPU schedulers, virus scanners, swapping heuristics, and so on. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates a radical restructuring of the operating system in order to reduce these redundancies and overheads.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is driven by a vision of the future where each application and system service runs in a dedicated virtual machine; moreover, the operating system is no longer a single piece of software running on bare hardware, but its functionality is decomposed into several independent layers between the virtual machine monitor and the unmodified application. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates previously unstudied classes of applications and host services, as well as new system layers for hardware management and storage, with the end goal of making per-application virtual machines practical on mobile devices. If successful, this research will establish a richer scientific understanding of the trade-offs in computer system design and dramatically improve the efficiency and flexibility of modern computer systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1149229</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Porter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>porter@cs.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1046</Code>
      <Text>CHEMISTRY CURRICULUM INITIATIVES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
