<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Elucidation of Dopant Effects in Ceria Supports on the Structure and Reactivity of Metal Nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>506000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Jing Zhou of University of Wyoming will investigate doped ceria-supported metal nanoparticles. The effect of dopants in ceria on the structure and chemistry of supported metal catalysts will be elucidated by the catalytic and surface chemistry studies of nickel and gold nanoparticles supported on a series of well-defined model ceria thin film surfaces with selected titanium and zirconium dopants using combined spectroscopy and microscopy techniques. The research will have a significant impact in the field of catalysis because it focuses on fundamental investigations of catalyst structure and reactivity at the nano-scale regime to provide the necessary foundation for the development of improved catalysts. The proposed research will also provide ample training for graduate undergraduate students in catalysis and nanoscience. Prof. Zhou will actively recruit students from underrepresented minority groups and female students to join her program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mechanistic understanding of nickel and gold particles supported by doped ceria can help improve steam-reforming of ethanol and CO oxidation, two very important processes in chemical industry. In addition, Prof. Jing Zhou will promote the awareness and dissemination of knowledge in nanoscience to a broad range of students and the general public through the Nanoscience Art Show and scanning tunneling microscopy demonstrations to K-12 classrooms.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1151846</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jzhou2@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
      <CityName>Laramie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
      <StateCode>WY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8650</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7905</Code>
      <Text>MPS SUST ENERGY SCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
