<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Mask Video Projection Based Additive Manufacturing at the Micro-scale over Large Areas</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven R. Schmid</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) project is to establish a micro-scale additive manufacturing process based on dynamic mask video projection for the fabrication of three-dimensional computer-aided design models with high throughput. Novel approaches by integrating optical, mechanical and software designs will be systematically studied to elucidate the mechanisms through which a projection image can be continuously moved in high speed without losing its native resolution. The related process models and dynamic mask image planning techniques will be established to achieve the desired accuracy, resolution and speed. The educational objective is to promote engineering through hands-on education and product/process innovations based on additive manufacturing technologies. Key education activities include outreach to high school and community college students, new curriculum development for university and working professional levels, and an open source project for the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will contribute a novel micro-scale additive manufacturing process that may lead to newer industrial applications and device designs in a host of industries such as aerospace, automobile, defense, medical, and consumer products. The investigation into process modeling, process planning, and capability characterization will also result in a fabrication tool with gigapixel resolution. Such a tool, if available, will significantly contribute to the future biomedical and engineering research related to tissue engineering and engineered textures. Through its integrated education and outreach activities, this CAREER project would provide essential infrastructure, exciting teaching materials and interesting lab projects to students at every level from K-12 to graduates. Advanced knowledge on additive manufacturing technologies and their novel applications would increase domestic students? interest in science and engineering and promote advanced manufacturing to a broader population.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/03/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/03/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1151191</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yongchen@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/03/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1468</Code>
      <Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>082E</Code>
      <Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
