<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IIS: III: Workshop on Discovery Informatics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The workshop aims to identify the research challenges and opportunities for transforming the scientific discovery process through advances in computing and information sciences in general, and intelligent systems in particular. It seeks to define a research agenda in Discovery Informatics. The workshop is organized around three themes: (1) efficient experimentation and discovery processes, (2) practical issues in building and refining predictive models from scientific data, and (3) social computing for science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The participants include experts and visionaries in the areas of knowledge representation and inference, machine learning and data mining, experiment design and planning, information integration, computational models of discovery, collaborative technologies, robotics, social networks, visualization, and representative application (science) domains. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research in Discovery Informatics is expected to integrate advances in multiple subdisciplines of artificial intelligence and cognitive science to develop the next generation informatics driven exploratory apparatus for scientific discovery. The resulting formal frameworks and computational tools have the potential to not only accelerate discovery but enable new modes of discovery by providing the tools that empower scientists to reach across disciplinary boundaries. Such tools can also contribute to enhanced modes of teaching and learning in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of the workshop (including the workshop report) will be freely disseminated to the larger scientific research and educational community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1151951</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yolanda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gil</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gil@isi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
