<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Center for Turbulence Research Summer Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitrios Papavassiliou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1152924&lt;br/&gt;Moin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant provides partial travel support for students and early-career scientists from U.S. universities to attend the Center for Turbulence Research (CTR) 2012 Summer Program. This will be the fourteenth biennial CTR Summer Program and the first with NSF support. CTR Summer Programs involve about 50 participants from outside of Stanford who join about 30 Stanford participants and NASA scientists for a one-month period of intense study. The 2010 program was the largest to date with 83 participants from 13 countries, including participants from 10 U.S. universities and national laboratories. A competitive process is used to select the participants. They are selected based on the merits of their research proposals, their proposal?s relevance to areas of interest to CTR, and their research credentials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit : The bulk of the Summer Program involves hands on interrogation of numerical simulation databases for testing of models and hypotheses proposed by the participants. Additional calculations to generate new databases may be performed during the Summer Program. The participants are divided into focus groups based on their proposed areas of research. The primary objective of CTR is to stimulate and produce advances in understanding and prediction of complex multi-physics turbulent flows for engineering analysis. The primary means by which CTR seeks to achieve these objectives is by bringing together groups of bright and accomplished individuals in fields bearing on turbulence to address problems of practical interest. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The special biennial Summer School provides opportunity for a concentrated collaborative effort by about fifty advanced graduate students, their advisors, research scientists, and engineers from industry and National Laboratories. An important element of the Summer Program is the weekly tutorials. These tutorials are delivered by leading experts in areas of interest to the participants, and typically last about two hours each.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1152924</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Parviz</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>moin@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
