<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: High-Performance Metal Pretreatments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>710219</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project aims to develop a chromate- and phosphate-free metal surface pre-treatment product that reduces cost, and provides significant environmental and health benefits. Iron and zinc phosphate chemicals are currently widely used in surface treatment processes, which require from 7 to 10 process steps, consume energy to heat treatment baths, and produce a large quantity of waste that must be treated. This adds cost, and results in phosphate discharge to the environment. Based on the Phase I project, a chromate- and phosphate-free pre-treatment chemical will be further developed in this project. This chemical reduces the number of pre-treatment process to less than 5 steps, can be used at ambient temperature, and produces 90% less waste. It is expected to demonstrate enhanced performance in corrosion protection and paint adhesion over similar products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader commercial impacts of this project will be to dramatically reduce cost, complexity and negative environmental impact of metal surface pretreatment in manufacturing processes without compromising performance. Potential applications will be in automobile, aerospace, steel (coil coatings), consumer electronics, appliance, and many other industries. An important societal impact will be the better protection to workers in plants, as this process is not toxic and does not require elaborate waste disposal procedures. This project will also enhance the scientific understanding of mechanisms by which pretreatments contribute to the protection of metals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1152518</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>VanOoij</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wvanooij@ecosiltech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/23/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Danqing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhud@ecosiltech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>ECOSIL Technologies LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Fairfield</CityName>
      <ZipCode>450143018</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5138582365</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>160A Donald Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
