<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Clues to the Cryosphere: Symposium for the National Science Teachers Association Annual Meeting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>76667</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter T. West</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposal is to obtain support for a teacher symposium at the National Science Teachers Association (NSTA) Annual Meeting in April of 2012 in Indianapolis called ?Clues to the Cryosphere.?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Drawing on both Arctic and Antarctic researchers make presentations and the proposers? experience in organizing a similar symposium at NSTA in 2010, researcher Christine Foreman and Education and Outreach specialist Susan Kelly plan a variety of high-profile education and outreach polar science activities on behalf of the Office of Polar Programs (OPP) during the four-day conference. These will include a four-and-a- half-hour symposium for educators, six individual sessions that are designed to follow the symposia, a staffed OPP booth in the exhibit area for the duration of the conference, two workshops for teachers held in conjunction with the exhibit hall, and three web seminars that serve to extend learning opportunities after the national conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/04/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1153662</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Foreman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cforeman@montana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/04/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Montana State University</Name>
      <CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
