<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Surface-Enhanced Solar Energy Conversion System for Advancing Alternative Energy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>419550</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division Professors Shanlin Pan and Arunava Gupta of the University of Alabama will investigate surface-enhanced solar energy conversion systems for advancing alternative energy. Intense electromagnetic field around plasmonic antenna of well-defined metallic nanostructures will be utilized to enhance the light absorption cross-section of visible-light-active photocatalysts for photoelectrochemical water splitting and other photoelectrochemical reactions. Advanced photoelectrochemical, spectroscopic and microscopic tools, such as ultrafast transient absorption spectroscopy, photoelectrochemcial microelectrode, and microelectrode, will be used to probe the interfacial charge transfer dynamics and local photoelectrochemistry near the surface-enhanced photocatalysts. The comprehensive research program includes the following components: nanostructure fabrication, structural characterization, photoelectrochemical and spectroelectrochemical studies, and theoretical modeling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The work brings together a multidisciplinary team that will make significant contributions to scientific knowledge, education outreach and infrastructure in a study related to renewable energy, which is an area of top priority for the nation. The scientific outcomes of the project will include both advances in the fabrication of a new class of nanostructured photocatalysts and fundamental understanding of their photoelectrochemical and materials characteristics. Results from the work are relevant both for improving the water splitting efficiency of visible-light-active photocatalysts to produce hydrogen and power efficiency of hybrid organic photovoltaic devices. The PIs will collaborate with the Alabama Science in Motion (ASIM) Program to develop a clean energy education program for high school minority and underrepresented students and teachers in west central Alabama. The proposed project will provide support for graduate and undergraduate students, including underrepresented minorities, which will contribute to their broad interdisciplinary training. An important aspect of the proposed project is the capacity to provide hands on experience in topical research areas. Project personnel will play a key role in several ongoing education and outreach activities related to the proposed research. These include collaboration with local schools to facilitate participation by high school students in research, public tours and demonstrations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1153120</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shanlin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>span1@bama.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arunava</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gupta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>agupta@mint.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5560</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY CONVERSION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7289</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
