<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TCUP: Biology, Ecology, Conservation Genetics and Management of the Ornate Box Turtles (Terrapene ornata ornata) in South Dakota</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>191572</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;Little is known about ornate box turtles in South Dakota and further research linked directly to defining effective conservation programs are critically needed. This research implements an integrative conservation approach to achieve the following objectives: 1) Assist South Dakota Game, Fish and Parks (SDGFP) in implementing the South Dakota Wildlife Action Plan, 2) Estimate the home range and the geographic range of ornate box turtles in South Dakota through the use of ecological niche modeling, 3) Document macro- and microhabitat use, 4) Describe movements and document daily and seasonal activity periods, and 5) Estimate gene flow among local populations using a landscape genetics approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broadening Participation&lt;br/&gt;This research will improve the research experience for Native American undergraduate students at Oglala Lakota College(OLC) by providing training in ecological field research delivering hands-on, place-based STEM instruction and will facilitate the advancement of Native American student education by bridging OLC undergraduate students interested in Conservation Biology to the Master of Science in Integrative Genomics (MSIG) at the Black Hill State University(BHSU).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1153443</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Garth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spellman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>garth.spellman@dmns.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/06/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alesangra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Higa</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ahiga@olc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oglala Lakota College</Name>
      <CityName>Kyle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>577520490</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6054556000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 490</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
