<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Building a Community of MESA/STEM Scholars Initiative</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lidia C. Yoshida</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Through the "Building a Community of MESA/STEM Scholars Initiative" (MESA stands for Mathematics, Engineering, Science Achievement), City College of San Francisco (CCSF) is supporting a total of up to 250 scholarships for a diverse group of academically talented, financially needy students across the STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each year, CCSF recruits a minimum of 40 students from the CCSF School of Science and Mathematics to apply for the S-STEM scholarship program who are both financially needy and academically talented - and who are representative of the great diversity of CCSF overall. Scholarship participants receive one-on-one academic counseling and participate in cohort-building activities that expose and link them to a wide range of career opportunities and provide them with personal empowerment strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project provides students access to numerous innovative initiatives in the STEM fields currently in place at CCSF, including cutting-edge programs in biotechnology (such as stem cell technology), computer networking and information technology (including the convergence of optical and network systems), and several others.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a community college, CCSF provides one of the most affordable educational options in the San Francisco Bay Area, and through this program it offers extraordinary educational access to STEM students from a broad range of ethnic, economic, cultural, and age backgrounds. Due to its affordability, even a small award substantially relieves CCSF students of financial burdens that often inhibit their academic success.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1154588</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Trinh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tran</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tttran@ccsf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fmoore@ccsf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>City College of San Francisco</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941031214</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4152393000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>33 Gough Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
