<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EPSCoR 2030 Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99684</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01120000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>EPSCoR</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Denise M. Barnes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Number: EPS-1155975 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: EPSCoR 2030 Workshop&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: West Virginia Higher Education Policy Commission&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to conduct a workshop with representatives from the National Science Foundation (NSF), the EPSCoR community, and recognized leaders of industrial and legislative bodies from both EPSCoR and non-EPSCoR jurisdictions. This workshop, entitled EPSCoR 2030, will be a timely follow-up to the ?EPSCoR 2020: Expanding State Participation in Research in the 21st Century ? A New Vision for EPSCoR? workshop held in 2006 and seeks to review progress on recommendations from EPSCoR 2020 and make needed adjustments. In addition, EPSCoR 2030 seeks to continue the dialogue with NSF on a shared understanding of EPSCoR goals and metrics and the most effective actions to enhance research competitiveness nationally. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The EPSCoR 2030 Workshop will provide NSF senior management with recommendations for increasing the quality and broadening the scope of research in EPSCoR jurisdictions, for more effectively developing and utilizing their science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) talent over the next decade, and for better targeting available funding to those jurisdictions for which the EPSCoR program can provide the largest incremental benefit to their research infrastructure. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Recommendations from the workshop are expected to prompt sustainable improvements in physical, human, and cyber infrastructure with EPSCoR jurisdictions as well as broader collaborative activities leading to collective solutions to challengers of regional and national importance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1155975</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paul.hill@wvresearch.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Higher Education Policy Commission</Name>
      <CityName>Charleston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>253012841</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3045580281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1018 Kanawha Blvd East Suite 700</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
