<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A novel approach for evaluating temporal and spatial changes in trophic structure of the mesopelagic eastern Pacific</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>516441</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David L. Garrison</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Anthropogenic and natural climatic perturbations drive changes in population dynamics of species, the structure and function of food webs, and biogeochemical processes. The PIs propose a comparative analysis of three major ecosystems to investigate temporal change in the structure of mesopelagic food webs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The PIs will investigate temporal changes in the structure of mesopelagic food webs in three major ecosystems: the California Current, Eastern Tropical Pacific, and the Peru-Humboldt Current over the past 50 years using a globally distributed apex predator as an indicator species. The predator is the sperm whale, Physeter macrocephalus, and the PIs will use stable isotope ratios of carbon and nitrogen as indicators of habitat and diet. Isotope values from bulk tissues of teeth and skin (C and N) as well as specific amino acids (N) will be used to address two primary objectives: (a) examine temporal patterns in the trophic position of sperm whales (as an indicator of changes in mesopelagic trophic structure) and baseline isotopic values (as indicators of nutrient cycling); and (b) use isotopic values, which vary among systems, to define the population structure of sperm whales from past and present times, and connectivity among populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project will be conducted by researchers from academia and NOAA/NMFS with expertise in stable isotope analysis, trophic ecology, and ecosystem-based management of protected species. As such, it represents an opportunity for collaboration between scientists with complementary skills and from diverse institutions to compare structure and function of ecosystems across the eastern Pacific. Moreover, it represents a collaboration between academia and a federal agency with research and management responsibilities. The project will support a postdoctoral scholar (Iliana Ruiz-Cooley), a Ph.D. student, and undergraduate students to enhance their career and collaborative opportunities. The PIs anticipate that the results of their study will provide unique data to evaluate the effects of perturbations within and among mesopelagic ecosystems. This information may allow the scientific community to relate trends in climate to changes in trophic position of top predators and nutrient cycling, allowing more robust understanding of possible responses to future warming. Finally, as the first systematic applications of compound-specific stable isotope analysis to marine mammals, the project should be highly instructive for future evaluations of the feeding ecology, population structure and dynamics of endangered marine mammals. As such, this novel approach and unique historic perspective will be directly applicable for stock assessment and management.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1155728</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>plkoch@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCarthy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdmccar@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1650</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
