<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Experiences for Undergraduates Site: Ecology in Human-Dominated Landscapes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>392617</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Sites award has been made to Miami University that will provide research training for 12 students, for 10 weeks during the summers of 2012-14. The program focuses on collaborative research emphasizing ecological questions in landscapes influenced by human activity. Students will conduct individual projects with the guidance of faculty mentors and be part of research "clusters" consisting of 3-4 students and mentors. Clusters form collaborative teams focused on themes that tie together their individual research topics. Thus, students will have the opportunity to work in multi-disciplinary research teams, structured similarly to research groups solving real-world problems. One workshop will be offered in collaboration with the Myaamia Project, a tribal initiative to enhance the understanding of and appreciation for the history, language, and culture of the pre-European people that occupied SW Ohio, which will enable students to explore alternative relationships with the land that result in different approaches to environmental problems. Another workshop will examine aspects of the scientific profession, including careers in ecology, preparation and delivery of scientific presentations, and responsible conduct in research. Students will also participate in sessions on scientific and environmental ethics and field trips to sites of local ecological interest. Finally, each student will present his or her research as an oral presentation, an electronic poster, and a written paper that will be developed into a manuscript for publication. The project will recruit a diverse group of students including underrepresented minorities, first-generation college students, and students from colleges with little research opportunities. Students are selected based on academic record as well as their interest in and potential for research. Students are tracked to determine their further participation in academic study, their career paths, and the lasting influences of the research experience. Information about the program will be assessed by various means, including use of an REU common assessment tool. Miami has a long and excellent history of involving undergraduates in research and has excellent facilities for executing this REU site, including a diverse array of human-dominated ecosystems (including a nearby field station), and state-of-the-art laboratory facilities. More information is available by visiting http://www.muohio.edu/ecoreu or by contacting Ann L. Rypstra (513-785-3238 or rypstral@muohio.edu).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156703</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rypstra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rypstral@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bergdj@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Miami University</Name>
      <CityName>Oxford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>450563653</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5135293600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 E High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7972</Code>
      <Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7405</Code>
      <Text>IRAQ</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
