<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Sensing, Monitoring, and Detection: From Molecules to Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry (CHE) at the National Science Foundation supports the Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at Florida international University. The REU Program will bring 9 students to campus for 10 weeks each summer to conduct research in a supportive research environment. These students will pursue team-oriented summer projects in the interdisciplinary field of sensing, participate in seminars and workshops, present their work within and outside their scientific teams in widely-attended venues at the FIU campus, and be encouraged to pursue a career in research and discovery. Within the interdisciplinary area of sensing, the students will participate in representative projects across analytical/environmental, biological, inorganic, organic, physical/theoretical, and forensic chemistry. Emphasis will be placed both on rigorous scientific training and the immersion of students in an environment connecting scientific research with the real world. The REU Site will provide faculty and peer mentorship and promote student involvement in graduate student life. As part of the proposed activities, participating faculty will give presentations on ethics and bioethics in science, major scientific breakthroughs, and the role of scientists in modern society. Student selection will focus on minorities and women nationwide, with an emphasis on students from small colleges in Florida who have limited access to research. through faculty and peer mentorship, and their involvement in graduate student life. As part of the proposed activities, participating faculty will give presentations on ethics and bioethics in science, major scientific breakthroughs, and the role of scientists in modern society. Student selection will focus on minorities and women nationwide, with an emphasis on students from small colleges in Florida who have limited access to research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156886</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Konstantinos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kavallieratos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kavallie@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jaroslava</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miksovska</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>miksovsk@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida International University</Name>
      <CityName>Miami</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
