<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: Bacterial Cell Surfaces Gordon Research Conference being held June 24-29, 2012 in Mount Snow Resort, West Dover, Vermont.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The study of bacterial cell surfaces is a topic of intense interest, and the Bacterial Cell Surfaces Gordon Research Conference has been one of the most useful and productive venues for bringing together new blood and old practitioners to keep this area vitally alive and to advance it in new and unexpected ways. The Bacterial Cell Surfaces Gordon Research Conference will be held June 24-29,2012 in Mount Snow Resort, West Dover, Vermont. The organizers of the conference include Kevin Young, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences and Tracy Palmer, University of Dundee, Scotland. The Gordon Research Conference on Bacterial Cell Surfaces has been one of the largest and most&lt;br/&gt;successful of the Gordon Conferences since its establishment in 1971. This conference will focus on the biogenesis, structure and function of bacterial envelopes and surfaces, including bacterial membranes, cell walls, surface appendages and polymers. The conference will include a diverse program of topics, model systems and approaches, combining biochemistry, molecular genetics, structural biology, biophysics, imaging and modeling. Oral presentations will be grouped into nine sessions: 1) Protein localization, 2) Secretion, 3) Cell morphogenesis, 4) Motility, chemotaxis and surface structures, 5) Special surface interactions, 6) Stress, transduction and transport, 7) Outer and inner membranes, 8) Cell wall, and 9) Cell division. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;With regard to educational value, the conference has a long history of showcasing investigators who are leaders in their field, while at the same time introducing new, young and early stage scientists. In addition to those young investigators scheduled for oral presentations, up to six poster presenters (typically postdoctoral fellows or graduate students) will be selected to give short talks during the morning sessions. The current program includes 31 speakers and is diverse in nationality (11 international), gender (12 female) and seniority (15 established investigators, 6 intermediate career, and 10 young and emerging scientists).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156128</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Young</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kdyoung@uams.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
