<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Practices and Perspecitves at VCU</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>253900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry (CHE) at the National Science Foundation supports the renewal of a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU). The VCU REU program encompasses a practices and a perspectives component. The program provides a valuable research experience (practices) for students predominantly from non-PhD-granting schools whose research opportunities are limited. It also develops student perspectives on scientific careers and career planning beginning with a training period that teaches skills common to all scientific research. Students quickly move to research labs to carry out their assigned research project. Development of the perspectives component continues with a visit to a local pharmaceutical facility (Pfizer), where the students participate in mock interviews and a panel discussion with a variety of scientists. Each student's oral and written communication skills are developed by: (1) writing a proposal; (2) revising their personal statement; (3) presenting a research poster at the halfway point; and (4) giving a final oral presentation and submitting a final written research report. The program's intellectual merit is defined by student participants conducting fundamental research. In this context, they gain perspectives on career decisions, specific technical expertise that gives them an advantage on their applications for jobs or graduate school, and the get see real life applications of a degree in chemistry or a related technical discipline. The broader impact of this REU program stems from its focus on recruiting students from universities where undergraduate research opportunities are not generally available. Women and minority participants are targeted specifically. This program provides research experiences to heighten students' interest in chemistry and to motivate them to remain in science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156892</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suzanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruder</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sruder@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sally</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hunnicutt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sshunnic@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
      <CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
