<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Intensive Mentored Research Experience for Undergraduates in Clinical, Cognitive, and Behavioral Neuroscience at an Urban Public College</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>291209</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Fahmida N. Chowdhury</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of the Neuroscience Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at Brooklyn College (BC) is to immerse diverse students in innovative research on clinical, cognitive, and behavioral neuroscience. Twelve students are selected annually for mentored research projects, especially undergraduates at ethnic-minority serving, public two-year and four-year institutions in the New York metropolitan area where the PIs have identified a need for such programming. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central component is a semester-long laboratory immersion under the close supervision of BC Psychology Department faculty mentors who have experience working with diverse students, which results in a completed research project. The Department offers a vibrant and highly collaborative research and teaching environment, and the faculty utilizes multiple approaches to understanding brain-behavior relationships. The REU site students are exposed to a variety of behavioral, neuroscientific, and computational methods to address their individual research topics. Students attend a weekly seminar that presents an overview of basic neuroscience principles and domain-specific topics relevant to research conducted in laboratories of core REU faculty. The seminar also address professional issues, including a module on ethics. In addition, students participate in a journal club and attend colloquia in which speakers from outside the Department present cutting-edge neuroscience research and applications. As a capstone experience, students present a poster at the annual Brooklyn College Science Research Day, where they compete with other undergraduates for awards based on the quality of their work and ability to communicate their findings. Some students also have the opportunity to assist in the preparation of a poster for presentation at a national scientific research meeting and/or a peer-reviewed manuscript. The PI team emphasizes the generation of high quality research and integration of psychological theory with the design, execution, and interpretation of neuroscientific data. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU site advances neuroscience discovery for the scientific and broader communities while promoting mentoring, learning, and professional development. The specific objectives are to: (1) increase participation of students from underrepresented groups (e.g., women, racial minorities, first-generation college students, veterans returning from active duty) in the field of neuroscience; (2) guide students through the scientific process, from generation of viable research questions to communicating study results; (3) immerse students in relevant didactics that complement their laboratory work and highlight its relevance and applied value; and (4) provide knowledge, skills, and exposure to leading neuroscience research, as well as opportunities for students to make contributions to this research, to enhance their competitiveness for graduate school or professional positions. Strong institutional support from BC of the City University of New York and clearly defined criteria for self-evaluation ensure that the PI team meets their stated goals. Importantly, this REU Program enables BC faculty members to supervise talented undergraduates, who might otherwise miss out on mentored laboratory and professional development experiences, and contribute to the training and advancement of the next generation of neuroscientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156870</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walder</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>DWalder@brooklyn.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rabin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>laura.a.rabin@dartmouth.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Brooklyn College</Name>
      <CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
      <ZipCode>112102889</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7189515622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research &amp; Sponsored P</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
