<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: 2012 Microbial Stress Response Gordon Research Conference to be held July 20-25, 2012 in South Hadley, MA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susanne von Bodman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The 2012 conference will continue its tradition of improving the scientific knowledge and technical capability of scientists who are studying stress responses of isolated microbes and microbial communities. More specifically, the 2012 conference emphasizes two new direction that are consistent with the Networks and Regulation cluster priorities. First, the conference focuses on an integrated perspective of stress response biology across scales of complexity from single to multicellular to microbe-host interaction systems. Second, the organizers make a concerted effort to include computational and systems-levelapproaches to study stress biology in microbes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The meeting offers numerous informal opportunities for young investigators to interact with senior researchers. Students and junior scientists will be selected for presentations based on their submitted abstracts. A particular effort will be made to recruit underrepresented minorities and participants from diverse geographical regions. Diverse participation is reflected also in the organizing committee with one of the two chairs being a female. Eleven of 32 invited and confirmed speakers/discussion leaders are females and two are members of an under-represented minority group.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156053</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Donohue</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tdonohue@bact.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
