<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Evaluation of the National Science Foundation's Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR) and Similar Programs in Other Federal Agencies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01120000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>EPSCoR</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Denise M. Barnes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Director: Kevin Finneran&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal: EPS-1157188&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: National Academy of Sciences&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Evaluation of the National Science Foundation?s Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR) and Similar Programs in Other Federal Agencies&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study is being conducted by the National Academy of Sciences? Committee on Science, Engineering and Public Policy (COSEPUP) to support the National Science Foundation in its efforts to comply with directives of the America COMPETES Reauthorization Act of 2010. This act became Public Law 111-358, when signed by President Obama in January, 2011. The Act contains numerous elements dealing with initiatives to strengthen the nation?s science, engineering, and education enterprises and contains language specific to several of the Foundation?s Offices and Directorates, including the Office of the Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR). It also contains language specific to the six other federal agencies with congressionally authorized EPSCoR and EPSCoR-like programs. Specifically, Section 517(f) calls for an assessment study of the federal EPSCoR programs at all seven agencies, and states that the National Academy of Sciences should conduct the assessment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The EPSCoR programs seek to expand and enhance the nation?s research capacity by working with the jurisdictions that receive lesser amounts of research funds from seven federal agencies. These programs have achieved various levels of success and have been evaluated and assessed individually. This study seeks to conduct a comprehensive study of all EPSCoR and EPSCoR-like programs and provide recommendations for their enhancements and improvements to achieve program goals consistent with the specific agency missions, as appropriate. The National Academies have long demonstrated their ability to assemble committees to perform rigorous assessments of government programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Collectively, the EPSCoR jurisdictions have developed research and education capacity and capability needed to address many of the science and engineering challenges facing the nation. Specifically, many of the jurisdictions have developed areas of expertise in energy, water and the environment, and workforce development. In addition, many of the nation?s future researchers are receiving their undergraduate or graduate training at institutions of higher learning within these jurisdictions, particularly students currently underrepresented in STEM. This study is expected to lead to recommendations to enhance coordination across the agencies with EPSCoR programs to maximize the impact of federal funding for building and sustaining competitive research infrastructure nationally. In addition, strengthened research capability in EPSCoR jurisdictions can contribute to their economic success as local industries often benefit from direct interaction with researchers who have access to infrastructure that sustains knowledge-based innovation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1157188</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Finneran</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Kfinnera@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7217</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
