<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developments in the understanding of processes in the P cycle: new concepts from the use of isotopic tracers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>41000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030205</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a request to support a workshop that will promote international scientific collaboration on phosphorus (P) cycling for earth, ocean and agricultural scientist as well as biologists, limnologists, archeologists and climate scientists. Phosphorus (P) is an essential nutrient for all living organisms; but while P resources are dwindling and in many environments, such as the tropics, P limits agricultural production, excessive P loading can cause eutrophication, reduce water quality and ecosystem alteration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will be held in June of 2012 in the Centro Stefano Franscini (CSF), Monte Verità, Switzerland, and will be co-funded by Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zürich (ETH Zurich). The workshop will be organized by Drs. S. Bernasconi, E. Frossard, and F. Tamburini (all form ETH Zürich) in collaboration with Dr. Adina Paytan (UCSC). The Swiss organizers will arrange for on site logistics and all of the organizers will share equal responsibilities in coordinating the scientific program. The meeting will focus on: (a) the current understanding of the P cycle and defining knowledge gaps, (b) introduction of new methodologies and technologies (with focus on stable isotopes) that may fill the gaps, and (c) fostering international collaborations that will use new tools to advance our knowledge on P in our environment. Participants will include researchers from universities and government research institutes, post docs, and students from many countries. The activity will bring together a diverse community of university professors, research scientists, post doctoral fellows and graduate students from all around the world including the United States, Europe, the Middle East and additional countries. Outcomes from the workshop will lead to new insights regarding application of innovative methodologies to the study of P in our environment and the impact of human activity on the P cycle. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Support under this travel grant is targeted to young U.S. scientists, enabling them to make important contacts in the international scientific community, and contributing to the training of the next generation of environmental scientists. Conclusions and outcomes from this workshop will be disseminated broadly in a proceedings document and likely culminated in publication of manuscripts in a special issue, dedicated sessions in international meetings and through relevant web portals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1157375</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paytan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>apaytan@ucsc.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
