<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Autonomous Sentinels for the Detection and Capture of Invasive Pathogens</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>359965</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1157962/Chin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this proposed research is to investigate and develop autonomous sentinels for pathogen detection and capture. A system composed of these sentinels will mimic the function of naturally occurring biological defensive systems, such as white blood cells. This autonomous sentinel system will have the capability of seeking out invasive bacteria, spores and toxins in liquid environments, detecting and capturing them. Once detected and captured, the invasive pathogens can be removed by retrieving the sentinels. These sentinels will be constructed of magnetostrictive materials and require no onboard power. The Intellectual Merits of this project are: 1) this research will further the scientific understanding of magnetostrictive alloys as a class of materials for sensor applications through both theoretical simulations and experimental verification and 2) novel methods of generating magnetostrictive powered propulsion will be investigated. New autonomous sentinel technologies developed under this proposal are anticipated to have Broader Impacts leading to a plethora of devices for food safety, biosecurity, point of care, home care, and environmental monitoring. In the area of food safety alone, the impacts could be monumental. Every year over 48 million Americans become ill due to eating pathogen contaminated foods. The resulting foodborne illnesses will lead to the hospitalization of approximately 128,000 people and the death of more than 3,000 at a cost of over $30 billion dollars. The autonomous sentinels developed under this project could be used to identify contamination of foods before human consumption. This would substantially improve the safety of our food supply, improve the quality of human life, reduce human suffering and deaths, and limit lost productivity due to foodborne outbreaks in the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1157962</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bchin@eng.auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/12/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Auburn University</Name>
      <CityName>Auburn University</CityName>
      <ZipCode>368490001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 Samford Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>019E</Code>
      <Text>SENSORS AND SENSING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>142E</Code>
      <Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
