<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Investigation of Emissions and Ozone Photochemistry over China and Their Environmental Impacts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>353192</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The rapid economic growth in China has led to large increases of pollutant emissions but current understanding of their subsequent chemical evolution, large-scale atmospheric transport, and environmental implications is limited. Recent observational evidence suggests that photochemistry over China has characteristics distinct from those considered by current generation of 3-D chemical transport models. These differences may reflect limitations in chemical schemes as implemented in current models or large underestimation of emissions for fast-reacting aromatics over China. Evidence also suggests an increasing influence of the trans-Pacific transport of emissions from China on O3 over the western United States. The research effort will improve scientific understanding of atmospheric photochemistry over China and the associated larger-scale implications via analysis of satellite and in situ observations and associated model calculations. The specific research objective is to investigate the effects of volatile organic compounds, particularly aromatics, on regional O3 photochemistry over China. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research problems that will be addressed through this effort are not only relevant to current understanding of atmospheric chemistry but will also provide the scientific basis for evaluating the environmental consequences of economic development and exploring effective emission control measures. One graduate student will be supported and trained in modeling and data analysis through the project. Results will be published in journal articles, presented to the public in lectures, and employed as case studies in graduate-level atmospheric chemistry courses. The collaboration of Chinese scientists in the research effort will facilitate the transfer of knowledge and technology and thereby help improve air quality in China and, indirectly, in the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1158867</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuhang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ywang@eas.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
