<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Dynamically Tunable Low-Loss Active Metamaterials For Wireless Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>501219</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of this project is to develop fast (~nanosecond) tunable-over-a-wide-band, low-loss, physically small, metamaterial-based RF front-end elements compatible with Digital-RF transceiver concept being developed in industry for a variety of commercial and military applications. We will focus on novel metamaterials based on superconductor elements to form extremely low insertion loss, physically and electrically small, highly tunable structures for the next generation of RF electronics. These metamaterials will allow us to increase performance while decreasing size and signature of antennas operating over wide bands, multibands and allowing dynamic real-time tuning. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The work will include the Josephson effect into metamaterials for the first time, leading to development of radical new applications of metamaterials and test several high-risk theoretical predictions. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work investigates and promotes applications of metamaterials for the RF and microwave industry. These developments will be of direct and measurable value to society through the generation of high-tech jobs, improvement of wireless communications, and a positive impact on quality of life. The PI has a history of broadening the participation of underrepresented groups (currently 50% of the research group are members of underrepresented groups), and is involved in numerous outreach activities. These activities will create new partnerships, collaborations, and facilities that will alter the landscape of the superconducting metamaterials field. The results will be disseminated through publications, talks and posters at international conferences, a research web site, and continuation of the extensive outreach activities by the PI and students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1158644</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Anlage</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anlage@squid.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oleg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mukhanov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mukhanov@hypres.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>097E</Code>
      <Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
