<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Grant for the sixth international workshop in interfacial fluid mechanics and transport processes-IMA 6. Haifa, Israel on June 18-21, 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eddie Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1159143&lt;br/&gt;Narayanan&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal requests for partial travel support for 10 participating U.S. scientists to attend the sixth international workshop and conference on thermal, fluid and interfacial phenomena in physico-chemical, materials and bio- processes at the Technion campus in Haifa, Israel on June 18-21, 2012. Participation in this conference is vital to the U.S. since scientists from around the world will meet to exchange ideas and seek potential collaborations for future work. This exchange of ideas will very likely develop new ideas to tackle current research problems. Research problems in materials processing, nanotechnologies and drug delivery as well as space technologies will be addressed. The themes of this conference are two-fold:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) industrial and practical applications (e.g., energy problems of heat pipes and evaporation, two phase flows, materials processing of thin films, and in micro-fluidics, fluid transport in novel processing involving interfaces and measurement of thermo-physical properties. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2) fundamental transport phenomena (e.g., interfacial instabilities in liquid bridges, Marangoni phenomena, two fluid problems, interfacial mass exchange and more.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The participating scientists will represent research areas funded by NSF through the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems (CBET). The scientists will represent academia, industry and government research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The wide range of participants will be expected to benefit the cooperative science programs between the U.S. and other countries as well as university/industrial collaborations. The proceedings of the conference will also be published by a well-known journal, the European Journal of Physics. The research ideas will be widely disseminated via libraries and the electronic media making a broad impact on the community of scientists and engineers. The published research ideas and discussions will encourage future novel research and fresh perspectives on technological problems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1159143</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ranga</FirstName>
      <LastName>Narayanan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ranga@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
