<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Understanding High School Pre-Engineering Student Design Cognition, Comparisons with Engineering Students</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>269078</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This engineering education research project will explore how high school students learn engineering design by investigating these students' misconceptions about engineering design. The investigators will use a longitudinal study of high school students in three states who engage in engineering design experiences. The analysis techniques to be employed are well-grounded in current theories. Comparisons with college students will provide insights on how students develop design competencies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project will be to guide existing projects and efforts that introduce elements of engineering and design into the K-12 curriculum, particularly at the high school level. As design becomes increasingly important in university engineering programs, an increased understanding of high school student's design experiences is need to help them transition from secondary school to college. The project will broadly disseminate findings among the engineering education and cognitive science communities so that the research can impact practice. This project overlaps with NSF's strategic goals of transforming the frontiers through preparation of an engineering workforce with new capabilities and expertise. Additionally NSF's goal of innovating for society is enabled by creating results and research that are useful for society by informing educational policy and practices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1160345</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgero1@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Mason University</Name>
      <CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
