<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fundamental Research in Quantum Field Induced Strain in Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>211948</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Fyhrie</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to elucidate the basic science underpinning quantum field induced strain in quantum dots. While tremendous efforts have been expended to understand the impact of mechanical strain on the electronic structure of quantum dots, initial results of the Principal Investigator (PI) also suggest a startling reverse effect i.e. despite absence of external strains, if the quantum dot is made small enough (1-3 nm range), the electronic structure change due to quantum confinement may induce a strain in the quantum dot which in turn will alter the band structure. The latter, in turn, will further alter the strain thus resulting in a nonlinear self-consistent type coupling. This provides a basis for the identification of novel size effects in the electronic structure of quantum dots beyond what is currently understood. Through the use of parameter-free ab initio methods complemented by multi-band envelope function approach, we will illustrate the physical implications of this new coupling through exploration of a (i) mechanism of universal optical actuation in nanowire structures, and (ii) impact of reverse coupling on non-radiative auger recombination and consequences for solar energy and laser applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;From a technological perspective, successful completion of the proposed research will enable a new paradigm in quantum dot engineering leading to an impact on next generation nano-electronics, photovoltaics, chemo-bio sensors, quantum electro-mechanical systems among others. Novel strategies will be implemented to increase enrollment of female students. To foster scientific literature appreciation among undergraduates, a mock "editor-reviewer journal forum" will be used. An ongoing NSF-funded GK12 program run by the PI in close cooperation with Houston area schools will be leveraged for outreach to K-12 schools. In this program, graduate students use "science behind Harry Potter" to revitalize science education in schools while at the same time learning valuable communication skills that teach the art of articulating complex scientific ideas to audiences of all type.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1161163</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pradeep</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>psharma@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/29/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1630</Code>
      <Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>027E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1084</Code>
      <Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
