<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>College of Engineering, Mathematics and Science Recruitment and Retention Center</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>899888</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ron Buckmire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This NSF STEM Talent Expansion Program (STEP) project is increasing the number of students graduating with undergraduate STEM degrees through increased recruitment and retention of students in the College of Engineering, Mathematics, and Science (EMS), at the University of Wisconsin-Platteville. UW-Platteville, a STEM campus focused primarily on undergraduate education, serves over 7,400 students in a rural community. A Recruitment and Retention Center is being developed within the academic unit, which hosts tutoring and mentoring programs and also serves as a centralized location for College of EMS efforts; a significant focus is on supporting traditionally underrepresented STEM students. The STEP project builds on the success of existing programs, some of which are currently supported by the NSF. A structure is being provided to facilitate cohort development; increase networking opportunities including mentoring, advising and research; promote career development through internships and co-operative education; and support career selection and job placement. Students involved with the NSF STEP program are preparing for the 21st century workforce by participating in high impact practices including mentoring, internships, co-ops, scholarly engagements, workshops, service, outreach and conferences, which affect persistence and stimulate academic achievement excellence and career placements in STEM. Extensive analysis of the success of the programming offered through this STEP project is being conducted in order to increase the knowledge of best practices in the scholarship of teaching and learning. The number of STEM degrees awarded at UW-Platteville increases by over 20% by the end of this funding.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1161180</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Curras</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>currasc@uwplatt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hudson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hudsonw@uwplatt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Summers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>summerss@uwplatt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tammy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Salmon-Stephens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>salmont@uwplatt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Platteville</Name>
      <CityName>Platteville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>538183001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6083421261</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 University Plaza</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1796</Code>
      <Text>STEM TALENT EXPANSN PGM (STEP)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
