<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: Medium: Collaborative Research: Systematic Analysis of Protocol Implementations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>446860</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Systematic Analysis of Protocol Implementations&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Internet protocol development and standardization has long been driven by the philosophy of 'rough consensus and running code.' The downside to this approach is that protocol specifications are rarely rigorously verified, even for properties that fall within the capabilities of protocol verification techniques. Further, the 'rough' nature of the approach means that some important design decisions are inevitably omitted from the specification or are defined ambiguously. Therefore, in practice the correctness, performance, and resilience of network protocols are implicitly defined by vendor and open-source implementations of the protocol specification, and these implementations are based upon the developers' varying interpretations of the standards document. This leaves developers in a bind: they are unsure of the properties of the protocol specification, and do not have tools to reason about the properties of complex protocol implementations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. This project will develop a general approach and an associated tool that will enable developers and expert users to systematically analyze a variety of properties on a range of protocol implementations. The approach builds upon recent advances in program analysis techniques in novel ways that are tailored towards the special properties and requirements of protocol implementations. Moreover, the project will instantiate the general approach with new analyses for important tasks that are largely manual and highly error-prone today, including interoperability testing and precise tracking of state changes over time (e.g., to identify anomalous state sequences or characterize protocol complexity).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is based on the observation that protocol implementations have an implicit internal structure, in the form of a state machine that embodies the key behavioral properties of the implementation. Due to the complexity of protocol implementations, this state machine will typically not be completely inferable by program analysis. To address this problem, the project will develop operators on a protocol implementation that allow developers to specify scalable and precise views of the underlying state machine. Developers can additionally use these views to perform a targeted concrete execution of the protocol on a real topology in order to investigate the particular property under consideration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The outcome of the project will be a software system called Spa. Developers will provide protocol implementations and use their expertise about the protocol and its properties of interest to specify appropriate operators and guide targeted concrete execution. The project will evolve Spa operators using experiences gained from applying Spa to several protocol analyses that have not been previously considered, and will start with a set of operators that have been informed by the PIs' preliminary research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact. The protocols that underlie access to our networked world must be reliable, robust to attacks, and must perform well over a range of conditions and in dynamic environments. This project will equip developers and experts to systematically analyze the behavior of their protocols, and will result in an overall improvement in the reliability, robustness, and performance of deployed protocols. The project will accelerate the adoption of the research by making Spa available to researchers and developers, publishing its research results in top networking and programming language conferences, and educating students on the developed research methods by incorporating them in curricula. It will also engage underrepresented groups and undergraduates in research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1161595</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
      <LastName>Millstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>todd@cs.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
