<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Problems in number theory and representation theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Gunnells proposes to work on problems in number theory and&lt;br/&gt;representation theory in three broad areas. First, he will focus on&lt;br/&gt;topics related to cohomology of arithmetic groups and allied areas,&lt;br/&gt;such as geometry of locally symmetric spaces and connections with&lt;br/&gt;arithmetic geometry. Second, he will study multiple Dirichlet series&lt;br/&gt;attached to Weyl groups and affine Weyl groups and their connections&lt;br/&gt;to combinatorics, representation theory, and automorphic forms.&lt;br/&gt;Third, he will investigate the geometry of Kazhdan-Lusztig cells in&lt;br/&gt;Coxeter groups and their connections with combinatorics and&lt;br/&gt;representation theory. As a major writing project, he will continue&lt;br/&gt;to work with Hirzebruch and Zagier on the updating of their book "The&lt;br/&gt;Atiyah-Singer theorem and elementary number theory."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal deals with number theory and representation theory.&lt;br/&gt;Number theory is the study of the properties of the whole numbers, and&lt;br/&gt;is the oldest branch of mathematics. Representation theory is the&lt;br/&gt;systematic study of symmetry, through the development of simple&lt;br/&gt;mathematical objects that encode the fundamental irreducible pieces of&lt;br/&gt;symmetry. A principal aim of the proposal is to explore relationships&lt;br/&gt;between these two subjects in the spirit of the "Langlands&lt;br/&gt;philosophy," which predicts deep connections between number theory and&lt;br/&gt;representation theory. Today the questions and phenomena addressed by&lt;br/&gt;these subjects serve as driving forces in much of contemporary&lt;br/&gt;mathematics research. Moreover, the subjects have contributed many&lt;br/&gt;applications in such diverse areas as codes and data transmission,&lt;br/&gt;chemistry, physics, and theoretical computer science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0801214</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gunnells</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gunnells@math.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
