<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI-Medium: Collaborative Research : Corpus-based Studies of Lexical, Acoustic, And Discourse Entrainment in Spoken Dialogue</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>343768</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tatiana D. Korelsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Participants in human-human conversation often entrain to one another, adopting the&lt;br/&gt;vocabulary and other behaviors of their partners.&lt;br/&gt;Evidence of this has been found from laboratory studies and observations of real life&lt;br/&gt;situations. We are investigating many types of entrainment in two large corpora of&lt;br/&gt;human-human conversations to improve system behavior in Spoken Dialogue Systems&lt;br/&gt;(SDS). We want to discover which types of entrainment occur generally across&lt;br/&gt;speakers and which seem to be speaker-specific, which types of entrainment can be&lt;br/&gt;reliably linked to task success and perceived naturalness, and which types of&lt;br/&gt;entrainment can be automatically modeled in SDS.&lt;br/&gt;Our research has importance for the construction of better SDS.&lt;br/&gt;Currently, research SDS have attempted to entrain users to system vocabularies to&lt;br/&gt;improve speech recognition accuracy: Since users are likely to employ the same&lt;br/&gt;vocabulary in their answers that systems use in their queries, systems have a better&lt;br/&gt;chance of recognizing user input correctly if they can predict word usage. However,&lt;br/&gt;there has been little attempt to create SDS that entrain to user behavior, despite&lt;br/&gt;evidence that human beings rate humans and systems that behave more like them&lt;br/&gt;more highly than those that do not. Our work focuses on determining which types of&lt;br/&gt;system entrainment to users will be most important to users and most feasible for SDS.&lt;br/&gt;Our results will be disseminated through papers and presentations at speech and&lt;br/&gt;language conferences. We will also provide publicly available annotated corpora for&lt;br/&gt;future research by others.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0803159</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ani</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nenkova</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nenkova@seas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
