<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanowire-Based High-Frequency, High-Q Electromechanical Resonators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to develop high-frequency, high-quality factor (Q) nano-electromechanical resonators and integrated resonator/sensor systems. The approach is to build flexural-mode electromechanical resonators using chemically synthesized nanowires, either after growth or through a controlled direct-growth method. The nanowire resonator system offers both GHz operation potential and reduced internal and clamping losses due to its small size, single-crystalline material structure, smooth surfaces and a large aspect ratio.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merits: A systematic approach to improve the quality factor and the resonance frequency will be carried out through carefully designed material studies, device fabrication and analysis. Integration of nanowire resonators with other on-chip components will be explored through selective growth of nanowire bridges. Quantum-limited position measurements will be attempted by coupling a GHz resonator with an electrical transducer. The high-frequency, high-Q system will be suitable for a number of applications including ultra-sensitive mass, force and position detection, and open new frontiers such as mechanical quantum states and entanglement of the mechanical/electrical degrees of freedom. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This program will provide educational and training opportunities for at least one graduate and one undergraduate student at any given year, with an emphasis on recruiting students from underrepresented groups. Knowledge and techniques developed during research will be incorporated into a new, comprehensive undergraduate course and disseminated to the general public through publications, technology transfer, websites and a textbook. Students in inner-city, high-need school districts will also be engaged through a research experience for teaches program, high-school class visits and online exhibits.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0804863</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wluee@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
