<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Mechanically Robust Structural Color System Based on Biomimetic Principles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>293786</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gary Fischman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nature has perfected the use of structured materials that prevent (or enhance) high external reflection and produce intense coloration. The research objective of this award is to develop a mechanically robust color system, based on the structural mechanisms which give butterfly wings and beetle shells such intense color. The research approach combines thin film modeling to design a range of biomimetic structures with laboratory created analogs of single and multilayered thin films. The work will further focus on improving naturally occurring structures by providing structures capable of withstanding the rigors of industrial processing. Deliverables include a catalog of index of refraction raising materials and their effects as thin film composites; a demonstration of the effects of introducing air pockets into the thin films and the tunability of the refractive index; modeling thin structurally colored films; creation and characterization of multilayered biomimetic structures; and finally transition into an industrially relevant form.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this proposed work advances the knowledge of structural coloration and the mechanical properties of such materials, which are typically mechanically weak in nature. This proposal explores the interface between materials science and engineering, optics, and chemistry in both academic and industrial settings and how to transition them from an academic structure to an industrially relevant and utilizable product. The research has potential to be directly utilized in a wide range of industries from paints, fabrics, display technology, personal care and cosemetics and antifouling coatings. This project will impact a wide range of individuals working in the PIs lab, including, high school students, high school teachers, undergraduates and graduate students. Students working on this project gain insight not only into the science behind structural coloration, but into industrial applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0804543</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carlo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>steven.carlo@avon.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Caroline</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schauer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cschauer@coe.drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1633</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1444</Code>
      <Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1633</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
