<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symmetry and Commensurability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99212</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0805908&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Genevieve S. Walsh&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two n-manifolds are commensurable if they have homeomorphic&lt;br/&gt;finite-sheeted covers. This notion is particularly useful for&lt;br/&gt;3-manifolds. For 3-manifolds which admit a geometry,&lt;br/&gt;commensurability respects this geometry. In light of the recent&lt;br/&gt;proof of geometrization for 3-manifolds, classification into&lt;br/&gt;commensurability classes is a refinement of the classification of&lt;br/&gt;3-manifolds by which geometry they admit. This applies to&lt;br/&gt;3-manifolds which have been decomposed along 2-spheres and&lt;br/&gt;2-tori. Questions concerning virtual properties of&lt;br/&gt;$3$-manifolds, such as if a 3-manifold is virtually Haken or&lt;br/&gt;virtually fibered, are also questions about its commensurability&lt;br/&gt;class. Commensurability also respects certain number-theoretic&lt;br/&gt;properties of 3-manifolds. A classification of hyperbolic&lt;br/&gt;3-manifolds up to commensurability would be very useful for the&lt;br/&gt;field. A first step towards understanding commensurability&lt;br/&gt;classes of hyperbolic 3-manifolds is understanding&lt;br/&gt;commensurability classes of hyperbolic knot complements. The PI&lt;br/&gt;proposes to work on the conjecture that there are at most 3&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic knot complements in a given commensurability class,&lt;br/&gt;and to understand how these commensurabilities can&lt;br/&gt;occur. Commensurability is also a useful equivalence relation on&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic surfaces, with the definition that two hyperbolic&lt;br/&gt;2-manifolds are commensurable if they have isometric&lt;br/&gt;finite-sheeted covers. The PI proposes to further develop this&lt;br/&gt;theory, in particular to understand commensurability classes of&lt;br/&gt;surfaces with large symmetry groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3-manifolds are spaces which locally look like a 3-dimensional&lt;br/&gt;ball. In particular, our universe is a 3-manifold and we do not&lt;br/&gt;know which one it is. A deeper understanding of&lt;br/&gt;commensurabilities amongst 3-manifolds would significantly refine&lt;br/&gt;geometrization for 3-manifolds. Knot complements are a naturally&lt;br/&gt;occurring class of 3-manifolds, and thus good candidates for&lt;br/&gt;study. 2-manifolds, or surfaces, are spaces which locally look&lt;br/&gt;like a 2-dimensional disc. Hyperbolic surfaces are the most&lt;br/&gt;common type of surface and are used in an extremely wide variety&lt;br/&gt;of scientific contexts. The study of symmetry and&lt;br/&gt;commensurability is very useful for these surfaces. The PI&lt;br/&gt;regularly speaks on her work to diverse audiences. Any results&lt;br/&gt;from this research will be described in research seminars, posted&lt;br/&gt;on the arXiv, and broadly distributed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0805908</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Genevieve</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walsh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>genevieve.walsh@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tufts University</Name>
      <CityName>Medford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021555807</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6176273417</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>20 Professors Row</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
