<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>123000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carter Kimsey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2008. The fellowship supports a research and training plan entitled "Resolving regulatory networks underlying developmental fate of maize inflorescence meristems" for Andrea L. Eveland. The host institution for this research is Cold Spring Harbor and the sponsoring scientists are Dr. David Jackson and Dr. Doreen Ware. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In maize reproductive growth, the shape of clusters of flowers on a stem (inflorescence morphology) and their branching structures are determined by highly organized stem cell populations in the plant tissues giving rise to flowers, floral meristems. Genetic studies of mutants in meristem determinacy have identified key genes that regulate flower cluster (inflorescence) branching and their basic molecular mechanisms. However, global interactions linking these genes to important metabolic and regulatory pathways have not been resolved. This research utilizes a series of large datasets based on these mutant analyses to construct regulatory networks regulating the developmental fate of maize inflorescence meristems. Datasets will be organized into a framework that can be continuously referenced and updated as additional datasets become available. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Training objectives of this research include techniques in programming, computational genomics skills, and undergraduate mentorship. The broader impacts of this research include the developing an infrastructure for understanding molecular and genetic interactions and answering key biological questions regarding developmental and metabolic processes through bioinformatics. Additionally, the research has agricultural significance as results may shed light on grain yield.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0805655</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eveland</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>08/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Eveland Andrea L</Name>
      <CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326115500</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1398</Code>
      <Text>BIO INFOR POSTDOCT RSCH FELLOW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
