<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Constraining Double Degenerate Mergers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>501260</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Womack</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>By virtue of their use as standard candles, Type Ia supernovae are key tools in our quest to measure cosmological parameters, to probe the nature of dark energy, to understand the origin of matter, and to unravel the final fate of the universe. However, despite their adoption as distance indicators, questions of possible systematic effects remain open. Observations of individual Type Ia supernova explosions, double white dwarf binary systems, and Type Ia supernova rates in galaxies suggest that they may originate from different progenitor systems and may depend on the population of the host galaxy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Here, a comprehensive theoretical analysis will be undertaken that will examine merging white dwarfs as a pathway for producing Type Ia supernova. The hope is to better understand possible systematic effects and thereby improve the fidelity of future cosmological observations. The work is expected to lead to an understanding of the Type Ia supernova features produced from double-degenerate mergers based on first-principles physics that can be tested against current and future observations conducted by instruments such as the Supernovae Ia Progenitor Survey (SPY), Large Synoptic Survey Telescope (LSST) and Joint Dark Energy Mission (JDEM). The analysis includes developing a variety of double white dwarf Type Ia supernova progenitor systems, multi-dimensional simulations of the dynamical merger event with better mass resolution and input physics than previous studies, and statistical tools to generate a set of models that are in the best agreement with the observations of double white dwarf binary systems and double-degenerate Type Ia supernova candidates. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will also impact a variety of other areas including cosmology, numerical methods, stellar evolution, massively parallel simulations, and galaxy evolution. This research will also promote national and international partnerships, specifically the LSST consortium and the JDEM enterprise. The project will serve as trans-disciplinary platform for training young scientific talent through the support of a postdoctoral research fellow and the results will be integrated into large classes for undergraduate non-science majors that are intrinsically diverse. Through writing, teaching and public lectures, the team will also broadly disseminate their results to the public. The codes developed here, including software for stellar evolution, nuclear reaction networks, equations of state, thermal conductivities, deflagrations, detonation, numerical methods and hydrodynamics will continue to be added to and release to the public throughout the research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0806720</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Timmes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fxt44@mac.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Evan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scannapieco</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>evan.scannapieco@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1215</Code>
      <Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1206</Code>
      <Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
