<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:Workshop NYC International Polar Weekend 2008-2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34410</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter T. West</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The New York City Polar Science Weekend Symposia in 2008 and 2009 share the excitement of polar research and the International Polar Year 2007 with a broad public audience. Each weekend event will consist of family-friendly performances and presentations, a lecture series tailored for more adult audiences, and an interactive Polar Fair of researchers working with visitors to understand research questions in the polar regions. This program design deliberately allows and encourages people to learn in several different ways: listening and viewing as well as interaction with scientists through one-on-one question and answer, demonstrations, and personal participation. The symposia convey the critical role of the poles in global climate and the dramatic changes that are already underway and they promote an understanding of what can be done to mitigate and adapt to global warming and an appreciation for careers in science and education. The main goal of this project is to enhance public understanding of science through a focus on the polar regions. As many as 5,000 people, families, individuals and school groups, are anticipated to participate during each two-day experience. At least 30% of museum visitors are members of under-served communities. These symposia will reach a diverse population, of visitors and presenters and through partnering with New York's Urban Advantage program for middle schools and New Visions for high schools, to serve economically, linguistically, and culturally diverse families. This project will be integrated with other AMNH programming and, through evaluation, examine how the event influences visitors and presenters. While the main goal is engaging the public in understanding and appreciating polar environments and culture, by involving ca. 50 local scientists and other scholars in developing general presentations, activities and resources, we will also build the capacity of these academics to become active and articulate spokespeople throughout the duration of the IPY and beyond. Performers and presenters in 2008 and 2009 will represent a wide variety of institutions including the American Museum of Natural History, Barnard College, Columbia University, Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, the Explorers Club, Wings World Quest, New York Times, New York University, NASA, the Central Park Zoo, Anne Aghion Films, the Cold Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory in New Hampshire, the Inuit throat singers from Canada and other international partners.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0806933</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roberto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borrero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rborrero@amnh.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elaine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Charnov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>charnov@amnh.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/15/2008</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Museum Natural History</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100245192</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2127695975</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Central Park West at 79th St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0311000</Code>
      <Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5208</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH AND EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5295</Code>
      <Text>IPY (GENERAL)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
