<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Frames as codes and classifiers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>112257</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Bodmann&lt;br/&gt;0807399&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The mathematical description of redundant linear&lt;br/&gt;representations of analog signals is called frame theory, and it&lt;br/&gt;is central to open problems in many fields of applied mathematics&lt;br/&gt;such as approximation theory and numerical as well as statistical&lt;br/&gt;analysis. In short, a frame is an (over)complete set of vectors&lt;br/&gt;that gives stable expansions. Previous works have measured the&lt;br/&gt;error correction capabilities of frames with means derived from&lt;br/&gt;geometric or functional analytic formulations. However, for&lt;br/&gt;purposes of signal communication and statistical analysis,&lt;br/&gt;information theory should provide the guiding principles for&lt;br/&gt;optimal design. The goal of the project is to close this gap by&lt;br/&gt;combining frame and information theory. Applying&lt;br/&gt;information-theoretic optimality criteria to frame design is&lt;br/&gt;expected to have a significant impact on all tasks that involve&lt;br/&gt;analog signals being transmitted or interpreted in the presence&lt;br/&gt;of noise. The investigator seeks to characterize and construct&lt;br/&gt;linear signal encoding and decoding maps for two specific areas&lt;br/&gt;of applications: Find frames with associated encoding and&lt;br/&gt;decoding maps that achieve the information-theoretic optimum for&lt;br/&gt;(1) error correction of digital streaming media and (2)&lt;br/&gt;classification of signals in noisy microscopy images. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Digital signal transmissions have revolutionized our daily&lt;br/&gt;lives, from cellular phones and Voice-over-Internet-Protocol&lt;br/&gt;telephony to high-definition television and other streaming&lt;br/&gt;media. The use of digitization helps suppress distortions&lt;br/&gt;typical for analog devices and allows seemingly faultless&lt;br/&gt;communication by incorporating redundancy, that is, repetetive&lt;br/&gt;information. However, at times the digital nature of error&lt;br/&gt;suppression leads to artifacts that do not resemble the graceful&lt;br/&gt;degradation we recall from analog transmissions. The reason for&lt;br/&gt;this deficiency is that the general-purpose digital communication&lt;br/&gt;protocols are not well-adapted to the properties of the encoded&lt;br/&gt;analog signal. The investigator aims to restore the possibility&lt;br/&gt;of graceful degradation to streaming media sent across the&lt;br/&gt;internet, or to wireless communications in unreliable&lt;br/&gt;environments. The optimal design of analog-digital encoding has&lt;br/&gt;similar implications for the decoding of analog signals, such as&lt;br/&gt;the extraction of information from microscopy images in biology. &lt;br/&gt;The reliable monitoring and classification of cell constituents&lt;br/&gt;in microscopy images is essential for measuring physiologic&lt;br/&gt;responses in cells (such as the stages in the cell cycle) and for&lt;br/&gt;detecting anomalous behavior that occurs as a result of disease. &lt;br/&gt;Classifying cell behavior is relevant for the evaluation of drugs&lt;br/&gt;with high-throughput assays, including the development of&lt;br/&gt;cancer-cell growth inhibitors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0807399</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bernhard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bodmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bgb@math.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
