<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Properties of Repeating Sequence Copolymers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>386000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will focus on the synthesis and characterization of an extended family of repeating sequence copolymers that include a blue-light emitting oligofluorene component. Although Nature has established the power of sequence in creating a high diversity in properties with a limited monomer pool, sequence remains underexploited in synthetic copolymers. A novel diversity oriented synthesis strategy will make possible the efficient creation of a set of polymers appropriate for systematic studies. By correlating the properties of these repeating sequence copolymers prepared with sequence and block dispersity in this system, a more general understanding of the relationship of properties to sequence will be derived. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor Tara Y. Meyer of the Department of Chemistry at the University of Pittsburgh. Professor Meyer's research efforts revolve around the development of synthetic approaches to highly sequenced polymers and the correlation of properties with sequence. In addition to the positive impact on the materials industry, the unique light-emitting properties of the proposed polymers should contribute to the design of new optoelectronic technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0809289</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tmeyer@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/10/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
