<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Condensed-Phase Dynamics Resolved by Multidimensional Population Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>432400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Berg will undertake research in condensed matter chemistry, namely fast time-scale dynamics in supercooled and high viscosity liquids. Berg and his group will continue to develop multidimensional spectroscopic methods to analyze condensed-phase dynamics in complex systems. In the Multiple Population Period Transient Spectrocopies (MUPPETS) technique developed in the PI's laboratory, experiments using multiple kinetic decay periods can disentangle heterogeneous from homogeneous origins of nonexponential kinetics. The technique will be applied to several problems, including studies of DNA charge transfer; conjugated polymer aggregates; local viscosity in microstructured systems such as micelles, bilayers, and vesicles; and supercooled liquids.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project deals with important issues in the behavior of fluids, such as the relationship between the dynamics of single molecules and that of the collective behavior of fluids. Existing theories have been partially successful in accounting for the dynamical properties of fluids, and the present work addresses fundamental issues that have in the past been treated only slightly. New experimental techniques together with the associated theory will be developed. The results from this project are likely to impact understanding in many areas of condensed phase dynamics. This research will be conducted with the aid of graduate and undergraduate students and postdoctoral research associates, who will gain valuable experience through their involvement in contemporary forefront research in physical chemistry. These experiences will of great advantage in their further studies or employment in industry, government laboratories, or academia.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0809306</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>berg@sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1960</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURE AND REACTIVITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
