<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Understanding the Factors that Govern Invasion (and coexistence), a Case Study with an Anomalous Asian Ant.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8484</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniel J. Mook</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>OISE-0809267 (Dunn, North Carolina State University)&lt;br/&gt;"Understanding Factors that Govern Invasion (and coexistence): A Case Study with an Anomalous Asian Ant"&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a planning visit to Okayama, Japan by the PI and two graduate students to build a collaborative research program with Professor Kenji Matsuura?s social insect working group. The collaboration focuses on understanding the factors that facilitate invasion of species and differences in life history of invasive species in their native and introduced ranges, with particular focus on Pachycondyla chinensis. P. chinensis was introduced into the eastern U.S. from East Asia as early as 1903. While long unnoticed, the species has expanded its range and can now be found from Florida to New York, showing signs in some areas of dominating local ant assemblages. In contrast to most invasive ant species, P chinensis does not have tropical origins. Its native and invaded habitats are similar in species richness and share many genera. Where invasive, it can inhabit both disturbed and undisturbed habitats. Thus, pachychondyla chinensis is an interesting exception to ?the rules? for invasive ants and offers a novel opportunity to understand biological invasions by ants. During the planning visit, scheduled for summer 2008, the team will visit potential field locations around Okayama, compare existing results, and design a series of experiments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0809267</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rrdunn@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
      <CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
