<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III-COR-Small: Beyond Keyword Search: Enabling Diverse Structured Query Paradigms over Text Databases</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>448976</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The text available on the Web and beyond embeds unprecedented volumes&lt;br/&gt;of valuable structured data, "hidden" in natural language. For&lt;br/&gt;example, a news article might discuss an outbreak of an infectious&lt;br/&gt;disease, reporting the name of the disease, the number of people&lt;br/&gt;affected, and the geographical regions involved. Keyword search, the&lt;br/&gt;prevalent query paradigm for text, is often insufficiently expressive&lt;br/&gt;for complex information needs that require structured data embedded in&lt;br/&gt;text. For such needs, users (e.g., an epidemiologist compiling&lt;br/&gt;statistics, as reported in the media, on recent foodborne disease&lt;br/&gt;outbreaks in a remote country) are forced to embark in labor-intensive&lt;br/&gt;cycles of keyword-based document retrieval and manual document&lt;br/&gt;filtering, until they locate the appropriate (structured) information.&lt;br/&gt;To move beyond keyword search, this project exploits information&lt;br/&gt;extraction technology, which identifies structured data in text, to&lt;br/&gt;enable structured querying. To capture diverse user information needs&lt;br/&gt;and depart from a "one-size-fits-all" querying approach, which is&lt;br/&gt;inappropriate for this extraction-based scenario, this project&lt;br/&gt;explores a wealth of structured query paradigms: sometimes users&lt;br/&gt;(e.g., a high-school student in need of some quick examples and&lt;br/&gt;statistics for a report on recent salmonella outbreaks in developing&lt;br/&gt;countries) are after a few exploratory results, which should be&lt;br/&gt;returned fast; some other times, users (e.g., the above epidemiologist&lt;br/&gt;investigating foodborne diseases) are after comprehensive results, for&lt;br/&gt;which waiting a longer time is acceptable. The project develops&lt;br/&gt;specialized cost-based query optimizers for each query paradigm,&lt;br/&gt;accounting for the efficiency and, critically, the result quality of&lt;br/&gt;the query execution plans. The technology produced will assist a vast&lt;br/&gt;range of users and information needs, by enabling efficient, diverse&lt;br/&gt;interactions with text databases -- for sophisticated searching and&lt;br/&gt;data mining -- that are cumbersome or impossible with today's&lt;br/&gt;technology. The research and educational components of the project&lt;br/&gt;will rely on -- and encourage -- a tight integration of three&lt;br/&gt;complementary Computer Science disciplines, namely, natural language&lt;br/&gt;processing, information retrieval, and databases. The project will&lt;br/&gt;also provide data sets and source code, for experimentation and&lt;br/&gt;evaluation, to the community at large over the Web (http://extraction.cs.columbia.edu/).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0811038</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gravano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gravano@cs.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
