<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STEM Institute at Shelton State Community College</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>453130</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Caesar R. Jackson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The C.A. Fredd Campus of Shelton State Community College, founded in 1963, is a small Historically Black College with a strong presence in West Alabama. This HBCU-UP program is designed as a result of a thorough needs assessment that was supported through the use of an HBCU-UP planning grant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed HBCU-UP project will establish a STEM institute on the C.A. Fredd campus of Shelton State Community College, which has an overall aim of strengthening current STEM programs. Six components comprise the Institute: i) high school component; ii) undergraduate student activities; iii) infusion of technology; iv) curricular enhancement; v) faculty development activities and vi) transition to four year college, and subsequently to graduate school. The implementation project is a continuum that begins with the high school component, strengthens the 2-year STEM curriculum at the college, and then encourage and facilitate entrance into 4-year STEM programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Activities that will be a part of the STEM Institute include: a six week, intensive High School Summer Institute for rising seniors, and incoming college freshmen; professional development for high school STEM teachers; well defined faculty-student mentoring supported by professional development activities for faculty; implementation of undergraduate student research and summer internships; technology enhancement in STEM courses; and course restructuring aimed at gatekeeper courses. The transition to four year institutions will be encouraged and enhanced by student participation in research with faculty from four year colleges and Ph.D. granting institutions. This is further facilitated by a statewide transfer articulation agreement within Alabama.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This comprehensive project is aimed at increasing the number of C.A. Fredd campus students successfully completing introductory and advanced DTEM courses, increase academic performance in these courses; increase the number of students participating in research and internship activities, and increase the number of students gaining admission to 4-year STEM degree programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0811147</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rose</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krose@sheltonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Range</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rrange@sheltonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Channing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Howington</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chowington@sheltonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Camille</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cochrane</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccochrane@sheltonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Shelton State Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354054017</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053912472</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9500 Old Greensboro Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
