<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ACS Symposium entitled "NMR Spectroscopy of Polymers: Solutions, Melts, and Solid State," April 6-10, 2008, New Orleans, LA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070012</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The ACS Division of Polymer Chemistry is sponsoring a five-day symposium entitled "NMR Spectroscopy of Polymers: Solutions, Melts and Solid State" consisting of nine oral sessions (with more than 50 speakers) and a poster session that will be held as part of the Division of Chemistry's technical program at the Spring 2008, National ACS Meeting to be held in New Orleans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Once objective of the symposium is to bring together the leading scientists from around the world to exchange thoughts and make presentations of their recent work in the utilization of NMR spectroscopy to characterize both synthetic and naturally occurring polymers. Foreign speakers will use this trip as part of a seminar tour at U.S. universities. We anticipate that this meeting will have an attendance of approximately 150.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A second objective of the symposium is the education and development of graduate students, post-doctoral associates, and young faculty. To this end, we have scheduled tutorial lectures as the first session of the symposium and more general lectures to start each day that are intended, in part, to be pedagogical. Expenses will be associated with under writing graduate students, post-doctoral associates and younger faculty attendance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0811141</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rabolt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rabolt@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>English</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alan.d.english@usa.dupont.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
