<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAR-PF: Biogeochemistry of Nitrogen Associated with Discharge of Coal Bed Methane Production Water: Transport and Fate in Western Watersheds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>160000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Rebecca Barnes is awarded an NSF Earth Science Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a program of research and education at the United States Geological Survey, Boulder. Dr. Barnes will examine the effects of coal bed methane (CBM) extraction in the chemistry of streams in the Powder River Basin, Wyoming. The research goals will be accomplished by examining the changes in nitrogen budgets and behavior in the semi-arid watershed. The investigation will be based on intensive sampling of stream waters, and field and laboratory experiments to determine changes in the nitrification rates. Chemical analyses of water will include ammonium concentrations and nitrogen and oxygen isotopes. These results will contribute to better understanding of the chemical effects of coal bed methane extraction on stream waters. The information can be used to inform decisions as new CBM extraction areas begin production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, Dr. Barnes will collaborate with faculty from the University of Colorado - Boulder, Fort Lewis College and the Mountain Studies Institute in developing field based classes for members of the San Juan Mountains community to foster watershed literacy. This community was selected because there is potential for CBM extraction in the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0814457</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barnes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/28/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Barnes Rebecca T</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803030000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
