<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>University of Missouri CELDi Research Site</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375032</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence A. Hornak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Title: I/UCRC: CELDi at MU&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Missouri-Columbia&lt;br/&gt;Abstract Date: 03/30/2008&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award establishes University of Missouri-Columbia (MU) as a research site of the Industry/University Collaborative Research Center (I/UCRC) for the Center for Engineering Logistics and Distribution (CELDi). Other sites of this collaborative research center include the University of Arkansas (lead), Oklahoma State University, Lehigh University, Clemson University, University of Oklahoma, University of Louisville, Texas Tech University and Virginia Tech. The mission of this center is to provide integrated solutions to logistics problems through modeling, analysis, and intelligent systems technologies. MU will be a strong partner of CELDi and should be able to immediately contribute to the logistics systems analysis and design, supply chain modeling, and material flow design and improvement. MU has a team of researchers who are capable of providing immediate assistance in research related to the integration of logistics components in large, complex inter/multi-modal systems. CELDi will benefit from the expanded research expertise and involvement of top Fortune 500 companies that MU will bring to the table. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;University of Missouri-Columbia will make significant contributions to the mission of CELDi. The quality and quantity of research conducted will expand the impact of CELDi in technical, educational and outreach activities. The research team at MU is multidisciplinary with faculty participating from industrial engineering, systems engineering and transportation engineering perspectives as well as management logistics and agricultural economics. MU has a clear plan to involve students in its research, and the nature of the proposal ensures that the proposed research will have significant impact on industrial practice through close collaboration with industrial partners. Both the undergraduate and graduate education at MU will be positively impacted by MU?s participation in CELDi.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0815195</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Noble</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>noblej@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wooseung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jangw@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0400000</Code>
      <Name>Industry University - Co-op</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
