<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sterol Biosynthesis in the Marine Dinoflagellate, Karenia brevis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>156246</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project will examine sterol biosynthesis in Karenia brevis, a unicellular, eukaryotic alga of great environmental and economic importance that forms yearly harmful blooms in the Gulf of Mexico. The biosynthesis of sterols, ringed lipids thought to contribute to membrane integrity, has been elucidated in great detail in yeast and some plants, but not in dinoflagellates. Preliminary data suggest a more plant-like pathway for K. brevis rather than the yeast-like pathway that has been hypothesized to date in other dinoflagellates. The objective of this project is therefore to elucidate important biochemical steps in the biosynthesis of brevesterol and gymnodinosterol, the primary sterols of K. brevis, by determining structures of selected intermediates that accumulate during exposure to particular fungicides. This project will be the first to elucidate specific biosynthetic steps in the production of K. brevis sterols. This is of particular importance because, despite the significant historical attention given to dinoflagellate sterols as environmental biomarkers for this class of algae, few have turned their attention to how these molecules are produced. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Undergraduate students will actively participate in the laboratory studies at Middle Tennessee State University (MTSU). The chance for undergraduate students to participate in such a project will both train the students and hopefully excite them, thereby helping to propel them into strong Ph.D. programs at other institutions. This training and motivation of students in areas of basic scientific research is an important component of the activities. The forecasted shortfalls in young scientists in the United States is of concern to all, and including students in basic research at earlier points in their careers has been recommended as a means of encouraging more students to pursue careers in science. The goal is therefore to produce valuable information on a very economically and environmentally important marine alga, while at the same time enticing students into this exciting area of biochemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0816787</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leblond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jeff.Leblond@mtsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Middle Tennessee State University</Name>
      <CityName>Murfreesboro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>371320001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6154947848</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1301 E. Main</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
