<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Role of a Host ion Pump in RNA Virus Recombination</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>612000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael L. Mishkind</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Host - virus interactions are greatly affected by the exceptionally rapid rate of virus evolution. Evolution of viruses is frequently driven by genetic recombination, a process that allows viruses to overcome immunity, to infect new host species and change disease symptoms in all types of living organisms. Virus recombination is also a major factor in emergence of new viruses, which is a continuing threat to our society. &lt;br/&gt;Therefore, studies on the effect of the host on the viral recombination process are critical to unravel virus evolution, which is currently poorly understood. This project focuses on a recently discovered key host factor affecting RNA recombination in Tomato bushy stunt virus. The host factor is Pmr1p Ca2+/Mn2+ ion-pump, which is a ubiquitous and conserved protein playing critical roles in human genetic diseases, such as Hailey-Hailey Disease and Darier Disease. In order to characterize the role of Pmr1p in viral RNA recombination, the investigator will use advanced genetics tools available for plant and yeast, which is a model host, in combination with biochemical approaches. This research is expected to lead to important new discoveries in viral recombination and contribute key knowledge to the role of the host in virus evolution and virus-host interactions.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact: The research holds promise of benefiting society by leading to groundbreaking results in the area of virus recombination/evolution, host-virus interaction and the emergence of new viruses. The major limitation of current antiviral methods is that they could quickly become ineffective due to rapid virus evolution. Better understanding of viral RNA recombination will have tremendous impact on our abilities to develop better, longer lasting antiviral strategies. Education component: High school and undergraduate students will actively participate in research in the investigator's laboratory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0817790</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nagy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pdnagy2@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
