<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: FASEB-2008 Conference on Mechanisms in Plant Development, August 10-14, 2008 in Saxtons River, VT</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas P. Jack</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Studies of how plants grow and develop are vital for our ability to continue improving agricultural productivity and efficiency while minimizing negative environmental impacts. Investigators around the world are working to understand mechanisms of plant development using a variety of experimental systems and techniques. It is of utmost importance for investigators in this diverse and rapidly moving field to have a forum for discussion of recent work in which common principles and new themes can emerge, and in which key, unanswered questions can be identified. This proposal is for partial funding for a FASEB Summer Research Conference entitled "Mechanisms in Plant Development" to be held August 10-14th, 2008 in Saxtons River, VT (organized by Neelima Sinha and Cris Kuhlemeier). This conference, held every other year for the past twenty years, has a small size (~100 participants) and will facilitate the distillation of new themes and principles emerging from recent work in the plant development field, as well as fostering new acquaintances and collaborations between participants with shared interests. Participants will include principal investigators, postdocs, and Ph.D. students, 40-50% of whom are expected to be female based on the recent history of this meeting. The conference program includes seven sessions. For each session, speakers were chosen based on the high quality and interest value of their ongoing research, and on our knowledge of their ability to give a clear and engaging presentation. In addition, speaker choices were made to create a balance between male and female speakers, between junior, intermediate and senior investigators. Moreover, several speakers were invited who employ emerging technologies and approaches in their research. Daily poster sessions and 10-12 short talks will provide opportunities for all participants to present their work to an international audience. There will be ample time for informal discussions among participants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0818767</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neelima</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sinha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nrsinha@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1118</Code>
      <Text>PLANT FUNGAL &amp; MICROB DEV MECH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
