<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Consortium at Seventh International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multi-Agent Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas H. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports US student researchers to travel to the Doctoral Consortium and the premier international conference on autonomous agents and multiagent systems. The Seventh International Joint Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS 2008) will be held in Estoril, Portugal between May 12 and May 16, 2008. The conference provides these students with a platform to present their research results and allows them to participate in valuable discussions that will likely shape the future of this critically important field. The technical program is complemented with an array of workshops, tutorials and other events, as it has in previous years. The wide variety and significance of the topics typically presented at AAMAS, in both the technical program and the workshop program, provides a great opportunity for students to share, exchange and learn from each others successes and failures. A Doctoral Mentoring Program is available for Ph.D. students in advanced stages of their research. This program will provide an opportunity for students to interact closely with established researchers, to receive feedback on their work and to get advice on managing their careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0818761</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scerri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pscerri@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
