<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Chromosome evolution: Models and tests</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>789998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Scheiner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Genome research has recently revealed that chromosomes often evolve at astounding rates. The evolutionary forces responsible for these changes are very poorly understood. This research will study those forces using a combination of mathematical models and statistical analyses. There are three specific research themes: (1) models to explain rapid evolutionary changes in which a pair of chromosomes determines sex (seen for example in salmon and tilapia), (2) models to explain how chromosome number and gene arrangement change over evolutionary time, and (3) statistical analyses of data on a new gene arrangement in Drosophila that will test the models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will have five kinds of impact beyond its contributions to basic science. First, it will illuminate history of the human genome, which has experienced substantial chromosomal evolution. Second, it will provide key insights regarding how disease vectors (notably the mosquitoes that transmit malaria) have adapted to humans and thus become more virulent. Third, the project will develop and distribute computer software useful for a wide range of genetic analyses. Fourth, the project will train young scientists at the undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral levels and will give them opportunities to work with collaborators abroad. Fifth, the research will develop international partnerships between laboratories in the US, the UK, Australia, Switzerland, and France.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0819901</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kirkpatrick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kirkp@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
