<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Role of Subcortical Systems in Hippocampal Memory Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>449135</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The ultimate goal of this project is to understand mechanisms responsible for memory processing in the brain. Although several factors contribute to the formation of memories, it is well recognized that the encoding of information in the brain depends on two critical processes: attention and meaning. In effect, events are best remembered when they are attended to and when they are meaningful. In mammals, it is further generally acknowledged that information is initially stored in the hippocampus of the brain. In previous studies using the rat model, the investigator identified a system of connections in the brain that generate the so called theta rhythm of the hippocampus, which appears to serve a direct role in the encoding of significant (or meaningful) information in the hippocampus. Specifically, the hippocampus receives information from various regions of the cortex, and theta may serve to amplify information bearing signals from the cortex, leading to their storage in the hippocampus. In a similar manner, another system of inputs to the hippocampus from the midline thalamus has been identified that appears to code for the dimension of attention to environmental events. This project will, in part, examine the effects of selective activation (or inactivation) of inputs to the hippocampus that are responsible for attention and meaning in memory processing in this structure. More specifically, the manner and degree to which these manipulations will enhance (or impede) learning and memory in rats will be examined. These studies should significantly contribute to an understanding of mechanisms of memory formation in the brain. The researcher engages undergraduate and graduate students in his research projects and continues to disseminate his experimental findings in various professional and lay forums.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0820639</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vertes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vertes@ccs.fau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Atlantic University</Name>
      <CityName>BOCA RATON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>334316424</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5612970777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>777 GLADES RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7714</Code>
      <Text>MODULATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1096</Code>
      <Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
