<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Scalable Knowledge-based Middleware for Networked and Mobile Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>314282</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sol J. Greenspan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SRS-0820208/0819845&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TITLE: Scalable Knowledge-based Middleware For Networked And Mobile Systems&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Boon Thau Loo (University of Pennsylvania)&lt;br/&gt;Co-PI: William C. Regli (Drexel University)&lt;br/&gt;Senior Personnel: Joseph B. Kopena (Drexel University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research investigates scalable, knowledge-based middleware supporting content-based addressing and routing in mobile, networked systems. It incorporates and integrates two aspects: Ontological reasoning about system resources and declarative networking within routing components. At the application layer is OntoNet, a knowledge-based framework for representing and reasoning on system elements. Declarative, formal techniques provide service discovery and composition, content-based messaging, and distributed querying using OWL-Net, a subset of the OWL description logic. This work includes development of propagation strategies that are efficient and robust in mobile, networked environments. Network layer support is provided by declarative networks, a rule-based framework for compact, high-level protocol specifications. Declarative networking enables rapid prototyping and verification as well as online adaptation and meta-reasoning. This research will include extension of declarative networking to more readily support highly dynamic mobile wireless systems. The intellectual merit of this proposal is development of a unified, declarative framework for distributed organization of knowledge and information in real-world systems. It draws from many areas such as the Semantic Web, databases, and networking. Potential broader impacts are richer and more extensible platforms for real-world networks usable in emergency response, logistics, infrastructure monitoring, and ubiquitous computing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0820208</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Boon Thau</FirstName>
      <LastName>Loo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>boonloo@cis.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7724</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE FOR REAL-WORLD SYSTMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7944</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
