<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Networking Equipment to Establish a High-Performance Computing and High-Bandwidth Research Network at an HBCU</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>365573</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>robert pennington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposal requests networking infrastructure to establish a high-performance computing, high-bandwidth, robust, and intelligently managed converged data research network; to be utilized as a shared resource in the College of Mathematics, Natural Sciences, and Technology (CMNST) at Delaware State University (DSU), a Historically Black University (HBCU). The network infrastructure will support and enhance the research, research training and education activities and capabilities in the Departments of Applied Mathematics and Theoretical Physics, Biological Sciences, Chemistry, Computer and Information Sciences, Mathematics and Physics and Pre-Engineering.The requested infrastructure will support research, research-training, and education at an HBCU where the vast majority of students are from underrepresented groups. It will contribute to the Nation?s global competitiveness by providing cyberinfrastructure at an HBCU that will be utilized to educate and prepare underrepresented groups for the 21st century scientific, engineering, and technical workforce. In addition, it would close the digital divide at this institution and provide the advanced networking infrastructure necessary to fulfill the CMNST and University?s research and educational mission well into the 21st century. Establishing a robust advanced high-speed and high-bandwidth networking infrastructure would give the CMNST the capability to establish more meaningful research collaboration especially with colleagues at larger research institutions, and facilitate access to geographically distributed computing resources, data repositories and digital libraries. It will enable high-quality computational research, video conferencing, the ability to move large data sets and work remotely. In addition, it will give us the capability to make our resources available to others via the network and allow the CMNST to more effectively recruit and maintain faculty and students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0821129</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Al-Sameen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>akhan@desu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Delaware State University</Name>
      <CityName>Dover</CityName>
      <ZipCode>199012277</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028576001</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 N. Dupont Highway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7684</Code>
      <Text>STRATEGIC TECHNOLOGIES FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7684</Code>
      <Text>STRATEGIC TECHNOLOGIES FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
