<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BRIGE: Building the Foundation for Nanoscale Interface Design</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174937</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to develop and validate a physically representative molecular model of thin film lubrication. Key to the success of the project is direct, quantitative comparison of model predictions to experimental data obtained through collaboration with experts in the field. The simulation will take advantage of advanced, accelerated molecular dynamics techniques to match the operating conditions and materials properties of the corresponding experiments. The validation will be performed by comparing the predicted and observed relationships between speed, film thickness, and friction. The experimentally validated model will be used to gain new insight into the behavior of thin film lubrication and how this behavior is influenced by molecular-scale events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this project will provide a knowledge base for rational design of thin film lubricated interfaces. Such interfaces are becoming extremely common as applications continue to get smaller and faster. Small-scale components have correspondingly smaller lubricated interfaces where the lubrication phenomena are still not well understood. The current project will directly address this need thereby building the foundation for development of numerical design tools for thin film lubricated interfaces. The technical objective of the project is integrally related to its outreach goal, increasing participation of women in mechanical engineering by redefining the external perception of field. The cutting-edge, molecular-scale simulation technology that will be employed to develop a practical design tool is representative of a new concept of mechanical engineering, and supports improved participation of women by increasing their awareness of the exciting role this field is playing in design and development of emerging nanoscale technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0821875</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ashlie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amartini@ucmerced.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7741</Code>
      <Text>BROAD PARTIC IN ENG (BRIGE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
