<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Information Technology Research (ITR): Sensitive Information in a Wired World</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>161872</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Weber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Increasing use of computers and networks in business, government,&lt;br/&gt;recreation, and almost all aspects of daily life has led to a&lt;br/&gt;proliferation of sensitive data (i.e., data that, if used improperly,&lt;br/&gt;can harm data subjects or other relevant parties), and concern about&lt;br/&gt;the ownership, control, privacy, and accuracy of these data has become&lt;br/&gt;a top priority. Despite significant technical accomplishments &lt;br/&gt;in relevant research fields (e.g., cryptology and security, database&lt;br/&gt;systems, and data mining), there is no comprehensive, end-to-end&lt;br/&gt;technological infrastructure for handling sensitive data over &lt;br/&gt;the entire course of their lifetime, nor is there even widespread social&lt;br/&gt;agreement about the rights and responsibilities of major stakeholders&lt;br/&gt;in our data-intensive, networked world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is a multi-institutional, multi-disciplinary, multi-modal&lt;br/&gt;project that looks comprehensively at sensitive data in a networked&lt;br/&gt;world. There are two main academic centers of activity (Yale and&lt;br/&gt;Stanford), three smaller-scale academic participants (Stevens&lt;br/&gt;Institute of Technology, NYU, and the University of New Mexico), and&lt;br/&gt;substantial participation by non-academic partners, including&lt;br/&gt;technology companies, (IBM, HP, and Microsoft), representatives of&lt;br/&gt;user communities (Citigroup, NIH, Yale Center for Medical Informatics,&lt;br/&gt;the Census Bureau, and the Secret Service), and DC-based policy&lt;br/&gt;organizations (The Center for Democracy and Technology and The&lt;br/&gt;Electronic Privacy Information Center).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A major technical theme of the project is privacy-preserving data&lt;br/&gt;mining, and, more generally, techniques for meeting the potentially&lt;br/&gt;conflicting goals of respecting individual rights and allowing law&lt;br/&gt;enforcement and other legitimate organizations to collect and mine&lt;br/&gt;massive data sets. Other technical agenda items include (1)&lt;br/&gt;accessibility and reliability of distributed data (2) operating on&lt;br/&gt;encrypted databases, (3) remote control of data, (4) repelling hostile&lt;br/&gt;data, and (5) auditability of data-management systems. Because these&lt;br/&gt;technical goals are affected by lack of agreement about the meanings&lt;br/&gt;of basic terms, most notably "privacy," a major goal of the project is&lt;br/&gt;the development of a conceptual framework for the study of rights,&lt;br/&gt;responsibilities, and public policies focused on sensitive-data&lt;br/&gt;handling. This part of the project incorporates the notion of&lt;br/&gt;"contextual integrity," which considers both the context and the&lt;br/&gt;content of data sets in assessing sensitivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Projected outcomes of the project include a next generation of&lt;br/&gt;technology for handling sensitive information that is qualitatively&lt;br/&gt;better than the current generation's and an effective conceptual&lt;br/&gt;framework for policy making and philosophical inquiry into the rights&lt;br/&gt;and responsibilities of data subjects, data owners, and data users.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0822269</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wright</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rebecca.wright@rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1688</Code>
      <Text>ITR LARGE GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7371</Code>
      <Text>CYBER TRUST</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1656</Code>
      <Text>LARGE SCALE NETWORKING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
