<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fiber optic surface enhanced Raman sensor for high sensitivity and automatic molecule identification</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to develop and demonstrate a novel fiber sensor based on surface enhanced Raman scattering (SERS) using metal nanostructures for chemical, biological, and environmental detection. The approach is to integrate 1) novel nanoparticle substrates that provide the high sensitivity and consistency, molecular specificity, and applicability to a wide range of compounds; 2) a unique hollow core optical fiber probe with double SERS substrate structure that provides the compactness, reliability, low cost, and ease of sampling; and 3) an innovative matched spectral filter set that provides automatic preliminary molecule identification.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is to eliminate some of the existing road blocks for the practical applications of current SERS sensors. The novel sensor developed is a transformative technology since its unique capabilities will help revolutionize the way chemical and biological detection is conducted, with potential single molecule detection capability. This in turn will impact many aspects of human lives, ranging from medicine and national security to food safety and to chemical and environmental industries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are to maintain the competitive edge of the US through the multidisciplinary education and training of students in the fast growing fields of nanoscience and nanotechnology. Promotion of diversity is focused on the encouragement and recruitment of women in science and engineering, with the PI as a role model. Outreach to local and Bay Area K-12 schools will involve high school students to participate in the research and inspire children to be future scientists and engineers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0823921</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Claire</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>claire@ee.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhang@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
