<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Australia Dissertation Enhancement: Cytonuclear Interactions in a Hybrid Parthenogenetic Gecko (Heteronotia binoei)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Clive Woods</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0824991&lt;br/&gt;Moritz&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: U.S.-Australia Dissertation Enhancement: Cytonuclear Interactions in a Hybrid Parthenogenetic Gecko (Heteronotia binoei)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a doctoral dissertation enhancement project between Dr. Craig Moritz and his student Matthew Fujita in the Museum of Vertebrate Zoology at the University of California, Berkeley and Dr. Michael Kearney in the Zoology Department at the University of Melbourne in Australia. Parthenogenetic organisms, which reproduce clonally without sex, are often hybrids with mismatched mitochondrial and nuclear genomes. This perpetual cytonuclear mismatch can have important phenotypic consequences which may alter our view of the paradox of sex. Compared to sexual forms, parthenogenetic geckos of the Heteronotia binoei complex exhibit altered physiological performance and developmental stability, phenotypic traits potentially associated with cytonuclear interactions in the electron transport chain of aerobic respiration. The researchers will investigate disrupted epistatic interactions in the coevolved cytonuclear complexes in parthenogenetic Heteronotia that may have resulted from their hybrid origin and/or subsequent genetic changes. Variation in cytochrome c oxidase activity among four clonal lineages of Heteronotia will be used to examine the interactions of two distinct mitochondrial lineages in different nuclear backgrounds. The data will contribute to an international collaboration integrating genomics, biochemical assays, and physiological data to understand the origin, evolution and phenotypic consequences of hybrid parthenogenesis in Heteronotia binoei, with broader implications on identifying genomic processes in allopolyploid organisms and understanding and resolving the paradox of sex. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is sufficient overlap of interests between the University of California and the University of Melbourne to indicate that they can successfully pursue the activities proposed and that the interaction will benefit both sides. Results from this research are relevant to genome evolution, diversification, speciation (genomic incompatibilities), phenotypic variation (physiology), the evolution and maintenance of sex and the identification of genomic processes in allopolyploid organisms. This research will provide the US graduate student an excellent opportunity to receive a global research experience. It is anticipated that he will maintain contacts and collaborations with the Australian researchers and students throughout his career</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0824991</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moritz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>craigm@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fujita</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkfujita@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
