<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BRIGE: Understanding Engineering Students through the Lens of Identity Theory - Implications for Recruitment and Retention of Underrepresented Students</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>208643</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard N. Smith</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This BRIGE project addresses the widespread and pervasive problems of maintaining global competitiveness by increasing the number of engineering graduates, improving the representation of women and minorities in engineering, and understanding how to improve recruitment and retention of engineering students. Employing identity theory provides a unique perspective and a much needed understanding of our students. The goal of this research is to employ a mixed methods approach by collecting quantitative and&lt;br/&gt;qualitative data to better understand the multiple identities of our students and the factors that shape these identities. The study includes freshman and senior STEM students at James Madison University as well as freshmen and senior students at four additional institutions with engineering programs by conducting interviews questionnaires and personal identity instruments. We are looking for significant breakthroughs to contribute to our basic understanding of our students? multiple identities as a means of also understanding what activities, experiences, circumstances, and settings shape their identities (particularly their identity as engineers). Apart from the findings that will contribute to our basic understanding of students, the ultimate deliverable will be a survey instrument, Engineer Identity Survey (EIS), interview protocol and questionnaires that could be used by engineering programs at various levels. The PI is well-positioned with a foundation of related work and strong early career motivation to pursue this research, publish and disseminate the research and findings. This BRIGE grant would provide a strong research foundation upon which the PI can pursue more engineering education research funding.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0824337</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Olga</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pierrakos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pierraox@jmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>James Madison University</Name>
      <CityName>HARRISONBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>228077000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5405686872</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>MSC 5728</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7741</Code>
      <Text>BROAD PARTIC IN ENG (BRIGE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
