<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Novel Computational Simulation Methodology for Complex Structural System Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>260000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kishor Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will establish a new structural engineering computation paradigm by developing a novel meshfree simulation methodology for the analysis of complex structural systems. Inelastic large deformations, and material separation and complex failure modes are special features of structural response in performance-based limit states, and existing finite element technology has proven to be inadequate to address these features efficiently in structural design simulations. Thus, there is a need to explore and develop new tools to efficiently analyze and accurately predict the performance of structures in the era of simulation-based design of the civil infrastructure for unconventional loads with large deformation response. The adoption of maximum-entropy meshfree methods in conjunction with stable nodal-integration schemes within a co-rotational formulation is conceived to overcome the current limitations of finite elements. Outcomes from the project include a new methodology to facilitate the assessment of existing infrastructure to extreme loads and procedures to enable simulation-based structural design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The outcome of this research effort will spur new innovative methods to deal with nonlinear analysis of complex structural systems subjected to extreme loads such as earthquakes, blast and impact. External collaboration with researchers at the National Institute of Standards and Technology will provide an excellent opportunity to initiate graduate student exchange and hence enable the development of a strong foundation in experimentation and simulations for improved design of structural systems. The project also includes an educational component that seeks to introduce undergraduates and K-12 students to exciting and emerging methods in structural computation thereby encouraging them to pursue careers in structural engineering and eventually contribute to the national effort to preserve and protect the nation?s infrastructure.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0826513</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sashi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kunnath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>skkunnath@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Natarajan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sukumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsukumar@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1637</Code>
      <Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>039E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>040E</Code>
      <Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
