<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Superlow Fouling Materials Inspired by Naturally Occurring Zwitterions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert M. Wellek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0827274&lt;br/&gt;Jiang&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Zwitterionic-based materials are highly effective at resisting biomolecular attachment from complex media due to their strong hydration. Thus, they are potentially an excellent alternative to commonly used, but unstable poly(ethylene glycol) (PEG). Natural zwitterions in living organisms have unique combinations of positive and negative charges in such a way that makes them effective and stable in complex media. However, it is hard to predict the performance of these natural zwitterions based on their molecular structures alone. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The objective of this work is to establish connections between the structures of natural zwitterions and their hydration capabilities from both molecular simulations and experimental measurements. By learning from natural zwitterions, better zwitterionic materials with unique properties required for specific applications will be designed. The success of this work will transform the field of biointerfaces and biomaterials, for which one will enter the new era beyond PEG. This work will also open up new opportunities to study organic ions and zwitterions, which have not yet been examined in depth. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: These superlow fouling zwitterionic materials will enable the development of many critical technologies, such as drug carriers with long circulation time, protein arrays for reliable diagnostics, and low-fouling membranes for wastewater treatment. One graduate student and two underrepresented undergraduate students will participate in this project. The PI is developing a new course on ?biomolecular Interfaces.? Results from the proposed work will contribute significantly to the new course.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0827274</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shaoyi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jiang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sjiang@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/10/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1414</Code>
      <Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>054E</Code>
      <Text>Molecular engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
