<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multi-scale modeling of health behavior choices: Water, sanitation, and child survival in Africa</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1244805</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jonathan W. Leland</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Davis - 0827384&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Multi-scale modeling of health behavior choices: Water, sanitation, and child survival in Africa&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project integrates theory and methodologies from behavioral sciences, epidemiology, and microeconomics so as to better understand behavior change processes related to water, sanitation, hygiene and health. The broad research goal is to assess the extent to which, and the mechanisms by which, household-level information about risk for enteric illness (specifically water quality and hand cleanliness data) affect household perceptions and behavior related to water management, sanitation practices, and personal hygiene. The research approach includes (1) the collection of household and community information through repeated, structured surveys of households; (2) the collection and microbiological analysis of water and hand samples from household members; (3) the use of these water and hand rinse test results as personalized informational treatments that will be randomly assigned to clusters of households; (4) the modeling of observed changes in behavior, contamination levels, and/or health outcomes as a function of human, cultural, and physical environmental factors operating from the individual to the community scale; and (5) ?process tracing? in order to characterize specific causal mechanisms underlying observed changes. The field site for the project is in Tanzania, where one in six children dies before his/her fifth birthday, with diarrhea being the second leading cause of death after malaria. The project also seeks to inform research communities focused on decision making and behavior change related to health. Whereas the particular focus of the project relates to water, sanitation, and hygiene, the framework employed is relevant for many other areas of health research, particularly those in which both technology use and behavior change are involved.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0827384</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abby</FirstName>
      <LastName>King</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>king@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexandria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boehm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aboehm@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jenna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jennadavis@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
