<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Globally Optimal Process Network Synthesis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>308203</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Burka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0829211&lt;br/&gt;Manousiouthakis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit &lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to advance the state of the art in globally optimal synthesis of process networks using the Infinite DimEnsionAl State-space (IDEAS) method developed by the PI. He plans the following research: &lt;br/&gt; 1. Conceptual and Computational Advancement of IDEAS &lt;br/&gt; 2. Batch Reactor Network Synthesis - Identification of the Attainable Region &lt;br/&gt; 3. Globally Optimal Fuel Cell Network Synthesis &lt;br/&gt; 4. Automatic Generation of Globally Optimal Cryogenic Liquefaction Networks &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In carrying out this research, he will: &lt;br/&gt; A. Seek new solution methods for the IDEAS Infinite Linear Program (ILP) that yield lower bounds that are guaranteed to converge to the global minimum.&lt;br/&gt; B. Seek a novel IDEAS formulation for batch process networks. This is the first time that application of IDEAS will be pursued for a network of dynamic processes such as batch reactors. Issues related to network causality will also be addressed. &lt;br/&gt; C. Either develop a new or use existing fuel cell models to establish whether these models satisfy the properties for incorporation into the IDEAS framework, including any assumptions that must be made on the model properties to make this the case. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The application of IDEAS to cryogenic liquefaction networks will yield novel cryogenic cycles. Synthesis of such cycles will be pursued using software packages which include a user-friendly GUI. This software package will be incorporated into classroom work for students, along with documentation explaining the power of the method and its limitations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact &lt;br/&gt;The IDEAS methodology has been shown to advance the state of the art in process network synthesis and to provide a designer with a synthesis methodology that does not restrict a priori the network structure. The method applies just as well to chemical engineering process design as it does to electrical engineering (fuel cells, hybrid electrical systems, etc.), operations research (mathematical developments in infinite dimensional linear programming, parallelized solution of large scale linear programs, etc.), and cryogenic engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research activity will provide training for K-12, undergraduate, and graduate students by exposing them to high level mathematics and cluster computing technology. This work will also contribute to diversity by facilitating more research projects for K-12 students like those provided by the UCLA Center for Excellence in Engineering and Diversity (CEED). This past summer (2007) the PI had a minority high school student do a summer research project using the IDEAS method through the Science Mathematics Achievement and Research Technology for Students (SMARTS) program run by UCLA CEED. The PI plans on involving more students of all levels in order to foster their interest in engineering and higher education. The conceptual advancement of IDEAS could impact several research areas (mathematical programming, cryogenics, reaction engineering, fuel cell systems engineering) and several industries (power production, hydrogen production, refrigeration, and others).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0829211</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vasilios</FirstName>
      <LastName>Manousiouthakis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vasilios@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1403</Code>
      <Text>PROCESS &amp; REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>047E</Code>
      <Text>REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>050E</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL PROCESS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7752</Code>
      <Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
