<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Visualizing Thermo-Fluid Dynamics at Low Temperature</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Theodore L. Bergman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0829455&lt;br/&gt;Van Sciver&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partial support is provided for a workshop focused on visualizing thermofluid dynamics at low temperatures, which will be held in Texas on November 20 - 21, 2008, as a satellite meeting for the 2008 APS Fluid Dynamics Conference. The purpose of this meeting is to bring together an international group of researchers, especially from Japan and Europe, to exchange research findings in this field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to the intellectual merit of the conference, there currently exists a lack of fundamental understanding of thermofluid processes in liquid and superfluid helium, such as the role of turbulent transport. Flow visualization may enable improved comprehension of such transport processes. This workshop will bring together this focused research community in one venue to discuss their research results and to enhance the potential for international collaboration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the conference include NSF support for a number of junior and female researchers. Since the workshop will be held in conjunction with the APS Fluid Dynamics meeting, it will be relatively easy for interested researchers to attend. A major goal of this workshop is to produce increased international collaboration opportunities among US, Japanese, and European researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Thermal Transport Processes (TTP) Program, and by the Fluid Dynamics Program, of the Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems (CBET) Division.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0829455</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van Sciver</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vnsciver@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>057E</Code>
      <Text>Thermodynamics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>064E</Code>
      <Text>Convection heat and mass transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
