<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CT-ISG: Power to the People: Tools for Explaining Access-Control Consequences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>206250</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Weber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Without their realizing it, end-users have been turned into authors of access-control policies. Everywhere from Google to Facebook to Microsoft HealthVault and beyond, these policies are usually hidden behind simple user interfaces, but ultimately the users are responsible for setting and then taking responsibility for the consequences of these policies. Indeed, the apparent simplicity of the interfaces sometimes belie the significance of the outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Because applications are a black-box to end-users, it becomes difficult for users to predict the consequences of an action. Users see only their view of the world, but their access-control decisions affect the views of others. End-users need tools to determine the effect of their decisions, with special emphasis on the effect of policy changes. This project is developing user-friendly means to browse and investigate the details of these effects and changes. The underlying techniques are firmly grounded in theory, resulting in formal accuracy guarantees rather than approximate answers. The tools themselves summarize information in ways that account for the cognitive expectations and biases of users.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this project comes from the focus on end-users rather than programmers and other technical users. Some end-users are too eager to embrace new technologies without fully appreciating their consequences, while others are too tentative due to their concern about (sometimes imaginary) problems they might create. The tools from this project help the former become more cautious, and the latter more confident. The net result should be a more savvy, yet vastly more inclusive, Cyber society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0830929</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dougherty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dd@cs.wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fisler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kathryn_fisler@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7371</Code>
      <Text>CYBER TRUST</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7795</Code>
      <Text>TRUSTWORTHY COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
