<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Holographic Algorithms and Reductions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Balasubramanian Kalyanasundaram</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The theory of holographic algorithms is expressed by the properties of realizable signatures. The new algorithmic design principles initiated by Les Valiant use these signatures to find efficient and unconventional algorithms for a variety of counting problems. We have already developed a substantial theory of symmetric signatures, which are particularly useful since they have clear combinatorial meanings. However in order to understand the full power of holographic algorithms we must understand realizable but unsymmetric signatures. The theory of unsymmetric signatures is substantially more involved. We propose to work toward a complete classification theorem of unsymmetric signatures based on matchgates and Pfaffians.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research in particular, and in computational complexity theory in general, is to gain a fundamental understanding of the nature of efficient computation. Holographic algorithms challenge our conception of what is efficiently computable. This study will sharpen the boundary of what is and what is not efficiently computable. The proof techniques developed may also be broadly applicable in related areas of complexity theory. The classification theorem for all realizable signatures (including symmetric as well as unsymmetric signatures) will go a long way toward an understanding of what the ultimate capabilities are with these unconventional holographic algorithms.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0830488</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jin-Yi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jyc@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
