<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NECO: Robust, Delay-Tolerant Sketches for Aggregating Sensor Data Streams</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>228264</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph Lyles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NeTS-NECO: Robust, Delay-Tolerant Sketches for Aggregating&lt;br/&gt;Sensor Data Streams&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Emerging data-intensive mobile sensor networking applications promise&lt;br/&gt;a close observation of the world around us at a relatively low data&lt;br/&gt;acquisition cost. In these applications, it is a challenge to&lt;br/&gt;aggregate observation streams from distributed sources, due to the&lt;br/&gt;bandwidth and delay constraints of the network, and the energy costs&lt;br/&gt;of data transmission. This project develops techniques for processing&lt;br/&gt;voluminous sensor data streams within the resource constraints imposed&lt;br/&gt;by a distributed infrastructure-less network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Techniques are designed to summarize the observation streams into&lt;br/&gt;small space "sketches". By disseminating sketches rather than the raw&lt;br/&gt;data, it is possible to trade-off reduced communication cost for&lt;br/&gt;approximate answers to user queries. The project investigates the&lt;br/&gt;technical challenge of making the sketches robust and suitable for&lt;br/&gt;transmission over unreliable links. The sketches are delay-tolerant,&lt;br/&gt;i.e. they can tolerate long and variable network latencies. Various&lt;br/&gt;classes of queries are supported including: basic aggregates of&lt;br/&gt;numerical and categorical data, multi-dimensional temporal and&lt;br/&gt;geographic aggregates, and time-decayed aggregates. The design of&lt;br/&gt;sketches is informed and inspired by the recent rapid progress made in&lt;br/&gt;the area of massive data stream processing. The project will result in&lt;br/&gt;new algorithms and data structures for sketching sensor data with&lt;br/&gt;provable guarantees on the quality of answers. The research is&lt;br/&gt;expected to benefit data-intensive sensor networking applications that&lt;br/&gt;are critical to our society, such as earthquake, pollution, and&lt;br/&gt;traffic monitoring.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0831903</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Srikanta</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tirthapura</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>snt@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
