<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2008 Bridge To The Doctorate (BD)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>987000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dr. A. James Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The New York City Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (LSAMP), under the leadership of the City University of New York, 2008 Bridge to the Doctorate (BD) program will recruit and retain recent LSAMP STEM Graduates into a research/academic career that leads to the completion of a Ph.D. degree. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent Tier 1 LSAMP graduates from the National LSAMP pool of graduates, and LSAMP graduates who have completed no more than one full-time semester equivalent of graduate study shall constitute the group that will be invited to apply for the Bridge to the Doctorate program in 2008. LSAMP senior undergraduates are allowed to participate in Bridge activities. Bridge students will be beneficiaries of a proactive retention and professional enrichment program that will include academic and research mentoring, GRE workshops, roundtable discussions with advanced doctoral students, faculty and administrators, and attendance and participation at local and national professional conferences. The at-large faculty pool associated with the CUNY Graduate Center, and CUNY Institute/Center Directors will serve as Bridge faculty/research advisors. The Alliance will continue to partner with Brookhaven National Labs to provide cutting-edge research training during the academic year and summer terms. International research experiences will also be integrated into the training of all selected BD scholars.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Progress and results of the Bridge to the Doctorate program will be disseminated at the NYC LSAMP Urban University Conference Series, and through its Virtual Community (http://nyc-amp.cuny.edu), and Newsletter. The Urban University Conference Series, held annually since 1998, attracts over 5,000 participants, and among other networking opportunities, provides the opportunity to recruit enrolled undergraduate scholars to CUNY for graduate study, or to other doctoral granting institutions. The BD scholars represent a resource of STEM trainees that are poised to be involved in Informal Science and Math Education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NYC LSAMP Bridge to the Doctorate program will add 89 students to the Ph.D. pipeline from Cohorts 1-6 (2003 through 2010).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0832975</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neville</FirstName>
      <LastName>Parker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>parker@utrc2.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY City College</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9133</Code>
      <Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
