<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Collaborative research in rapid assessment of algal physiology using synchrotron-based Fourier transform infrared imaging supported by chemometrics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>128544</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this collaborative Small Grant for Exploratory Research (SGER) funded by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry (ASC) program of the Chemistry Division Prof. Carol Hirschmugl of the University of Wisconsin Milwaukee and Prof. Frank Vogt of the University of Tennessee will combine innovative spectroscopic (Synchrotron-based infrared imaging with a multi-element detector) and computational(chemometrics) methods for in-vivo studies of algal cells responding to a changing environment. The project goal is to achieve a better understanding of the strategies microalgae adopt to allocate resources focusing on the responses to changes in the availability of carbon and nitrogen. The newly developed methodology will enable the study of the role of carbon dioxide (a green house gas) on algal systems in great detail. Notably, methodologies presently used to study algal cells include tedious biochemical analyses, which are difficult to impossible to use in the studies of living cells. This research could potentially impact important environmental science and engineering research fields including climate change research, potential production of biodiesel, and ecology. Several graduate students across several disciplines will be involved in these research efforts. In addition, high school students and teachers, REU students and students from Appalachia will participate in this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0832298</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mario</FirstName>
      <LastName>Giordano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>m.giordano@univpm.it</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hirschmugl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cjhirsch@uwm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee</Name>
      <CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4142294853</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O BOX 340</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
