<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-Korea Workshop and International Student Forum on Bio-inspired Sensor Technology &amp; Infrastructure Monitoring</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>37840</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>OISE-0748465 (Zhang, Yunfeng Lehigh University)&lt;br/&gt;U.S.-Korea Workshop and International Student Forum on Bio-inspired Sensor Technology and Infrastructure Monitoring&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a U.S. Korea workshop on the integration of bio-inspired sensors and information processing into civil infrastructure structural health monitoring. Topics will include (1) bio-inspired sensor technologies; (2) structural health monitoring and nondestructive testing methods; (3) bioinspired information processing technology such as sensor data fusion, data mining, and knowledge discovery; (4) bio-inspired sensing materials and biomimetics sensors; and (5) infrastructure monitoring and field implementation. The workshop will bring together approximately 40 U.S. and Korean researchers, postdocs, and graduate students with an emphasis on the inclusion of early career, women and underrepresented minority scientists and engineers. The key Korean collaborator is Professor Chung-Bang Yun of the Korean Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST) and Director of the Smart Infra-Structure Technology Center (SISTeC). The Korean participants come from the KAIST and observers from China, Japan and Singapore will also participate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0832362</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yunfeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zyf@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
