<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSEC on Molecular Function at the Nano/Bio Interface</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11850000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Nanoscale Science and Engineering Center (NSEC) at the University of Pennsylvania, the Nano/Bio Interface Center (NBIC), designs and controls molecular functionality, quantifies behavior of individual molecules and interactions at organic/inorganic interfaces to establish the foundation for understanding the interface of physical and biological systems. The NSEC unites investigators from five schools (the School of Engineering and Applied Science, the School of Medicine, the School of Arts and Sciences, Wharton Business School, and the Graduate School of Education) to provide, not only new directions for the life sciences but also for engineering, in a two-way flow essential to fully realizing the benefits of the intersection of biology with nanotechnology. A comprehensive program uses fundamental research enterprises as a platform for curriculum development, pre-college educational programs, out reach to the community, and commercialization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two multi disciplinary research teams are focused on: optoelectronic function in synthetic biomolecules and mechanical motion of molecules from physiological systems. In each area physical interfaces probe, control, or influence the outcome. A cross-cutting initiative brings together investigators who develop nanoscale measurement tools to produce the next wave of innovation in probes of molecular function and enables research in both teams. To enable these advances the NBIC has established the Nano/Bio Probe Facility. The Nano/Bio Probe Innovation Facility assembles a comprehensive set of enabling research tools to support research interactions that would otherwise be difficult or impossible to sustain. The Facility is unique to Penn, where the newest advances in probing single molecule and nanostructure behavior are made available to the research community. The facility opened in 2005 and now has over 80 users. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NBIC established and leads a large portfolio of educational programs. An undergraduate minor in Nanotechnology now serves 70 students from 3 schools and with representation from all engineering departments. The graduate certificate in Nanotechnology has an enrolment of 20 students. An annual summer high school academy offers a residential program on Nanotechnology that obtains enrollment of ~25 students/year. A strong theme of NBIC outreach addresses professional development of pre-college teachers in the Philadelphia region. A highlight is the Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) program that is a collaboration with Drexel University. A partnership with Alabama State University has established programs to impact the pipeline of future scientists and engineers. A variety of community outreach activities are highlighted at the annual NanoDay@Penn.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0832802</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johnson@dept.Physics.Upenn.Edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/02/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bonnell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bonnell@seas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/02/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1248</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS-OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1675</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1736</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS CENTERS &amp; EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>J444</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1359</Code>
      <Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1675</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7623</Code>
      <Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
