<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Albert Einstein Distinguished Educator Fellowship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>998675</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Celestine Pea</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: This proposal seeks funding to support the continuation of the National Science Foundation?s participation in the Albert Einstein Distinguished Educator Fellows Program. The 1994 Albert Einstein Distinguished Educator Fellowship Act gave official responsibility for overall administration of the program to the Department of Energy (DOE). The Triangle Coalition manages the program on behalf of DOE. The fellowship program is designed to provide opportunities for teachers to work on educational issues and/or programs in a federal agency or congressional office. It is guided by the following objectives: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;? To provide outstanding elementary and secondary mathematics, science and technology education teachers the opportunity to bring to Congress and appropriate branches of the Federal government the insights, extensive knowledge, and practical experience of classroom teachers; &lt;br/&gt;? To increase the understanding, communication, and cooperation between Congress and Federal agencies; &lt;br/&gt;? To increase the understanding, communication and cooperation between the Federal government and the science, technology and mathematics education community; and &lt;br/&gt;? To gain insights and understanding of national educational issues, which can then be transferred back to the classroom. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The program promotes professional growth in STEM areas; fosters the exchange of ideas that are relevant to STEM education at the national and state levels through conferences, meetings, workshops, and presentations; provides opportunities for teachers to have input at levels were STEM policymaking decisions are made; and awards outstanding teachers for their contributions to STEM education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funding for this proposal is sought for a three-year period to support the participation of up to eight Fellows for each year of the project duration. These Fellows will be guests of the Foundation for eleven months beginning September 2008 through July 2009. The following directorates/offices at NSF in which Fellows will serve are determined by the individual Program Officers and may vary from year to year. Beginning September 2008, the Division of Research on Learning in Formal and Informal Settings; Division of Graduate Education; Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship; Polar Programs; Directorate of Geosciences; Office of International Science and Engineering; and the Office of Cyberinfrastructure will host Fellows in FY09. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The proposer outlined a wide range of activities for the Fellows that involve other federal agencies, governmental officials, and business partners. It is likely that the Foundation will benefit from classroom experiences shared by these teachers during their tenure at NSF. The program offers opportunities for teacher to make connections between the larger policymaking body and educational research, thereby, resulting in a win-win situation for both teachers and the Foundation. Additionally, the program provides opportunities for teachers to learn from and build networks with other teachers nationally and internationally.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/06/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0833984</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vance</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ablott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ablottv@triangle-coalition.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Triangle Coalition for Science and Technology Education</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>222013000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7035165960</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1840 Wilson Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1733</Code>
      <Text>GEOSCIENCE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5130</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC COORDINATION &amp; INFOR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7179</Code>
      <Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7645</Code>
      <Text>DISCOVERY RESEARCH K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9199</Code>
      <Text>UNDISTRIBUTED PANEL/IPA FUNDS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
