<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ACT!: An alternative teacher preparation program for talented professionals seeking licensure in secondary science and mathematics teaching</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599817</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen B. Bergin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project provides critical financial support for 50 career changer students (over five years) who are preparing to teach in high need schools. ACT! is an alternative teacher licensure program for secondary science and mathematics (grades 6-12). In its second year of operation, ACT! has enrolled 56 students to date. ACT! provides highly qualified individuals with the pedagogical skills necessary to teach secondary students, and to provide leadership in science and mathematics education in their future school districts. ACT! specifically recruits post-baccalaureate mid-career professionals. The delivery and content of the program are grounded in principles of adult learning (Brookfield, 1986; Merriam &amp; Caffarella, 1999; Smith &amp; Pourchot, 1998). The ACT! program is designed to recognize the unique backgrounds, learning and experiences that individuals with real life experience in science or mathematics can bring to secondary teaching, the very real need to maintain some level of income while in a teacher preparation program, and time and geographic limitations related to maintaining family and work obligations. Consideration is being given to increasing the numbers of minorities, persons with disabilities and underrepresented genders relative to science and mathematics teaching fields. The ability to provide financial support greatly enhances the mission to support mid-career professionals as they transition to careers as professional educators. The University of Wisconsin Oshkosh Office of Field Experience (OFE) works extensively with 22 different school districts in the six counties surrounding Oshkosh. OFE also has standing agreements to place student teachers in three urban centers (Milwaukee, Racine, and Beloit) and a tribal school in Wisconsin (Menominee Indian School).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0833324</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lizotte</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mlizotte@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beeth</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>beeth@uwosh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tammy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ladwig</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tammy.ladwig@uwc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Oshkosh</Name>
      <CityName>Oshkosh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>549013551</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9204241415</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 Algoma Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
