<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nazareth College Robert Noyce Scholar Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>749692</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan T Prival</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nazareth College is increasing the number of qualified and effective mathematics and science teachers committed to teaching in high-need K-12 school districts by recruiting 22 undergraduate and graduate students into programs leading to certification in adolescence education Grades 7-12 in the areas of mathematics, biology, and chemistry and in childhood/middle childhood education Grades 1-6 (with majors in mathematics or the sciences). Recruitment efforts target STEM professionals and persons from underrepresented backgrounds. The project is a collaboration with the Rochester City School District, the Rochester Area Colleges (RAC) Center for Excellence in Math and Science Education, Monroe Community College, and the Science Teachers Association of New York State Central Western Section. The School of Education and the College of Arts and Sciences provide an integrated experience for teacher education students as they gain expertise in both content and pedagogy. The evaluation is measuring the impact of the program on increasing the number of graduating STEM educators and their contributions to student learning in high-needs districts and exploring best practices for recruiting, supporting, and retaining highly qualified STEM teachers for high-needs schools. By providing highly qualified teachers in high-needs districts, the project seeks to positively impact student learning and encourage students to consider pursuing careers in STEM related fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0833264</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lynn</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Brien</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lobrien9@naz.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
      <LastName>DaBoll-Lavoie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kdaboll9@naz.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Nazareth College of Rochester</Name>
      <CityName>Rochester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146183703</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5853892419</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4245 East Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
