<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>UMBC Noyce Scholars Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>750000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lidia C. Yoshida</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of Maryland, Baltimore County (UMBC), in collaboration with the public school districts of Baltimore County, Howard County and the City of Baltimore, is recruiting and supporting undergraduate STEM majors to pursue careers in secondary teaching of STEM disciplines (Math, Science, Technology). The project targets undergraduate STEM majors at UMBC as well as transfers from local area community colleges nearing the conclusion of their sophomore year who may have not previously considered careers in teaching. The project includes a five-year support network beginning during the initial experiences of pre-service teacher education and sustaining support through the conclusion of three years as a full time teacher. The UMBC Noyce Scholar Program provides approximately $15,000 in scholarships and stipends to three cohorts each consisting of 12 undergraduate STEM majors. Each Noyce scholar completes a bachelor's degree in a STEM discipline by the conclusion of the first phase (Initial Certification) of the program. During the completion of the second phase (Induction Support), each scholar completes a Masters of Arts in Education degree that includes an additional 18 credit hours of STEM disciplinary content. The scholars engage in paid summer STEM research laboratory experiences as both an undergraduate (summer of senior year) and during their early years as a full time teacher (summer following their second year of teaching). These experiences are supported through leveraging NSF sponsored REU and RET supplements garnered by currently funded UMBC STEM faculty. Extensive interaction with a population of high-needs students occurs during the initial summer experience, during the following academic year and during the Scholars' culminating senior year teaching internship. In addition to preparing 36 highly qualified secondary teachers of STEM disciplines, the project provides an opportunity to investigate and disseminate aspects of the model. Assessment of the key components of the undergraduate teacher preparation model provides information associated with the types of incentives, experiences, marketing strategies and collaborations that can significantly increase the interest of STEM majors for considering a career in teaching. Similar information can be learned from the components of the induction support plan.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0833316</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Singer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jsinger@umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zengel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zengel@umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nagaraj</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neerchal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nagaraj@math.umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland Baltimore County</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4104553140</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Hilltop Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
