<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: ISBE 2008 conference, to be held at Cornell University in August 2008</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>daniel wiegmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal # 0834252: Support for ISBE 2008 conference&lt;br/&gt;PI: Sandra L. Vehrencamp&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Support from the NSF will provide funds for the 12th biennial congress of the International Society for Behavioral Ecology (ISBE) to be held at Cornell University in August 2008. ISBE congresses are exceptionally international in composition and held alternately in the New World and the Old World. ISBE meetings are also unusually gender-balanced, both in participation and in leadership, and the strongly international membership and meeting structure are designed to facilitate interactions between the most well known researchers in the field and the many younger scientists and students from around the world who attend these meetings. ISBE congresses tend to place a greater emphasis on the theoretical bases and processes of behavioral evolution than Animal Behavior Society meetings. The explicit blend of theory and experiment has continued to be the main thread linking members of the Society as topics have evolved and shifted in popularity. Taxonomic coverage is broad, ranging from invertebrates to vertebrates including humans, and primary topics include communication, cooperation and conflict, sexual selection, personality, and foraging strategies. The 2008 ISBE congress has attracted a record number of participants (1020 scientists), the largest conference ever held at Cornell and a challenge for the campus. Press coverage will disseminate the exciting new scientific findings into the news services for worldwide distribution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0834252</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vehrencamp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slv8@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell Univ - State: AWDS MADE PRIOR MAY 2010</Name>
      <CityName>Ithica</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502488</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
