<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Recursion: Structural Complexity in Language and Cognition</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>64737</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04000000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan Straumanis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Workshop on Recursion&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is well-known that language is an window into the human mind, not&lt;br/&gt;just because our words reveal our thoughts, but because the way we put&lt;br/&gt;words together reflects principles of organization that allow&lt;br/&gt;creativity to flourish. Recent mathematically based research in&lt;br/&gt;linguistic theory has identified computational principles that promise&lt;br/&gt;to provide the software behind our neurological hardware. This&lt;br/&gt;workshop will bring together linguists, biologists, psychologists,&lt;br/&gt;philosophers and computer scientists who are discovering how these&lt;br/&gt;linguistic principles provide the abstract basis for language learning&lt;br/&gt;and learning in general. Central to this enterprise is a simple&lt;br/&gt;concept, recursion, the idea of building complex structures through&lt;br/&gt;repeated application of simple rules, which may provide a metaphor for&lt;br/&gt;the organization of all human action.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop is timely because research on complex structures in&lt;br/&gt;language and cognition is now reaching a point where the various types&lt;br/&gt;of complexity can begin to be defined with sufficient precision to&lt;br/&gt;consolidate results and discover the sources and limits of complex&lt;br/&gt;human cognition. By identifying the ways in with complex structures&lt;br/&gt;and complex can arise from the application of simple rules, this&lt;br/&gt;research lays the foundation for new ways of designing curriculum for&lt;br/&gt;optimal learning, new perspectives on artificial intelligence and new&lt;br/&gt;insight into the evolutionary changes that distinguish animal&lt;br/&gt;cognition from human cognitive abilities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/29/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/29/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0834032</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roeper</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>roeper@linguist.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/29/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Speas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pspeas@linguist.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/29/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7704</Code>
      <Text>Science of Learning Activities</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
