<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integration of Bioinformatics into a Biology Curriculum</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>85910</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Terry S. Woodin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Muhlenberg College Departments of Biology, Chemistry, and Mathematics and Computer Science are jointly integrating bioinformatics into multiple biology and biochemistry courses at three levels: introductory, intermediate, and advanced. There are two major educational goals for this project: 1) to improve undergraduate sophistication about bioinformatics, and 2) to increase the mathematical content in the biology and biochemistry curricula. The project is serving approximately 200 biology, biochemistry and neuroscience majors each year. One introductory biology course, three intermediate level biology laboratory courses, and three advanced courses in biology and biochemistry are introducing new bioinformatics components or are expanding and improving existing components. Laboratory curricula feature multiple-week investigative experiences that build on existing experimental schemes. The curricular goals are being supported by a new genomics and proteomics core laboratory facility that features real-time PCR and 2-D gel electrophoresis. In addition, multiple laptop computers are enabling students in introductory and upper-level courses to work on challenging problems in smaller discussion sections and laboratories. The new computers allow instructors to explore computational applications, and the underlying mathematics, more effectively in the classroom. Faculty development, in the form of a one-time week-long inter-disciplinary on-site bioinformatics course, is supporting the curricular goals, inspiring faculty in the use of the new technology, and encouraging collaboration among biologists, biochemists, and computational scientists. The increased faculty expertise and interdisciplinary collaboration is also resulting in undergraduate research projects in bioinformatics or projects that rely on bioinformatics as an integral tool within the research design. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The project adapts and implements published curricular suggestions for improving undergraduate education in biology and bioinformatics. The over-arching mission is to educate more quantitatively-literate biology students. Faculty development, the potential for new collaborations in courses and student research, and the new laboratory core facility itself are having a significant impact on the local science environment. The value of bioinformatics as a tool for improving quantitative instruction and the specific instructional schemes themselves are being assessed through student surveys and other instruments as appropriate. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: Familiarity with basic bioinformatics and computational approaches is increasingly a necessity for professionals in a range of areas related to the life sciences. The assessment of curricular outcomes from the project is being disseminated broadly to provide a reference point for the development of similar strategies and projects at other undergraduate institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0836869</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wightman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wightman@muhlenberg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Clifton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kussmaul</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kussmaul@muhlenberg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marten</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edwards</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Edwards@muhlenberg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hark@muhlenberg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Keri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Colabroy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>colabroy@muhlenberg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Muhlenberg College</Name>
      <CityName>Allentown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>181045586</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4846643000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>24th and Chew Streets</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
