<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Small Grant for Exploratory Research: DGF-NSF Research Conference on Contextualizing Economic Behavior</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>103216</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frank P. Scioli Jr.</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES-0836134&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator will hold a conference, jointly organized and funded between the US National Science Foundation and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (German Research Foundation) (DFG. This conference explores research frontiers between recent developments in behavioral economics and economic sociology. The conference includes 80 scholars,(40 each from the US and Germany) whose research informs these boundaries. Scholars include senior and junior researchers representing a broad range of universities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent developments in economics and sociology point to the need to broaden the range of concepts and variables taken into consideration when economic behavior is studied. They point to the need to contextualize economic action and to rethink economic behavior itself, by broadening our understanding of its internal processes and engagements as well as its biological foundations. The objective is to explore the advances in several research communities with regard to such questions, and to bring these communities together across disciplinary boundaries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference format is designed to enhance cross-disciplinary exchange and explore agreements and disagreements between the research communities. Sessions are focused on a single topic, and consist of up to four presentations and one discussant who are selected to represent different research communities. Junior scholars are expected to attend and participate in the full conference, and a poster session provides a venue for presentations on original research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts include the development of cross-disciplinary research initiatives, dissemination of graduate student and post-doc research, and enhancement of US/Germany collaborative research possibilities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0836134</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eckel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ceckel@econmail.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
      <CityName>Richardson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1320</Code>
      <Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
