<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Intricate Molecules from Nature as an Avenue for the Development of New Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>544820</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this CAREER Award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor Armen Zakarian of the Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry at Florida State University. This research project is directed toward the development of new methods for the synthesis of complex natural products. Several methods based on sigmatropic rearrangements and enolization chemistry form the foundation of the project. These include a Lewis-acid mediated hetero-Cope rearrangement that will be used to assemble oxazine rings, a tandem reaction for the synthesis of functionalized cyclohexenols incorporating a stereogenic quaternary center, and the stereoselective generation of tetrasubstituted acyclic enolates. This project, which will improve efficiency of chemical synthesis, will expand the scope of organic compounds available for research in areas such as drug development and materials science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Professor Zakarian will also initiate variety of educational programs designed to increase awareness of the benefits of chemical research to society. These programs include the development of a museum-based series of activities that will expose the general public to state-of-the-art organic chemistry and have the potential to attract young students to careers in science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0836757</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Armen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zakarian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zakarian@chem.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1950</Code>
      <Text>METHODOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
