<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Smart Biomaterials for Tissue and Regenerative Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150368</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myles G. Boylan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Interdisciplinary(99) This project provides integrated laboratory experiences for undergraduate students in biomaterials and regenerative tissue engineering. Seven laboratory modules focus on the development of smart biomaterials to engineer soft tissues. Faculty members from two universities are involved in project development. The hands-on laboratory experiences are enriched by workshop/seminars that employ the active learning mode as opposed to the use of traditional passive lectures. The labs are improving the educational experiences of undergraduate students enrolled in several Engineering and Science Disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;The project targets an unmet need in an interdisciplinary field of science and engineering education. The interdisciplinarity of the topic makes it challenging to prepare students adequately for work in the field. The plan is to develop lab modules in tissue engineering. The modules are addressing technical methodologies and biocompatibility of test tissues. These modules are applicable to programs in various departments nationwide, such as Chemical Engineering, Materials Engineering, Biomedical and Biological Engineering, Chemistry and Biosciences, all of which now teach courses at the interface of biomaterials and tissue engineering. A strong component of the approach is the ability to utilize an automated assessment system to quantify the learning outcomes and suggest improvements based on information collected during the laboratories. The particular technical area of Smart Biomaterials for Tissue and Regenerative Engineering has seen recent intense activity in the private sector as technologies mature and reach commercialization potential. This trend has attracted several commercial companies to participate in the program. Educating students with practical experiences using these technologies and enabling them to be interdisciplinary partners is of value and transferable across K-12 educational levels.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0837163</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wootton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wootto@cooper.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lelkes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pilelkes@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lowman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alowman@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elisabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Papazoglou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esp25@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>McEachron</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mceachdl@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
