<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Investigation of alternative conceptions about Plate Tectonics across the expert-novice continuum: When a well-known theory isn't so well known</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>214683</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter Lea</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Geology (42)&lt;br/&gt;This project is investigating students' and experts' conceptual understanding of plate tectonics. Because plate tectonics is the conceptual model through which most dynamic processes on Earth are understood, a solid understanding of the basic tenets of the model is crucial in developing future geoscientists and a scientifically literate public. The overarching goals for this project are to 1) highlight specific concepts that pose barriers to students' comprehension; 2) make faculty aware of the extent of the problem by disseminating results in presentations and journal publications; 3) investigate whether or not the complexity, interdisciplinarity, and the continual evolution of the plate tectonic model leads to alternative conceptions being embedded within instructional tools, with the potential for passing these alternative conceptions on to current undergraduate and graduate students; and, 4) improve educational practices by making instructors aware of common alternative conceptions held by students as well as problems with equivocal representations in figures, and by suggesting alternative approaches to teaching about plate tectonics using images. Lecture Tutorials are being developed that specifically target alternative conceptions and problem areas revealed in the research. The Lecture Tutorials will be disseminated via publication and through a faculty workshop at a national conference. This project impacts several communities, including geocognition researchers, faculty and students. This project is contributing to the STEM education knowledge base by generating a unique, comprehensive data set of plate tectonics conceptions across the expert-novice continuum. Additionally, this work is having significant implications for future geoscience education practice and research, by providing insight into the importance and impact of commonly used illustrations for development of conceptual models.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/07/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0837185</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jessica.smay@sjcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Libarkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>libarkin@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Libarkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>libarkin@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/26/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kortz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kkortz@ccri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clarksco@uwec.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clarksco@uwec.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/26/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
