<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Luminescence Spectroscopy in Molecular Assemblies and New Energy Conversion Materials: Integration Across the Undergraduate Curriculum</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149945</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph Grabowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Chemistry (12)&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. A collaborative group of educators from the Chemistry Department or from the Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biophysics Department are implementing the use of two fluorescence spectrophotometers as a means for catalyzing an integrated modification of the undergraduate chemistry and biochemistry laboratory curriculum. The modified curriculum is providing undergraduate students with a broad introduction to luminescence and associated topics, including a multiyear exposure to the scientific processes underlying solar energy conversion and energy transport in both synthetic and living systems. A thorough and integrated introduction to luminescence&lt;br/&gt;spectroscopies and luminescent materials in the undergraduate curriculum has become important for a number of reasons. Fluorescent assays are widely used in the characterization and analysis of biological and biomimetic materials, and in parallel with the sequencing of the human genome there has been an explosion in the use of single molecule fluorescence studies in all areas of bioscience. Luminescence spectroscopy is at the heart of the development of many forms of nanoscience, especially the development of new nanomaterials for solar energy conversion. By offering practical and in-depth laboratory experiences that explore these important topics, students are enhancing their understanding of fluorescence as a probe of the dynamics of molecular systems and are becoming familiar with recent advances in contemporary research fields such as solar energy conversion, nanoscience, and biochemical fluorescence spectroscopy. The fluorescence spectrophotometers are being used by both Chemistry and Biochemistry undergraduates, in years three and four of their curriculum, including in Analytical, Physical and Inorganic Prep classes, along with a Biochemical Techniques laboratory. Experiments are being developed that investigate a) light absorption and excited state creation, energy transfer, and luminescence decay; b) fluorescence emission, resonance energy transfer (FRET), and anisotropy in molecular assemblies, emphasizing the effect of microenvironment on these processes; c) biochemical applications of anisotropy and FRET in measurements of biomacromolecular binding affinity and reaction kinetics; and d) the competition between luminescence and electron transfer in solar energy conversion systems created from linked semiconductor and oxide nanoparticles. The last of these involves a cross-course collaborative capstone experience for students in Inorganic and Physical Chemistry laboratories. Experiments are being designed using a "bottom-up" approach so that appropriate overlap of the most significant issues occurs throughout the students' training.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. Approximately 250 students are enrolled in the affected courses each year. As a result of this curricular modification, these students are developing an enhanced understanding of fluorescence and a number of related topics while being exposed to important areas of contemporary research. They are gaining appreciation for the collaborative and cross-disciplinary nature of science. Under the guidance of the faculty, graduate teaching assistants carry out much of the experimental development, and are benefiting both educationally and professionally. An additional solar energy education outreach component is being implemented in collaboration with the undergraduate chemistry club. Materials developed over the course of the project will be made accessible to the wider scientific community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0837398</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pemberton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pembertn@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>S. Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Saavedra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>saavedra@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deirdre</FirstName>
      <LastName>Belle-Oudry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbelle@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Horton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nhorton@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oliver</FirstName>
      <LastName>Monti</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>monti@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
