<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Introduction of a Guided-inquiry Curriculum in Organic Chemistry by Means of Microwave-assisted Synthesis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>135302</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph Grabowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Chemistry(12) A sophomore organic laboratory curriculum based on microwave-mediated synthesis is being developed, in which the conceptual link between laboratory and classroom is strengthened. Guided-inquiry laboratory activities are also being created to increase conceptual learning and foster the development of practitioner knowledge. In addition to the acquisition of the necessary microwave reactors, the project is providing for faculty-student collaborative development of curriculum materials. A thoroughgoing evaluation of the project learning outcomes is being conducted by an external evaluator.&lt;br/&gt; The project is addressing the great need for robust, safe, and user-friendly procedures to use in a typical sophomore organic laboratory. Furthermore, while other investigators have reported on the successful introduction of guided-inquiry components into the organic laboratory curriculum, the current proposal is embarking on the first major undertaking to capitalize on the advantages of microwave-assisted synthesis in creating a more student-centered laboratory experience. In addition, this program is generating new knowledge in the realm of teaching and learning.&lt;br/&gt; The acquisition of the microwave equipment is establishing a regional center of expertise and infrastructure in microwave chemistry, available to the many colleges and small universities within a 50-mile radius of Allegheny, and an existing junior high science enrichment program is benefiting from the equipment. Student and instructor materials are being collected into a virtual lab manual. The curriculum materials, as well as the new knowledge on teaching and learning acquired from assessment, is being shared with the broader community at cross-cutting conferences on chemistry and education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0837640</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shaun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murphree</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smurphre@allegheny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/10/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Allegheny College</Name>
      <CityName>Meadville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>163353902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8143325380</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>520 North Main Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
