<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Mid-Infrared Interband Cascade Photodetectors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75029</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective:&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to explore a new class of mid-infrared (IR) photodetectors based on the interband cascade (IC) structures, which can cover a wide infrared spectral range from 3 to 12 microns by merely adjusting quantum well layer thickness. Our goal is to achieve high performance and low noise IC photodetectors (focus on 4-7 microns) at room temperature or thermoelectric (TE) cooler temperatures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;IC photodetectors are based on a new operation principle combining advantages of very fast intersubband relaxation and interband tunneling for carrier transport and relatively slow interband transitions. This research will advance the understanding of physical processes such as carrier transport and photon absorption in IC photodetectors. Unlike photodetectors based on intersubband transitions, IC photodetectors are sensitive to normal incidence radiation. Furthermore, carrier transport/collection in the IC photodetector is immune from background doping and material quality variations in contrast to conventional semiconductor and type-II superlattice detectors. Hence, this research will provide opportunity to investigate new phenomena associated with underlying physics in interband cascade structures and devices, and lead to high performance mid-IR photodetectors that can operate at or near room temperature. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;This research will generate new knowledge in the design and understanding of quantum semiconductor structures and devices. The realization of high-performance mid-IR photodetectors will have significant impacts on medical, industrial, defense and homeland security applications. This work will provide students unique opportunities to have education, training and research through the inherent multidisciplinary topics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0838439</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rui</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rui.q.yang@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
      <CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
