<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: High-efficiency Multi-carrier Ribbon-beam Amplifier for Wireless Communications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I research proposal will demonstrate an innovative Ribbon-Beam Amplifier (RBA) which significantly advances the state-of-the-art in solid-state and vacuum electronic Radio Frequency (RF) amplification. The goal is to determine the feasibility of a ribbon-beam amplifier that is highly efficient (56%), broadband (1930-1990 MHz), and high power (100 W in continuous-wave operation). As a next-generation RF amplifier, the RBA is expected to be applicable to third-generation (3G) wireless communications and future wireless communication platforms such as emerging fourth generation (4G) and ultra-wide-band (UWB) wireless communications. If successful, this project will lead to commercially deployable RBA products overcoming the limitations of existing solid-state multi-carrier power amplifiers (MPCAs) which have low efficiency, complex and expensive linearization circuits, and narrow instantaneous bandwidth (30 MHz).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed technology will significantly lower both the capital cost and operating cost of commercial wireless base station amplifiers. Using increases in efficiency of a factor of 2 to 3 over current solid state products provides for cost reduction in primary power usage by the amplifiers themselves; operating cost and capital cost reduction from lower power output requirements of backup power sources such as batteries and auxiliary power generators needed for power outage conditions; smaller power supplies; and smaller less expensive cooling systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/12/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/12/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0838893</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bemis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tbemis@beampower.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/12/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Beam Power Technology, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Sudbury</CityName>
      <ZipCode>017761142</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9783760143</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>142 North Rd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
