<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Discover Corps Fellowship: Nanomaterials: Bridging the Achievement Gap</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>172425</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Christina Bauer of the Georgia Institute of Technology is a Discovery Corps Postdoctoral Fellow for 2007-2009. The research is targeted at the preparation and study of silica encapsulated metal nanoparticle clusters with well-characterized structures. Bauer also will investigate the fluorescence properties of dyes bound to these composites. This work could contribute towards understanding the parameters important for achieving metal-enhanced fluorescence and lead to the development of highly fluorescent nanoprobes for use in biological labeling and sensing. The service component of this DCF project is aimed at the education and mentoring of undergraduates from underrepresented groups. The goal of the work is to prepare and encourage these students for advanced education and careers in chemistry, particularly in the nanomaterials field. Bauer will give demonstrations and lectures at community colleges and HBCUs in the Atlanta area, including Georgia Perimeter College and Clayton State University, where she will also advise students in planning their scientific careers. Bauer also will supervise students from these institutions in undergraduate research at Georgia Tech and facilitate their recruitment into summer internships at Sandia National Laboratories to work on collaborative projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Discovery Corps Fellowship is supported by the Division of Chemistry and the Office of Multidisciplinary Activities. The Discovery Corps Fellowship Program seeks new postdoctoral and professional development models that combine research expertise with professional service. Discovery Corps Fellows leverage their research expertise through projects that address areas of national need. Their projects enhance research capacity and infrastructure and contribute to workforce development and job creation. The Discovery Corps Program supports both Postdoctoral Fellows and Senior Fellows.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0838320</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bauer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbauer@chem.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1988</Code>
      <Text>CHEMISTRY FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1988</Code>
      <Text>CHEMISTRY FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
