<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Connecting Interactive Projections to Online Social Communities with Personalized Media</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Errol Arkilic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will develop the technologies&lt;br/&gt;to connect interactive projections to online social networks via personalized media for advertising, entertainment, branding and other uses. Entertainment and advertising companies have not yet fully leveraged the impact of Web 2.0 communities because these communities are inherently personal. The innovation ties the linearly scalable technology of interactive projection to the exponentially scalable technology of online Web 2.0 social communities in order to exploit these communities for advertising, entertainment and education. This is done by creating a standardized technological framework to share personalized videos created with experiences from interactive projections via online social communities and an open API to allow enthusiastic public extensions to the platform.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the project will be to create a scalable business for creating personalized media with interactive projections, developing an irresistible value proposition for advertising agencies, entertainment firms, museums and other customers with access to public space. By rapidly and skillfully developing the online product, the effort has the potential to create a new niche within the rapidly growing alternative media advertising market of $73Billion. The anticipated market size of this niche is $1.4Billion for this new sector within five years.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/12/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0839804</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Snibbe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scott@snibbeinteractive.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/12/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Snibbe Interactive, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941032822</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4158221442</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1073 Howard Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
