<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Novel Fire-Resistant Toughened Benzoxazine Resins</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99949</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Josephine Yuen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project seeks to develop and demonstrate flame-resistant, polymer-composite materials based on novel benzoxazine resin chemistries. Recent work by Composite Technology Development, Inc. (CTD) has shown that thermosetting polymer resins based on these materials offer significantly improved flame and moisture resistance as compared to other resins commonly used in composite manufacture (e.g., epoxy and cyanate-ester chemistries). Despite these encouraging preliminary results, significant impediments exist to the widespread application of benzoxazine resins. In particular, most potential markets and customers are adverse to the introduction of "non-heritage" material systems, due to lack of familiarity and potential changes to processing and manufacturing techniques dictated by the new materials. Hence, and in order to overcome this barrier to market entry, a more fundamental understanding of the material design and synthesis is needed with which to tailor commercially-viable versions. Therefore, the focus of this project is to design and synthesize benzoxazine-based polymers with suitable processing characteristics and mechanical performance for large-scale commercial composite applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts/commercial potential of this project is the develoment of viable, flame resistant benzoxazine-based polymers with suitable processing characteristics and mechanical performance (especially improvements in strength and toughness) for large-scale commercial composite applications. Assuming the barriers to market entry can be overcome, benzoxazines could revolutionize a variety of markets. Most immediately, there is opportunity to dramatically improve the flame resistance of composite materials in civilian and military aircraft, as well as naval vessels. Similarly, there is great potential to improve the safety of composite consumer goods (e.g., furniture, electronics, etc.), and products being employed by homeland security, and law enforcement agencies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/21/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0839381</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hooker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>matt.hooker@ctd-materials.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/21/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Composite Technology Development, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>800263359</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3036640394</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2600 Campus Drive, Suite D</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
