<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Mystery of Matter: Search for the Elements (Planning Grant)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul W. Jennings</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The periodic table of chemical elements is an array that is confusing to the uninformed and profoundly simplifying and full of crucial information to the informed. It represents some of the most basic information for the construction of what people see, feel and breathe. Due to the table's complex appearance and the way it is described; many individuals shun its informative base. This proposal is a planning grant application that intends to develop a multi-media presentation, which includes TV, web site, a teachers DVD, and an outreach plan, to bridge this knowledge gap in a user freindly manner. It will make educating minority children one of its priorities. The basic premise for their bridge is that people will better grasp the aspects of the chemical elements if they humanize the elements by discussing them as products of scientists and that scientists are people. The success of this effort is critical. While chemistry affects every aspect of human life, it is one of the least understood sciences. If successful, this project may well pave the way for additional programming.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0840266</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lyons</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stephenlyons@comcast.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Filmmakers Collaborative, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Melrose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021763933</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7816621102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6 Eastman Place Suite 202</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
