<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Deep-Biosphere Research Coordination Network</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499418</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Scientists have postulated the existence of a widespread community of microorganisms living at high temperatures kilometers below the Earth's surface, supported by geological energy sources. The purpose of this Research Coordination Network is to foster a growing, dynamic, and predominantly young community of scientists studying life that exists in the dark, deep marine biosphere. The ramifications of this subsurface hidden biosphere are numerous and may lead to paradigm shifts in the biosciences and geosciences. To date, deep biosphere studies have focused on microbes in relatively shallow marine sediments or in terrestrial mines, wells, and drill-core samples. However, these data do not permit a true global census of subsurface life. The largest potential subsurface biome is also the least accessible: the deep ocean subsurface. This biome also has importance for global-scale biogeochemical processes, including the carbon, energy, and nutrient cycles. Depending on geothermal gradients and physico-chemical limits of life, the subsurface biosphere may extend to a depth of 5-10 km, or more, and occupy a volume several orders of magnitude greater than the continental biosphere. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The RCN will develop coordinate science activities in the community of deep-biosphere researchers. It will also promote education among several disciplines that contribute to the research through interlaboratory exchanges for students in this field. The RCN will meet these goals through meetings, workshops, student exchanges, and a web site. Additional activities for outreach include newsletters, web sites for information on tools and techniques, and special sessions at scientific meetings. The RCN will establish a research institute named DEBI (Dark Energy Biosphere Institute) that will foster the growth of research into the deep biosphere.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0840985</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Amend</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>janamend@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katrina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edwards</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kje@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
