<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RCN: Enzymes in the Environment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>524420</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010209</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Enzyme RCN Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Extracellular enzymes produced by bacteria and fungi are involved in innumerable biogeochemical processes and are central to providing services to terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems. One very important process is the biological decomposition of organic matter in soils and sediments, which is a critical component of the global carbon cycle. Furthermore, the natural attenuation of polluted soils and waters depends on the activities of extracellular enzymes. However, our ability to understand and manage biogeochemical processes for beneficial outcomes such as carbon sequestration, optimizing ecosystem productivity, and bioremediation is constrained by our limited knowledge of the diversity and functional capabilities of extracellular enzymes. The overall goal of this Research Coordination Network is to advance our understanding of enzymes in the environment through improved communication, collaboration, and spurring new initiatives. The network will accomplish this goal by organizing workshops, data synthesizing, standardizing methods, and through maintaining a project website.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Research Coordination Network addresses a need to advance our understanding of the controls on the production of enzymes by different microbes, their stabilization and turnover, and their in-situ activity. Currently, our understanding is constrained by (1) limited methods for measuring actual enzyme activities in various environments, (2) limited discourse across disciplinary and ecosystem boundaries, and (3) limited synthesis of current research into an integrated conceptual framework that feeds into ecosystem models. New advances in genomics and other molecular approaches will allow for rapid advances in this field. This network will enhance collaboration and communication between the international community of scientists involved in various aspects of this research. Broadening participation of underrepresented groups in science will be promoted by active recruitment, participation in a lab exchange program to gain research experience, and by promoting participation of a diverse group of researchers in various network activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0840869</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dick.78@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wallenstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>matthew.wallenstein@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stromberger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Mary.Stromberger@ColoState.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1181</Code>
      <Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1664</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
