<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Single-Molecule Studies of Surfactant Mobility at the Solid/Solution Interface</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>502000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Analytical and Surface Chemistry (ASC) program of the Division of Chemistry supports the research program of Professor Daniel K. Schwartz of the University of Colorado at Boulder. Prof. Schwartz and his coworkers are developing and employing total internal fluorescence microscopy methods to study the dynamic behavior of individual molecules as they adsorb and move at the solid/liquid interface. They are also developing new methods that can probe molecular proximity and conformation simultaneously as this behavior is studied. This project will lead to a fundamentally new understanding of the way molecules interact with and move on surfaces; this information will impact a number of technological areas, including microarrays for medical diagnostics, catalytic conversion of biomass to biofuels, pharmaceutical separations, and others. Moreover, it will enable advances in nanotechnology -in particular the use of molecular self-assembly to prepare miniaturized structures and devices. The graduate students and postdoctoral researchers who work on this project are trained to become innovative researchers or leaders in the high-tech industry. Through this project, Prof. Schwartz and his coworkers are also providing research training for undergraduate students as well as enrichment opportunities for K-12 students through programs including the Colorado High School Honors Institute and the Science at CU outreach program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0841116</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schwartz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Daniel.Schwartz@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1972</Code>
      <Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1972</Code>
      <Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7203</Code>
      <Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
