<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Exploratory Research: Integration of Multiscale Nanowire Devices and their Thermoelectrical Characterization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>59856</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charalabos C. Doumanidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The main goal of this project is to realize the fabrication of multiscale electric devices based on conducting nanowires and their characterization by using nanomanufacturing principles such as self-assembly, dielectrophoresis, and focused ion beam nanolithography. The objectives include the following tasks:&lt;br/&gt;(a) hierarchical integration of nanowires into multiscale electric devices, and&lt;br/&gt;(b) characterization of individual nanowires in terms of Seebeck coefficient and thermal conductivity.&lt;br/&gt;The self-assembly technique and dielectrophoresis will be combined to control individual nanowires and attract them into desired pairs of microelectrodes. Fountain pen-based metal nanoink soldering or electron-beam metal deposition techniques will be adapted to enhance the conductivity between metal electrodes and nanowires. Focused ion beam will be used to define a nanostructure such as nanoheater/nanothermometer for aiding the characterization of individual nanowires. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The importance of the of the proposed work lies in the fact that the investigation of thermal and electric properties of nanowires will provide a fundamental database for thermoelectric devices, which in turn contributes to developing alternative energy sources. The proposed integration method will provide a practical means for nanomanufacturing massive and multiscale nanowire-based thermoelectric devices. The proposed work yields significant information on the Seebeck and Peltier coefficients of one-dimensional nanostructures. The research outcomes of nanomanufacturing and properties of nanomaterials investigated in the project will contribute to establishing a new research and education program in the recently established Mechanical and Energy Engineering Department at the University of North Texas. A systematic effort will be made to recruit minorities to this research project through the Texas Academy of Mathematics and Science program. Talented undergraduate students with a high degree of financial need in this program are ensured of success as they are engaged in the various research experiences proposed herein.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0841265</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tae-Youl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Choi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tae-youl.choi@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Texas</Name>
      <CityName>DENTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1155 Union Circle #305250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
