<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The role of sediments in the maintenance of biodiversity in freshwater marshes: Implications for global environmental change</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>659308</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saran Twombly</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Freshwater marshes, transition areas between land and water, are critically important in the functioning of watersheds and estuaries. The existence of these ecologically important areas is threatened by rapid environmental changes that disrupt the feedbacks between the physical and biological processes critical to marsh formation. Remote sensing of marsh surface elevations, extensive field observation of the interactions between elevation, sediment dynamics and vegetation, and spatially explicit modeling will be used to forecast the impact of global environmental change on freshwater marsh plant diversity, sediment deposition and erosion, and, hence, the maintenance of complex marsh surfaces in a changing world. The development of coupled geomorphic-ecological models of marsh surface evolution, models which are still uncommon and do not explicitly consider the biological complexity of marsh ecosystems, will be advanced by the interdisciplinary nature of the research. In addition, consideration of spatial processes (landscape heterogeneity, disturbances, and local dispersal of plant propagules), and their impacts on plant biodiversity, will contribute to biodiversity theory. The simultaneous consideration of biodiversity theory and geomorphology is a unique integration of two traditionally separate disciplines that should offer tremendous advances in both fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using a tidal freshwater marsh in the Potomac River estuary as a natural laboratory, results will be used to inform ongoing efforts to restore the study site and freshwater marshes in general. Resource managers and restoration practitioners working to preserve and restore an important marsh ecosystem near the nation's capital will be engaged as partners in this project. Additional outreach will result from participation in a teacher internship program, and training will be provided for graduate students and for young scientists working with senior investigators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0841394</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gardner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gardner@al.umces.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katharina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Engelhardt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kengelhardt@umces.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elmore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aelmore@umces.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Palinkas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cpalinkas@hpl.umces.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>216130775</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4102212014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 775</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1128</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL CLUSTER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1128</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL CLUSTER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1355</Code>
      <Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
