<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Electrochemical Studies of Redox Cofactors in Photosynthetic Reaction Centers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>475171</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David A. Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Photosynthetic systems use reaction center proteins to direct electrons across membranes to convert solar energy into chemical energy. The products of green plant photosynthesis are carbohydrates and oxygen, which form the basis for life on earth. Reaction center proteins are ideal experimental systems for examining these processes because they can be readily isolated, purified, and modified for studies seeking to establish the details of how they function. In addition, reaction centers serve as excellent model systems on which to base solar energy collection devices. This project aims to develop a functional understanding of reaction center proteins in photosynthetic systems utilizing advanced electrochemical studies. Ultrathin films containing the proteins will be used to facilitate electrical communication with electrodes and to provide rapid analysis of the protein-bound charge carriers. Advantages to this approach are that only tiny amounts of protein are required, and the films provide environments similar to that found in nature. Computer simulations of the experimental data will extract basic parameters that characterize key reactions and energies of the photosynthetic charge transfer processes. Such knowledge is critical for understanding how reaction center proteins achieve directional charge transport across membranes to produce carbohydrates and molecular oxygen. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The broader impacts of this project include making fundamental contributions to the understanding of photosynthesis as a basis for the design of novel solar energy conversion devices. New graduate students and existing staff will be supported to assist in the research, thus providing employment for these individuals as an aid to the American economy. The project will provide a rich training ground in modern, interdisciplinary, bioscience research and education for the participants, which if possible will include underrepresented minorities and women. The modern techniques learned and the research experience gained will help to prepare them for productive scientific careers in the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>475171</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0842500</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rusling</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>James.rusling@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Frank</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>harry.frank@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
