<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Ion Pairing and Aggregation of Bis(trifluoromethanesulfonyl) amide Ionic Liquids in Media of Low Polarity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>236329</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program, Professor Markus Hoffmann of The College at Brockport, State University of New York, and his students will investigate the ion pairing and aggregation behavior of ionic liquids dissolved in low polarity solvents. Specific focus will be on ionic liquids containing the bis (trifluoromethansulfonyl) amide anion, which have unusually long ion-pairing lifetimes in these low polarity solvents. The research will employ nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) methods, specifically diffusion ordered spectroscopy (DOSY), to measure molecular diffusion parameters. The NMR data will be augmented by classical viscometric, conductivity and tensiometric measurements. Additional calorimetric studies, done in collaboration with Prof. Dr. Ondruschka and Dr. Stark from the Institute for Technical Chemistry and Environmental Chemistry at the Friedrich-Schiller-University (FSU) in Jena, Germany, are expected to result in a complete thermodynamic description of the ion-pairing and aggregation equilibria.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ionic liquids have been the subject of increasing interest in science and industry because they have the potential to replace traditional organic solvents that are volatile and hazardous. This research will contribute to our fundamental understanding of ionic liquids, and in particular the connection between their intermolecular (and inter-ionic) interactions and their observed bulk behavior. The participating undergraduate students will benefit immensely from the research experiences with respect to their professional preparation. In this regard, the additional involvement of ACS SEED high school students is a valuable contribution to encourage students from underrepresented groups early in their educational development to pursue careers in the sciences. In an attempt to bring the excitement of research into the chemistry curriculum at The College at Brockport some of the experiments will also be integrated as project-based experiments into the physical chemistry laboratory</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0842960</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Markus</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hoffmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mhoffman@brockport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY College at Brockport</Name>
      <CityName>Brockport</CityName>
      <ZipCode>144202932</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5853952444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Foundation of SUNY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
