<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Arboreal snake locomotion: A model system for studying effects of musculoskeletal design and environmental variation on three-dimensional movements</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>422545</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Ellis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will use electromyography, three-dimensional kinematics and force measurements to study the arboreal locomotion of snakes as a model system to better understand axial function of vertebrates and very general features of musculoskeletal systems and motor control. The narrow and cylindrical surfaces, inclines and gaps between branches in complex three-dimensional arboreal environments pose several demands well suited for determining: the limits and tradeoffs for musculoskeletal performance, proximate factors influencing gait selection, and the role of sensory information for modifying motor output and choosing different routes in complex environments. The study species have considerable variation in musculoskeletal anatomy that is universally important for function including: the ratio of tendon to contractile tissue length within muscles, the cross-sectional areas of muscle, total body length to weight, and the numbers and mobility of skeletal joints. This anatomical variation likely reflect tradeoffs between being flexible vs. stiff, strong vs. weak, and heavy vs. light, all of which are generally important as well as specifically relevant for snakes performing the different ecologically relevant tasks of actively bending to conform and grip cylindrical surfaces vs. supporting a body draped loosely over widely spaced branches. One study species is the brown tree snake, which causes costly power outages in Guam, but determining the surfaces that are impassable for this species and obtaining information on route choice and gap-bridging should facilitate managing this destructive invasive species. Interdisciplinary collaborators include a cognitive scientist specializing in the integration of perception and motor control and applied biologists who are attempting to decrease the economic costs of the brown tree snake. The project emphasizes providing opportunities for early career development of biologists from diverse backgrounds, disseminating scientific results to a wide audience including web materials, and providing lectures with an emphasis on evolution for K-12 students and the local community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0843197</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jayne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bruce.jayne@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
      <ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
