<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Outreach Activities for the National Science Foundation?s Innovation Through Institutional Integration (Icubed) Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>349665</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marilyn J. Suiter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Quality Education for Minorities Network&lt;br/&gt;Title: Outreach Activities for NSF?s Innovation through Institutional Integration Initiative&lt;br/&gt;Ref: Shirley McBay&lt;br/&gt; HRD 0844766&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With National Science Foundation support, the Quality Education for Minorities Network (QEM) will provide outreach and technical assistance to minority-serving institutions to increase their knowledge and understanding of the National Science Foundation?s Innovation through Institutional Integration (I-cubed) initiative. The Innovation through Institutional Integration initiative challenges institutions to think strategically about the creative integration of NSF-funded awards and is itself an integrative, cross-cutting effort within the Directorate for Education and Human Resources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;QEM will conduct six two-day information and technical assistance workshops for two-person teams form minority-serving institutions. The workshops will be held in geographically dispersed areas of the country and are designed to accommodate 144 participants during Fall 2008 and Spring 2009.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The technical assistance offered will enable minority-serving institutions to develop an inventory of current NSF ? and other Federal entity funded STEM projects on their campuses and learn about the mission and key concepts of the I-cubed program. The technical assistance will enable participants to critically examine intra- and inter-institutional opportunities for partnerships, international initiatives, and efforts at critical junctures that have synergistic and integrative potential for advancing STEM research and education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Outcomes of the proposed project include increased participation of the minority-serving institution community in the Innovation through Institutional Integration initiative, as well as enhanced minority-serving institution infrastructure for STEM research and education through innovative and institutional integration. As opportunities provided by the I-cubed program are better understood and minority-serving institutions develop competitive I-cubed proposals, the pool of principal investigators engaged in integrative STEM education and research programs will represent a more diverse source for ideas and talent to improve STEM initiatives.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0844766</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shirley</FirstName>
      <LastName>McBay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smmcbay@qem.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>QUALITY EDUCATION FOR MINORITIES NETWORK</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200362406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026591818</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1796</Code>
      <Text>STEM TALENT EXPANSN PGM (STEP)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
