<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Investigation of Antimicrobial Resistance Genes in the Annotation of Bacillus Anthracis Genomens</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>135678</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Interagency Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funds are being provided to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention via an interagency transfer for a new project on antibiotic resistance and antibiotic gene annotation in the Bacillus anthracis genome. Bacillus anthracis is an important pathogen that is sensitive to many antibiotics. Yet it, curiously, carries genetic coding for resistance to many of these same antibiotics. Through laboratory experiments, this research will determine which of the loci identified as penicillin, tetracycline, or macrolide resistance genes in strains of B. anthracis actually encode a resistance determinant; the incorrect annotations will be corrected based on the verified data. DNA sequences upstream and downstream of the resistance determinants will be analyzed to determine if mobile genetic elements are present. This research will improve the quality and usefulness of B. anthracis genome annotations. The potential for developing a resistant phenotype when the organism is exposed to antimicrobial agents will also be investigated. All corrections to genome annotations will be made available to the scientific community by submission to public databases. Data on gene identification, expression, and associated antimicrobial susceptibility phenotypes will be published in appropriate peer-reviewed journals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will be providing student training in bacterial genetics, bioinformatics, and molecular laboratory techniques. Validated information on antimicrobial resistance genes in biothreat agents is of particular importance to national biodefense. Any potential for resistance must be confirmed and taken into consideration when selecting an antimicrobial agent for widespread distribution and for mass treatment of the public. Any diversity detected and verified in the antimicrobial resistance genes or in the associated DNA sequences will be extremely important in identifying and tracking B. anthracis strains for microbial forensics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0844451</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weigel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Lweigel@cdc.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CDC/CCID/NZVED/BDFBMD/BZB</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303294018</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4046931318</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Clifton Road NE MS C-09</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
