<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Rapid Non-Enzymatic Sample Preparation for Mass Spectrometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Franco Basile at the University of Wyoming is supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program in the Chemistry Division to study a challenging area of an important analytical detection method - mass spectrometry. Specifically, Professor Basile's research centers on the use of non-enzymatic processes (e.g., microwave digestion, pyrolysis, and electrochemistry) as alternatives to typical enzymatic digestion for pre-treatment of biological samples for mass spectrometric analysis. The research combines historical techniques with modern practices. Outcomes of Dr. Basile's work are likely to make a significant contribution to many areas of mass spectrometry. For example, field portable mass spectrometers would greatly benefit from shortened sample preparation protocols and the dramatically reduced need for reagents - focus areas for this research project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Basile integrates aspects of this work with the Summer Research in Analytical Chemistry (SRAC) Program, which includes participation of high school students and their teachers from around the State of Wyoming. The program fosters independent research skills and excitement about science for students, and equips teachers with better understanding of some of the tools used in modern analytical chemistry techniques.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0844694</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Franco</FirstName>
      <LastName>Basile</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>basile@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
      <CityName>Laramie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
      <StateCode>WY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
