<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: A Genomics Approach to Identifying the Factors Influencing Phylogenetic Accuracy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>688129</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maureen M. Kearney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Phylogenetic trees are the foundation of all comparative biology. Because phylogenetic relationships among many groups of organisms are still poorly understood, the identification of the factors compromising accuracy in molecular phylogenies is critical for improving the accuracy of the tree of life. The yeasts represent a superb model to address this question, due to the abundance of genomic data for the group. This project will analyze numerous yeast genomes to: identify the complete set of molecular markers across yeasts; obtain an accurate phylogeny of yeasts; and to identify the factors that negatively influence the phylogenetic utility of certain molecular markers. The outcomes of the proposed research will aid the generation of a more accurate tree of life, and the development of statistical methodology for overcoming the effects of factors that compromise phylogenetic accuracy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The information conveyed by phylogenies is a cornerstone of evolutionary theory, the central organizing principle of biology. However, the meaning of phylogenies is frequently misinterpreted by students and professionals alike. To promote understanding of phylogenetics across the educational continuum, the project will involve (i) training of high school teachers and students on the principles and concepts of phylogenetics, (ii) development of an undergraduate course which will integrate research results into the curriculum of the science classroom and laboratory, and (iii) training of the next generation of scientists in the PI's laboratory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>688129</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0844968</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Antonis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rokas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>antonis.rokas@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
      <CityName>Nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
