<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Experimental Investigation of Highly Nonlinear Granular Crystals for the Development of New Mechanical Systems and Acoustic Metamaterials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>418000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Siegmund</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) project is creating and understanding new metamaterials based on engineered, ordered granular crystals. Metamaterials are artificially composite systems, having their fundamental components (for example spherical grains) arranged in precise geometrical structures, that present properties not found in other natural systems. It will study how stress waves propagate in these new materials with experiments, and will develop numerical and analytical models to predict their behavior. It will research wave behavior at interfaces and will study the interplay of discrete effects and periodicity, disorder and localization, creating parallels with other physical phenomena. The understanding provided by studying these new materials will allow the creation of novel devices like tunable acoustic lenses, vibration absorbers, energy traps and actuators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The societal impact of this work can be identified with the potential discovery of new systems that will affect everyday life (i.e. new acoustic methods for imaging/surgery, protective systems and signal transformation/redistribution in communication). It will also offer a great educational platform: creating and understanding new mechanical systems requires learning how to balance in depth fundamental physics with imagination, inspiring young generation to ?think out-of-the-box?. It will engage graduate, undergraduate, and high school students in several cooperative activities combining groundbreaking studies with the development of practical applications and patentable devices. It will particularly emphasize undergraduate education, motivating women and underrepresented groups toward science. The multidisciplinary aspects of this work will foster collaborations with other research institutions, with industry and with the broader community. The proposed plan will create two new academic courses and will organize summer schools with strong international emphasis.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/29/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0844540</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chiara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Daraio</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Daraio@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/29/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1630</Code>
      <Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>027E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9231</Code>
      <Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
