<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Information Theory and Coding for Wireless Broadcast Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>phillip regalia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009&lt;br/&gt;(Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CAREER: Information Theory and Coding for Wireless Broadcast Networks&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broadcast is a fundamental nature of wireless communication. With appropriate coding architecture, the broadcast nature of wireless communication can be used to the advantage of simultaneously transmitting to several receivers at high rates. Most of the previous work focused on the following two scenarios: 1) to deliver the same message to each of the receivers; 2) to deliver completely different messages to different receivers. Between these two ?extreme? broadcast scenarios, there is a rich collection of ?intermediate? problems with message sets of interesting configuration and significant engineering appeal. Understanding the limits and the appropriate coding architectures of broadcast networks with general message set configurations is a relatively unexplored challenge that must be addressed to fully harness the broadcast advantage of wireless communication.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research takes a fundamental information-theoretic view of broadcast networks to shed insight into what coding architectures are appropriate for different message set configurations. An important component of this study is the focus on concrete and physically motivated models of wireless network communication. Of particular interest is to understand the impact of multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) communication. Specifically, this research studies: 1) the impact of message set configuration on the appropriate coding architecture of wireless broadcast networks; 2) secrecy communication under physically motivated models; and 3) the value of receiver message side information for broadcast network communication. The research program is complemented by an educational effort to train the next generation of engineers to become skilled in the design of wireless networks, which involves developing a new course on information theory for wireless systems and writing an accompanied textbook.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>400000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0845848</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tieliu@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7937</Code>
      <Text>NETWORK CODING AND INFO THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
