<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Advanced Silicon-Germanium Nanowire Heterostructures Combining Band Structure Engineering and Modulation Doping</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>464249</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tania Paskova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical: This CAREER award includes a multifaceted research project on silicon and germanium nanowires and heterostructures. The research plan aims to develop novel Si/Ge heterostructures at the nanoscale using bottom up growth techniques, to investigate their intrinsic electronic properties (e.g. carrier mobility, carrier concentration), and to design and fabricate novel, one-dimensional electronic devices with high electron mobility. Specifically, the research will address the following vectors in the area of nanowire growth and fabrication: (1) Design and grow high mobility one-dimensional electron systems using radial band-structure engineering and modulation doping in Si/Ge core/shell structures. (2) Develop new methods to fabricate low resistance contacts to semiconductor nanowires, which will make it possible to explore the intrinsic electronic properties, as well as to enable high performance nanowire transistors. (3) Investigate the magneto-transport properties of nanowire devices down to low temperature as a spectroscopic method, and in particular to measure electron density and intrinsic mobility.&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic research issues in a topical area of materials science with high technological relevance. Silicon and germanium nanowires represent a particularly attractive platform for future device fabrication at the nanoscale because of their compatibility to the current electronics architecture: complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS). The project offers an excellent opportunity for training of students in an interdisciplinary environment. Through this CAREER, the PI will integrate the results of his research activities with the courses taught at the undergraduate and graduate level, and with outreach activities and events; include undergraduate students as participants in the proposed research activities, with an emphasis on diversity; and inspire hundreds of K-12 underrepresented students in outreach activities and events organized in collaboration with the Women in Engineering Program at the University of Texas in Austin.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0846573</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Emanuel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tutuc</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>etutuc@mer.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
