<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Experimental studies of the rheology and flow properties of liquefied biomass in wall-bounded turbulent flows</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitrios Papavassiliou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0846359 &lt;br/&gt;White&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Better understanding of the fundamental fluid physics of liquefied biomass in wall-bounded turbulent flows is of practical importance for the scale-up of biorefineries and the design of biomass pipelines. Both are needed to accomplish the United States biofuel objective of providing 30% of the nation's transportation fuels with biofuels. To meet the goals of the project, The PI plans to improve the temporal and spatial resolution of ultrasound correlation velocimetry, evaluate the rheology and structure of liquefied biomass fluids, and characterize wall-bounded turbulent biomass flows. These studies will provide previously unobtainable information that will enable predictive estimations of the transport of liquefied biomass in wall-bounded turbulent flows. The role of turbulence in energy sector technologies will be the theme of the educational and outreach activities. Drawing on the research topics, the objective is to educate students and educators through industrial research opportunities, workshops, and outreach that understanding the effects of turbulence and their control is critically important to current and future energy systems. The broader impacts of the research are to acquire and transfer fundamental knowledge to allow greater use of 'homegrown' renewable fuels in the US; acquire and improve a UCV system allowing the study of a variety of other rheological, multiphase, opaque fluid flow problems; and attract and train highly qualified students interested in the fields of energy, turbulence, and complex fluids. Integration of education and research activities is achieved by offering industrial research opportunities for the PI's graduate students, syllabus enrichment, K-12 outreach, continuing education, and participating in University outreach days by including lab tours and demonstrations. Lastly, the PI will actively recruit target minorities to work in his labs and potential Ph.D. students through Project REIS@UNH (Research Experience In Science at UNH), a collaboration between UNH and the Harlem Children Society; and postings in several publications targeting minority populations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0846359</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>White</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chris.white@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Hampshire</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6038622172</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
      <StateCode>NH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
