<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Efficient Monte Carlo Methods in Engineering and Science: From Coarse Analysis to Refined Estimators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>409950</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sheldon Jacobson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) project is to investigate and develop a framework that exploits asymptotic analysis, expressed at a coarse scale, to systematically generate efficient rare-event simulation algorithms for complex stochastic systems, which must necessarily be implemented at a fine scale. The objective is to study five types of environments that exhibit stylized features that have not been well studied in rare-event simulation, namely, a) Stochastic recursions with heavy-tails (which are used to model insurance risk and reservoir processes), b) Heavy-tailed queues (which arise in database and networking applications), c) Counting problems and inference for combinatorial structures (arising in sociology and biology), d) Location of objects immersed in a random medium (with particular emphasis on military applications where one needs to find targets that have eluded detection for long time), and e) Random fields (which arise in settings such as oceanography, environmental studies and medical imaging). The strategy consists in connecting large deviations analysis with algorithmic design of efficient simulation estimators. A key tool that we exploit in the design and performance analysis of our algorithms is a systematic use of Lyapunov bounds for Markov chains, combined with parametric families of importance sampling distributions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Events such as environmental or natural disasters, major market crashes, pension and insurance breakdowns and terrorist attacks are rare but consequential. If successful, the proposed research program will provide efficient computational tools for risk assessment of such events which exhibit features such as heavy-tails, complex dependence and incorporation of combinatorial objects. Efficient evaluation of rare-event probabilities can provide decision makers with key quantitative policy assessment metrics and accompanying insights. Examples include computing the probability that a target is able to evade a set of detectors as well as its conditional most likely location, and assessing ruin probabilities for purposes of sizing the capital reserve of insurance and financial companies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/29/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0846816</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blanchet</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jose.blanchet@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/29/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0107000</Code>
      <Name>Operations Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5514</Code>
      <Text>OPERATIONS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>073E</Code>
      <Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>072E</Code>
      <Text>NETWORKS &amp; QUEUING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>077E</Code>
      <Text>SIMULATION MODELS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
