<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER:Integrated Research and Education on Nano Ionic Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) project is to advance high throughput electrochemical manufacturing with nanoscale precision. Experimental characterization and numerical modeling will be developed on the mechanics and transport properties of the solid electrolyte stamp that governs the atomic scale dissolution and growth at the interface. This enhanced understanding of fundamental science, will enable confinement and control of the ionic transport in this novel nanomanufacturing process in a programmable manner. Finally, a set of nanodevices for energy conversion and for advanced imaging will be demonstrated using this novel manufacturing process.&lt;br/&gt;The envisioned solid state electrochemical manufacturing technology promise cost-effective and versatile process tools to fabricate metallic and ceramic nanostructures in a single step. The success of this project will enable practical applications of electronic, biomedical, photonics, and energy conversion devices. The educational objectives of the CAREER project are focused on providing new career perspectives for a new generation of students towards the nanomanufacturing arena. Integrated with the research activities of this nano-ionic manufacturing project are development of new graduate courses and summer research programs of nanomanufacturing. To attract woman and minority in high schools to engineering discipline, a new project Art Through the Mind of a Engineer will be developed. The PI also plans to strengthen ongoing outreach activities with high school science teachers to demonstrate science and engineering concepts involved in implementing novel nanomanufacturing tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0846771</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nicfang@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
