<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on GeoSpatial and GeoTemporal Informatics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Workshop on GeoSpatial and GeoTemporal Informatics (GSTI'08) focuses on geo-spatial and geo-temporal informatics. The motivation for the organization of this workshop comes from the substantial challenges posed to traditional geoinformatics by the emergence of novel technological devices, artifacts and methodologies, including (but not limited to) sensors and sensor deployment techniques (e.g., geosensor networks, video cameras on-board unmanned aerial vehicles, hand-held devices and more). These innovations represent the rapid evolution of the traditional static and centralized geocomputational paradigm. They are drastically changing the types of data that are collected, analyzed, and disseminated, they are broadening the applications in which these datasets are used, and they are also expanding the corresponding user community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In order to address this evolution and its impact on the future of science and engineering research and ultimately on the needs of society, the workshop will bring together a number of leading researchers from the US and overseas. The objective is to identify the emerging major challenges in geospatial and geotemporal informatics, and to make relevant recommendations to the scientific community, anticipating future needs and demands. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research challenges addressed by GSTI'08 extend the frontiers of traditional geospatial research, addressing computer science issues such as spatiotemporal queries over diverse data feeds, mobile computing, location-based services, streaming data integration and mining, automated updating of geospatial databases, VR modeling, and computer vision. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GSTI'08 Workshop is to be held in the Washington, DC metropolitan area in the fall of 2008. The workshop is expected to have significant impact by identifying research areas that need to be pursued in order to support and respond to emerging and predicted societal needs. The workshop results, including a report, will be widely disseminated via the Web site (http://www.ggs.cos.gmu.edu/workshops/GSTI-08/) and other venues.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0847881</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peggy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Agouris</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pagouris@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Mason University</Name>
      <CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
