<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Metallonitrene/Alkyne Metathesis and Beyond: Transition Metal Catalyzed Oxidative Amination For Organic Synthesis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is directed toward the discovery of new chemistry for catalytic C-N, C-C and C-O bond formation using high oxidation state transition metals with reactive nitrenoid or amide ligands and the application of these new methods to the synthesis of chemically and medicinally relevant targets. As an integral part of this research we aim to establish an in depth understanding of the requirements for the formation of reactive metallonitrenes and understand how different transition metals and their ligand environments affect the reactivity of the nitrene ligands. Complementing the tangible scientific and technological gains arising from the successful implementation of this research program is the implicit development of human potential and education of our next generation of scientific leaders. Although a prominent educational component of this program involves the advanced scientific training of graduate students in an environment that fosters creativity and rigor, this project will also encompass efforts by the P.I. to develop and implement new curriculum and pedagogy at the undergraduate level, with a focus on scientific method and problem solving as a means of understanding fundamental organic chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor Simon Blakey of the Department of Chemistry at Emory University. Professor Blakey's research efforts revolve around the development of new cascade reactions for the formation of selected chemical bonds between carbon, nitrogen and oxygen, building complex molecular architecture from simple building blocks. These reactions are expected to be transformative, with the potential to impact the discovery of new medicines, streamline processes for the large scale synthesis of important nitrogen containing compounds and access new functional motifs for applications in materials chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0847258</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Simon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blakey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sblakey@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Emory University</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
