<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Electron Injection in Nanostructured Materials: New Paradigm of Transparent Conducting Oxides</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Z. Charles Ying</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;Technical: This CAREER project includes integrated research and education activities. The research explores novel nanocomposite materials that allow independent control of the carrier concentration and mobility of transparent conducting oxides for potential electro-optical applications. This will be accomplished through the self-assembly of high carrier concentration metallic nanoparticles in high mobility transparent conducting oxide materials. The project examines how microstructure and morphology of embedded nanoparticles influence the electrical and optical properties of such systems and determines the fundamental mechanisms responsible for the improved conductivity. The goals of the research activities are: i) Establishment of fundamental correlations between basic physics of nanocomposite based transparent conducting oxides and experimental observations of improved electrical conductivity and transparency; ii) Development of a basic understanding of the electron delocalization of metal nanoparticles embedded in a transparent conducting oxide matrix with different electronic and optical properties; and iii) Elucidation of the influence of solid-ion interactions on the nucleation, growth, and subsequent crystallization of nanoparticles embedded transparent conducting oxide films.&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: The project addresses basic electronic/photonic materials research issues in a topical area of materials science with high technological relevance. Improvements in transparent conducting oxide conductivity have the potential to increase the energy conversion efficiencies of solar cells as well as increase the speed and energy efficiency of optoelectronic devices. The educational component of this CAREER award is expected to enhance the infrastructure of the renewable energy research at the University of Pittsburgh. The PI plans to develop a new course, Energy Applications of Nanostructured Materials, focusing on the correlation between solar energy and nanomaterials. This course is expected to be integrated with a new Nanotechnology Certificate at the University of Pittsburgh, which should make the Materials Science and Engineering program at the University more visible in nanoscience and sustainability educations. In addition, the results obtained through research activities will be utilized to develop a prototype solar cell for outreach to high school students with an emphasis on under-represented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>400000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0847319</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jung-Kun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jul37@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
