<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Electrochemical Oxidation and Sensing/Molecular Electronics Applications of Chemically- and Electrochemically-Synthesized Metal Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Francis P. Zamborini of the University of Louisville is supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry to study the electrochemical reactivity and oxidation potential of silver and gold nanostructures as a function of size, shape, and surface chemistry. A second thrust of this supported research is to electrochemically synthesize Silver nanowires for sensing and molecular electronics applications. The proposed nanostructures will be characterized by spectroscopic, electrochemical and microscopic techniques. This research will lead to a better understanding of the effect of the size and shape of chemically and electrochemically synthesized nanostructures on the oxidation potential and the mechanisms of electron transfer at these nanoscale dimensions, which will push the field forward towards technological applications in miniaturized electronics, chemical sensing, and catalysis. Graduate and undergraduate students will participate in all aspects of the proposed research, and high school students will participate through outreach activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848883</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zamborini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>f.zamborini@louisville.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/06/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Louisville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>402021959</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5028523788</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>The Nucleus</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
