<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Feeding and exciting bone cells with interstitial fluid movement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Krastan B. Blagoev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project the PI will measure the permeability of the lacunar-canalicular bone porosity and will develop a poroelastic model to predict the interchange of interstitial fluid between the lacunar-canalicular porosity and the much larger pore size vascular porosity in normal, cyclic, whole body motion (e.g., walking). The techniques for accomplishing these measurements have been explored in a pilot study. The development of a poroelastic model to predict the interchange of interstitial fluid between the lacunar-canalicular porosity and the much larger pore size vascular porosity in normal, cyclic, whole body motion introduces a new concept of nested pore space structures. Understanding bone mechanotransduction is fundamental to the understanding of how to treat osteoporosis, how to cope with microgravity in long term manned space flight and how to design prostheses that are implanted in bone tissue to function for longer periods. The research project will involve CCNY and City Tech students, students at the CCNY High School for Math, Science and Engineering as well as students at M.S. 319, the Maria Teresa Maribal School. The NYC professional community interested in bone health will be kept abreast of research developments in the public NYC Bone Seminar Series.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848491</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cowin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sccowin@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY City College</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
