<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Summit on Measuring the Impacts of Project-Based Service Learning on Engineering Education to be held February 19-20, 2009, in Washington, DC.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>66806</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell L. Pimmel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Engineering - Other (59)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to explore the impacts of project-based service learning (PBSL) on engineering education. Central to this study is a summit on the measurement of these impacts with twenty leaders in engineering PBSL and assessment attending. Equally important to the study is the creation of a pre-summit report on the state of PBSL in engineering education with an emphasis on evaluation. This document, a synthesis of evidence in the literature and information from summit participants, provides a broad review of existing PBSL programs, their impacts, and the assessment methods used in studying them. The summit agenda is designed to identify desired outcome metrics, quality assessment methods, and key next steps needed in understanding the impacts of PBSL on engineering education. The pre-summit and summit findings are being combined into a nationally disseminated final report and presented in several conference presentations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0848636</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kurtis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Paterson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paterskg@jmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
      <CityName>Houghton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
