<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Design and synthesis of new (electro-active) ladder and helical polyphenylene motifs for molecular wires</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>387490</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation supports Professor Rajendra Rathore of Marquette University in a research project that will integrate the disciplines of synthetic organic chemistry, molecular recognition, and material science. The aim is to study and exploit new cofacially-stacked benzenoid structures that can be potentially utilized to develop various electronic and optoelectronic devices in the emerging field of nanotechnology. The study of the proposed novel molecules, using various spectroscopic techniques including time-resolved spectroscopy, will help to expand the understanding of through-space electronic coupling between cofacially arrayed phenylenes and eventually lead to functional materials for practical applications. The design and synthesis of new cofacially-stacked polyphenylene structures presents an important step that will lead to the development of a variety of new molecular and supramolecular nanostructures that will achieve photoinduced charge separation over long distances with high quantum efficiency and will create exciting challenges for future research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposed research will present opportunities for high quality training for both graduate and undergraduate students in multidisciplinary research. Professor Rathore has shown a commitment to broadening participation by the inclusion of women and underrepresented groups in his group through active recruitment of these students. Marquette University has established close ties with Alcorn State University, a Historically Black University (HBCU), from which a number of graduate students have been recruited. By continuing to publsh his research in high quality journals, Professor Rathore will significantly impact the field of organic electronics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>387490</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0848871</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rajendra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rathore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rajendra.rathore@marquette.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Marquette University</Name>
      <CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4142887200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 1881</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
