<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Collaborative Research - Mechanisms behind non-Redfieldian P Cycling in Water Masses of the Southern Ocean, New Insights from X-ray Spectromicroscopy and Electrodialysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>47549</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter J. Milne</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In much of the global ocean the (Redfield) ratio of nitrogen (N) to P is remarkably constant, both in the concentrations of these nutrients in seawater and in the plankton species that it supports. A number of studies of sub-Antarctic mode water, a convectively formed descending water type identifiably by its exceptionally uniform properties, suggest that high latitude P cycling is altered from the Redfield balance resulting in unusually enriched P compared to low latitude waters . &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Synchrotron based x-ray spectromicroscopy will be used to chemically characterize and spatially map, at sub micron dimensions, the abundance of several P forms (e.g. polyphosphates, organo-P compounds) in organisms and marine particulates. These samples will be taken along the cruise track of the I/B Oden as it transits from Punta Arenas to McMurdo Station, through the Bellingshausen, Amundsen and Ross Sea regions,and which will provide a unique data set from a remote and understudied ice shelf and under-ice ecosystem. Characterization of Antarctic ocean P status is expected to shed further light upon aspects of Southern Ocean P biogeochemistry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As well as using novel characterization techniques, which may lead to a transformative restatement of aspects of Southern Ocean P chemistry, this project meets an additional SGER criteria of representing a quick response to an international field campaign opportunity afforded by the transect of the Swedish ice breaker I/B Oden from Punta Arenas to McMurdo through the Bellingshausen, Amundsen and Ross Seas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0849474</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brandes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jay.brandes@skio.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Skidaway Institute of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>Savannah</CityName>
      <ZipCode>314111011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9125982400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 Ocean Science Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0311000</Code>
      <Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5113</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
