<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Insight from Lamprey Genome: Investigations of the GnRH-GTH System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>444000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will emphasize approaches to studying brain hormones and receptors that utilize new methodologies that are becoming available through the disciplines of hormonal genomics and proteomics, and presenting themselves through knowledge of basal vertebrate systems. Based on previous and present findings, this research will include novel studies using established techniques and developing complementary molecular techniques to, in part, increase the understanding and insight into the molecular and functional evolution of brain and pituitary hormones and receptors. The studies will focus on the molecular, biochemical and functional studies of brain gonadotropin releasing hormone and pituitary gonadotropins in lampreys to test the overall hypothesis that these hormones and their receptor(s) share common functional and developmental features compared to later evolved vertebrates. The research will examine the roles that modifications in interactive cellular networks, represented by genes and their products (hormones, receptors, and signaling molecules), have on biological function from the perspectives of molecular, cellular, and systems biology. This research has and will include graduate and undergraduate students who will be trained and involved in all aspects of this project. Outreach activities will include presentations to the general public at different kinds of forums such as the annual NH Sea Lamprey Appreciation Day as well as collaborations with investigators from other institutions. In addition, the PI and her laboratory will continue their collaborations with students and staff at New Hampshire Technical Community College (NHCTC) and students at UNH.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0849569</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stacia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sower</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sasower@cisunix.unh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Hampshire</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6038622172</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
      <StateCode>NH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
