<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Opportunities and Challenges in Uncertainty Quantification for Complex Interacting Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75696</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Manish Parashar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Workshop on Opportunities and Challenges in Uncertainty Quantification for Complex Interacting Systems, to be held at the University of Southern California in the early part of 2009, will provide a forum where issues of uncertainty quantification and model validation in predictive science will be addressed. The Workshop will bring together leading scientists from physics-based modeling, network science and social networks to explore the fundamental similarities and differences in the challenges facing them. The gradient in the level of maturity and scientific opportunities provided by these three themes will serve to drive knowledge mixing and transfer between all participants. Challenges and opportunities will be identified and a community of researchers and collaborators seeded. This Workshop will greatly accelerate the maturity of these methods and bring them, much faster, to a point where they can fulfill their promise as an enabling technologies for economic growth and societal sustainability.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0849537</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghanem</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ghanem@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
