<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative:Development of a Hydrogen Discriminating Low Temperature 1-D Nanocomposite Microsensor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this collaborative proposal is to realize fast, sensitive and discriminating detection of hydrogen detection at room temperature using a novel nanomaterial integrated microsensor. The approach is based on one dimensional porous nanostructures and array architectures of conducting oxides. The nanostructures will be prepared by sol-gel processing, electrospinning and fast laser induced self-organization while the sensor platform will be prepared by lithographic approaches.&lt;br/&gt; The intellectual merit of this work will come from the application of fundamental scientific and engineering principles of nanofabrication, materials chemistry and electronics to novel sensor design. Specifically, understanding the relationships between one dimensional nanostructure, its architecture, oxide chemistry, and electronic response will permit a quantitative basis for design and fabrication of fast and sensitive metal oxide semiconductor sensors at the nanoscale.&lt;br/&gt; The broader impact will come from cutting-edge interdisciplinary research and education activities in science and engineering across two institutions and neighboring schools involving underrepresented undergraduates, graduates and K-12 students/teachers. This project will ensure training of next-generation scientists and engineers in the areas of critical national need. The training and educational programs will equip the students with knowledge and skills for the integrated use of bottom-up nanomaterial synthesis and top-down device design approaches. Considering the recent public awareness on the need of clean alternative energy, the NSF support for this hydrogen sensor research provide a novel scientific and engineering springboard for the cost-effective design and fabrication of such sensors, that are crucial for storage, transportation, and distribution of hydrogen as an energy source.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0850574</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ramki</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kalyanaraman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ramki@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/10/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
