<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collapse of the Submarine South Flank of Kilauea Volcano, Hawaii: Constraints from GPS-Acoustic Data</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>92055</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard L. Carlson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Collapse of the flanks of ocean island volcanoes poses several significant hazards, including earthquakes and tsunamis. The south flank of Kilauea is a currently active volcanic collapse feature. There is evidence that Kilauea's south flank is rapidly moving seaward, with attendant risk of large earthquakes and/or tsunami. In addition to the obvious need to understand and monitor this potential hazard, Kilauea is a natural laboratory for studying the mechanics of the collapse process. The emerging model of the process at Kilauea is constrained by onshore GPS (Global Positioning System) measurements, offshore seismic profiles and vertical deformation of the seafloor measured by GPS-Acoustic methods. However, horizontal motions are not well constrained. This project will provide additional constraints by using new methods to estimate horizontal motions using GPS-Acoustic data collected in previous years. New processing approaches are expected yield horizontal resolutions of 0.7 to 2.2 cm/yr. Well resolved horizontal displacements will be used to test and refine models of the collapse process. In terms of broader impacts this work has obvious implications and application to the significant risks that arise from the instability of this flank of Kilauea and similar sites elsewhere. Improving GPS-Acoustic methods will also contribute the broader impacts of this work, as will training a young scientist.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0850875</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>C. David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chadwell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cchadwell@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/05/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
