<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Molecular Biosciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>430892</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). The University of California -- San Francisco (UCSF) REU Site will provide a research program for undergraduates during the summers of 2009-2012. Ten students will be selected each year to participate in a ten-week program in the area of molecular biosciences, specifically biochemistry, cell biology, genetics and genomics. The REU program combines an outstanding laboratory research experience with activities designed to foster scientific communication and facilitate a transition to graduate school. The programs will take place at Mission Bay, a state-of-the-art research facility housing more than 200 research laboratories. The centerpiece of the UCSF summer research program is an intensive laboratory research experience in which students are paired, based on their research interest, with UCSF faculty mentors. Students receive hands-on training using cutting edge biological techniques to creatively solve problems in modern biology. The research program includes daily interaction with a graduate/PhD level research co-mentor, faculty research presentations, a mentored journal club component, and oral/poster research presentations. The second component of the REU program is a co-curriculum designed to foster scientific communication skills, increase scientific breadth, and prepare students for the graduate school admissions process. The co-curriculum includes faculty-led sessions focused on preparing a graduate school application, interviewing skills, scientific oral and poster presentation skills, and a workshop focused on issues related to diversity in the biological sciences. An optional GRE preparation course is available. In addition, students will have the opportunity to share their research experiences and mentoring skills with high school-level summer interns at UCSF. The program culminates with widely attended student poster and oral research presentations. Students will be recruited nationally and applications from under-represented minority and disadvantaged (economically or first in college) students are strongly encouraged. Students receive a stipend, dormitory-style housing, travel to and from the program, passes for local public transit and access to free campus transportation services. Further information and application materials are available on the program website: http://saawww.ucsf.edu/diversity/REU, or by contact The Program Director, Dr. Carol Gross, or the Program Coordinator, Kalai Diamond, at (415) 514-0840, Kalai.Diamond@ucsf.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>430892</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0851539</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gross</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cgross@cgl.ucsf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/29/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Francisco</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941034249</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4154762977</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1855 Folsom St Ste 425</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
