<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Paleontological Investigations to Recover Fossil Monkeys from the Middle Cenozoic of South America</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>172470</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carolyn Ehardt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;The pattern of monkey evolution in South America is poorly documented and little understood. Some argue that New World monkeys (Platyrrhini) known from 16-20 million year old rocks of Patagonia predate the origins of the modern families, that is, they are 'stem platyrrhines'. Others argue that they are early representatives of the modern platyrrhine families. The two alternative interpretations have profound implications for how the evolutionary radiation of platyrrhines is viewed. Further fossil material of early platyrrhines will contribute to resolving this debate. A joint team of US and Argentine paleontologists will search for fossil primates in ~16 million-year-old rocks of the Santa Cruz Formation and its equivalents in Patagonian Argentina. Collecting will concentrate on proven localities and expand collecting efforts to other lesser-known sites said to be richly fossiliferous from the Atlantic coast inland to the Andean front at 50-55 degrees South latitude. &lt;br/&gt;Analysis of the existing materials and recovery of even more complete specimens of primates will offer a rare insight about the phylogeny and adaptations of these early anthropoid primates. A phylogenetic analysis will clarify the pattern of diversification of South American platyrrhine monkeys and help to refine hypotheses about the origins of the modern platyrrhines families. To reconstruct adaptive profile of the various extinct species, a team of scientists from the US, Argentina and Brazil will study various aspects of the teeth, skulls and limb bones to reconstruct important details of the each species' adaptation and life history. &lt;br/&gt;Collections of other faunal remains by the field group will fill out the environmental context in which early platyrrhines evolved. A second team of research specialists headed by the Argentine scientists will study the functional anatomy and ecomorphology of non-primate fossils. Much work already has been undertaken to study the sloths and armadillos. Using these established approaches as a model, the research group will extend this work to encompass other major mammal groups including rodents, notoungulates, and marsupials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0851272</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rfkay@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
