<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Euromembrane 2009, to be held in Montpellier, France September 6-10, 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12300</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0852751&lt;br/&gt;Noble&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Travel funds are requested to partially support the US participation in the Euromembrane Conference September 6-10, 2009, in Montpellier France. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;EUROMEMBRANE 2009 is organized by the European Membrane Institute IEM, (http://www.iemm.univ-montp2.fr) in cooperation with the National Graduate School of Chemistry (ENSCM) and the University Montpellier 2 (UM2). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the conference is to bring together research and practitioners to discuss the most recent developments in the field of polymer, hybrid and inorganic membranes through oral and poster presentations, and formal and informal discussions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;EUROMEMBRANE 2009 is expected to gather more than 500 participants. Previous sessions had participants which were approximately 60% from Europe, 15% from the US and Asia, and approximately 10% from other countries. Approximately 35-40 US academic researchers are expected for EUROMEMBRANE 2009. The total expenses for attending the conference are estimated at $2600 - $3000 per US participant. The NSF funds will be used to support roughly 25% of the total student travel costs and 10% of the travel costs for the faculty. Preference will be given to academics that give presentations and students that give a poster or oral presentations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Faculty and student support will have broad impacts as it will increase the international visibility of U.S. Universities, demonstrate the high level of student research in the U.S., and help to attract an upcoming young generation of professionals to the rapidly growing areas of membrane science and technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0852751</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Noble</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nobler@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1417</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL &amp; BIOLOGICAL SEPAR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>052E</Code>
      <Text>MAT &amp; PROC FOR CHEM SEPARATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
