<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Agricultural Science Summer Undergraduate Research Education and Development Program (ASSURED)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The New Mexico State University's Chile Pepper Institute will provide a research program for undergraduates during summers of 2009-2011. Ten students will be selected to participate in a 10-week research program, called Agricultural Science Summer &amp; Research Education and Development (ASSURED). Students will conduct research in genomics, plant science and agriculture. The goal of the program is to have underrepresented first generation college students from immigrant farm labor families expand their appreciation of agricultural science in a university, research-rich context. Students engage in research that explores questions relevant to agricultural science and learn about various careers available in agriculture from research in genetics and microbiology to crop production. In the ASSURED research environment, students take real life situations and apply the scientific method to the discovery process. Students learn from mentors and contribute to the research program of the mentors. Student projects include genetics, breeding, plant physiology, insect control, economics, weed control, agricultural engineering, and many others. Weekly group meetings, workshops and lectures cover ethical conduct in research, career choices, and others. The students are required to prepare an oral presentation, a poster presentation and a written report on their research findings. Students with disabilities are also eligible for the program. More information is available by visiting http://www.chilepepperinstitute.org/agricultural-science-sum.html, or by contacting the Program Director, Dr. Paul Bosland, at 575-646-3028 or hotchile@nmsu.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0852044</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hamilton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whamilto@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/04/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bosland</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pbosland@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/04/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
      <CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
      <ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
