<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research at CLEO-c</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>561000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Randal Ruchti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will fund the on going research program of the Wayne State University Elementary Particle Physics group on analyses of the CLEO-c data. The group consists of two faculty, Professors Bonvicini and Cinabro, and three graduate students working towards their PhD degrees. The NSF supported the group participation in the construction and operation of the CLEO detector as well as data taking. This research grant will enable the continuation the group analysis effort and allow them to complete the physics analysis of the CLEO-c data. The Analysis effort concentrate on the studies of three body charm decays using the Dalitz technique, measurements of D D-bar mixing parameters taking advantage of the quantum correlations of the D mesons produced at CLEO, and in rare charm decays. The three graduate students will concentrate on searches for higher order Fock states in rare semi-leptonic D decays and correlated Dalitz plot studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant will also support the extensive involvement of the group in undergraduate student's research via an REU/RET program. This program achieves its intrinsic goals of promoting undergraduate and younger student interest in careers in science, technology, and engineering, especially among the under-represented, and making connections with K/12 teachers. The group found that in addition the students and teachers in the program have been able to make a significant contribution to their research effort.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0852719</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cinabro</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.cinabro@wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Giovanni</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bonvicini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>giovanni@physics.wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wayne State University</Name>
      <CityName>Detroit</CityName>
      <ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5057 Woodward</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1221</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
