<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Control of atoms-light and nuclei-X-ray photons interactions in solids via quantum interference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>385000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ann Orel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research program explores the physics of quantum coherence effects in optical crystals doped with rare-earth or transition metal ions. Such ions have atomic like structure of discrete energy levels in the band gap of the host materials. They are often refereed to as atomic gas lattices or frozen atomic gases. Their potential advantages are high atomic density, absence of atomic diffusion and collisions, compactness, scalability, robustness and compatibility with optical fiber communications. We study the possibilities of the efficient control of both linear and nonlinear optical responses (such as resonant absorption, refractive index, group velocity, frequency conversion, etc.) based on excitation of the long lived spin coherence in these materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of the broader impact the research program extends fundamental concepts of atomic and quantum optics to solid-state physics. The exploration of quantum coherence phenomena in solids may open realistic prospects for various applications, including quantum information storage and processing, improvement of spatial resolution, controllable optical delay lines, development of new solid-state lasers (in particular, in the traditionally difficult UV, VUV and X-ray frequency ranges), efficient frequency conversion, generation of ultimately short pulses, ultra-sensitive magnetometry, spectroscopy, metrology, and others. It provides excellent opportunities for young researchers to be trained both theoretically and experimentally in the advanced fields of quantum, coherent, nonlinear and ultrafast optics, photonics, solid-state and laser physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0855668</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Olga</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kocharovskaya</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kochar@physics.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
