<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: Third International Symposium on Nanotechnology in Construction; Prague, Czech Republic; May 31-June 2, 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>lawrence bank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This travel grant is to provide partial funding for a group of US engineers and scientists attend the NICOM3 conference to be held in Prague, Czech Republic on May 31 - June 2, 2009. This is the 3rd International Symposium on Nanotechnology in Construction. The last of these conferences was held in Bilbao, Spain in November, 2005. This will be the third in this series of conferences, held every few years. For the NICOM2 conference in Bilbao, the NSF supported the attendance of a number of US engineers and scientists to permit them to gain exposure to the extensive applications of nanotechnology in construction materials being performed in Europe and the rest of the world. In addition to the attendance of numerous engineers and scientists working in the field, there are also numerous companies in concrete-related industries that are in attendance. A diverse group of participants has been nominated for selection that have experience in nanotechnology and, in many cases, are relatively new to this area of research, so that they can particularly benefit from exposure to engineers and scientists who are strongly involved in current advances in nanotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/03/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0855034</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schweitzer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schweitz@phys.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kurtis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kkurtis@ce.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Konstantin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sobolev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sobolev@uwm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
