<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Radio telescopes and gravitational-wave observatories: Two windows on the same Universe</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>80000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). Over the past few decades, radio astronomy has replaced our serene, optical view of stars and galaxies with a more dynamic one of exotic objects and violent phenomena. Today we are on the verge of another revolution in astronomy, as a new generation of observatories prepare to make the first detections of an entirely new spectrum of radiation: gravitational waves. This project will advance the fields of both radio and gravitational-wave astronomy through a series of coordinated observations between the world's largest radio observatories (the Arecibo and Green Bank radio telescopes), and the most sensitive gravitational-wave observatories (the LIGO and Virgo detectors). One component of the project is to perform detailed radio measurements of exotic compact rapidly-spinning stars known as radio pulsars. A second component would be to perform rapid radio follow-up observations of any detected bursts of gravitational radiation, such as might accompany the collisions of compact stars and black holes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By obtaining precise data on known radio sources that may also be gravitational sources, one can dramatically increase the sensitivity of gravitational-wave searches targeting these objects. Meanwhile, if a putative gravitational-wave burst is accompanied by radio emissions, this will significantly improve confidence in the reality of these early gravitational-wave detections. Both types of observation will hasten the advent of gravitational-wave astronomy, giving complementary views of some of the strangest phenomena in the Universe. These observations will be performed by a specially-trained cadre of student observers recruited from the Lower Rio Grande Valley, providing unprecedented educational and technical opportunities to the academically underrepresented and economically disadvantaged community of this region.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>80000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0855432</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Teviet</FirstName>
      <LastName>Creighton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>teviet@phys.utb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The University of Texas at Brownsville</Name>
      <CityName>Brownsville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>785204956</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9568827849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One West University Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1252</Code>
      <Text>LIGO RESEARCH SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
