<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Understanding the Stability and Reactivity of Radical Cations for Improved Overcharge Protection in Lithium-Ion Batteries</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>413000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James Lisy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Through this award, funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics, and Mechanisms - B Program of the Division of Chemistry, Prof. Susan A. Odom from the University of Kentucky will seek to improve the stability of radical cation forms of aromatic molecules used as redox shuttle electrolyte additives for overcharge protection in lithium-ion batteries. The lifetimes of the radical cations in a variety of solvent environments, including carbonates used as battery electrolytes will be characterized to determine decomposition products upon oxidation. Analysis of these products will determine (i) how solvent environment affects the reaction outcome, (ii) what features results in more stable radical cations, and (iii) if there is a correlation in radical cation persistence vs. the number of cycles overcharge protection in a lithium-ion battery before redox shuttle decomposition. Higher oxidation potential shuttles for new cathode materials will be synthesized and methods to stabilize the resulting radical cations, by surrounding them in protective cages and extending electronic delocalization, will be explored.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research project have potential to provide benefits to the scientific community and our society in the development of new materials for the improved performance and safety of energy storage materials, specifically lithium-ion batteries. As the number of hybrid electric vehicles and the need for storage of renewable energy sources continue to grow, it becomes more important to have reliable energy storage. Electrolyte additives that improve the safety and lifetimes of lithium-ion batteries are needed to expedite the growth of this technology for use in multiple applications. This project will expose students at different levels (high school, undergraduate, and graduate students) to scientific research, in a growing area of social and practical importance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1300653</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Odom</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>susan.odom@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5560</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY CONVERSION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7905</Code>
      <Text>MPS SUST ENERGY SCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
