<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Probing Inflationary Cosmology with CLASS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>267000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harshal Gupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Thomas Essinger-Hileman is awarded an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a program of research and education at Johns Hopkins University. The fellow's research program is to measure the polarization of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) with the Cosmology Large Angular Scale Surveyor (CLASS). The proposed research addresses fundamental questions of the origin and nature of the Universe and helps astrophysicists test competing theories of the birth of the Universe. Such measurements were regarded a top scientific priority in the 2010 Decadal Survey of Astronomy and Astrophysics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will facilitate the creation of high-sensitivity polarization and temperature maps of the CMB and directly test inflationary models of the very early, energetic Universe. Cosmological inflation would produce a gravitational-wave background at a level that directly corresponds with the vacuum energy density at the end of inflation. By looking for the odd-parity signature of a gravitational-wave background in the CMB polarization, the so-called "B modes," CLASS will investigate physics on grand-unification-theory (GUT) energy scales of 10^16 GeV. In contrast, the Large Hadron Collider is designed to probe energies up to 7x10^3 GeV. CLASS will form a multi-frequency observatory at a high-altitude site, and it is unique among current and planned ground-based experiments in aiming at the reionization bump in the B-mode power spectrum at large angular scales. The PI will lead the development, commissioning, and field calibration of the 90 GHz receivers for CLASS. This will include the design of a novel focal plane architecture for monolithic arrays of feedhorn-coupled, transition-edge-sensor polarimeters, as well as unique thermal filtering strategies incorporating silicon-powder filters of his own design. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project include a significant educational component. The fellow will undertake a program of educational outreach in partnership with the Johns Hopkins Center for Educational Outreach to convey exciting developments in cosmology to high school students in a predominantly African-American school district over a two-year period. As the research progresses, the fellow will communicate developments through audio and video media, weblogs, and photographs. He will meet with a group of 10th- and 11th-graders monthly to engage the students in the research happening in the lab and at the telescope in Chile. The presentation materials developed for this program will then be expanded to reach a broader audience through existing programs such as the annual physics fair at Johns Hopkins, as well as through an interactive presentation on the World Wide Telescope web site. This narrative tour of the sky as seen by project telescopes will present the project's results in cosmology to a broad, global audience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1302924</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Essinger-Hileman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Essinger-Hileman Thomas</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085405608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1609</Code>
      <Text>NSF ASTRON &amp; ASTROPHY PSTDC FE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7697</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
