<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CONFERENCE: 55th Annual Maize Genetics Conference to be held March 14-17, 2013; St. Charles, Illinois</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>33650</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 54th Maize Genetics Conference (MGC) will be held at the Pheasant Run Resort, St. Charles, IL on March 14-17, 2013. This conference assembles scientists from industry and academia to discuss the latest research developments on many areas encompassing maize genetics The 2013 conference will have an outstanding program consisting of four plenary speakers: Michael J. Scanlon (Cornell University), Julia Bailey-Serres (University of California, Riverside), Jen Sheen (Harvard Medical School), and James Holland (USDA-ARS/North Carolina State University). The core program will consist of 35 18-minute oral talks scheduled in the morning sessions and two afternoon poster sessions with the four plenary talks held in the evening. The 2013 MGC meeting will have a special drought workshop consisting of oral presentations by scientists from academia and industry [Marc Cooper (Dupont Pioneer), Roberto Tuberosa (University of Bologna) and Dan Dyer (Syngenta Seeds) followed by a panel discussion on future strategies to enhance drought tolerance in this major cereal crop. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Maize Genetics Conference is not only an exciting scientific meeting but provides outstanding opportunities for graduate students and postdoctoral scientists to interact with outstanding scientists within and outside the maize community. The meeting actively emphasizes and supports the training of students and postdocs in developing their communication and interpersonal skills. The conference is unique in that it attempts to support the hotel and meal costs of all student attendees. Detailed efforts are planned to broaden the participation of women and members of groups under-represented in the sciences. The funding provided by NSF will broaden participation and help defray the costs of participation of students from the U.S. scientific community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1302963</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Becraft</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>becraft@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paula</FirstName>
      <LastName>McSteen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcsteenp@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9109</Code>
      <Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
