<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Women in Numbers/Femmes en nombre</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Women in Numbers/Femmes en Nombre workshop will take place October 14-18, 2013 at the Centre International de Rencontres Mathematiques in Luminy, France. The primary focus of the conference will be on collaboration on open research problems in number theory. A secondary focus will be on dissemination of recent work by active researchers. The conference will bring together established researchers, junior faculty, and advanced graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference will follow the model of the previous Women in Numbers Conferences (WIN and WIN2) held at Banff International Research Station in 2008 and 2011. Prior to the conference, each participant will be assigned according to her research interests to a working group involving a mix of senior and junior mathematicians, and in some cases advanced graduate students. Each group will have one or two leaders drawn from the participating senior mathematicians. Before participants arrive, they will be in contact with their group leaders, who will suggest research projects and provide background reading and references. The goals of this workshop are&lt;br/&gt;(1) to highlight research activities of women in number theory;&lt;br/&gt;(2) to increase the participation of women in research activities in number theory;&lt;br/&gt;(3) to train female graduate students in number theory and related fields;&lt;br/&gt;(4) to build a research network of potential collaborators in number theory and related fields; and&lt;br/&gt;(5) to provide information on women in number theory with an inclusive approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More information can be found on the conference webpage: http://www.math.ucsd.edu/~alina/luminy/index.html</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1303457</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bucur</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alina@math.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brooke</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feigon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bfeigon@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
