<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Heegaard splitting of 3-manifolds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>196462</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI plans to study topology of 3-manifolds, especially Heegaard splittings of 3-manifolds. The first part of the project is to investigate the relation between the Heegaard genus of a 3-manifold and the rank of its fundamental group. This research is built on the PI's recent success in constructing a hyperbolic counterexample to the Rank versus Genus Conjecture. The second goal of the proposed research is to answer a long-standing question in 3-manifold topology concerning Heegaard genus and a degree-one map. This question asks whether it is possible to have a degree-one map from a 3-manifold to another 3-manifold with larger Heegaard genus. This question is related to the Poincare Conjecture as well as a few other important questions in 3-manifold topology. The third part of the project is to solve a conjecture of Morimoto and Moriah on tunnel number of knots in the 3-sphere. The PI plans to develop new tools and use techniques from his previous work to achieve these goals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Three-manifolds are objects modeled on the 3-dimensional space that we are living in. A donut and the spatial universe are both examples of 3-manifolds. These objects arise naturally in many contexts in physical and other natural sciences and model many interesting phenomena. A geometric way of studying 3-manifolds is to cut a complicated 3-manifold into a pair of simpler 3-dimensional pieces called handebodies along a 2-dimensional surface. This decomposition is called a Heegaard splitting. The PI plans to study 3-manifolds using Heegaard splittings. The research targets several central questions in low-dimensional topology and knot theory, which has potential impact on other areas of scientific investigations, such as the topological structures of DNA.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1305613</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>taoli@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Boston College</Name>
      <CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
