<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Microscopic Theory of Many-Particle Systems from Nuclear Matter to Cold Atoms</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>533480</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project continues an interdisciplinary program to develop fundamental theories of many-particle systems, ranging from ultradense nuclear matter in ultrarelativistic heavy ion collisions and in neutron stars to ultracold atomic and condensed matter systems. Nuclear theory will be applied to study the properties of matter formed under extreme conditions of temperatures and pressures, to matter in neutron stars, with the aim of understanding observations and experiment and, conversely, using observations of neutron stars to learn properties of matter under extreme conditions. This research makes important interdisciplinary connections between nuclear and QCD problems and cold atom systems and will apply expertise in quantum fluids to predict the behavior of dilute helium solutions used in the proposed experiment at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory Spallation Neutron Source to detect the electric dipole moment of the neutron.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding new states of matter and connections between them provides broad intellectual insights into the basic properties of matter ranging from the hottest to the coldest many-particle systems in the universe. By integrating students and post-doctoral fellows into a diverse program that crosses the traditional boundaries between nuclear, particle, condensed matter and atomic physics, the PI and his colleagues provide unique opportunities for young researchers to think and create across disciplines. The scientists trained in this program have generally gone on to have significant impact in research at U.S. universities and national laboratories, as well as abroad.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1305891</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baym</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gbaym@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1284</Code>
      <Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1285</Code>
      <Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1285</Code>
      <Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
