<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Vanni</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PRFB Fellowship: Molecular evolution of the somatosensory system in mammalian hibernators&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Organisms display a wide spectrum of tolerance toward cold. Hibernators can survive harsh winter conditions by entering a reversible state called torpor, during which they display hypothermia (0-5°C), hypometabolism and unusual resistance to cold. Several orders of mammals have examples of hibernators, including the Rodentia order (ground squirrels, hamsters, marmots). It is unknown what are the cellular and molecular mechanisms underlying this adaptive behavior in mammals and whether they are evolutionarily conserved. The goal of this project is to determine if hibernators from the same Rodentia order (ground squirrels and Syrian hamsters) use the same molecular platform, or whether they evolved unique temperature adaptation mechanisms independently. An integrative approach that includes: histological, morphological, functional and transcriptomics analyses will be used to identify and characterize molecules that support cold tolerance and tuning of thermosensation. The multiple approaches described in this proposal will identify novel molecules and will shed light on a largely unexplored physiological process. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to contributing to scientific knowledge about the evolution of the molecular mechanism that governs hibernation, this proposal will provide training opportunities to undergraduate students and post-graduate trainees. Trainees will perform a range of duties including animal care and sample preparations, which will provide them with a full research experience. Progress reports, oral presentations and journal clubs will complement their training. It will promote their participation in summer internships and in career fairs. High school students in the community will benefit from presentations about hibernation, neuroscience and pursuing a career in science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1306144</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vanessa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matos-Cruz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/21/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Matos-Cruz Vanessa</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065360812</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1157</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY POSTDOC RSRCH FLW-NEW</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1036</Code>
      <Text>BIO MINORITY POSTDOC RESEARCH FELLOW PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
