<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nuclear Structure Studies Using Direct Reactions with Rare Isotope Beams</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98660</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kenneth Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The primary goal of the proposed research program is to investigate the shell structure of exotic, neutron-rich nuclei by direct reactions. These kinds of reactions are an excellent tool to probe the single particle properties of nuclei and gain information on the nuclear wave functions. Comparisons of the experimental results with state-of-the-art theoretical calculations will give new insights on the nuclear potential such as the role of tensor forces and three-body components.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the proposed project includes building an active research program in nuclear structure physics at Central Michigan University. This project will provide opportunities for undergraduate and M.S. students to actively participate in experiments carried out at world leading research facilities. Students can apply their skill outside of the class room and gain new experience in simulating and analyzing experimental data, setting up data acquisition systems and developing a new particle detection system. The students will be expected to publish their results and present their research at national and international conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1306297</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathrin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wimmer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wimme1k@cmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Central Michigan University</Name>
      <CityName>Mount Pleasant</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488590001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9897746777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research &amp; Graduate St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1233</Code>
      <Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7621</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
