<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Supramolecular Complex Formation and Transport of Anions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, George Gokel of the University of Missouri-St. Louis studies the chemical interactions that are involved in binding and transport of negatively charged species called anions, especially the complex and important anions DNA and RNA. A simple class of compounds called "tris-arenes", was found to bind to DNA and to mediate its transport through biological membranes into cells. The approach in this work is to address the fundamental chemical questions concerning the strength and selectivity of binding, the dynamics and energetics of binding, the structure(s) of the complexes formed, and the mechanisms of transport. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A particularly important impact of this work is the availability of these chemical tools to biological researchers involved in gene therapy research. The broader impacts of this project also involve training undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral researchers, disseminating research results through publications and presentations at national conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1307324</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gokel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gokelg@umsl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Saint Louis</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3145165897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ONE UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
