<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Active and nonlinear silicon photonics using hybrid thin-film lithium-niobate + silicon</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399226</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to overcome fundamental performance limitations in today's lightwave communications devices by using a hybrid nanophotonic waveguide cross-section, consisting of a bonded stack of silicon and of a ferroelectric oxide, e.g., lithium niobate. The approach is that modulators and nonlinear optoelectronic devices will be fabricated using the hybrid material, formed by oxide thin films being transferred onto a planarized silicon photonic chip using a low-temperature plasma-assisted bonding process which preserves diodes and transistors in the silicon chip.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this proposal is to realize, via use of this hybrid material system, optoelectronic devices that perform beyond the possibility frontier of devices fabricated using either material system alone. In the context of silicon photonics, the project will demonstrate a robust and high nonlinearity without sacrificing high index contrast. The project will also demonstrate more complex waveguide structures than possible in conventional lithium niobate structures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this proposal is firstly, to benefit the information-driven infrastructure needs of modern society by enabling faster data networks without increasing energy consumption. Secondly, this GOALI collaboration between a university and a small business, both having committed interest in this area of research, involves two-way researcher visits, and technology and knowledge transfer. Results from this collaboration will be published in peer-reviewed literature, will form components of graduate student thesis research, and will provide a roadmap to future commercialization by interested parties. The project also target opportunities for interdisciplinary education and training of underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1307514</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shayan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mookherjea</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smookherjea@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>S</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sriram</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sri@srico.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>094E</Code>
      <Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
