<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Vanni</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Unbiased Determination of Genome Wide Mutations Rates in Single Bacterial Replication Events&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;From Darwin's theory of natural selection to Mendelian inheritance and variation, many theories have preceded experimental evidence explaining evolution and population genetics. Specifically, the relationship between mutation rate and its effect on a strain?s fitness in a population of competing strains remains elusive, despite it being absolutely essential for understanding the mechanism of evolution and speciation. Current methods that assay mutations suffer from outputting information free of clonal interference, and insufficient resolution to probe rare single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that occur in the single-cell level. Thus, these approaches are not neutral, and select against deleterious mutations. An innovative cell sorting and culture microfluidic system will deliver unbiased genome wide microbial mutation rates that include neutral, synonymous, and deleterious mutations. Using this technology, the relationship between fitness and genome wide mutation rates can be directly examined. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Fellow will receive interdisciplinary training in the physics and engineering of microfluidics (Dr. Paul Blainey), biology, and informatics (Dr. Eric Alm). All data will be open to use for development of educational material and for aiding phylogenic reconstruction. Additionally, an automated DNA sequencing library preparation device design and operational knowledge will be made public for reduced library preparation cost for the entire sequencing community. The Fellow will also mentor undergraduate students to teach the power of bringing engineering approaches to answer basic science questions in evolutionary biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1308852</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Soohong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kim Soohong</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021391204</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8054</Code>
      <Text>Inters Biol and Math and Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7174</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOC FELLOW IN SCI, MATH EN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
