<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: The genetic architecture and ecological function of a novel coloration phenotype</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20778</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Irwin Forseth</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A fundamental goal in evolutionary biology is to understand how natural selection acts on organisms to form novel traits. Coloration is a key way in which animals interact with their environments and may serve many important roles, including attracting mates or avoiding predators. Although the adaptive context of coloration is well studied in wild populations, we know very little about the genetic basis of this important trait, limiting our interpretation of how coloration evolves. This proposal investigates the genetic basis and ecological function of sexual dichromatism (coloration that differs between males and females of the same species) to test hypotheses about the evolution of this trait in a diverse group of frogs. Specifically, this research integrates functional genomics, ecology, and behavior to elucidate both the genetic basis of a trait and its function under different selective environments. &lt;br/&gt;The fieldwork component of this research takes place in the forests of sub-Saharan Africa, which are home to incredible amphibian diversity, much of which is still undescribed. Amphibian surveys associated with this project will therefore contribute to ongoing efforts to document and conserve species diversity in this region. To facilitate these efforts, the PIs have developed a collaborative network of researchers, NGO personnel, and students (from Equatorial Guinea and the USA) with shared interests in conservation and biodiversity research. The PIs on this grant have an established record in student training (including under-represented minority and international students), outreach, and public communication of science, which will continue in this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1309171</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zamudio</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krz2@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/01/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sparks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jps66@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rayna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bellrc@si.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7378</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
