<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Vanni</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Investigating the influence of movement behavior on the spatial spread of invasive species: A case study with the Burmese python in South Florida&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Predicting the geographic spread of invasive species is central to understanding and predicting their ecological impacts. Numerous studies have acknowledged that an accounting of complex animal behaviors in models of spatial spread give rise to more accurate predictions of the dynamics of invasions. Individual-based models can incorporate behavioral complexity in movement and provide a method for predicting the effects of movement and dispersal strategies on spread dynamics. The Burmese python (Python molurus bivittatus), a native of southern Asia, is established in South Florida and is currently expanding its range northward through the Florida peninsula and southward into the Florida Keys. The fellow will analyze empirical studies on the movement capacity of Burmese pythons and use these data to parameterize spatially-explicit, individual-based models to investigate the influence of movement behavior on Burmese python spread dynamics. This study will provide informative predictions of spread rate and invasion routes of pythons and insight into the influence of movement and navigational capacity on species' population dynamics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fellow will develop expertise in computer simulation modeling, mathematical modeling, and empirical data analysis. This project will result in additions to a simulation model (SEARCH) that is available for use by wildlife and natural resource managers. The teaching plan includes training undergraduates in research, developing lectures for entry-level undergraduate science classes, and designing and implementing an upper-level undergraduate biology course in dynamic modeling. The fellow will mentor underrepresented minority students through the Davidson Research Initiative, TERRA Environmental Center, and the Ada Jenkins Center.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1309144</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shannon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pittman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pittman Shannon E</Name>
      <CityName>Columbia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652013603</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8054</Code>
      <Text>Inters Biol and Math and Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7137</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7174</Code>
      <Text>POSTDOC FELLOW IN SCI, MATH EN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
