<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometric and quantum topology in low dimensions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>146066</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed project concerns several problems in geometric and quantum topology in dimensions 3 and 4. Based on his recent work, the PI proposes an approach to the A-B slice problem, a formulation of the topological 4-dimensional surgery conjecture for non-abelian free groups. In recent years algebraic invariants have been found for key examples of decompositions of the 4-ball, and the goal is to combine them to formulate an obstruction to surgery in the context of the A-B slice problem. The project also includes a number of problems in quantum topology; some of them are motivated by the PI's recent work with Cooper on categorification of the Jones-Wenzl projectors. Specific problems concern algebraic structures underlying categorified spin networks and the colored Jones polynomial, and an approach to categorification of 3-manifold invariants using ideas related to localization. The PI's ongoing collaboration with physicist Fendley is aimed at identifying higher categorical structures in the context of quantum statistical mechanics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Topology is the study of shapes that locally look like the Euclidean space. Topological study of shapes in dimensions 3 and 4 is particularly important due to connections with physics, and it became apparent in the 1980s that the geometric classification in these "low" dimensions is a substantially more difficult problem than that in dimensions greater than four. At the same time, a wide array of tools and insights from other areas of mathematics and theoretical physics is available for solving topological problems in three and four dimensions. A part of this project will use such algebraic tools to address the classification of large-scale 4-dimensional shapes. The relevant algebraic invariants (in particular, the Milnor group) precisely encode the topological information about the motion of strings in 3-space. Another part of this project will explore interdisciplinary connections between Topology and Statistical Mechanics, with expected applications in both fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1309178</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vyacheslav</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krushkal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krushkal@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
