<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Low Probability of Detection Wireless Communications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>374724</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Chengshan Xiao</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this project is to establish the fundamental underpinnings&lt;br/&gt;of low probability of detection (LPD) communication systems operating over&lt;br/&gt;classical or quantum mechanical channels. This provides a transformative&lt;br/&gt;impact in two ways: (1) establishing a new approach that transforms the&lt;br/&gt;largely dormant (and socially compelling) area of LPD communications;&lt;br/&gt;(2) introducing and developing the foundations of the LPD optical channel,&lt;br/&gt;which requires quantum mechanical considerations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is based on a fundamental approach to the LPD&lt;br/&gt;communications problem that employs a broad array of tools to establish&lt;br/&gt;a new branch in the large field of wireless communications security.&lt;br/&gt;This project will also demonstrate the intellectual richness of the&lt;br/&gt;security problem that arises when quantum mechanical considerations&lt;br/&gt;are considered in optical communications. Tools from classical&lt;br/&gt;communications and networks, in particular information theory, mix&lt;br/&gt;with tools from quantum information systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are focused on impacting society and education.&lt;br/&gt;The hiding of the existence of transmissions while still communicating&lt;br/&gt;reliably has clear application in both military and civilian societal&lt;br/&gt;contexts. The results of this project will allow communicating parties&lt;br/&gt;and those whom attempt to detect them to understand the fundamental&lt;br/&gt;limits on such communication and techniques to achieve those limits.&lt;br/&gt;Finally, the project includes an integrated program of educational&lt;br/&gt;engagement that utilizes the extensive resources of both UMass-Amherst&lt;br/&gt;and BBN, with the latter contributing both theoretical expertise&lt;br/&gt;and experimental facilities for quantum information processing&lt;br/&gt;that will provide a unique opportunity for UMass students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1309573</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Towsley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>towsley@cs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goeckel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>goeckel@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>153E</Code>
      <Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>154E</Code>
      <Text>Computat systems &amp; security</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
