<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in China</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Ian Rowen of the University of Colorado, Boulder to conduct a research project in the Social, Behavioral and Economic sciences area during the summer of 2013 at Fudan University in Shanghai, China. The project title is "Tourism and State Territory in 'Greater China.'" The host scientist is Yingzhi Guo.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;How is tourism reconfiguring "Greater China," and in particular, relations between the People's Republic of China (PRC) and Taiwan? Over 1 million Chinese tourists visited Taiwan in 2011, even though the PRC continues to point over 1000 ballistic missiles at what it considers a breakaway province. This marks a profound regional change, with direct tour arrivals from China only permitted to arrive in Taiwan starting in 2008 after decades of tension and travel bans. This ethnographic research project uses tourism as a lens to analyze spatial politics between the PRC and Taiwan, and to explore the relationship between tourism and state territoriality in general. Examining tourism in Taiwan sheds light on the political and cultural implications of the rapid development of China's outbound tourist market, soon to be the world's largest, with over 100 million annual visits overseas projected by 2019. Additionally, this project's theoretical framework brings tourism practice into larger discussions about state power and spatial practice. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, the Fellow will present the research to his associates at Fudan University, and collaborate on surveys and other research tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1310669</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>ian</FirstName>
      <LastName>rowen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rowen Ian G</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803050000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
