<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in China</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds James McKee of the University of Central Florida to conduct a research project in Engineering during the summer of 2013 at the Chinese Academy of Sciences Suzhou Institute of Nanotechnology (SINANO) in Suzhou, China. The project title is "Processing of Continuously Drawn Yarn from Self-Aligned Carbon Nanotube Paper." The host scientist is Dr. Qingwen Li.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Carbon nanopaper (CNT) possesses many potential applications in composites and other uses, but a critical issue is the creation of production-scale aligned nanopaper. The alignment is key to producing controllable properties of the nanopaper that can be tailored to the intended application. This project investigates the nanotube fabric and yarn production practices in place at the sponsor institution, namely the drawing process used, and how it can be applied to the solution-filtration methodology currently practiced to produce in-plane aligned CNT papers and yarns. The degree of alignment and anisotropy between the drawn carbon nanotube yarns produced at Suzhou Institute of Nanotechnology (SINANO) is being compared with the randomly oriented solution-filtration produced nanopaper produced at the Fellow's home institution. The conceptual model gained from this study will ultimately be applied to the current process in use to produce continuous, aligned carbon nanopaper. Carbon nanotube paper and fabric have immediate applications in the aerospace industry for repairable electromagnetic shielding and lightning strike protection schemes for composite bodied aircraft that represent a vast improvement over the current metal-mesh techniques and can implemented with the composite manufacturing techniques that are already well-known in the aerospace industry. The weight savings these materials would allow for increased fuel efficiency in the transportation sector, improving vehicle performance in sector that affects everything from food prices to leisure air travel. With the improvements to conductivity, flame resistance, and static and dynamic mechanical properties created with standard, randomly oriented nanopaper, the ability to create continuous and even aligned nanopaper represents a new ability to use nanomaterials in large aerospace and structural applications more efficiently. The obvious industrial benefits are impressive, as is the long-term environmental effect as the efficiency increase would reduce vehicle emissions and part longevity. Additionally, the benefits of the integration of the nanopaper into wind turbines could potentially improve blade longevity, radar signature (many wind turbine farms are semi-invisible to radar), and lower lifetime operating costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1310995</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>McKee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>McKee James</Name>
      <CityName>Orlando</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328286047</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
