<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Semiarid Soil Microbial Response to Global Change</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19479</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saran Twombly</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Microbes mediate many important ecosystem services yet remain relatively poorly understood. This research examines how microbes - the bacteria and fungi that occur in soils - contribute to the ability of grassland ecosystems to respond to climate change. Desert grassland soils harbor high microbial diversity, but collecting, identifying and interpreting this diversity remains a challenge. Genomic tools will be used to identify the microbes in grassland soils under different environmental conditions. This information on microbial community composition will be linked with previous measures of microbial function in order to predict how microbes and their associated plant communities will respond to climate change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Grasslands provide many ecosystem services that benefit humans, yet they are changing rapidly in response to climate change and human land use. Results from this study will be communicated to the public in collaboration with the Sevilleta National Wildlife Refuge in central New Mexico. Educational materials and exhibits for the Refuge's new Visitors' Center will be developed based on this project. In addition, the researchers will participate in the Junior Scientist Outreach Program, a new outreach activity coordinated by the University of New Mexico Department of Biology. This activity targets 4th and 5th grade students from under-represented groups and engages then in hands-on activities coordinated by the research scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1311028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ladwig</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lladwig@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sinsabaugh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rlsinsab@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Collins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scollins@sevilleta.unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
