<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Observations of physical impacts following Hurricane Sandy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>27910</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>H. Richard Lane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>RAPID: Observations of physical impacts following Hurricane Sandy&lt;br/&gt;Robert Weiss, Jennifer L Irish, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, EAR-1312813&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Hurricane Sandy made landfall near Atlantic City on October 29th 2012. Sandy was classified as a Category I hurricane; however, a non-tropical weather system merged with Sandy and created a unique situation that resulted in catastrophic damage along the shores of New Jersey and New York. To this end, the record surges produced by Hurricane Sandy resulted in record damages in built and natural environments in New York and New Jersey. Hurricane Sandy provides the unusual opportunity to observe and collect information for the purpose of comparing sedimentary deposits resulting from storms versus those originating from recent tsunamis. PIs will focus on New Jersey and New York due to the magnitude of the impact and severity of the damages. In the reconnaissance surveys PIs will measure flood elevations and inundations of the storm surge, which are similar data collected during tsunami reconnaissance field surveys. This is important in designing protective infrastructure for either or both and for deciphering in the stratigraphic record whether there is a key signature for distinguishing tsunami from storm deposits. This interdisciplinary RAPID proposal will also integrate quantitative descriptions of the flooding zone from an engineering and geoscientific perspective with qualitative information from governmental entities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1312813</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Irish</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jirish@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weiss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weiszr@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7459</Code>
      <Text>SEDIMENTARY GEO &amp; PALEOBIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
