<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CONFERENCE: 2013 FASEB Conference on Genetic Recombination and Genome Rearrangements to be held July 21-26, 2013 in Steamboat Springs, CO</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen C. Cone</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: The Federation of American Societies of Experimental Biology (FASEB) conference on Genetic Recombination and Genome Rearrangements will be held July 21-26, 2013 in Steamboat Springs, Colorado. Genetic recombination plays a key role in molding genome structure and maintaining genome integrity in all organisms. DNA damage can be produced by environmental agents or by endogenous processes, most notably by errors and mechanistic failure during chromosome replication. Genetic recombination, both homologous and non-homologous, repairs this damage. These repair events have the potential to create genetic change, and chromosome rearrangements caused by inaccurate repair are often associated with the transition to cancer. For sexual reproduction, homologous recombination ensures proper chromosome disjunction during meiosis and generates genetic diversity. Programmed chromosomal rearrangements generate diversity in cells of the immune system, as well as in disease-causing microorganisms. While considerable progress has been made in understanding the mechanisms and biological consequences of genetic recombination, much remains to be learned regarding the underlying mechanisms and regulation of this fundamental biological process, and the conference is devoted to progress towards this goal. Topics to be covered include biochemistry and mechanisms of recombination, connections between replication, repair and recombination in eukaryotes and prokaryotes, meiosis, genome rearrangements and evolution, and maintenance of genome integrity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Progress in any scientific field is fostered by communication between researchers, and this is an important aim of the conference. It will assemble about 200 investigators who study diverse aspects of recombination, in a range of biological systems and with different experimental approaches. All attendees give platform or poster presentations covering new and unpublished work, and there is ample opportunity for discussion from all participants. An abstract book will provide abstracts and participant contact information, to facilitate interaction beyond the time frame of the meeting. Progress also requires the incorporation of researchers who are new to a field. Special efforts are made to include young investigators and members of underrepresented groups, including women; for many, this will be their first opportunity to present. To further promote this goal, one in six platform slots are allocated to talks selected from abstracts, and are expected to be directed to young investigators. A "Meet the Experts" session is dedicated to fostering interaction between speakers and other attendees, especially graduate students and postdocs. In addition, travel scholarships will be used to encourage participation by young investigators, trainees and by members of underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1313692</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wolf-Dietrich</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wdheyer@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Federation of Amer Societies For Exper Biology</Name>
      <CityName>Bethesda</CityName>
      <ZipCode>208143998</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3016347013</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9650 ROCKVILLE PIKE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
