<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Internal Photo Emission Energy Converters Based on a Wide Band Perfectly Absorbing Nanocomposite Metamaterial</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase (SBIR) I project aims to develop a new class of solar cell based on an internal photoemission device geometrically configured as a near perfect, broadband, isotropic absorber. Realizing the potential of this technology would bring to market a solar cell that is commercially competitive with other solar technologies on a cost per watt basis and are able to fabricated on a flexible substrate. Internal photo-emission converters have received renewed interest, but published power conversion efficiencies are well below the theoretical limit. A primary limiting factor in previous attempts has been limited light absorption in the metal. Our preliminary simulations and tests show enhanced light absorption across a broad range of angles and wavelengths when the absorbing metal is configured in a nanocomposite layer in a perfect absorber structure. The objective of Phase I is to validate the preliminary simulations by fabricating and testing a functioning device.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is primarily in the field of solar energy conversion. Successful completion of Phase I and Phase II of this research and development effort will enable commercialization of a low cost and long lifetime solar cell technology that can be manufactured on a flexible substrate using roll-to-roll processing techniques. This technology will provide a new cost competitive entry into the flexible and conformable solar cell market.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1315307</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>BalaKrishna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Juluri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bkj@pienergy.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pacific Integrated Energy</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921303062</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8583500435</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>12264 El Camino Real</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
