<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: High Temperature Corrosion Protection of Copper by the Application of an Aluminum Based Diffusion Coating</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will evaluate a low cost ceramic coating process to protect copper and its alloys from high temperature corrosion. The excellent thermal conductivity, workability, and relative chemical inertness of copper and its alloys make them attractive candidates for heat exchangers and electrical heating elements in water heating appliances. Unfortunately, high-temperature oxidation and condensate corrosion of copper heat exchangers limits their service life. To continue the use of copper in these applications, chemically inert, high temperature coatings with good thermal conductivity are required. The objective of this project is to achieve a range of ceramic and cermet coatings with varying thermal conductivity behavior through tailoring the composition and process variables of the coating.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is development of a disruptive, low cost ceramic coating process with wide-ranging applicability. The technology is amenable to a consumer appliance and automotive markets where corrosion protection is critical. These include home appliances, transportation radiators and heater cores, as well high temperature industrial brass and copper heat exchangers. If successful there are some important societal impacts?the more efficient water heater designs should lead to reduced materials consumption and greater diffusion of the high efficiency heater models into the market. For automotive applications, improved energy efficiency should result in reduced energy costs and reduced pollutants from lower exhaust emissions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1315631</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kidner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>n.kidner@nextechmaterials.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NEXTECH MATERIALS LTD</Name>
      <CityName>LEWIS CENTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>430359423</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6148426606</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>404 ENTERPRISE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
