<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2013 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Atmospheric Chemistry; Mount Snow, Vermont; July 28 - August 1, 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 2013 Atmospheric Chemistry Gordon Research Conference (GRC) will take place at Mt. Snow, VT, July 28-August 2. It will bring together an international group of atmospheric scientists who specialize in diverse research topics and who represent research in universities, government laboratories, and private research institutes. The central objective of the conference is to promote exchange of information and ideas on topics of contemporary interest in atmospheric science. The meeting is broad in scope, covering topics such as climate, air quality, the stratosphere, the biosphere and oceans, and atmospheric chemical mechanisms. The Gordon Research Conference format provides a unique combination of intellectual exchange via formal presentations, off-the-record exchanges from the floor, discussions at the poster sessions and the casual interactions outside the meeting. The format also encourages participants to bring their most recent and provocative results to stimulate discussion at the cutting edge of the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2013 Atmospheric Chemistry GRC will follow in this tradition, and will include sessions on the following topics: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; * Perspectives on Atmospheric Chemistry and Climate&lt;br/&gt; * Energy, Emissions and Atmospheric Impacts&lt;br/&gt; * Nucleation&lt;br/&gt; * Atmosphere Ocean Interactions&lt;br/&gt; * Aerosol Chemistry and Consequences&lt;br/&gt; * New Directions in Atmospheric Oxidation&lt;br/&gt; * Anthropogenic Biogenic Interactions&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, this conference has a long tradition of mentoring young scientists--that is, graduate students and new post-doctoral scientists--and initiating them into this interdisciplinary field through both the formal and informal conference activities and the ACCESS ("Atmospheric Chemistry Colloquium for Emerging Senior Scientists") which immediately precedes the GRC. The contributions of young scientists to the discussions at GRC will be an integral part of the scientific discourse there.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1317826</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>steven.s.brown@noaa.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
