<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NRI: Small: Reducing Trunk Musculoskeletal Forces During Manual Work</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1017136</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to develop a set of advanced engineering principles for design of the exoskeleton systems that reduce the internal musculoskeletal forces and oxygen consumption in a person during a variety of laborious tasks in various workplaces. The hypothesis is that these systems will decrease the severity and number of work-related back injuries while enhancing worker safety in automobile assembly plants and distribution centers. The research approach progresses from the exploration of the human-machine interaction when both the flow of power and information between the device and human dictate the overall functionality and performance of the device. Employing the dynamic models of various elements in this human-machine interaction, passive impedances and actuators will be developed for the exoskeletons. A set of experiments will be conducted to quantify the effect of the exoskeleton system on human trunk in sagittal plane, in frontal plane, and rotation around the spine. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the technologies proposed here will manifest in the development of broad classes of exoskeleton devices for workers who repeatedly move objects in factories, warehouses and distribution centers. This project will yield a set of engineering principles that decrease the risk of injuries due to repetitive maneuvers in distribution centers and in auto assembly plants. This project further will increase the availability of affordable assist systems for workers and improve the quality of life for workers. The educational impact of this research is derived from the proposed concerted effort to integrate education with research. Graduate and undergraduate engineering students will benefit through involvement in the research. The prototypes developed in this research project will enrich educational platforms for the study of design, modeling, and control of assist devices interacting with humans.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1317978</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rempel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.rempel@ucsf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Homayoon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kazerooni</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kazerooni@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8013</Code>
      <Text>National Robotics Initiative</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8086</Code>
      <Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9231</Code>
      <Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
