<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSR: Small: PROM in Clouds: Exploiting Scheduling for PeRformance OptiMization in Clouds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>495157</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Cloud computing is emerging as an attractive computing paradigm, where&lt;br/&gt;both hardware and software resources can be leased from a cloud&lt;br/&gt;provider to achieve better economy of scale, elasticity, availability,&lt;br/&gt;and flexibility for a plethora of services. A major challenge in&lt;br/&gt;designing such cloud platforms is in providing high and predictable&lt;br/&gt;performance along with Quality of Service (QoS) guarantees. The&lt;br/&gt;performance unpredictability is attributed to a myriad of factors&lt;br/&gt;including system scale, workload dynamism, virtualization overheads,&lt;br/&gt;resource sharing and contention.&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this proposal is to investigate performance&lt;br/&gt;enhancement and performance quantification techniques in a cloud&lt;br/&gt;environment through three intertwined tasks.&lt;br/&gt;First, a comprehensive scheduling framework consisting of a high-level&lt;br/&gt;job scheduler and a fine-grained resource manager will be developed&lt;br/&gt;for efficient management of cloud resources for performance enhancement.&lt;br/&gt;Second, performance prediction models will be developed for estimating&lt;br/&gt;job completion time (JCT) in a cloud platform.&lt;br/&gt;Third, for providing QoS guarantees, a control-theoretic model&lt;br/&gt;incorporating the proposed scheduler and analytical models will be&lt;br/&gt;developed. Measurements on real platforms with MapReduce &lt;br/&gt;and other representative cloud workloads will be used to validate the&lt;br/&gt;proposed ideas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses one of the main concerns of cloud computing -&lt;br/&gt;What are the performance implications if my application is moved to a&lt;br/&gt;cloud? If successful in answering this question, it would have a tremendous&lt;br/&gt;impact on the cloud-enabled application domains. The cross-cutting&lt;br/&gt;nature of this work can foster new research avenues.&lt;br/&gt;In addition to undergraduate and graduate student training in areas&lt;br/&gt;such as architecture, distributed systems, and performance modeling,&lt;br/&gt;special attention will be given to involving women and minority&lt;br/&gt;students in this project. The modeling tools and techniques developed&lt;br/&gt;in this research will be made publicly available.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1320478</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chitaranjan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Das</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>das@cse.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
