<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2013 Atomic Physics GRC, June 23-28, 2013 at Salva Regina University in Newport, Rhode Island</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The funding from this grant will be used to support students so they can attend the twenty-first in a series of Atomic Physics Gordon Research Conferences to be held at the Salva Regina University in Newport, RI from June 23-28, 2013. This meeting will continue the tradition of focusing on emerging areas of research within the discipline and major advances in existing areas of atomic physics and related fields. The program and speakers are to be chosen based on input from a wide range of practicing atomic physicists. The areas to be addressed at this conference include both theoretical and experimental developments, with emphasis on areas that offer significant challenges and opportunities as we look to the future of the field. In 2013, we include sessions on Quantum Simulation and Optical Lattices, Mesoscopic Physics, Quantum Information and Quantum Optics, Dipolar Gases and Cold Molecules, Rydberg atoms, Pulsed Light Spectroscopy, Precision Measurements, and Bose and Fermi Gases. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The informal nature of the conference, in which no proceedings or publications result, allows for the kind of free exchange of information and open discussion not always possible in other venues. The Atomic Physics Gordon Conference provides a unique opportunity to assemble a critical number of leading researchers in related but differing specializations, along with significant numbers of students and young researchers, who bring new points of view to the most exciting and demanding problems at the forefront of physics research. Effort will be made to welcome a diverse pool of registrants to the conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1321191</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jin@jilau1.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
