<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Oceanographic Instrumentation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>57081</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James S. Holik</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A request is made to fund additional and back-up instrumentation on the R/V Roger Revelle, a 273? general purpose Global vessel; the R/V Melville, a 279?general purpose Global vessel; the R/V New Horizon, a 170?, general purpose, Ocean/Intermediate vessel and the R/V Sproul, a 125? general purpose Coastal/Local vessel. All four vessels are operated by Scripps Institution of Oceanography as part of the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System research fleet. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Both R/V Roger Revelle and R/V Melville are Global vessels and support multidisciplinary oceanographic research in all of the world?s ocean basins. R/V New Horizon focuses primarily on offshore California but has been used for work throughout the Pacific. The primary working area for R/V Sproul has been the continental shelf and coastal environments off Southern California. In 2013, R/V Roger Revelle is scheduled for 247 days with NSF days accounting for 31% of the total sailing schedule; R/V Melville is scheduled for 316 days with NSF days accounting for 44% of the total sailing schedule; and R/V New Horizon is scheduled for 157 days with NSF days accounting for 50% of the total sailing schedule. R/V Sproul, a vessel owned by the State of California, has no NSF days in 2013 and only one day currently funded on the vessel.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Oceanographic Instrumentation requested in this proposal includes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;RDI 150 KHz OS ADCP $66,110 &lt;br/&gt;H2000 ROV Spares $21,567 &lt;br/&gt;H2000 ROV Cable and Modifications $57,081 &lt;br/&gt;10m2 MOCNESS Components $46,279 &lt;br/&gt;TOTAL $191,037 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under criterion two of the Proposal Guidelines. They provide infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF). The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1321002</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Woody</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sutherland</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wosutherland@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
      <LastName>Appelgate</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bappelgate@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5413</Code>
      <Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
