<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EarthCube Domain End-User Workshop: Community-Based Cyberinfrastructure for Petrology and Geochemistry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99975</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030107</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This workshop will bring together scientists from the petrology and geochemistry domains, data managers, sample curators, and cyberinfrastructure specialists to gather requirements and develop a vision for an advanced information and knowledge management system that will transform the way petrological and geochemical data and samples are acquired, analyzed, published, and re-used across the geosciences in the conduct of science. The outcomes of this workshop will provide guidance to the EarthCube initiative from the petrology-geochemistry community to design and develop the architecture of an Earth Science cyberinfrastructure that is aligned with the end-users' needs for data and sample access, software tools for data and metadata acquisition, workflow support, data analysis, data visualization, and modeling, computing capabilities, interoperability with data from other domains, as well as policies and procedures that address the scientists' concerns regarding, for example, data sharing, data citation, intellectual property, sample curation, and career advancement. The workshop report will be made widely accessible on the web.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1321723</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kerstin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lehnert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lehnert@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8074</Code>
      <Text>EarthCube</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
