<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ICOB: Investigation of AMPA-type glutamate receptor interaction with the accessory SynDIG protein family</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>317762</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Evan Balaban</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Cell-to-cell communication in the nervous system is mediated by small chemicals called neurotransmitters that are released from one cell and bind to receptor proteins present on the membrane of the adjacent cell in a process called synaptic neurotransmission. The amino-acid neurotransmitter glutamate and its conjugate glutamate receptors are responsible for the majority of the excitatory neurotransmission in the mammalian brain. Glutamate receptors are protein complexes of four subunits that assemble in various combinations, creating membrane-embedded ion-channels of different types and properties. In recent years, it has become increasingly evident that glutamate receptors are acted on by various auxiliary factors that regulate channel properties and localization at synapses. Therefore, elucidating the structure and function of glutamate receptors in general, and how these receptors are modulated by association with accessory proteins in particular, is central to understanding the basic principles of brain physiology. This grant will concentrate on the interaction of the AMPA-type glutamate receptors with the SynDIG protein family. A combination of molecular biology, biochemistry and electrophysiology experiments will be undertaken to test the hypothesis that SynDIG proteins influence the delivery of AMPA-type glutamate receptors to the cell surface of the postsynaptic membrane as well as alter the properties of ion flow through the glutamate receptor channel critical for synaptic neurotransmission. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposed studies include integration of the research and education activities of the PI, specifically in the context of broadening the participation of undergraduate students from underrepresented groups (primarily Hispanic/Latino) pursuing postgraduate degrees in science. Undergraduate participation will be directed by the PI in conjunction with graduate students in the laboratory, thereby integrating research, teaching, and scientific community outreach activities for students pursuing graduate studies in the laboratory. Additionally undergraduate and graduate students will participate in international exchanges as part of the collaboration with the Israeli PI for this project which is jointly supported by NSF and United States-Israel Binational Science Foundation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1322302</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elva</FirstName>
      <LastName>Diaz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ediaz@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7712</Code>
      <Text>ORGANIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
