<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Might Young Makers Be The Engineers Of The Future?</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The purpose of this study is to understand Young Makers in K-12 and how their knowledge,&lt;br/&gt;skills, and attitudes might prepare them to pursue advanced STEM education and careers. This&lt;br/&gt;study will advance the currently limited knowledge of the Young Maker community by&lt;br/&gt;developing theory characterizing Young Makers and their pathways through the lens of formal&lt;br/&gt;engineering education. The aim is to establish evidence as to how Making benefits Young&lt;br/&gt;Makers and affects their pathways to STEM majors and related careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this study will transform the conversation of who Young Makers could become,&lt;br/&gt;linking Making with engineering in the same way that students who excel in science and math&lt;br/&gt;are pointed toward engineering by parents and career counselors. By sharing a diverse (by age,&lt;br/&gt;gender, and ethnicity) set of success profiles of Young Makers widely in the formal education&lt;br/&gt;system to students, K-12 school administrators, university leaders, admissions officers, and to&lt;br/&gt;Young Makers both online and at Young Maker community events, we aim to illuminate&lt;br/&gt;pathways for Young Makers to become the engineers of the future. In addition, this study could&lt;br/&gt;inform future innovation in formal K-12 STEM pedagogy based on successful attributes of&lt;br/&gt;informal engineering education and tinkering activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1329321</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Micah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lande</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>micah.lande@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jordan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Shawn.S.Jordan@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7715</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
