<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2013 Chemical Reactions at Surfaces GRS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carol Bessel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Catalysis Program of the NSF Division of Chemistry supports the request of Professor Peter C. Stair of Northwestern University, and Nancy R. Gray of Gordon Research Conferences, to partially support the travel and registration of twenty U.S. graduate students and postdoctoral fellows to attend the 2013 Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) and Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Chemical Reactions at Surfaces held at Les Diablerets Conference Center in Les Diablerets, Switzerland on April 27-28, 2013. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Gordon Research Seminar informs the participants about the conduct of science in the USA and Europe, encourages young scientists to fully participate in the scientific process by making presentations to their peers and mentors, and exposes less experienced researchers to diverse research areas in surface science. The international conference location and the expected participation by young USA and European scientists provides a first-hand comparison of scientific research on the two continents and the informal atmosphere formed from a group of peers promotes participation. Student attendees/presenters span diverse fields so as to inform the audience broadly. This conference is a leading venue for dissemination of research spanning fundamental surface chemistry, catalysis at surfaces, synthesis of surfaces, surface photochemistry, solid-liquid interfaces, environmental and aerosol interfaces, tribology, gas-surface scattering and reactions, and novel materials and environments. Along with a panel of senior surface scientists, selected students address fundamental questions about challenging research in the field of surface science as well as questions on future career opportunities, and differences and similarities in career paths available in North American and Europe.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1329211</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stair</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pstair@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
