<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Understanding Regulatory RNA-protein Networks to Control Cellular Metabolism</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>482833</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Larry Halverson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual merit&lt;br/&gt;Control of cellular metabolisms is one of the main objectives of modern cellular and biomolecular engineering. The recent discovery of noncoding RNAs as regulators has led to an entire new class of metabolic regulation that has already found a significant place in synthetic biology and metabolic engineering. However, the mechanisms by which regulatory RNAs interact with entire protein networks to simultaneously regulate multiple metabolic pathways in response to external inputs are less understood. This project aims to apply a novel method that employs recently developed in vivo molecular characterization tools and quantitative modeling approaches towards: (1) investigating basic molecular features used by regulatory RNA-protein interactions in the context of stress-response mechanisms, and (2) translating experimental data into quantitative kinetic models that capture the interplay between external stresses, metabolic changes, and molecular interactions. This research will result in furthering our understanding of how molecular regulators function in vivo and in the context of natural cellular networks, contributing to a more complete picture of cell behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts&lt;br/&gt;These studies will have the broader impact of providing new means and approaches for cellular engineering through exploiting the unique modes of RNA-protein regulation. The results of this research are expected to find broad applications in improving the productivity of microorganisms in economically interesting biotechnology processes. Furthermore, establishing a general interdisciplinary platform for studying how RNA regulators function in vivo and in the context of entire metabolic networks will be of value to the broader research community. In addition, this project will support broader outreach efforts to a low-income underrepresented community through the "Raising Future Scientists" program. This program will seek to increase awareness among middle school and high school students, and also their parents, about the societal problems that engineering and science can address and solve.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1330862</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lydia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Contreras</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lcontrer@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baldea</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbaldea@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1491</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8011</Code>
      <Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>009E</Code>
      <Text>Metabolic engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1491</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
