<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Experimental and Theoretical Studies of Charge-Charge Interactions in Proteins</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>924022</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jaroslaw Majewski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The major goal of this research project, jointly funded by Molecular Biophysics in the Division of MCB and Physics of Living Systems Program in the Division of Physics, is to understand the role of charge-charge interactions in determining the thermodynamic stability of proteins and modulation of the folding energy landscape. It relies on the synergy between computer simulations and experiments. This study will test the hypothesis that charge-charge interactions on the protein surface are important determinants of the folding energy landscape. Approaches developed during the previous funding cycle significantly advanced the ability to predict the effects of surface charge-charge interactions on protein stability and provided an important tool that allows the combination of computer simulations, inspired by the energy landscape theory, with experimental measurements of the rates for protein folding/unfolding. Specific questions that will be addressed are: What is the role of charge-charge interactions in shaping the folding energy landscape? What is the effect that electrostatic interactions have on defining the protein kinetic stability? What is the role of salt-bridges in defining the stability of collagen molecule? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI is actively involved in curriculum development and serves as an Undergraduate curriculum adviser for Biochemistry and Biophysics majors at RPI. In addition he engages high school, undergraduate and graduate students in both computational and experimental aspects of research in his laboratory. Over 50% of trainees are females or members of underrepresented minorities. The majority of the high-school and undergraduate students who were trained in the lab continue their education in STEM disciplines. The research will provide a systematic study of the mechanism of protein stabilization by charge-charge interactions by uniquely combining a variety of biochemical, biophysical and computational tools. As such, it is expected that the knowledge accumulated as a result of these experiments will lay the foundation to future studies of these fundamentally important issues with broad implications for many different areas of biotechnology that use proteins including development of next generation of biosensors, environmentally friendly catalysts and robust biomaterials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1330249</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Makhatadze</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>makhag@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7246</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8007</Code>
      <Text>BioMaPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1144</Code>
      <Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
