<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SFF Symposium Student Support 2013; Austin, Texas; August 12-14, 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhijian Pei</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Annual International Solid Freeform Fabrication Symposium - An Additive Manufacturing Conference is a topical meeting that is a research exchange in the area of Additive Manufacturing, also known as Three Dimensional Printing and Rapid Prototyping. Over 25 percent of meeting attendees historically are students. The objective of this grant is to make the 2013 meeting more accessible to students by cost sharing the majority of the student registration fee. The 2013 meeting is expected to be similar in demographic but slightly larger in size compared to last year's 2012 meeting. The 2012 meeting drew 170 researchers from all over the world, representing 12 countries. There were 114 talks and posters presented. Thirty five universities were represented, 19 of which were domestic. For the 2013 meeting, this funding will enable the student registration fee to be set at $225, compared to the anticipated actual meeting cost per participant of $530.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The benefit of this grant is facilitating access of students to the Solid Freeform Fabrication Symposium. Providing student access to other students working in their area as well as world-class research and researchers will contribute to the development of future researchers in the field. Students are encouraged to present their work personally. The strong international participation gives domestic participants an excellent opportunity to gain valuable information firsthand on research in the field. The meeting is an excellent model for advancing discovery and understanding while promoting teaching, training and learning. The networking of world-class researchers with students is strong. The meeting is a pinion for research infrastructure by the networking of research personnel and information.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1331096</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bourell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbourell@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/21/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
