<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Wind, Thermal, and Earthquake Monitoring of the Watts Towers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13731</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kishor Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Rapid Research Graant (RAPID) award is to collect data of vibrations caused by wind gusts and earthquake tremors on Watts Towers representing multiple sculptures located in Los Angeles, California. Watts Towers are a collection of 17 artistic steel towers constructed by the artist Simon Rodia during 1921-1955. The towers vary in height with the tallest towers are 30 meters high. The art work is registered as a national Historic Landmark. The Los Angeles County Museum of Arts is planning to conserve these art towers over a long term. Since the towers are complex and unique structures, the response and vibration characteristics of the structures to natural phenomena should be understood so that a long term repair and conservation strategy can be established. Wind and other natural environmental elements have caused deterioration to the facades of the structures. Several structures suffer from cracking of the mortar cover and loss of ornaments. Santa Anna winds, which occur during March and April, are one of the major elements that cause vibration of the structures. The project will install structural response recording instruments to collect data during the high wind period of March and April. Principle Investigator plans to use instruments from the UCLA NEES site. Accelerometers, strain gages, inclinometers, and anemometers will be installed at the site and on a tall sculpture to record wind speeds and structural responses. The instruments will also capture several moderate earthquakes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The recorded data will be analyzed to assess structural characteristics and level of vibration of the structure. The results will permit Los Angeles County Museum of Arts conservators to develop refurbishing strategies for long-term life of the sculptures.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1331299</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ertugrul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taciroglu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>etacir@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1637</Code>
      <Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>039E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>040E</Code>
      <Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>043E</Code>
      <Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1576</Code>
      <Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
