<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Broadening Participation Research Project: Advancing Interest and Motivation (AIM) for STEM Careers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>349697</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Earnestine P. Easter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Fayetteville State University will implement an HBCU-UP Broadening Participation Research in STEM Education project to examine the impact of the Advancing Interest and Motivation (AIM) model on student career interests, motivation, self-efficacy, career outcome expectations, and employment outcomes in STEM. The PIs also propose a supplemental study using structural equation modeling and path analysis to study self-regulation and its influences on STEM career interests and progression. AIM is designed for Fayetteville State seniors from the Departments of Biological Sciences, Chemistry and Physics, and Mathematics and Computer Science in collaboration with the Office of Career Services and STEM faculty. The research framework is based on social cognitive career theory. The project will use aspects of the theory as a guide to develop a broadening participation model for HBCU STEM students designed to enhance career self-efficacy, share career expectations, advance interest and motivation to pursue STEM careers, and improve job search skills via a coordinated set of learning experiences involving STEM faculty, alumni, Office of Career Services, and STEM professionals in the workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will inform STEM teaching and career development intervention strategies. The findings could contribute to the current body of information regarding phenomena associated with STEM majors that do not pursue STEM careers, an important aspect to understand in trying to increase the representation of minorities in the STEM workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1332555</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Flowers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lflowers@livingstone.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lamont</FirstName>
      <LastName>Flowers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lflower@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fayetteville State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>283014252</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9106721141</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 Murchison Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8212</Code>
      <Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
