<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>LARISSA Data Compilation and Writing Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>31735</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lisa Clough</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports a dedicated workshop devoted to synthesizing the data from a multi-year interdisciplinary field and laboratory study into the complex interaction of earth systems in the Northern Antarctic Peninsula. The Larsen Ice Shelf System, Antarctica (LARISSA) is an International Polar Year-supported project devoted to furthering our understanding of a vulnerable region of the Earth that is undergoing rapid changes of climate and ecosystem function. This 3 day workshop will unite all participating Principal Investigators (PIs), post-docs and students in one venue to provide an effective forum to discuss the integration of the various results and plan the next steps for dissemination and peer review publication. The complexities of field work logistics and difficult sea ice conditions have forced the team to adapt to varying field sampling strategies and, because of this, an extra amount of synergy is required in order to harvest the scientific outcomes of the various disciplines which include: physical oceanography, glaciology, marine and Quaternary geology, marine biology, geodesy, and climatology. The efforts of the LARISSA program included four marine expeditions and numerous field visits to the Antarctic Peninsula in the past three years, and there is a tremendous amount of data that needs to be presented and discussed amongst the members of the collaborative research team.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will involve both senior and junior PIs, as well as PhD to undergraduate students. The workshop will convene a critical mass of researchers with a diversity of contributions, which will benefit all participants. The long-term results of this workshop will be to expand and disseminate the impact of LARISSA results beyond the PI community of scholars. The data distribution plan has directives to make the results available to the broader community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1334058</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eugene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Domack</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>edomack@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hamilton College</Name>
      <CityName>Clinton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>133231218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3158594678</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>198 College Hill Rd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5292</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC INTEGRATED SYS SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
