<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Topology Optimization of Structures Accounting for Damage Uncertainties</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>355001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Malak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to introduce a new design paradigm in structural engineering that employs topology optimization for generating optimal structures that are resistant to multiple forms of damage and thus lead to robust designs. Previous topology optimization research has generally ignored the topic of damage, and assumed purely elastic behavior, thereby limiting the applicability of this technique to a relatively narrow class of engineering materials and structures. This objective will be achieved through (i) creation of a novel computational framework that simultaneously combines topology optimization and continuum damage mechanics, considering a wide range of material damage models such as brittle damage, creep damage and damage due to impact loading, (ii) application of these algorithms to existing structural design problems to uncover novel design concepts not seen in conventional designs, and (iii) development of an educational program for students and postdoctoral fellows focused on damage modeling and structural optimization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will expand the range of applicability of topology optimization to a wide range of disciplines, leading to more robust structures that are less susceptible to failure due to material damage. Educational activities and dissemination of the research will impact the engineering community by generating interest in engineering design and promoting creativity and innovation in the next generation of engineers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1334857</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Haim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Waisman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hw2286@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1464</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING DESIGN AND INNOVAT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>067E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>068E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>073E</Code>
      <Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9148</Code>
      <Text>TOOLS &amp; TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9231</Code>
      <Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
