<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Investigations on the Cycling of Mercury from the Ocean to Fog and Deposition to Land in Coastal California</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>229111</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henrietta N. Edmonds</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Monomethyl mercury (MMHg) is a highly toxic form of mercury in the marine environment, with the ability to bio-concentrate in aquatic food webs and threaten human health. Recent studies have indicated that fog deposition of MMHg may represent an important source of this toxic compound to terrestrial ecosystems that are impacted by fog, however these processes are poorly understood. Researchers from the University of California Santa Cruz, California State University Monterey Bay, and San Jose State University will conduct experiments using a network of fog observation sites (FogNet) along the California coast to examine the spatial and temporal distribution of MMHg in fog and its potential sources. Results from this study will help to better elucidate the role of fog in transporting MMHg to terrestrial ecosystems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This study will provide scientific training for undergraduate and graduate students, including individuals from underrepresented groups, in a number of universities in California. FogNet will create a collaborative research network between state universities, federal entities, and non-governmental organizations. Results from this study will benefit society at large through furthering general knowledge on the cycling of toxic mercury.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1334252</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coale</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>coale@mlml.calstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wesley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wheim@mlml.calstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1670</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7696</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT, HEALTH &amp; SAFETY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9156</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
