<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Metal Organic Vapor Phase Epitaxy (MOVPE) Reactor for Nanostructured Materials Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>706671</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation award to the Rochester Institute of Technology funds the purchase of a metal organic vapor phase epitaxy (MOVPE) system for growth of III-V thin film crystals and nanostructures. The MOVPE system is customized for growth of an array of both traditional and novel semiconductor materials containing arsenic, phosphorous and antimony. The instrument will support the study of a range of new material systems spanning research topics in next generation photovoltaics (PV), III-V on silicon optoelectronics and electronics as well as quantum dot (QD) and nanowire based lasers and photovoltaics. The MOVPE tool is further enabling research in the area of heterogeneous integration of photonics which will enable the realization of low cost high performance optoelectronic chips with active photonic functionalities, such as, lasers, amplifiers, modulators and radio-frequency photonic devices. Furthermore, this tool will support the seamless integration of robust QD lasers with high performance silicon photonic devices, which has the potentials to the meet challenges to the realization of complete optical interconnects that are low-cost and have high performance and efficiency. The tool will be part of RIT's state-of-the-art clean room user facility and be available to research teams across multiple disciplines and universities. The tool will play a central role in RIT's growing multi-disciplinary PhD program in Microsystems Engineering, it will strengthen the graduate training program around new material growth and epitaxy, and optical and electronic devices. A new course based on epitaxy of thin-films is being developed. Other activities include educating personnel from local companies in microelectronic technologies through short course programs, collaboration with RIT Middle College program to introduce high-school students to PV technologies through cleanroom tours and hands-on experiences, and outreach sessions to the general public at RIT's annual Imagine RIT festival. In addition, this tool serves to provide resources and support for academic and industrial partners. It not only provides the technical resources and development for state-of-the-art and next-generation devices, but through the graduate training program, the next generation of experienced scientists and engineers.&lt;br/&gt;*****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation award to the Rochester Institute of Technology (RIT)supports the purchase of a metal organic vapor phase epitaxy (MOVPE) system for growth of thin film crystals and nanostructures. The MOVPE system is customized for growth of an array of both traditional and novel materials containing arsenic, phosphorous and antimony. The system will be used to study a range of new material systems spanning research topics in next generation photovoltaics, optoelectronics and electronics as well as quantum dot (QD) and nanowire based lasers and photovoltaics. The tool will be part of RIT's state-of-the-art clean room user facility and be available to research teams across multiple disciplines and universities. The tool will be playing a central role in RIT's growing multi-disciplinary PhD program in Microsystems Engineering, allowing for a strong graduate training program around new material growth and epitaxy and optical and electronic devices. A new course is being developed around the MOVPE and related characterization equipment. Other activities include educating personnel from local companies in microelectronic technologies through short course programs, collaboration with RIT Middle College program to introduce high-school students to PV technologies through cleanroom tours and hands-on experiences, and outreach sessions to the general public at RIT's annual Imagine RIT festival.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337592</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wei_guo@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Seth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hubbard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smhsps@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Preble</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sfpeen@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Forbes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dvfsps@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rommel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slremc@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
      <CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
