<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI Collaborative: Development of iRehab, an Intelligent Closed-Loop Instrument for Adaptive Rehabilitation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200109</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal #: 13-38118 Collaborative Proposal #: 13-37866 &lt;br/&gt;PI(s): Makedon, Fillia S collaboration with PI(s): Betke, Margrit &lt;br/&gt;Athitsos, Vassilis; Gatchel, Robert J; Huang, Heng; Romero-Ortega, Mario I &lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Texas-Arlington collaboration with Institution: Boston Univeristy &lt;br/&gt;Title: MRI/Dev :Collab Dev. of iRehab, an Intelligent Closed-loop Instrument for Adaptive Rehabilitation &lt;br/&gt;Project Proposed: &lt;br/&gt;This project, developing of an instrument referred to as iRehab, aims to enable personalized rehabilitation therapy for individuals suffering from brain injury, motor disabilities, cognitive impairments, and/or psychosocial symptoms. The instrument, a modular rehabilitation device, in its simplest form consists of a computer, a camera, and adaptive software for assessment and training of cognitive functions. In its final, most complex form, the instrument will integrate data from a 4-degree-of-freedom robotic-arm with gimbals and torque sensing, a Kinect sensor, multiple cameras, an eye-tracking device, a touch screen, a microphone, and an fNIRS brain imaging sensor. &lt;br/&gt;The instrument will be developed in two phases. In the first phase, the investigators develop a Barrett robot arm. In the second phase, the instrument will extend to a Kinect sensor, multiple cameras, an eye-tracking device, and related low-cost components, along with the assessment software for assessing motor function and cognitive, emotional, and personality functioning. &lt;br/&gt;iRehab consists integrates multidisciplinary methodologies and sensors to assess and assist the cognitive and physical rehabilitation of persons affected by various impairments. This work highly interdisciplinary work follows a cyber-physical approach. It provides new research opportunities across the fields of human-centered computing, computer vision, assistive technology, robotics, machine learning, and neuroimaging. This work advances research in human brain activity mapping, personalized medicine, and big data. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The proposed instrument exhibits potential for large broader impact as it directly contributes to future healthcare and human wellbeing improving accessibility to affordable rehabilitation for a broad range of patients. The instrument is likely to accelerate the recovery of a large spectrum of injuries and diseases including those causing motor, neurological, and cognitive disorders. An education plan includes course development, internships, workshops and tutorials, and an on-line resource center. In addition to many educational impacts, impact will be felt on the fundamental research in the areas addressed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337866</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margrit</FirstName>
      <LastName>Betke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>betke@cs.bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
