<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an X-Ray Diffractometer for Undergraduate Education and Research in Materials Characterization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>77808</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Descrition:&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) grant will support acquisition of a X-Ray diffraction system for undergraduate education and research in materials characterization across multiple disciplines including Physics, Chemistry, Chemical Engineering, Mechanical Engineering and Industrial Engineering at Kettering University, Flint, Michigan The award will enhance cross-disciplinary research and training at all levels, especially in areas such as, a)investigation and characterization of La(1-x)SrxMnO3 and iron oxide (Fe3O4) nanoparticles for biomedical applications, b) characterization of carbon nanotubes (CNTs) synthesized by atmospheric plasma method, c) characterization of polymer based composite materials incorporating CNTs, d) characterization of atmospheric plasma deposited thin films, e) characterization of composite materials for biogas separation membranes, and f) investigation and characterization of ceramic materials for solid oxide fuel cells. The investigators of this proposal mentor a number of undergraduate students in their research efforts; the results of their investigation are usually published in peer reviewed journals. These students also make presentations at the local, regional, and national meetings. Thus, the instrument will help talented students in their research exploration. In addition, more than twelve courses across four departments will be benefited by the development of new laboratory experiments and teaching aid that will use X-Ray diffraction instrument. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) grant will support acquisition of a X-Ray diffraction (XRD)system for undergraduate education and research in materials characterization across multiple disciplines including Physics, Chemistry, Chemical Engineering, Mechanical Engineering and Industrial Engineering at Kettering University, Flint, Michigan. The award will play a major role in original contributions to research in the areas that are identified as national grand challenges with broad societal impact in technologies involving novel materials, renewable energy production and storage, and nanotechnology for biomedical applications. It will also add an extra dimension to the existing materials characterization techniques at Kettering, which include an environmental scanning microscope, Raman spectrometer, and photoluminescence instrument for characterizing materials. The X-Ray diffraction system will facilitate stronger integration of the on-campus and off-campus co-op-work mediated education into a holistic education model. In addition, the system will help develop a stronger research and education liaison between Kettering University and its industrial partners. The award will help with recruitment and retention of students, including under-represented groups into careers in science and engineering by using the XRD to spark interest through nationally recognized outreach and recruitment programs at Kettering University. The instrument will also be used for professional development for high school and middle schools teachers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337615</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Corneliu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rablau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crablau@kettering.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lihua</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lwang@kettering.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Prem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vaishnava</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pvaishna@kettering.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nartker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>snartker@kettering.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bahram</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roughani</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>broughan@kettering.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kettering University</Name>
      <CityName>Flint</CityName>
      <ZipCode>485046214</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8107629677</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 University Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9141</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD. INST - EQUIP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
