<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Conference on Nitride Semiconductors ICNS10, August 25-30, 2013. To be Held at the Gaylord Hotel Convention Center, National Harbor MD.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed project seeks financial support for the participation of student, underrepresented groups and young researchers in a conference to be held at the Gaylord Hotel Convention Center, National Harbor, MD, from August 25 to 30, 2013.. The International Conference on Nitride Semiconductors ICNS10 will address research areas in Wide bandgap group-III nitrides. This annual meeting offers an important forum to review and identify all aspects of energy efficiency electronics, infrared and solid state lighting. The topics are divided into twelve sections and the committee has assembled a group of invited speakers, experts in the field, for each section: Bulk and Template Growth, Epitaxial Growth and Structural Properties, Nanostructures and Novel Nitride Alloys, Light Emitting Diodes and Improving Efficiency, Lasing and Laser Diodes, Power and High Frequency Devices, Optical and Magnetic Properties, Solar Cells and Energy Harvesting, Device Fabrication and Reliability, InN and Related Materials, Theory and Modeling of Materials and Devices, Sensors and Photodetectors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1340370</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wetzel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wetzel@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Ardie Butch</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dillen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dillen@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
      <CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
