<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Planning for a Teacher Fellowship/Master Teacher Fellowship Program to Serve High-Need Schools in Urban Southwestern Connecticut</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>192347</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lidia C. Yoshida</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>University of Bridgeport (UB), in partnership with neighboring high-need school districts (Bridgeport, Norwalk, and Stamford) proposes to engage in a highly effective Capacity Building Project leading to the design of a combined Teaching Fellowship/Master Teaching Fellowship (TF/MTF) program. The investigators are developing a program to recruit, prepare, and retain secondary science teachers committed to teaching physical science in high-need school districts in urban Southwestern Connecticut. The project is developing the capacity to recruit ten TFs from UB's student body preparing to graduate in science-related and five MTFs from in-service secondary science teachers who already serve in partner school districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project supports the advancement of discovery through the identification of effective ways of recruiting, preparing, and retaining high-school science teachers in urban high-poverty settings, ultimately leading to enriched and effective learning experiences of underrepresented students in science, and their consequent increased recruitment into science-related careers. In addition, the project is providing essential information for practitioners and scholars by analyzing the practices of expert science teachers who are successful in high-poverty urban school districts, and making their images public (presentation at national conferences and publication in peer-reviewed journals). Third, the benefits of the project to society consist in the potential applications of these findings at a larger scale. As such, it serves as a model of science education improvement in high-need schools for adoption by other teacher preparation institutions nationwide.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1340037</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nelson</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ngoh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ngoh@bridgeport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ioana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Badara</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ibadara@bridgeport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Buket</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barkana</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbarkana@bridgeport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Navarun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gupta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>navarung@bridgeport.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Bridgeport</Name>
      <CityName>Bridgeport</CityName>
      <ZipCode>066045620</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2035764973</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>126 Park Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7908</Code>
      <Text>Teaching &amp; Mstr Tchng Fellows</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
