<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The IEEE International Conference on Healthcare informatics (ICHI) is the premier international forum concerned with the application of computer science principles, information science principles, information technology, and communication technology to address problems in healthcare, public health, and wellness. The ICHI 2013 program includes several invited talks by leading researchers in Health Informatics, contributed paper presentations, as well as several workshops on emerging topics. ICHI 2013 is scheduled to be held during September 9-11 in Philadelphia, PA, USA.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award supports approximately 20 students from U.S. universities to attend the ICHI 2013 doctoral consortium, an event that is specifically targeted to Ph.D. students. Special effort will be made to actively encourage women and members of other groups that are currently underrepresented in STEM disciplines to participate. The doctoral forum enables doctoral students to benefit from one-to-one mentoring from senior researchers, and interactions with other students in Health Informatics at a critical stage in their careers. The award contributes to the education and training of the next generation of researchers and educators in an increasingly important area. It also helps broaden the participation of members of underrepresented groups and women in Health Informatics research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1342445</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccy24@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Drexel University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158955849</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 8th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8018</Code>
      <Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
