<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Miltiwavelength Integrated Nanphotonic Transceivers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposed device research incorporates material research and nanofabrication technology with new system approaches to enhance current fiber optic networking capabilities. The work is based on research results from a grant made by the previous NSF CISE EMTNano program that involved silicon phontonics, nano fabrication and nonlinear optical polymer research. The device research involves miniaturizing optical components to the nano-scale, thereby extending the t reach of optics to ever shorter distances. The miniaturization permits enhancement of bandwidth through the use of on-chip dense wavelength division multiplexing allowed by silicon photonics components. The miniaturized system with reduced power consumption permits use of broadband sources instead of a multitude of stabilized lasers. This new system approach promises not only breakthroughs in size and cost but an epiphany in the approach to control of process and thermal variations. The material research involves high temperature electro-optic chromophores that exhibit high electro-optic coefficients when guested in polymeric hosts. The nanotechnology includes infiltration and poling of these novel composite polymers in slotted silicon nano-waveguide structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposed research include energy conservation, education and economic benefits. IT equipment consumes several percent of the annual national energy consumption of 3.6 PW-h. Efficient computing will increase IT capacity while lowering energy consumption. This research impacts education in numerous ways. The program will provide research opportunities for graduate and undergraduate students. The research results will be published as well as incorporated into courses in a timely fashion. The PI has a track record in encouraging participation of minority students and women and will continue to expand these efforts under this program. The proposal is based on the previous discoveries in fundamental research efforts and addresses the theme of the NSF I-Corps Teams, that is, to innovate scientific discoveries into technologies, products and processes that benefit society. Overall, the proposed work will broadly impact the society by providing the next-generation computing and information technology (IT) on which the society increasingly depends.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1342641</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mickelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mickel@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
