<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: EAGER: Enhancing the Cyber Security Workforce - The Human Angle</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>138051</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed study provides extensive new data in two scarcely examined research areas. The first is the overall impact that cyber competitions have on enhancing the cybersecurity workforce. There is widespread anecdotal evidence of the benefits of individual competitions, but a large-scale, carefully constructed study is needed to determine outcomes and causal relationships. Additionally, it is the first thorough examination of the psychological characteristics of people interested in cybersecurity. Related research has examined the personality traits of IT professionals, the cognitive styles of computer "hackers," and the academic abilities associated with success in STEM programs. However, no studies have focused exclusively on the cybersecurity field. The findings hold promise to transform existing ideas about the types of people who are qualified and willing to pursue careers in cybersecurity. Increasing the number of trained cybersecurity professionals is crucial to the continued success of both public and private enterprises. Competitions, such as NYU-Poly's digital "Capture the Flag" challenge, represent a promising approach towards accomplishing that goal using hands-on competition as a stimulus for learning. However, in order to improve the efficacy of future challenges, it is first necessary to examine the impact of past endeavors. Competitions present a unique opportunity to explore the psyche of individuals who have already displayed an interest in cybersecurity. Examining that population provides insight into the reasons why certain qualified individuals pursue careers in cybersecurity, while others do not. Such insight can also serve as an invaluable guide for the organizers of future efforts aimed at attracting a larger number of talented individuals to the cybersecurity workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1342091</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nasir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Memon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>memon@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7434</Code>
      <Text>CNCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
