<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Efficient Temporal-Spatial Spectrum Sharing through Voluntary Exchange</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>896629</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nancy A. Lutz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to develop more efficient and flexible access to radio spectrum. Typically radio spectrum bands are allocated by the FCC to commercial and noncommercial users who can be thought of as "primary users." Such a user may not need to utilize the spectrum all of the time. This has led to the existence of "secondary users" who access the spectrum opportunistically. However, such secondary usage can bring interference to other secondary users and primary users. Furthermore, primary users have little motivation to permit this type of secondary use as there is no benefit to them and only risk.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To encourage spectrum sharing and enhance spectrum efficiency, it is important to have a mechanism or solution concept that creates the correct incentives for both primary and secondary users. However, there are significant communication costs as well as limitations involved in the sale or exchange of spectrum bands. Therefore, spectrum sharing through voluntary exchange is proposed to address these challenges for efficient spectrum access. The research project outlined here will determine which type of spectrum sharing mechanisms would be better for primary users, secondary users, and for society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, voluntary exchange mechanisms including monetary exchange and barter are examined to promote spectrum sharing between primary and secondary users where both the communication costs and constraints for information exchange are reflected in the spectrum sharing models. Moreover, new ways to avoid interference for users located in different regions are examined to further enhance spectrum efficiency.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Sharing spectrum and improving spectrum efficiency are current priorities of lawmakers and spectrum regulators, as evidenced through the National Broadband Plan (2010), the PCAST report on sharing spectrum between the federal government and non-government users (2012), the Spectrum Act of 2012, and two presidential memoranda on the topic (2010 and 2013). Clearly, development and application of appropriate economic theories to foster more opportunities for spectrum sharing is a desirable outcome with significant broader impact to all stakeholders, including commercial broadband providers, public safety, homeland security, and national defense.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1343380</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiangwei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xwzhou@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alison</FirstName>
      <LastName>Watts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wattsa@siu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Illinois University at Carbondale</Name>
      <CityName>Carbondale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>629014308</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6184534540</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Ofc. of Sponsored Projects Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7976</Code>
      <Text>EARS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
