<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Young scholar support for the 2013 annual meeting of the Society for the Study of Nanoscience and Emerging Technologies (S.NET), October 27-30, 2013, Boston</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Introduction&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award support is to provide support for an international conference, the fifth annual meeting of the Society for Study of Nanoscience and Emerging Technologies (S.NET). The conference will be held October 27-30, 2013, at Northeastern University in Boston. The funds being sought will enable students, postdoctoral researchers, and young scholars with few travel resources to fully participate in the 2013 meeting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will serve to facilitate further development of the S.NET. The requested support will enable participation in the conference by the rising generation of scholars, many of which may otherwise be unable to attend. This is worthwhile effort to encourage growth of the community of researchers devoted to anticipating the societal and ethical impacts of emerging technologies. It will promote broad ranging intellectual inquiry and contribute to the continued development of diverse bodies of literature on society and emerging technologies. and will&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The awards will promote the professional development of the recipients at a crucial stage in their careers, and it will help to ensure a diverse and representative society. In addition, it will enable scholarly work with applied benefits for the advancement of science and technology, product innovation and commercialization, sustainable economic development, and, as a consequence, the long-term material and physical betterment of humankind. It will also provide an important opportunity for the dissemination of US-funded nanotechnology in society research to international audiences, and will further the cross-cultural approaches to understanding technology development and social change.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1343126</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bosso</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c.bosso@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bennett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mgbenne1@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1675</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1675</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
