<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Graduate Student Workshops in Mathematics with Applications to Physics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports summer schools in Geometry and Physics held at The Simons Center for Geometry and Physics (SCGP) at Stony Brook University. The first summer school is titled "Moduli spaces and singularities: algebraic and differential-geometric approaches" and will take place in June-July 2014. The summer schools are aimed at graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scientific activities of the Simons Center for Geometry and Physics (SCGP) at Stony Brook University are supported by the Center's endowment, and are aimed at the research community of mathematicians and physicists. The goal of these activities is to further knowledge in the collaborative areas of theoretical physics and geometry. Modern theoretical physics has contributed a series of profound geometric ideas which gave rise to entirely new mathematical fields and revitalized older ones. By now there is a large and rapidly growing number of both mathematicians and physicists working at the interface between physics and geometry. The influence flows in both directions, with mathematical techniques and ideas contributing crucially to major advances in mathematical and theoretical physics. In addition to research workshops the SCGP plans to run summer schools in Geometry and Physics aimed at graduate students. The annual activity called for under this proposal is a two-week summer school for graduate students. The lion's share of the NSF support is for graduate student support (lodging and meals) during summer schools. The remaining funds are necessary to pay for travel and lodging of outside senior lecturers at the summer schools.&lt;br/&gt;The broad impact of this activity will be to bridge the existing gap between mathematicians and physicists at the level when new researchers are entering academia and encourage interdisciplinary research up the pipeline. The interdisciplinary character of the Center provides a nice environment for training graduate students and young researchers. An effort will be made to involve many women as participants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1343135</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abanov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alexandre.abanov@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morgan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmorgan@scgp.stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1265</Code>
      <Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
