<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Painting Between the Ice: Antarctic Biodiversity from the Dry Valleys to the Sea Floor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter T. West</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI proposes to collaborate with three field teams to study and create paintings focused on biodiversity&amp;#8232;in the McMurdo Dry Valleys and Ross Sea. She proposes to create a series of mural-size paintings based on organisms native to the Southern Ocean?s sea floor and the soil of the Dry Valleys. The paintings will explore uniquely adapted Antarctic invertebrates and their habitats &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to explore the benthic communities in the Ross Sea, either first-hand or through the observations of specimens gathered by scientifc divers. She proposes, if possible, ?to study, draw, and paint the organisms while they are still ?alive, flush with natural pigment, and illuminated by the unique&amp;#8232;blue glow of sunlight filtered through the ice covering the ocean?s surface.? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Painting en plain air, she also proposes to subsequently work with field teams to investigate and capture on canvas the complex soil ecosystems of Taylor Valley. She will observe and paint nematodes, tardigrades, and rotifers extracted from the soil in and around the Valleys? network of water&amp;#8232;tracks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1344504</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lily</FirstName>
      <LastName>Simonson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Simonson Lily</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900682708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5294</Code>
      <Text>Antarctic Education</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
