<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: An Integrated Search, Analytics, and Imaging (SAI) Platform for Clinical Decision Support and Mobile Health</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project proposes to develop and deliver to health care enterprises a next generation imaging, analytics, and search solution that meets not only the current needs of multi-enterprise medical image viewing, but satisfies emerging demands related to clinical decision support and mobile health. The project addresses one of the ?Big Data? problems of medical imaging, i.e. providing access anywhere within the healthcare enterprise to large studies, advanced imaging tools, and image-based analytics across a spectrum of devices from powerful personal computers to mobile devices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to translate novel research using quantitative imaging biomarkers into actual clinical practice. Medical imaging is commonly used for cancer screening, treatment planning, and monitoring but the results that come from purely qualitative interpretations of these images are not always definitive. Recent progress has shown that high-throughput extraction and analysis of advanced quantitative imaging features from medical images (?radiomics?) can be used to increase the accuracy and confidence of cancer screening in certain cases. The goals of this project are to incorporate these analytics into a commercially available system for medical image display and distribution which is necessary for widespread clinical adoption. These advances will enable health care providers to lower costs associated with unnecessary follow up exams as well as to improve patient outcomes through identification of tumors that are more likely to be resistant to treatment and to more efficiently and accurately monitor the response to treatment using medical imaging.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1345927</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chylla</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>roger.chylla@healthmyne.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/27/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>HealthMyne, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Madison</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537171945</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082396871</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>918, Deming Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
