<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RCN-UBE: Faculty Development Network for Undergraduate Biology (FDN-UB)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>498753</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher Meyer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This RCN-UBE network project seeks to advance the professional development of undergraduate biology faculty to improve teaching and learning of biology consistent with changes in undergraduate biology education that are called for in the Vision and Change report. Progress in faculty development has been hampered by limited interaction among faculty members, science education researchers, and higher education experts from across different institutional types, geographic locations, and demographic categories. This network will create, build, and support a community of practitioners who will analyze the state of the field of professional development, identify gaps in the practice of professional development, then engage professional societies and other organizations to engage in a series of coordinated and collaborative efforts to improve of faculty development. The goal is that improved opportunities for faculty development should enhance biology teaching and learning in all institutional contexts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Faculty Development Network for Undergraduate Biology will foster exchanges and partnerships between the major constituencies essential for effective biology faculty development through use of idea-generating network cluster meetings, all-network synthesis meetings, smaller working group meetings, and online collaboration tools. A Standards of Practice Working Group is synthesizing best practices, and compiling information and resources for professional development in biology education and for broader professional development communities. A Research Working Group is identifying gaps and disconnects in our understanding and/or practice of biology professional development as a starting point for developing future cross-institutional research projects to address questions related to best practices and ways to motivate and sustain change. Through the activities of the Sustaining Change Working Group, the network is partnering with centers, institutes, and national organizations to identify strategies for providing the local, institution-based follow-up needed to sustain changes initiated at national conferences and workshops. The network as a whole is interfacing with biology professional societies to develop society-based teams with common goals and materials for professional development in biology teaching and learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is funded jointly by the Directorate for Biological Sciences and the Directorate of Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education in support of efforts to address the challenges posed in Vision and Change in Undergraduate Education: A Call to Action http://visionandchange.org/finalreport/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1346570</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charlene</FirstName>
      <LastName>D'Avanzo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cdavanzo@hampshire.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/31/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Uno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>guno@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Allen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>deallen@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sirum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksirum@bgsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>April</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maskiewicz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aprilmaskiewicz@pointloma.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elrod</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>elrods@uww.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8015</Code>
      <Text>BIO Innovation Activities</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7513</Code>
      <Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1664</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
