<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: Serious Game for Energy Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>224497</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glenn H. Larsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This STTR Phase I project, Serious Game for Energy Science (SGES), proposes to address the question 'Can a serious game in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math (STEM), with artificial intelligence and teacher controls, engage the learner, impact student problem-solving abilities, increase interest in STEM-related activities/fields, and positively impact student learning outcomes in science, math, and reading comprehension?' Educational institutions have seen increased demand for technologies impacting learning outcomes and promoting STEM interest. As gaming becomes more broadly accepted, there is greater demand for Serious Games - games built specifically to enhance learning. This research innovation will develop two components to be modeled in STEM serious game development: (1) artificial intelligence, and (2) instructional management tool for teachers. SGES will accomplish this innovation as well as contribute to, and advance, the body of knowledge in Serious Game development. SGES research objectives are to determine the effects of a serious game in Energy Science on students: engagement, problem-solving abilities, interest in STEM-related activities and fields, and learning outcomes in science, math, and reading comprehension. Students will be inspired to learn about energy science, energy production, and environmental impacts by being immersed in an interactive world with interesting characters and engaging story objectives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercial impact of Serious Game for Energy Science (SGES) is an expandable model adaptable to learning objectives across grades levels and content areas. This research will establish models for artificial intelligence and teacher controls in serious games, and support teaching science, math, and reading comprehension with gaming. This will impact the commercialization of serious games in any science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) topic. With the increase use of serious games in learning, development of this projects' research-based model will increase the economic competitiveness of the United States in the serious games market sector. Innovative serious games like SGES can potentially increase knowledge/interest in STEM related skills/careers addressing national needs for STEM graduates in the workforce. SGES will enhance math, science, environmental literacy, and reading comprehension through student exploration of energy science, energy production, and environmental impact using problem-solving, critical thinking, communication, and collaboration skills. The project research results will impact the number of students entering STEM related careers or graduating with STEM degrees by engaging them through game play. The SGES project aims to improve STEM education for all grade levels and improve educator development by providing educators with an effective use of technology in the classroom.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1346484</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Trevathan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Monica.Trevathan@tietronix.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Willis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>willis@uhcl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tietronix Software, Incorporated</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770582794</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2814619300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1331 Gemini Av.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1505</Code>
      <Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1505</Code>
      <Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8031</Code>
      <Text>Education Products</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8032</Code>
      <Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8043</Code>
      <Text>System Design and Simulation</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
