<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>OPTION 1: Small-Business ERC Collaborative Opportunity for the Commercialization of an Extreme Ultraviolet source at 13 nm for EUV lithography tool inspection</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199936</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fixed Price Award</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Deborah J. Jackson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Overview:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, KMlabs will work with the currently active ERC in EUV Science and Technology&lt;br/&gt;in an effort to optimize and commercialize a tabletop coherent extreme ultraviolet source&lt;br/&gt;based on high-order harmonic generation (HHG), targeted specifically for 13.5 nm wavelength.&lt;br/&gt;The end goal of this project is to produce a commercial prototype that can produce efficient&lt;br/&gt;13.5 nm light to support EUV lithography tool development. Such a small-scale laser source&lt;br/&gt;can be used for a variety of lithography support applications including optics characterization,&lt;br/&gt;metrology, and mask inspection, which can help to ensure the rapid deployment of this critical&lt;br/&gt;technology, currently planned for ~2015.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit :&lt;br/&gt;CU-Boulder, as a part of the EUV ERC, has been developing coherent EUV technology for more&lt;br/&gt;than a decade. Their recent work has led to a more comprehensive understanding of how to optimize&lt;br/&gt;the HHG upconversion process to generate EUV or x-ray light at a particular target wavelength.&lt;br/&gt;This for the first time allows us to identify specific approaches that may allow for significant&lt;br/&gt;(up to 3 orders of magnitude) increases in coherent flux capability at 13 nm.&lt;br/&gt;KMlabs has proven track of record for successfully commercializing cutting edge scientific&lt;br/&gt;results?for example the eXtreme Ultraviolet Ultrafast Source (XUUS), introduced in 2009. The&lt;br/&gt;XUUS is a broadband coherent ultrafast EUV source optimized to generate 30 nm light, and &gt;15&lt;br/&gt;XUUS setups have been delivered to research customers worldwide. Optimization of this source&lt;br/&gt;for 13 nm will make it possible to address a much greater range of industry needs. We have&lt;br/&gt;identified three possible approaches for optimizing 13 nm flux. In this project we plan to&lt;br/&gt;perform a direct comparative evaluation of these approaches. Based on our physical understanding,&lt;br/&gt;we believe we can determine the global optimum for HHG conversion to 13 nm.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts :&lt;br/&gt;KMlabs and the EUV ERC will each leverage their technical strengths, and this project will&lt;br/&gt;serve to leverage the impact of EUV ERC technology on the science and technology enterprise.&lt;br/&gt;The rapid advance of microelectronics technology, as described by Moore?s law, has been a&lt;br/&gt;major driver of the global economy. This advance has been driven primarily by progress in&lt;br/&gt;lithography that allows for shrinking feature size. Current visible wavelength tools are straining&lt;br/&gt;against fundamental limits, and the International Technology Roadmap for Semiconductors has&lt;br/&gt;been anticipated a shift to EUV lithography for quite some time. The timeline for EUV had&lt;br/&gt;repeatedly experienced delays because the use of EUV light, which is strongly absorbed by&lt;br/&gt;all materials, is radically more difficult to work with than visible/UV.&lt;br/&gt;Nevertheless, recent progress in 13 nm EUV light sources for lithographic exposure has made&lt;br/&gt;its adoption for the 22 nm node-size in the next generation computer chips a high priority.&lt;br/&gt;EUV lithography remains untested at the systems and large-scale production level, with many&lt;br/&gt;unknowns. Improved capabilities for mask defect detection and characterization, for characterizing&lt;br/&gt;optics degradation with long-term use, and for tasks such as alignment and quality control,&lt;br/&gt;can all benefit from a usable tabletop at-wavelength laser source. An HHG-based coherent 13&lt;br/&gt;nm EUV light source is a relatively low cost, small-scale, contamination-free coherent source&lt;br/&gt;suitable for industrial application, and which has already been proven to enable new capabilities&lt;br/&gt;such as coherent diffractive EUV imaging with near-wavelength resolution, and for materials&lt;br/&gt;characterization. KMlabs plans to build on this proposed work in future with development of&lt;br/&gt;reflectometer/ellipsometer instruments, as well as an inspection microscope for EUV lithography&lt;br/&gt;applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1347407</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murnane</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Margaret.Murnane@Colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaoshi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xzhang@kmlabs.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>KAPTEYN-MURNANE LABORATORIES, INC.</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803013081</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3035449068</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4775 Walnut St. 102</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1480</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING RESEARCH CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>129E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: MANUFACTURING &amp; PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>130E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: MICRO/OPTO ELECTRONICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
