<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Open Source Tools for Processing of Raw LiDAR Observations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>204120</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This EAR Geoinformatics Program grant will support development of a suite of open source tools to allow users of Light detection and Ranging (LiDAR) data the ability to create point clouds and derivative products by starting at the raw LiDAR observations (i.e. range, angle, intensity, position, attitude), which is currently not possible using existing archived datasets and software. Broad objectives of this proposal are (a) to empower the researcher to exploit and tailor LiDAR post-processing to optimize data quality and meet science driven spatial and accuracy requirements and (b) to empower the scientist to focus on science questions without the need to consider time-consuming reformatting, data storage georeferencing and error estimation tasks. The developed tools would be amendable to both processing and analysis of airborne LiDAR, mobile laser scanning (MLS) observations, and static terrestrial (tripod) LiDAR data and would allow for tools to process full waveform observations. Scientific applications of high resolution LIDAR surface mapping span the fields of geomorphology, geodesy, hydrology, forestry, and resource management to name a few. The number of geoscientists employing LIDAR mapping for research is growing rapidly. A graduate student will be supported by this project and the resultant software will be distributed to users through the OpenTopography web portal and will be open source. Training with the developed tool set will be conducted through planned focused Earth science and remote sensing workshops.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1347092</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Glennie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clglennie@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Butler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hobu.inc@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7255</Code>
      <Text>GEOINFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
