<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Small Business - ERC Collaborative Opportunity to develop an instrument for trace detection of O2 using a high-finesse prism optical cavity and the Faraday Effect</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fixed Price Award</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Deborah J. Jackson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit :&lt;br/&gt;In this project a new fully optical CE-FRS detection scheme is proposed to mitigate needs&lt;br/&gt;for any chemical treatments of the sample gas that is usually required with currently available&lt;br/&gt;instrumentation for trace oxygen sensing. The project will leverage unique capabilities of&lt;br/&gt;development and commercialization of cavity enhanced technologies by Tiger Optics and the&lt;br/&gt;new sensing technology based on FRS developed and demonstrated by MIRTHE. Initially a proof-of-concept&lt;br/&gt;prototype system will be investigated based on a conventional two mirror high-Finesse cavity&lt;br/&gt;equipped with a custom FRS optics for signal extraction. Most importantly the proposed research&lt;br/&gt;will also explore the possibility of implementing CE-FRS using the Tiger Optics proprietary&lt;br/&gt;high-Finesse optical prism cavity technology. This unique technology would allow CE-FRS to&lt;br/&gt;be implemented in combination with standard cw-CRDS in the same commercial instrument, permitting&lt;br/&gt;sensitive broadband detection of paramagnetic and diamagnetic molecules simultaneously. The&lt;br/&gt;proposed technology will eliminate routine maintenance issues, chemical conversion uncertainty&lt;br/&gt;and other disadvantages typical for electrochemical systems or indirect sensing technologies.&lt;br/&gt;The proposed direct laser-based detection provides significant advantage in industrial applications&lt;br/&gt;where 24-7 continuous monitoring is required and in environmental applications where analyzers&lt;br/&gt;are often situated in remote locations with basic infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts :&lt;br/&gt;Development of a CE-FRS method will open up possibilities for sensitive monitoring of many&lt;br/&gt;other paramagnetic species. This method will be suitable for real-time monitoring of trace&lt;br/&gt;concentrations of radicals involved in combustion and atmospheric chemistry, i.e. NO, NO2,&lt;br/&gt;OH, HO2, and CH. In many cases, while the presence of these radicals is known, the reaction&lt;br/&gt;rates and abundances are not well known due to the lack of in situ monitoring capabilities.&lt;br/&gt;A direct laser-based method can provide a new tool for monitoring trace-radicals in a wide&lt;br/&gt;range of applications such as environmental monitoring, industrial process control or combustion&lt;br/&gt;diagnostics. Therefore scientific and engineering advancements in this field integrated with&lt;br/&gt;a comprehensive educational program addressing specific career development goals at each academic&lt;br/&gt;level from high school students to post-doctoral researchers, will provide an excellent training&lt;br/&gt;for the new generation</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1347523</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wysocki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gwysocki@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Erika</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coyne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ecoyne@tigeroptics.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tiger Optics, LLC</Name>
      <CityName>WARRINGTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>189762426</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2153436600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>250 TITUS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1480</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING RESEARCH CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>130E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: MICRO/OPTO ELECTRONICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>132E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: SENSING &amp; INFO SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
