<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Connections: STEM Educational Research Communities and Knowledge Transfer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>564921</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project, conducted by Search Technology, Inc., and Georgia Institute of Technology, will seek to better understand how research ideas are communicated in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) education. The project will use bibliometric analysis to study patterns in how research publications cite each other, mapping the flow of ideas within STEM education research as well as cognitive science research. This project will help show what are the key influences on STEM education research, and what makes STEM education research influential. This project will aim to help the STEM education research community develop and make better use of its research base, and work effectively with researchers from other fields. The Division of Research on Learning in the Education and Human Resources directorate supports this work as part of its mission to advance STEM education research, including research on STEM learning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first stage of the project will involve analyzing data bases covering a broad range of published research, examining patterns of citation. The second stage will focus on the influential report, How People Learn, published by the National Research Council, and include textual analysis of content. The third stage will involve outreach to the research community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1348765</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Porter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aporter@searchtech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Youtie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jan.youtie@innovate.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Search Technology Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Peachtree Corners</CityName>
      <ZipCode>300923328</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7704411457</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6025 The Corners Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7625</Code>
      <Text>REAL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7980</Code>
      <Text>Core R&amp;D Programs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
