<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Continental Scientific Drilling Program, ICDP</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5700000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leonard E. Johnson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ICDP is an internationally managed and operated Earth Science research program. It addresses&lt;br/&gt;fundamental geoscientific problems of global significance and is undertaken by international&lt;br/&gt;teams of scientists at carefully selected sites around the world. ICDP serves the entire Earth&lt;br/&gt;Science community and is peer-reviewed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Significant progress has been made in recent years in the conceptual understanding of the&lt;br/&gt;highly complex 'System Earth' with its numerous subsystems. As a result, it has become clear&lt;br/&gt;that scientific drilling is an indispensible tool in our understanding of Earth processes&lt;br/&gt;and properties. Drilling provides the only means of obtaining direct information on processes&lt;br/&gt;operating at depth. It allows for determination of in situ-properties of solid materials and&lt;br/&gt;fluids and permits testing of hypotheses and models derived from surface observations, remote&lt;br/&gt;sensing data and laboratory experiments. In addition, drill holes may be used as a natural laboratory for experiments and as an observatory for long term monitoring of ongoing active processes. Earth drilling, therefore, plays a critical&lt;br/&gt;role both in scientific research directed towards improved understanding of the workings of our planet and in solving urgent societal problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ICDP support is based on the 'comingled funding' principle and international costsharing. Each drilling project is independently organized in the form of a Joint Research Venture(JRV)between the ICDP and the Principle Investigator(s). This award provides continued support for the U.S. participation in ICDP.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1348185</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ulrich</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harms</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ulrich.harms@gfz-potsdam.de</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carola</FirstName>
      <LastName>Knebel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c.knebel@icdp-online.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>HELMHOLTZ-ZENTRUM POTSDAM - DEUTSCHES GEOFORSCHUNGSZENTRUM GFZ</Name>
      <CityName>Potsdam Germany</CityName>
      <ZipCode/>
      <PhoneNumber>4933128810</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Telegrafenberg A 17 14473</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>Germany</CountryName>
      <StateName/>
      <StateCode/>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8212</Code>
      <Text>INTEGRATED EARTH SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7571</Code>
      <Text>DEEP EARTH PROCESSES SECTION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
