<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER:Engineering Efficient, Thin-film Hybrid Photovoltaic Elements Based on Excitonic Energy Transfer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nadia El-Masry</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to engineer a new type of ultra-thin, flexible, yet efficient and robust photovoltaic solar cell. The approach is to employ solution processable semiconductor nanocrystals that are chemically grafted on electrically accessible, flexible Si nanopillar p-i-n junction substrates.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: The design of these novel hybrid solar cells is based on non-radiative and radiative energy transfer, which provides efficient electromagnetic coupling between highly absorbing nanocrystals and 3-dimensionally structured thin Si substrates. Such longer-range energy transfer mechanisms essentially avoid typical charge transfer problems leading to lower efficiencies of traditional bulk-heterojunction geometries. Optically thick nanocrystal multilayers with engineered energy transfer interactions will be grafted on dense arrays of nanopillars processed from thin Si substrates with enhanced light trapping capabilities and optimized p-i-n junctions for efficient charge separation and transport. Such nanocrystal-sensitized Si solar cells are expected to reach 15% conversion efficiency with minimal Si material requirements.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: The development of thin, yet efficient photovoltaic elements should assist in lessening our reliance on fossil fuels and contribute towards the development of domestic, eco-friendly and renewable energy-generating technologies and industries. Hybrid optoelectronics structures will be of interest for various light-emitting and sensor applications and such interdisciplinary approach will provide students with an opportunity to gain proficiency in the fields of photonics, materials science and engineering and physics and to connect to industrial projects and international collaborators. Strong effort will be devoted to involve undergraduate and pre-college students and facilitate their interest in science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1350800</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Malko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anton.malko@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/24/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
      <CityName>Richardson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>091E</Code>
      <Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
