<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Integrating Physical Models into Data-Driven Inference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>534826</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sushil Prasad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Individualized assessment of high-dimensional spatiotemporal systems - such as in-vivo human physiological systems - has been increasingly enabled by paralleled advances in two fields: computer modeling that supports quantitative understanding of the dynamic behavior and mechanism of these systems, and modern sensor technologies that continuously improve the quantity and quality of measurement data available for analysis. There is, however, a gap between the two fields that is ubiquitous in many application domains: the current state of computer modeling is generally decoupled from specific measurements of an individual system, while individualized data-driven analysis often struggles for realistic domain contexts. This project aims to bridge this gap by investigating and developing new methodologies, algorithms, and software that will enable the integration of complex domain knowledge - yielded by computer simulation of domain physical models - into the process of data-driven inference. The overarching theme of this research is flexibility and robustness. Specifically, it addresses the following three challenges: 1) to enable a plug-and-play inclusion of domain physical models catering to different efficiency vs. accuracy needs; 2) to further overcome the lack of measurements and potential errors in domain physical models by exploiting the low-dimensional structure in high-dimensional systems; and 3) to enable a robust adaptation of the time-varying error that potentially exists in domain physical models. The driving application of this project is individualized modeling of in-vivo cardiovascular systems - using noninvasive biomedical and physiological data - for improved prevention, diagnosis, and treatment of heart diseases. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The outcome of this project will contribute theoretically, algorithmically, and computationally to the foundations of statistical inference, and extend to a wide range of applications such as tumor modeling, climate modeling, systems biology, and finance. In addition, this project will deliver publicly-available multicore/GPU software that will encapsulate the most effective algorithms developed. These toolkits will contribute to the national effort toward noninvasive medicine and healthcare, while supporting numerous scientific applications involving data-driven modeling and inference. This project also includes an integrated educational and outreach program to foster interdisciplinary research training and to increase participation of underrepresented groups in STEM disciplines. It includes: 1) development and evaluation of "learning-by-doing" concept in graduate and undergraduate education; 2) research training for students from graduate to high-school levels, with a focus on engaging women and underrepresented students at an early stage; and 3) broader outreach activities to area K-12 students and Paramedic communities. The participation of women, underrepresented, K-12, and Paramedic groups are reinforced through continued partnerships between the PI and different programs offered in RIT, local school district, and community college.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1350374</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linwei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>linwei.wang@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
      <CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7361</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND WORKFORCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CL10</Code>
      <Text>Career-Life Balance Supports</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>019Z</Code>
      <Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
