<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Transport properties and morphology associated with bursting-bubble induced jetting phenomena</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>423620</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Bird, James&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1351466&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed CAREER project is focused on understanding the physic al mechanism of the generation of aerosol droplets as bubbles burst. Understanding the physics behind submicron aerosol formation is important in a host of engineering applications ranging from turbine corrosion to the dispersion of respiratory deceases, since their residence time in the atmosphere can be on the order of weeks. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;When a bubble bursts, a set of droplets is formed and these droplets break into other smaller droplets, the larger of which break up further creating a hierarchy of droplet sizes. Ultimately, submicron aerosol droplets are formed that are not predicted with current fluid dynamic models, since the primary physical mechanism responsible for their formation is unknown. The goal of this proposal is to explore three concepts on how jet drops from small bursting bubbles may account for observed submicron aerosols. One concept is that the empirical formulas that relate the size of millimeter bubbles to the size of jet drops that they produce may not be valid for micron-scale bubbles. Another concept is that satellite and sub-satellite droplets may develop when larger droplets are produced, and that these smaller droplets may account for the unexplained submicron aerosols. The final concept is that larger bubble-induced jets may couple with smaller jet drops or satellite drops and propel the smaller drops beyond the viscous sublayer. The PI will explore and evaluate these ideas using direct highspeed observations, numerical simulations, and appropriately dimensionalized experimental models.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results from the proposed work can find important applications with significant economic and societal impact, for example avoiding corrosion due to salt aerosols in sensors and engines operating in marine environments. Other applications on a local scale include modeling the airborne flux of aerosolized pathogens, such as bevotoxins from red tides to make better public policy decisions, such as which beaches to close. On a global scale, a better understanding of aerosol production is necessary to reduce uncertainty in global climate models, and will allow policy makers to better assess the risks and rewards of geoengineering mitigation strategies, such as deliberately injecting large amounts of sulfur particulates in to the atmosphere in hopes to counter the warming effects of greenhouse gases.&lt;br/&gt;The proposal also includes outreach and education activities that are complementary to the research project. It is proposed to develop workshops for pre-service Early Childhood Education teachers and intensive laboratory immersion experiences for seasoned in-service elementary and preschool teachers. Finally, the proposal includes a partnership with the Boston Museum of Science to develop new science modules that aim to increase scientific engagement between children and their parents.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1351466</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bird</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbird@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>058E</Code>
      <Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
