<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Multi-Functional Organic Electronics Through All-Conjugated Block Copolymers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>296633</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Organic materials broaden the scope and reach of electronic applications and devices by enabling their fabrication in previously inaccessible locations, surfaces, and applications. A common example is organic light-emitting diodes, which are widely used in commercial displays and have been demonstrated on flexible, transparent, and large-area surfaces. The capability to perform a range of functions, including light-emission, computing, sensing, solar energy conversion, energy storage, and catalysis is constrained by inherent disorder, especially at interfaces between organic semiconductors, and by a limited understanding of optoelectronic processes that occur at these interfaces. The central hypothesis of this work is that an emerging class of polymeric materials known as all-conjugated block copolymers can give enhanced energy and charge transfer, controlled nanoscale structure, and fundamental insight into the electronic properties of organic semiconductor interfaces. This hypothesis will be tested through the following research objectives: (1) quantify the role of crystallization, micro-phase segregation, and interfacial energy on the microstructure of all-conjugated block copolymer films, (2) develop a logical framework for improving the performance of OPVs, and (3) elucidate the role of interfacial structure and electronic properties on charge transfer between donor and acceptor organic semiconductors. This will be accomplished through polymer synthesis, structural characterization using grazing-incidence X-ray scattering, device fabrication and testing, and both steady-state and transient photophysical measurements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Organic electronic materials are widely used in applications such as lightweight LED displays and efficient, low-cost lighting. The work proposed here aims to increase the functionality of organic electronics for more ambitious targets, including affordable solar energy, printable computers, and rechargeable batteries. This will be accomplished through the development of novel materials capable of absorbing light, generating electricity, and transporting both positive and negative charges. Additionally, recognizing that community colleges educate large and diverse pools of future scientists and engineers, the Principle Investigator plans to establish a program for increasing the scientific literacy of community college students and encouraging their participation in undergraduate research programs. The outreach activities will provide community college students with knowledge of current research, familiarity with scientific writing and journal publications, and teamwork to discuss and solve problems. Students will also enhance their experience in chemistry, physics, and engineering through summer research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1352099</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rafael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Verduzco</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rafaelv@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
