<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Development of Mesoporous Metal-Organic Frameworks as a New Type of Platform for Enzyme Immobilization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>455000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eugene Zubarev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Solid State and Materials Chemistry program in the Division of Materials Research, Professor Shengqian Ma at the University of South Florida will develop mesoporous metal-organic frameworks (mesoMOFs) as a new type of host matrix materials for enzyme immobilization, which will not only circumvent the drawbacks of existing host matrix materials but also offer new platforms for "tunable" enzyme encapsulation. The aims of the proposed research include (i) design and synthesis of water-stable functional mesoMOFs; (ii) development of protocols to immobilize enzymes into mesoMOFs, characterizations of enzymes@mesoMOFs, and evaluation of their performances in enzymatic catalysis; and (iii) tailoring functional mesoMOFs as platforms for chemo-enzymatic and multi-enzymatic cascade catalysis. Mechanistic studies will also be performed to investigate the behavior of enzyme encapsulated within the mesoMOFs and to unveil the specific interactions between enzyme molecules and mesoMOF frameworks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Solid State and Materials Chemistry program in the Division of Materials Research, the proposed research aims to advance mesoporous metal-organic frameworks as a new type of host matrix materials for enzyme immobilization, which would impact chemical/fine chemical, pharmaceutical, and food industries: it will formulate new methodologies to construct functional metal-organic framework materials for a wider range of applications and help our understanding of enzymatic reactions in nature. The award will help the PI to establish a multidisciplinary research program of materials, solid-state chemistry, catalysis and biochemistry that will lead to the discovery of novel functional materials with profound relevance to energy sustainability and green chemistry. The proposed research will thereby provide the type of professional scientific training that would be desirable for STEM students. The integrated research and educational activities and proposed outreach programs will specifically target participation of minorities and underrepresented groups thus providing a platform to motivate and foster them for pursuing careers in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1352065</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shengqian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sqma@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/31/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1762</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7969</Code>
      <Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
