<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Network Frontier Workshop 2013; Evanston, Illinois; December 4-6 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Massimo Ruzzene</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This workshop support award is for the bi-annual meeting on complex networks "Network Frontier Workshop" to be held at Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois, December 4-6 2013. The meeting will bring together a diverse group of experts in complementary areas of network science, dynamical systems, and complex systems, with substantial emphasis given to topics that cut across disciplinary boundaries. Participants will include experts both in theory and in applications as well as students and postdoctoral researchers. They will, in addition, participate in discussions about future directions that are likely to lead to transformative research. The program will include tutorials, presentations by young researchers, and discussions about career opportunities, in addition to research talks by leading experts in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this workshop, presenters will report recent results in the area of network science and related applications. Participants will become aware of the latest results in their respective subfields, and will also be able to discuss with other experts in an interdisciplinary environment. This is expected to generate new insights and stimulate new interdisciplinary collaborations. In addition, the workshop will involve activities jointly organized with the Northwestern SIAM Student Chapter, which will include tutorials by experts, presentations by students and postdoctoral researchers, and discussions about career opportunities. The participation of early-career researchers will also help promote the transfer of expertise to the next generation of engineers, physicists, and mathematicians.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1352730</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adilson</FirstName>
      <LastName>Motter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>motter@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7478</Code>
      <Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>034E</Code>
      <Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
