<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Massive Stellar Explosions and their Host Galaxy Environments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan Wrobel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will enable Professor Maryam Modjaz of New York University to infer the properties of stripped supernovae (SNe) progenitors by measuring the properties of the local environment within their host galaxies. She will use the sample of 89 stripped supernovae from the Palomar Transient Factory survey, in order to reduce the known biases in previous samples toward high-metallicity galaxies. She will obtain spectra of the host galaxies and the portion of the host containing the supernovae. The mean metallicity in the host galaxy and in the SNe environments will be inferred from the Oxygen abundances measured from these spectra. The PI and her collaborators will also obtain high-resolution images of the more distant galaxies in order to map the blue-light distribution in the host galaxies. These will be used to characterize regions of active star formation and to determine the overall galaxy mass. The color and metallicity of the spatially-resolved region around the SNe will also be used to draw conclusions about the mass and metallicity of the progenitors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Long-duration gamma-ray bursts and stripped supernovae are among the most powerful explosions in the universe. Both are signals of the cataclysmic death of massive stars, but they contribute differently to the creation of heavy elements. The research funded with this award will lead to a better understanding of the chemical evolution of the universe by providing tools to determine which properties of stars determine their ultimate fate. This research will be integrated with the PI's education plans through two projects in cooperation with the American Museum of Natural History. Professor Modjaz will teach an after-school course entitled "Explosions in the Universe". The curriculum will be structured around teaching pedagogy that is likely to change student perceptions of the scientific process, using strategies and mentoring that enhance the learning of young women and underrepresented groups. In addition, the PI will coordinate astronomers at New York City area astronomy departments to participate in the Science Research Mentoring Program through AMNH. Through this program, high school students will participate in cutting-edge research and present their results at a workshop.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1352405</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maryam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Modjaz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mm5554@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
