<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>N2Women 2014 Student Travel Grants</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant supports students at U.S. institutions to attend the 4th Networking Networking Women (N^2Women) Workshop. This workshop will be co-足located with the 2014 annual conference of the ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication (SIGCOMM 2014), to be held in Chicago, Illinois, August 2014. The workshop will be a full-day event held on the Sunday preceding the main conference in order to foster connections between attendees early in the week. Moreover, we have selected the Sunday timeslot to avoid conflicts with the technical workshops associated with the conference, which will be held on the Monday preceding the conference. Priority will be given to students who will benefit from attending the workshop, but are unlikely to attend due to the unavailability of travel funding. Students attending the N^2Women Workshop will be encouraged to stay and attend SIGCOMM. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The intellectual merit of this proposal resides in the contributions that the student participants will make to (1) the N^2Women Workshop, (2) the SIGCOMM 2014 event (the premier conference in the networking communications field) and (3) the future scientific progress of the students? research. The exposure to the technical content of both the N^2Women Workshop and SIGCOMM 2014 will inspire students to address the tough problems in their respective field, with a long-足term benefit of scientific progress for these types of networks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The broader impact of this proposal is the development of the under-足represented graduate students who with this t ravel support are able to attend the N^2Women. The travel funds will allow these graduate students to attend high-足caliber technical presentations, be exposed to state-of-the-art research, and interact with leading researchers and fellow graduate students. We expect the impact to the students? careers from attending the N^2Women Workshop to be substantial.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1353944</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sami</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rollins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>srollins@cs.usfca.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of San Francisco</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941171080</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4154225203</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Contracts and Grants</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
