<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Resonance Force Microscopy for Nanoscale Manufacturing Process Monitoring</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1409994</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Debasis Majumdar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project aims to develop a production prototype of an automated nanoscale manufacturing process monitoring tool based on the resonance force microscope (RFM). The tool will combine image force microscopy (IFM, a version of RFM that measures the linear part of the susceptibility) and scattering near-field optical microscopy (sSNOM) with atomic force microscope for use in the hard disk drive (HDD) and semiconductor industries. sSNOM measures the dipole-dipole interaction force while IFM measures the dipole-dipole force gradient, both with nanometer spatial resolution. These techniques allow direct imaging of resonances associated with electrons, phonons, and plasmons. The capability to image plasmon resonances is well suited to probe the near-field (NF) profile associated with a plasmonic structure called near-field transducer (NFT) utilized in heat-assisted magnetic recording (HAMR). With HAMR universally viewed as the next generation technology for HDD industry, the need for a monitoring tool for mass production of HAMR head is acute since there is currently no simple way to probe the NF profile of NFTs. The objectives of the proposed project are (1) to successfully prototype an automated NFT characterization tool and (2) to field test it with one or more HDD manufacturers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will be felt not only in the HDD industry but across many industries. While the monitoring of NFT production is the near-term niche application for the automated tool, the same tool will have longer-term value for in-line characterization of physical and chemical properties of nanoscale materials and structures in the manufacturing environment of diverse industries, including, for example, the measurement of stress in the channel layer and chemical characterization of defects in semiconductor industry and monitoring of protein-based pharmaceuticals. In R&amp;D and academic settings, the RFM technique provides the capability to image individual biomolecules in situ, such as for the real-time monitoring of membrane protein dynamics on cells, which will provide unprecedented utility in biomedical and clinical research. A reliable label-free imaging tool with the capability to identify chemical bond information at the molecular level will potentially bring about revolutionary advances in many fields of basic and applied biological science, including drug discovery, proteomics, structural biology, and personalized medicine. The RFM technique will be simpler to implement as compared to other hybrid instruments involving high resolution microscopy, resulting in an affordable instrument for academic and research institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1353524</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Park</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sung@molecularvista.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Molecular Vista, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951191456</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4083061909</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 Great Oaks Blvd. #140</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1084</Code>
      <Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>165E</Code>
      <Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>169E</Code>
      <Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8240</Code>
      <Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
