<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Real-time, Low Cost Point-and-Shoot 3D Camera</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>749352</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project is aimed at developing a comprehensive software suite for 3D imaging. 3D imaging is the capture of physical shape and motion as digital data. The technology can be used to create special effects, take measurements in engineering, and automatically check product quality in factories. Current 3D imaging systems are often too expensive, too slow, or too inaccurate to provide viable commercial solutions. This project will develop new techniques for three areas within the broader topic of 3D imaging: reconstruction, inspection, and motion capture. The objective of the project is to develop fast software that can run on low-cost, commercially available sensors and computing hardware. The software will be designed to take advantage of new kinds of computer processors found in computers and mobile phones: heterogeneous processors. To provide high-quality results on this emerging computing platform, the project will develop new mathematical and software approaches.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will result from the introduction of low-cost, high performance 3D imaging tools to the marketplace. 3D printing is an example of the way in which reducing cost and making a technology easier to use can create entirely new applications and markets. The research objectives of this project will lead to 3D imaging products that are cheaper and easier to use than today's solutions. 3D imaging addresses large and growing markets in engineering, inspection, manufacturing, surveying, and product development. It can enhance these industries by reducing costs and saving time. Making the technology easier to use will allow it to be adopted more widely, cultivating new vocational skills and opportunities. An additional impact of this research will be to make 3D imaging accessible to researchers and professionals in new application areas such as medicine, consumer technology, and security systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1353432</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Slaughter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chris.c.slaughter@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lynx Laboratories Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787593925</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508234072</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3925 Braker Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
