<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SG: RUI: Pollinator competition and plant competition as mechanisms for evolutionary diversification in two hummingbird-pollinated plants of the Caribbean</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150353</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Ecologists have long sought to understand how competitive interactions within and between species shape patterns of species diversity in natural communities. Plant-pollinator competition differs from competition among animal species in a significant way: pollinators may compete for plants as much as plants compete for pollinators. This project examines the mechanisms by which competing pollinators partition flowering plants and whether such partitioning leads to floral diversification. The researchers will identify mechanisms using a combination of experiments in a large, enclosed garden mimicking a natural system, and field measurements of natural selection in wild populations of plants. The research adds a significant conceptual component to studies of ecological dynamics by directly linking ecological interactions between consuming pollinators to natural selection of their mutualist plant resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is a collaboration between an undergraduate college and a research institution. A minimum of ten undergraduates will be involved in every aspect of the work, from experiments with hummingbirds in the enclosed garden, to measurements of selection and reproductive success of plants in wild populations, to statistical analyses of data. Individuals from the host country of Dominica, West Indies, will participate in the field and laboratory studies to strengthen an international collaboration and to provide lasting knowledge in the host country once the project is completed. Findings will be disseminated to the public through popular articles in magazines in the USA and Dominica, podcasts in the USA, radio interviews and public lectures on Dominica and in the USA, on departmental websites, and public exhibits at the Smithsonian Institution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1353783</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>W. John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kress</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kressj@si.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Temeles</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ejtemeles@amherst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Amherst College</Name>
      <CityName>Amherst</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010025000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135422804</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Controller's Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7377</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1355</Code>
      <Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
