<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Characterization of the circadian clock in Nannochloropsis oceanica</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>655000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gerald Schoenknecht</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Circadian clocks are molecular oscillators with a period of about 24-h. Land plants use the interaction between their circadian clock and light signals to predict daily and seasonal changes. However, little is known on how light quality and the circadian clock reveal time, seasonal, and depth information in the marine ecosystem. The goal of this project is to study the circadian clock of the marine microalga Nannochloropsis oceanica. N. oceanica is currently used as a source of omega-3-fatty acids and due to its high lipid content is being investigated as a potential source of biofuel. N. oceanica belongs to the Stramenopiles a very diverse group of secondary endosymbionts that includes diatoms and plant pathogens such as Phytophtora. Although circadian clocks have been studied in animals, plants, fungi and bacteria, nothing is currently known about the molecular mechanisms regulating the circadian rhythms of Stramenopiles. As part of this project the PI's laboratory will start to identify the molecular components of the circadian clock and characterize the interaction between light signals and circadian rhythms in N. oceanica. These studies will advance our knowledge on the evolution of circadian oscillators, and provide a molecular framework to understand the role of circadian rhythms in phytoplankton physiology. In addition of training graduate students, the PI will provide laboratory research experience for undergraduate students planning to become secondary school teachers. These students will also have the opportunity to develop their own laboratory-teaching units.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1354721</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eva</FirstName>
      <LastName>Farre</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>farre@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
