<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: The Role of Patellin1/2 in Arabidopsis Vascular Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>281913</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gerald Schoenknecht</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The plant vascular system is of critical importance for normal plant function, yet the mechanisms that govern development of the intricate vascular patterns we observe in nature are largely unknown. The process begins when narrow files of cells are recruited from a field of cells in a pattern that predicts the final vein pattern. These cells subsequently develop into the procambium, the tissue that will ultimately produce the veins. The plant hormone auxin plays a pivotal role in this process. Directional canals of auxin flow determine the paths of recruitment of cells into the procambium. Polar localization of PIN auxin transport proteins, to the plasma membrane on one side of the cells of the developing procambium, results in these canals of auxin flow. The focus of this project is on the role of the Sec14-related proteins, PATELLIN-1 and -2 (PATL1/2), in the formation of a continuous vascular pattern in the plant model organism, Arabidopsis thaliana. Molecular genetic and imaging approaches will be used to test the hypothesis that PATL1/2 act in a signaling pathway that regulates PIN auxin transport protein localization in the developing vascular system. Completion of the project will provide insight into the complex process of vascular pattern formation. This enhanced understanding of vascular development may prove useful in designing genetic modifications of plants used for biofuels since the xylem of the veins makes up the bulk of plant biomass, a valuable source of renewable energy. This project also stands to broaden participation of women and underrepresented minorities in the biological sciences; Wellesley College is a private liberal arts college for women with a commitment to diversity. Undergraduates will be collaborators in all aspects of the scientific process, an experience that will provide excellent preparation for advanced training and which often translates into careers in science and medicine.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1354255</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>T. Kaye</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peterman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kpeterman@wellesley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/25/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wellesley College</Name>
      <CityName>Wellesley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024818204</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7812832079</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>106 Central Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
