<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Task Force to Re-envision the Network Office of the Long-term Ecological Research Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>114009</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010209</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saran Twombly</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) program currently supports a network office that coordinates research across the 26 active research sites, helps to organize an annual Science Council meeting along with a tri-annual All Scientists meeting, maintains and develops data maintenance programs to ensure data availability, and provides training sessions for information management and data collection. This project will support an effort to gather broad input on potential future roles and responsibilities of a network office, survey other research networks that do or do not have coordinating offices, and suggest potential structures for a future network office. The three goals of the project are appropriate and sufficiently inclusive to ensure that diverse opinions and options are considered. An inclusive list of scientific societies, research communities, and federal agencies will be consulted for input. The task force assembled to implement these activities consists of leading researchers in the fields of ecology, environmental biology, and ecosystem science. The results obtained will contribute significantly to the development of a network office that ensures communication and cooperation across the diverse LTER community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project are strong. The task force itself is comprised of 4 female researchers and one male, tipping the normal balance of scientific activities. The diverse activities planned will ensure that a wide range of ethnic groups is included along with individuals from very different sorts of institutions. Finally, the current network office has lead responsibility for a large number of LTER broader impacts, and these will figure heavily into the task force discussions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1355241</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
      <LastName>McKnight</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Diane.Mcknight@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ellison</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aellison@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goodale</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clg33@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1195</Code>
      <Text>LONG TERM ECOLOGICAL RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
