<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Advancing STEM Industries through Student Scholarships and Support Services</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>597210</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lidia C. Yoshida</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In order to address the needs of regional employers, this project at Chippewa Valley Technical College (CVTC) is creating pathways for its students to pursue careers in the STEM professional workforce. One pathway is providing well-qualified associate's degree graduates to employers in fields such as advanced manufacturing, construction and computing, while a second pathway leads to transfer to four-year institutions to pursue higher academic degrees as STEM majors. In addition to serving the needs of a growing industrial presence in western Wisconsin, the project is establishing a point of entry into STEM higher education for students in several rural high school districts in the vicinity of CVTC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;From a technical standpoint, the project is awarding 100 S-STEM scholarships to full-time students enrolled in the following associate's degree programs at CVTC: Industrial Engineering Technician, Civil Engineering Technician, Manufacturing Engineering Technologist, Information Technology-Network Specialist, Information Technology-Software Developer and Nano Engineering Technology. Besides the scholarships, support for the S-STEM scholars includes monthly events that focus on future educational and professional opportunities, access to a STEM Career Advisor, peer-led study groups and mentoring by faculty, alumni and industry professionals. Through the use of institutional research data and student surveys, outcomes being measured include the impact of the project on the enrollment, academic performance, retention and graduation of the S-STEM scholars, employment secured by program graduates and successful transfers to four-year institutions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1355958</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spaeth</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aspaeth@cvtc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wagner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwagner40@cvtc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Creviston</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>screviston@cvtc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hans</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mikelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hmikelson@cvtc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Chippewa Valley Technical College</Name>
      <CityName>Eau Claire</CityName>
      <ZipCode>547016162</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7158336419</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>620 W Clairemont Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
