<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SPARC3 Scholarship Initiative</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>611197</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Connie K. Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The S-STEM Program at Gaston College is using high-impact strategies to improve persistence and graduation rates for STEM students. Gaston College (GC) is a state-supported, open-door, comprehensive community college serving Gaston and Lincoln counties in North Carolina, and is a member of the 58 institution North Carolina Community College System (NCCCS). This program is intended for students preparing to transfer to a four-year institution for further study in any STEM discipline. This project enables the recruitment of larger numbers of STEM students and helps scholars address major barriers to completion through strong peer-support networks, and focused advising and mentoring. Success of the scholars is fostered by financial support, academic cohorts, mentoring, and supplemental group activities. While this project targets all STEM students, based on the demographics of the college and surrounding community, the project has a positive impact on the numbers of underrepresented students enrolling in and completing STEM programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Gaston College program uses high-impact strategies including cohort formation mentoring and meta-cognitive exercises to improve persistence and graduation rates for STEM students. The goals include (1) transformation of curricula through integration of inquiry-based instruction and development of a research methods course with an undergraduate research component as a capstone experience; (2) centralization of STEM student support services within a center environment to include advising, mentoring, cooperative work experiences and undergraduate research experiences, and tutoring; and (3) reduction of the unmet financial need of cohort students by providing scholarships. As part of the evaluation process, quantitative assessment is collected for both for scholarship recipients and the general population seeking Associate of Science degrees. Data include GPA, course grades, retention rates, enrollment and rates of progress towards degree, percentage of underrepresented groups, graduation rates, and transfer and/or job placement rate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1355569</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
      <LastName>Woodson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>woodson.heather@gaston.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ashley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hagler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hagler.ashley@gaston.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Armstrong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>armstrong.melissa@gaston.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gaston College</Name>
      <CityName>Dallas</CityName>
      <ZipCode>280349565</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7049226511</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Highway 321 South</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
