<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Vibrio as a model microbe for opportunistic heterotrophic response to Saharan dust deposition events in marine waters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200584</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Sieracki</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Overview: Dust and mineral aerosols are a significant source of micro and macronutrients to oligotrophic ocean surface waters. Evidence is growing that heterotrophic microbes may play key roles in processing deposited minerals and nutrients. Yet it is not known which components of dust stimulate the heterotrophic bacteria, which cellular mechanisms are responsible for the utilization of those components and how the activity of these bacteria affect the availability and utilization of dust-derived minerals and nutrients by marine autotrophs. Knowledge of these factors is key to understanding how dust deposition impacts carbon cycles and for predicting the response of tropical oceans to future changes in the frequency and intensity of dust deposition events. The objective of this project is to examine the specific effects of aeolian dust on heterotrophic microbes in a tropical marine system under controlled conditions. The central hypothesis is that in oligotrophic tropical systems numerically minor opportunistic bacteria are the first responders to influx of dust constituents and respond primarily by rapidly accessing soluble trace metals and limiting nutrients that are deposited with Saharan dust. The project will focus on two specific aims: 1) Quantify changes in community structure, composition and transcriptional activity among marine microbial populations upon exposure to dust, and 2) Identify key components in Saharan dust aerosols that stimulate or repress growth and/or activity in Vibrio, a model opportunistic marine heterotrophic group. The study will use a series of controlled experiments designed to identify and quantify heterotrophic microbial response to dust deposition events using both natural communities and model bacteria (Vibrio) through metagenomics, transcriptomics and atmospheric and marine biogeochemical techniques. This innovative approach will identify the most critical (reactive) components leached from dust aerosols on the microbial community as well as elucidate potential mechanisms of response.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: There is great interest in the biological response to dust aerosols given its potentially large influence on biogeochemical cycling, but there has been relatively little work that has addressed the mechanisms of response (especially among the heterotrophic microbial fraction) or identified the relative importance of specific constituents of dust aerosols. A detailed framework for microbial response (focusing on opportunistic heterotrophs) will facilitate efforts to link autotrophic and heterotrophic processing. This contribution is significant because it will provide one of the first end-to-end (chemistry to physiology to ecology) mechanistic pathways for marine biological response to desert dust aerosols.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The outcomes of this research will provide information on an often overlooked component of climate change, the long range effects of desertification, which could impact biogeochemical cycling throughout the oceans. Furthermore, working with Vibrio as a model will have the co-benefit of addressing the possible role of dust deposition on the global rise of a marine infectious agent. Additionally, this project will provide graduate, undergraduate and high school students with both training and active participation in research. All students will have opportunities to present their work at local and regional meetings as well as national (international) conferences. Through on-going programs at each institution, students from STEM under-represented groups will be recruited for research opportunities (and for entry into graduate programs). Additionally, through participation in the Georgia Coastal Research Council results of this work, and related issues in marine science and climate change, will be broadly disseminated to policy-makers and local (coastal) stakeholders through meetings, links to the GRGC website and listserv and targeted publications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1357140</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Landing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wlanding@fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1650</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8811</Code>
      <Text>Marine Microbial Ecology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9117</Code>
      <Text>MARINE BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
