<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IRES: International US-China Student Research Program in Advanced Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claire Hemingway</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on an international collaboration between US students from the University of South Florida (USF) and students and researchers from the University of Science and Technology of Beijing (USTB) China to conduct research related to Advanced Materials. For twelve weeks, the teams of students will study advanced aspects of Materials Science, specifically focusing on thin films and nanostructures, fracture and corrosion. They will be supervised by three professors at USTB, Xiaolu Pang, Kewei Gao and Lijie Qiao, along with the Principal Investigator. US students will travel to Beijing for three months each of three summers. Training in materials characterization will be provided to students from USF prior to the international visit to ensure that they make meaningful contributions and have a stimulating international research experience. Students will be encouraged to publish their scientific results in journals. Students will also be encouraged to disseminate and share their experience through presentations to diverse audiences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a result of this project, advanced materials will be developed and the results of the research will be published and disseminated through presentations. Students will form professional networks. Overall, this project will contribute to the development of a new generation of researchers trained with multidisciplinary and international skills.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358088</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
      <LastName>Volinsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>volinsky@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7727</Code>
      <Text>IRES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
