<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Research Experiences for Undergraduates in Chemistry at The University of Alabama</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>280000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Division of Chemistry (CHE) at the National Science Foundation, the Department of Chemistry at The University of Alabama is hosting 9 participants in a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) program for the summers of 2014 to 2016. These young scientists need exposure to modern research methods and tools as part of their training. This REU site aims to provide cutting-edge research training in chemical problems of relevance to the environment, materials, or biological chemistry. Students will be recruited primarily from the southeastern United States, and the Site will emphasize recruitment of students from underrepresented groups. The site will provide research experiences for a diverse student cohort who might not otherwise have access to research opportunities and help to prepare them for their future careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All participants will carry out projects under the supervision of active research faculty with experience in directing undergraduate students. Participants will choose research projects on a well-defined interdisciplinary problem in environmental, materials, or biological chemistry. Training gained during performance of these projects is enhanced by Monday and Friday one-hour seminars that together foster independence, maturity, and confidence and will develop researchers to think independently, search out new avenues of investigation, and to speak confidently in public. The program is enriched by a series of Wednesday seminars exploring ethical issues pertinent to chemical researchers. Students are housed in furnished on-campus apartments to promote social and intellectual interactions. Early in each summer's program, participants attend a series of meetings and activities designed to introduce the basics of scientific research while building camaraderie and a group identity. The program will help to improve the quality of the domestic graduate student pool.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358971</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Woski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swoski@as.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vincent</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>JVINCENT@BAMA.UA.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
