<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Study of the Spatial and Temporal Distribution of Atmospheric Gravity Waves Using Pressure Data From the Dense USArray Transportable Array</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>359396</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Margaret Benoit</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-technical statement&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The National Science Foundation has provided funds for an unprecedented observatory for study of the Earth's interior and the atmosphere. The USArray Transportable Array is a 400-station observatory that places broadband seismic and atmospheric pressure sensors on a Cartesian grid every 70 km across an area that spans 2,000,000 square km. Seismic data from these stations have provided high-resolution images of the Earth's interior beneath the continental United States, whereas the atmospheric data at these stations provide measurements of atmospheric phenomena. In a project recently funded by NSF, researchers at UCSD developed a method to detect very long wavelength pressure disturbances, and described how they traveled across the TA. Discussions with atmospheric researchers confirmed that these pressure disturbances detected on the Earth's surface coincided with gravity waves detected by satellite measurements, at 30-50 km altitude.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this research, the researchers are making further direct comparisons of satellite observations of gravity waves with pressure disturbances recorded at ground level, with the goal of determining when and where these phenomena occur. Since gravity waves play a large part in transferring energy from near the Earth's surface to the upper atmosphere, this research is contributing to the understanding of global atmospheric circulation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The upgrade of NSF's EarthScope/USArray Transportable Array (TA) to include air pressure sensors at each station has opened up new avenues for research into atmospheric phenomena and the interaction of the atmosphere and solid Earth. This network places high quality pressure sensors on a regular, dense Cartesian grid across an area of about 2,000,000 square km, a configuration that allows for quantitative analyses of a broad range of atmospheric wave phenomena. The UCSD group is using the new pressure data to study atmospheric gravity waves at the mid-latitudes spanned by the TA. The UCSD group has developed a technique to detect gravity waves with wavelengths greater than 100 km and characterize their propagation across the TA, yielding a quantitative measure of how their characteristics (speed, direction, period, and amplitude) may change with location across the full footprint of the TA. The method reduces the large volume of data from the TA into a quantitative record that can be used for further study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research includes a collaboration with Dr Lars Hoffmann (Juelich Supercomputing Centre) to compare gravity waves detected using satellite radiance data with those detected using UCSD's technique applied to TA pressure data. Satellites and ground-based pressure sensors provide fundamentally different platforms for studies of atmospheric gravity waves. Although these datasets and the analytical methods applied to them are completely different, a preliminary comparison of the results suggests agreement between the two. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are two main objectives of this effort. First, TA recordings of large convective events are being studied in detail and compared with satellite recordings of the same events. The objective is to determine whether gravity waves detected at ground-sited pressure sensors are coincident in time and location with stratospheric gravity waves, and whether gravity waves detected within the footprint of the TA are dominantly convective or orogenic in origin. The UCSD group is studying and documenting other characteristics of the detected gravity waves; specifically their speed, amplitude and direction. Second, a statistical study of the occurrence of gravity waves is being conducted with the objective of determining the diurnal, seasonal and regional trends in the occurrence rates of gravity waves. A key deliverable of this effort is the statistics of gravity waves during the 4-year study. The proposed research is contributing both to atmospheric science and to improved understanding of the effects of gravity waves on infrasound propagation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358520</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>de Groot-Hedlin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chedlin@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hedlin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hedlin@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/05/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>017F</Code>
      <Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1525</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>017F</Code>
      <Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
