<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SHINE: Estimating Source Locations of Interplanetary Type II Radio Bursts with Direction Finding Technique</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>193977</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ilia I. Roussev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The main goal of this 3-year SHINE project is to study the locations of the type II radio bursts at frequencies around and below 1 MHz by utilizing measurements from the Wind/WAVES and STEREO/WAVES radio instruments. The obtained radio source locations will be compared with the white-light images of Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs) taken by the SOHO/LASCO and STEREO/SECCHI coronagraphs and heliospheric imagers. This research project will shed more light on the origin of the type II radio emissions during CME events and related shock waves. Furthermore, the project team aims to test the validity of various theoretical models of the type II radio bursts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project contributes to broader societal activities, such as advancing the participation of women in science and improving the scientific literacy of the general public. The project team will present the results of this research project at national scientific meetings and will publish them in peer-reviewed scientific journals. In addition, the team will setup and maintain a website, where all relevant data for each analyzed radio event will be made available to the general public. The research and EPO agenda of this SHINE project supports the Strategic Goals of the AGS Division in discovery, learning, diversity, and interdisciplinary research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358274</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pertti</FirstName>
      <LastName>Makela</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pertti.a.makela@nasa.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Catholic University of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200640001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026355000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>620 Michigan Ave.N.E.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1523</Code>
      <Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1323</Code>
      <Text>SOLAR INFLUENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
