<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Physical Properties of Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>295319</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Caro</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION&lt;br/&gt;The Mississippi State University REU Site "Physical Properties of Materials" will expose students to the interdisciplinary nature of materials-related research and the intersection between the life sciences and engineering. The goal is to involve undergraduates in interdisciplinary materials research so that they are empowered to pursue advanced degrees and careers in science and engineering. Existing MSU research infrastructure and instrumentation will be utilized by participants with guidance from a group of materials science and engineering research mentors. The research experience will be complemented by trips to local industry to show how materials science/engineering can be applied to aerospace, manufacturing, and biomedical industries. The REU program boasts available research instrumentation and expertise, strong and sustained faculty and administrative commitment, and an independent assessment plan. Each student participant will be involved in an independent research project under the guidance and mentorship of a faculty member and involvement with a research team. Student projects address a diverse range of contemporary challenges in materials science research (e.g. biomaterials, nanoparticles, composites, and polymers) and will be part of larger, ongoing research projects within the faculty research groups so that participants can also gain an appreciation for the bigger science picture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION&lt;br/&gt;REU participants, faculty, and graduate student mentors will gain a greater awareness of, and appreciation for, the contributions of diverse disciplines to materials research. This project introduces participants to inquiry-based/interdisciplinary research, informs students about careers, and empowers students with the support and tools needed to pursue materials-related graduate degrees or careers. The intention is to prepare students to become future leaders and innovators in science and engineering. The educational objective is to prepare undergraduate students to pursue a career in engineering and science. The program has established 4 learning outcomes that students are expected to attain by the end of the 10-week program in order to achieve the educational objectives. These outcomes are: (a) Participants will demonstrate an ability to conduct experiments, as well as to analyze and interpret data. (b) Participants will have an understanding of professional and ethical responsibility. (c) Participants will effectively communicate scientific information in written, graphical and oral format. (d) Participants will demonstrate an ability to conduct self-directed learning. The learning outcomes will be directly assessed and the data will be systematically evaluated and used to continuously improve the research experience in successive years.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1359437</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Giselle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thibaudeau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>giselle@i2at.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Warnock</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwarnock@bagley.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
      <CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7222</Code>
      <Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1711</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
