<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sum frequency studies of liquid interfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>663981</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this award, funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms A (CSDM-A) Program of the Division of Chemistry, Professor Kenneth Eisenthal of Columbia University and his post-doctoral and graduate student colleagues are investigating the interactions of biomolecules at interfaces. The ultimate goal of the work by Professor Eisenthal and his group is to develop a better understanding of the physics and chemistry of biomolecules interacting with other molecules. Research like this could lead to better way of measuring the strength of interactions between biomolecules and drugs and other biomolecules. Young researchers working in Prof. Eisenthal's laboratory will be trained for jobs in the technical workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Prof. Eisenthal and his group are carrying out experiments using non-linear spectroscopic methods to investigate the behavior of biomolecules at microparticle interfaces including: (1) measurement of binding constants for small molecules with DNA; (2) measuring the relative orientation of small molecules bound to the same DNA; (3) studying the deformation of DNA induced by netropsin binding; (4) studying the plasmonic enhancement of secondharmonic generation for biomolecular studies. Prof. Eisenthal educates and mentors the young scientists in his laboratory, who go on to positions in academia, industry and the country's National Laboratories.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1360969</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eisenthal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kbe1@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9101</Code>
      <Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8990</Code>
      <Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
