<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CNIC: U.S.-Nepal Collaborative Research to Assess and Mitigate Pollution in the Densely Populated Kathmandu Valley</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>55500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lara Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical description &lt;br/&gt;This Catalyzing New International Collaboration (CNIC) award supports the U.S.-Nepal collaboration between Drs. Mohammad Iqbal, University of Northern Iowa (UNI) and Tara N. Bhattarai, Head, Department of Geology, Tribhuvan University (TU) for environmental research on the Bagmati River in the Kathmandu Valley. The goal of this project is three-fold: 1) provide US-students with exposure to environmental problems in Nepal, 2) engage with the Nepalese counterparts to develop field procedures that may be applicable nationally and internationally, and 3) conduct innovative research and exchange technical expertise to prevent further degradation of the environment. The Bagmati River has become highly polluted in recent decades due to the dramatic increase in population and urban development. TU will provide laboratory and office space for data analysis and management, and project coordination. Dr. Bhattarai will facilitate access to the hydrologic and meteorological data base maintained by the Department of Hydrology and Meteorology (DHM) in Kathmandu. This proposal requests funding for the first phase of this project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will apply scientific principles and methodology to solve an important environmental problem. Faculty and students will focus on developing an effective hydrological assessment scheme for a polluted body of water in a densely populated urban setting. A detailed procedure for water and sediment analysis will be applied to the Bagmati River study. The hydrologic characteristics will be studied to develop maps of pollution hotspots in an attempt to develop best management practice guidelines. Severe damage to watersheds resulting from accelerated urban growth is a worldwide problem. Globally, environmental policy makers are looking for new approaches to watershed management. The Bagmati study will provide insights into elements that are of primary importance to understanding temporal and spatial distribution of urban pollutants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader description &lt;br/&gt;This investigation establishes linkages among three critical aspects of urban watershed studies: ecosystem management, environmental health, and cultural awareness. Scarcity of fresh water is currently recognized as one of the greatest challenge of the 21st century. The research team proposes to deal with this challenge by sharing technical knowledge, expertise, and resources that will reduce the impact of environmental pollution in the densely populated Kathmandu Valley. The project will create unique opportunities for US students to gain experiential learning at an international location. They will work as a team with Nepalese students in an interactive learning environment that includes observation, syntheses of data, scientific reasoning, and conclusions. US and Nepalese students will learn to understand different cultural perspectives, and for the PI, this project will contribute to teaching effectiveness and the ability to work with international partners. A follow-on proposal to this CNIC award will be submitted to the NSF/DUE Improving Undergraduate STEM Education (IUES) program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1360515</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mohammad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Iqbal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>m.iqbal@uni.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Northern Iowa</Name>
      <CityName>Cedar Falls</CityName>
      <ZipCode>506140001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3192733217</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research and Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5976</Code>
      <Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7386</Code>
      <Text>NEPAL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
