<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Foundations for Practical Solar Fuel Schemes: Novel Photosensitizer and Catalyst Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>446000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award in the Catalysis program in the Division of Chemistry supports the work of Professor Stefan Bernhard at Carnegie Mellon University. The proposed work focuses on the design of novel materials for the conversion of sunlight into fuels. Solar energy conversion is of great societal interest, so this project inspires students to gain chemical knowledge and to become involved in chemical research. The educational activities at the undergraduate and graduate student level will focus on the theme of renewable energy, while outreach activities for non-scientists will both educate the public on energy issues and instill excitement for science in general.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Materials will be transition metal based and will address every step of catalytic fuel generation from light absorption to reductive fuel production and complementary water oxidation. For light absorption, a wide variety of dyes will be developed targeting both broad coverage of the solar spectrum and highly efficient activation of the fuel generating catalyst. Particular attention will be given to the ligation and geometry of the dyes such that they will be robust under illumination. Novel catalysts will also be envisioned exploring advanced modification of the architecture as a means of pushing the limits of performance and lifetime. Developed components will be tested in hydrogen producing catalytic systems and these systems will then be further evolved to function in the presence of the complementary water oxidation processes. It is the ultimate objective of this work to create a molecular system capable of splitting water into hydrogen fuel and oxygen using sunlight alone.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1362629</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bernhard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bern@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8607</Code>
      <Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8650</Code>
      <Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
