<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Extending the Plus Closure for Mixed Characteristic Rings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>89999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In the study of local rings of equicharacteristic p, the &lt;br/&gt;tight closure has proved very useful, This closure also extends &lt;br/&gt;nicely to local rings of equicharacteristic zero. Unfortunately this &lt;br/&gt;closure does not naturally extend to mixed characteristic rings. &lt;br/&gt;This project is designed to fill this void. In earlier work, the &lt;br/&gt;principal investigator defined four variants of an extended plus &lt;br/&gt;closure. As the name suggests, these closures are based upon the &lt;br/&gt;plus closure of an ideal, the set of elements which are in the &lt;br/&gt;extension of the ideal in some integral extension of the original &lt;br/&gt;ring. In the earlier work, a number of properties of the closures &lt;br/&gt;were demonstrated, In this project, additional properties will be &lt;br/&gt;demonstrated, While the benefits of this project will probably not &lt;br/&gt;be restricted to these, the objectives are the properties which shall &lt;br/&gt;allow the extended plus closure to fill the role of tight closure. &lt;br/&gt;Assuming the program is successful, the following will be &lt;br/&gt;demonstrated. Ideals in regular local rings will be shown to be &lt;br/&gt;closed. The colon-capturing property will be proved. The &lt;br/&gt;persistence property will be proved - an element in the closure of an &lt;br/&gt;ideal will remain in the closure upon taking homomorphic images. It &lt;br/&gt;should also be shown that an element which is not in the closure of &lt;br/&gt;an ideal of a local ring will also not be in the closure when the &lt;br/&gt;ideal is extended to the completion. A successful project will have &lt;br/&gt;major ramifications for the homological understanding of mixed &lt;br/&gt;characteristic rings. Among other things, this will imply the truth &lt;br/&gt;of the Direct Summand Conjecture.&lt;br/&gt; One of the most fundamental subjects in algebra is the &lt;br/&gt;understanding of ideals and modules in local rings. For those local &lt;br/&gt;rings which contain a field, tight closure has evolved as a way to &lt;br/&gt;give a unified presentation - and a simplified one - for many of the &lt;br/&gt;known properties of these objects. As a natural byproduct, it has &lt;br/&gt;also led to the discovery of new properties. Understanding of local &lt;br/&gt;rings which do not contain a field has always lagged behind. The &lt;br/&gt;principal investigator has proposed several closely related and &lt;br/&gt;highly promising candidates to play the role of tight closure in the &lt;br/&gt;alternate setting. In this project, the investigator will attempt to &lt;br/&gt;determine to what extent these new closures fill the void.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0100731</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heitmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>heitmann@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
