<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Reforming Math, Science and Technology Education in Northern New Mexico</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4993002</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed work would continue and deepen the work of the Northern New Mexico Network's first five years, which has been primarily devoted to increasing the capacity of teachers in 22 public school districts to understand, adopt, and implement standards-based instructional practices, based on the New Mexico State Standards, as well as hands-on science and math instruction. The goals of the project are: 1. Implementation of a comprehensive MST standards-based curriculum 2. High quality teacher and administrator professional development program. 3. Convergence of resources in support of increased student achievement in MST. 4. Development of a comprehensive assessment and accountability system. 5. Sustaining reform strategies. The scope of work will involve use of the Leadership Development for School Teams as the primary professional development vehicle for school administrators and the master teachers. The master teachers, termed Circuit Riders, will be assigned mentoring responsibilities in specific schools, and are in essence the field operation of the effort.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0100584</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Atencio</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>catencio@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Jemez Valley Public Schools</Name>
      <CityName>Jemez Pueblo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>870249609</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5058347391</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8501 Highway 4</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
