<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ergodic and Geometric Properties of Diffeomorphisms</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>108000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joe W. Jenkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Wilkinson will continue to extend her previous work toward an understanding&lt;br/&gt;of the dynamics of partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms.&lt;br/&gt;In particular, with her collaborators, Wilkinson proposes to address&lt;br/&gt;the issue of density of stable ergodicity in the space of partially &lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic diffeomorphisms, and the existence of Sinai-Ruelle-Bowen measures &lt;br/&gt;for these diffeomorphisms. Wilkinson will also study the dependence &lt;br/&gt;on smooth parameter of invariant structures for partially hyperbolic systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A diffeomorphism is a way of smoothly rearranging the points&lt;br/&gt;in a space. A diffeomorphism is a natural object, arising, for&lt;br/&gt;example, in the study of planetary motion. By applying a &lt;br/&gt;diffeomorphism repeatedly, one obtains a dynamical system; each iteration&lt;br/&gt;corresponds to a unit of time in the evolution of the system. For any &lt;br/&gt;given space, there are infinitely many diffeomorphisms, with widely&lt;br/&gt;varying dynamical behaviors; a goal of dynamics is to arrange &lt;br/&gt;diffeomorphisms into classes whose dynamical behavior can be understood.&lt;br/&gt;One class of diffeomorphisms whose dynamics are now well-understood&lt;br/&gt;are Smale's Axiom A, or hyperbolic, diffeomorphisms, which &lt;br/&gt;are chaotic: among other things, they display sensitive&lt;br/&gt;dependence on initial conditions. This project aims to better&lt;br/&gt;understand the behavior of another important class of diffeomorphisms,&lt;br/&gt;called partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms. Partially hyperbolic &lt;br/&gt;diffeomorphisms have many of the features of Axiom A systems,&lt;br/&gt;but their dynamical behavior is yet to be completely understood.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0100314</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilkinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wilkinso@math.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
