<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Physics-Based Finite-Dimensional Modeling and Adaptive Control of Underwater Vehicles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179544</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mario A. Rotea</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research program will develop finite-dimensional nonlinear dynamical models for underwater robot vehicles, and incorporate these models in the development of provably stable nonlinear controllers for dynamic maneuvering of underwater vehicles. This research will directly address the following two problems:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Nonlinear Finite Dimensional Dynamical Modeling: We are developing unsteady dissipative hydrodynamical models and numerical simulations for marine vehicles, and experimentally verifying these analytical models under the low-speed operating conditions typical for dynamically positioned vehicles engaged in survey, sampling, docking, and maneuvering operations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Stable Model-Based Nonlinear Adaptive Control: We are developing 6-DOF model-based adaptive tracking controllers, and experimentally evaluating both the new and previously reported techniques in full-scale experimental trials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal is to enable marine vehicles to perform missions presently considered either infeasible or impractical with existing manned and unmanned systems. The intellectual merit of the activity is the analytical development and experimental validation of finite-dimensional plant models with explicit dissipative structure, and the development and experimental validation of a new class of model-based adaptive identifiers and tracking controllers for underwater vehicles. The broader impacts of the activity include: Development and web-based dissemination of "Dynamics and Control of Marine Vehicles," a new course at JHU. Advances developed under the proposed research will be transitioned to the vehicles of the NSF supported National Deep Submergence Facility to improve their operational capabilities for U.S. oceanographic science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0100783</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whitcomb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>llw@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
