<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Differential Collision Models</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>131772</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eduardo A. Misawa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is aimed at conducting a dynamic analysis of the control and containment requirements for a high performance, axial piston, hydrostatic pump. Over the last thirty years, a great deal of information has been added to the literature which describes the control requirements for a standard swash-plate pump design; however, virtually nothing has been written on the topic of swash-plate containment. Also, within the pump industry itself, a few innovative companies have identified certain advantages in using a non-standard swash-plate design, which utilizes a variable primary swash-plate angle and a fixed secondary swash-plate angle; but, again, nothing has been added to the literature to generally describe and apply these advantages to a broad range of pump designs. In this ascertain the control and containment requirements for this design. Furthermore, this work will go a step beyond current-day practice by considering the general case when both the primary and secondary swash-plate angles vary. The outcome of this study will be to identify the mechanical and control requirements for this novel machine and to theoretically prove the advantages of implementing the design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the work of this research will be used to significantly enhance the performance of axial piston pumps that are widely used in fluid power applications today. The improved performance will be demonstrated in increased operating efficiency and quieter pumps. These improvements will be achieved by optimizing the internal pressure transients of the pump for operating conditions that may vary over a wide range during the normal duty cycle of the machine. A secondary impact will be to reduce valve-plate erosion within the pump. The overall objectives of this work are reduce waste and to increase the productivity of axial-piston pump technology. The successful accomplishment of these objectives will manifest itself in lower pump operating costs, longer product life, and a reduction in engineering time for product maintenance and design.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0100137</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>D. Dane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Quinn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>quinn@uakron.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Akron</Name>
      <CityName>Akron</CityName>
      <ZipCode>443250001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3309727666</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>302 Buchtel Common</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1632</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1039</Code>
      <Text>RENEWAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
