<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High Expectations for Learning Middle School Science (HELMSS)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David B. Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The mission of "High Expectations for Learning Middle School Science (HELMSS)"&lt;br/&gt;Pilot Local Systemic Change (LSC) is to nurture middle level scientific literacy throughout Rhode Island. The project is managed by a partnership of Rhode Island College, East Bay Educational Collaborative and ten partnering districts. The $658,000 project is funded by $200,000 from the National Science Foundation and $458,000 from Rhode Island College and the ten partnering districts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Goals include building a foundation for middle level science systemic change, developing cooperative relationships, building the capacity to implement standards-based curricula to deliver effective professional development and to provide materials support for all middle schools in Rhode Island.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;HELMSS is conceptualized as a three-phase, six-year project. Phase 1, "Initiating," began in 2000. Project personnel assessed teacher and system needs, designed courses, examined science frameworks and existing curricula and supported the piloting of middle school science instructional materials such as FOSS for Middle School and NSRC's Science and Technology Concepts for Middle Schools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Phase 2, "Building Capacity," (2001-2003) is the HELMSS Pilot LSC. The primary work of this phase is to build awareness of middle school science reform, forge new partnerships among other districts in the region, and develop middle school science teachers' capacity to lead their peers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Eighteen teachers will participate in three 45-hour science content courses and a seminar focusing on leadership, pedagogy, and curriculum. A principal seminar will enable them to work effectively with teachers on-site to support standards-based teaching and learning. By working closely with K-12 teachers and administrators, higher education faculty will improve middle level teacher preparation programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Phase 3, "Scaling Up," (2003-2006) is the HELMSS Comprehensive LSC. More than 100 Rhode Island middle level teachers will improve student performance in middle level science. All teachers will implement NSF-funded instructional materials and engage in professional development opportunities created during Phase 2, "Building Capacity".</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0101955</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>MacGregor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kniseley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkniseley@ric.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rhode Island College</Name>
      <CityName>PROVIDENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029081924</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4014568228</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>600 MOUNT PLEASANT AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7300</Code>
      <Text>TEACHER ENHANCEMENT PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
