<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Advanced Research Workshop on Future Trends in Microelectronics: the Nano Millennium, Ile de Bendor, France on June 24-29, 2001</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36618</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed ARW is to provide a forum for free-spirited exchange and debate of views,&lt;br/&gt;visions, and ideas. The format includes both prepared invited presentations and ad hoc&lt;br/&gt;contributions with uninhibited exchange of views and rebuttals. Some of the key luminaries&lt;br/&gt;will come to share their opinions and to lead the discussions on where the technologies &lt;br/&gt;are going and/or should be going. Balanced representations of advocacy and opposition&lt;br/&gt;will be intentionally sought.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each day will start with presentations given by key speakers on subjects in one or two&lt;br/&gt;chosen themes. It is then followed by debates and invited talks by other participants.&lt;br/&gt;All oral presentations (in morning sessions) are to focus on the presenter's views and&lt;br/&gt;projections of future directions, assessments or critiques of important new&lt;br/&gt;ideas/approaches, and NOT on their own achievements. The presenters are asked to be&lt;br/&gt;provocative and/or inspiring.&lt;br/&gt;Latest advances made and results obtained by the participants will be presented in the&lt;br/&gt;afternoon sessions in the form of posters and group/individual discussions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The day will be concluded by an evening panels session that attempts to further the&lt;br/&gt;debates on selected controversial issues connected to the theme of the day. Each session&lt;br/&gt;will be chaired by one forceful character that will invite 2-3 attendees of his/her choice&lt;br/&gt;to lead with a position statement, all other attendees being the panelists. The debate&lt;br/&gt;will be forcefully moderated and irrelevant digressions will be cut off without mercy.&lt;br/&gt;Moderators will be also assigned a hopeless task to forge a consensus on critical issues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For these considerations, a format has been choosen that is less rigid than normal workshops to&lt;br/&gt;allow and encourage uninhibited exchanges and sometimes confrontation of different views.&lt;br/&gt;A design a central theme will be designed together with the speakers for each day.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0101107</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Serge</FirstName>
      <LastName>Luryi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Serge.Luryi@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5980</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5914</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
