<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Facilitating Lenses on Learning: Developing Leadership to Support Excellent Teaching in Elementary Mathematics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1673137</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John S. Bradley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Under prior grants from the National Science Foundation, Education Development Center (EDC) has developed two year-long courses, called "Lenses on Learning: A New Focus on Mathematics and School Leadership," and "Lenses on Learning: Classroom Observation and Teacher Supervision," that provide school and district administrators with the opportunity to explore new ideas about mathematics, learning and teaching; to think critically about the nature of mathematics instruction; and to think through the implications of these ideas for how they support teachers and standards-based instruction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Building on previous work, this project ensures the availability of highly qualified Lenses on Learning facilitators on a national scale. Professional associations in mathematics and school administration, state departments of education, state-wide principal's academies, regional consortia for mathematics and science, and large school districts are project partners key to national dissemination efforts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Facilitator Institutes will provide prospective facilitators with the orientation and skills they need to teach either Lenses on Learning course. In the years 2001-2002, 2002-2003, and 2003-2004 EDC will offer year-long Facilitators Institutes, each consisting of a two-week residential summer program, on-line support during the following academic year, and two three-day retreats during the academic year. EDC also will offer facilitators an Advanced Institute. Participating organizations and districts are required to teach Lenses on Learning courses in their home sites in the year(s) following their participation in the Institute.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0101897</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kreed@edc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Education Development Center</Name>
      <CityName>Waltham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024538313</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6176182227</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>43 Foundry Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
