<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Assessment of Soil Erosion and Environmental Problems in China's Yellow River Watershed</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4736</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030109</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>L. Douglas James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0101353&lt;br/&gt;Sprigg&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Executive Vice-President of Northwest Science and Technology University of Agriculture and Forestry, Professor Li Jing, has sent personal invitations to 11 U.S. scientists to help China assess soil erosion and environmental problems in the Yellow River watershed. Nine of the 11 scientists are employees of the U.S. government. The two non-government scientists require support for international travel and related expenses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed participation of two non-governmental U.S. scientists broadens the range of scientific disciplines represented on the team. The trip would expose U.S. scientists working on the topic to programs under way and to field conditions in China and provide access to data that can be used to develop a scientific understanding of the process fundamentals in conditions more extreme than any found in the United States. All housing and travel expenses inside China will be supported by the host country. These funds would support international and incidental expenses for the two non-government members of the delegation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A report of the issues, observations, conclusions, and recommendations will be submitted to both the host and the NSF sponsor.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0101353</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sprigg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wsprigg@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1579</Code>
      <Text>HYDROLOGIC SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1325</Code>
      <Text>WATER &amp; ENERGY: ATMO, VEG, EARTH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
