<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Environmental Analysis and GIS: Addressing Regional Needs Through Teacher Preparation and Community Outreach</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>118962</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gerhard L. Salinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is facilitating the implementation of GIS and GPS technologies in two-year colleges and high schools in Georgia. Curriculum modules are being developed for high school students, and high school teachers are being provided necessary field equipment, data, and software to implement the modules. The modules are environmentally based and address current regional needs as specified by the Georgia Environmental Protection Division, including source water protection and land use analysis. The modules are based on courses developed through previous grant support to Gainesville College and Phi Theta Kappa entitled "Improving Science and Technology Education at Community Colleges."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Eight regional high schools are participating in the project. Teams of faculty/staff members from each school are working closely with Gainesville College faculty, staff, and students to develop custom GIS/GPS applications for their region and to integrate the instructional modules into the science classroom. The modules are being developed at Gainesville College and tested in geology and integrated science courses during the first year. Each teacher team is attending workshops and developing a plan for the integration of GIS/GPS into their school curricula during the second year. During the third year, each team is being required to implement their plans and disseminate their results to other teachers and schools. All teams are strongly encouraged to present outcomes at state and national conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0101639</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lewis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rogers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Semerjian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>csemerjian@gsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sheryl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swilliam@hermes.gc.peachnet.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gainesville College</Name>
      <CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>305031358</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6787173722</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Mundy Mill Road Box 1358</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
