<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Bifurcation in Dynamical Systems with Multiple Time Scales</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>377347</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Guckenheimer&lt;br/&gt;0101208&lt;br/&gt; The investigator studies slow-fast decompositions and&lt;br/&gt;bifurcations of trajectories in dynamical systems with multiple&lt;br/&gt;time scales. This extends the theory of bifurcation in generic&lt;br/&gt;families of dynamical systems to those with two time scales.&lt;br/&gt;Emphasis is placed upon relaxation oscillations, periodic orbits&lt;br/&gt;that have both slow and fast segments. The initial stages of the&lt;br/&gt;work seek a classification of degenerate decompositions appearing&lt;br/&gt;in periodic orbits of one parameter families with relaxation&lt;br/&gt;oscillations. Geometric methods are used to determine&lt;br/&gt;bifurcations associated with each degenerate decomposition.&lt;br/&gt;Numerical investigation of examples is used to motivate the work&lt;br/&gt;and to ensure that the results are directly applicable to&lt;br/&gt;biological models. Together with collaborators Kathleen Hoffman&lt;br/&gt;and Warren Weckesser, the investigator is reexamining a classical&lt;br/&gt;example, the forced van der Pol system that gave birth to the&lt;br/&gt;discovery of chaos for dissipative dynamical systems, and expects&lt;br/&gt;to give a full description of the bifurcations that occur within&lt;br/&gt;this system. He also develops algorithms for the computation of&lt;br/&gt;structures that are difficult to compute with existing methods.&lt;br/&gt; Rhythmic phenomena are ubiquitous in biological systems.&lt;br/&gt;Examples include the heartbeat, the cell cycle, circadian&lt;br/&gt;rhythms, legged locomotion, and electrical signals in the nervous&lt;br/&gt;system. Most of these involve multiple time scales. The&lt;br/&gt;investigator pursues new mathematical theory and computational&lt;br/&gt;methods that apply to dynamical systems with multiple time&lt;br/&gt;scales. Emphasis is given to models of neural systems, an area&lt;br/&gt;in which the presence and importance of complex dynamics are&lt;br/&gt;manifest. The investigations draw upon decades of research in&lt;br/&gt;characterizing generic phenomena observed in dynamical systems&lt;br/&gt;with a single time scale. The resulting body of mathematics,&lt;br/&gt;sometimes called chaos theory, needs extension and modification&lt;br/&gt;to fully explain the behavior of systems with multiple time&lt;br/&gt;scales. Those extensions are the goal of this project. On a&lt;br/&gt;longer time frame, the project lays foundations for coming&lt;br/&gt;generations of biological models for cellular processes such as&lt;br/&gt;gene expression and signal transduction. New biotechnology leads&lt;br/&gt;to ever more complicated reaction networks that are simulated as&lt;br/&gt;dynamical systems. This project produces results that aid the&lt;br/&gt;implementation and interpretation of such simulations of complex,&lt;br/&gt;multiple time scale dynamical systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/10/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0101208</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guckenheimer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmg16@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
