<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research in Knots, Links and 3-Manifolds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>65043</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0102231&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Xiao-Song Lin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central theme of this project is to explore as thoroughly as&lt;br/&gt;possible the significance of the Jones-Witten and Vassiliev&lt;br/&gt;invariants to knots, links, and 3-manifolds as topological&lt;br/&gt;structures. To be more specific, we will study the thermodynamic&lt;br/&gt;limit of the colored Jones polynomial using various probabilistic&lt;br/&gt;models; to explore beyond a simple formulation of the Casson&lt;br/&gt;invariant we found; to understand the congruence relation among&lt;br/&gt;Ohtsuki's invariants through congruence subgroups of the modular&lt;br/&gt;group; to find the normal form of a degree 1 map from a knot&lt;br/&gt;complement to another knot complement; to study the cohomology of&lt;br/&gt;knot complexes; to explore the applicability of classical&lt;br/&gt;techniques in 3-manifold topology to the study of Vassiliev&lt;br/&gt;invariants; and to continue the study of value and root&lt;br/&gt;distributions of the Jones polynomial.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The phenomenon of knotting is a fundamental feature of the space&lt;br/&gt;that we live in, and knot theory is thus an important part of&lt;br/&gt;mankind's scientific knowledge because it is aimed at&lt;br/&gt;understanding the interplay of mathematical formulae and space&lt;br/&gt;structures. It is no wonder that concepts and tools originated&lt;br/&gt;from knot theory have been used in many areas of mathematics, as&lt;br/&gt;well as in chemistry, biology, physics, and computer science. For&lt;br/&gt;example, geneticists utilize knot theory to understand the&lt;br/&gt;processes of DNA replication and the function of enzymes that&lt;br/&gt;"unknot" DNA strands, and chemists use knot theory to understand&lt;br/&gt;and distinguish between different types of molecules. Our ability&lt;br/&gt;to discern different knots could well be served as a test of our&lt;br/&gt;scientific understanding of space structures.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0102231</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiao-Song</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xl@math.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
