<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Problems in Gravitation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>433456</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Beverly K. Berger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Richard Matzner will carry out research in gravitational physics and&lt;br/&gt;relativity, utilizing the tools of mathematical analysis, comparison to&lt;br/&gt;observation, and computational modeling. He will apply these techniques&lt;br/&gt;to understanding the possible configurations of massive objects as&lt;br/&gt;described in general relativity, concentrating on black holes. He will&lt;br/&gt;study the way in which these objects can be described in computational&lt;br/&gt;terms, and the dynamics of these objects in interaction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main part of this work will concentrate on developing evolutions of&lt;br/&gt;black hole interactions. These are the strongest possible gravitational&lt;br/&gt;sources, and will produce strong gravitational wave events. They are a&lt;br/&gt;testbed in which our understanding of strong gravitational fields is&lt;br/&gt;exercised, and in which new theoretical concepts are developed. They are&lt;br/&gt;a difficult computational problem (large operation counts, large&lt;br/&gt;numbers of field variables), and require special techniques, very&lt;br/&gt;careful numerical handling, and very large computational resources.&lt;br/&gt;Thus they are an excellent domain to develop new computational&lt;br/&gt;infrastructure. And they may provide detailed predictions of the&lt;br/&gt;waveforms detected in the current and in future generations of&lt;br/&gt;gravitational wave detectors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0102204</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matzner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>matzner2@physics.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
