<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NER: Molecular Controlled Electronic Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>62010</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal was received in response to NSE, NSF-0019. The proposed research explores a new approach for increasing the density of logical operations in electronic circuits by using the polarization response of organic molecules. A key element of this approach is to use a Molecular Controlled SEmiconductor Resistor (MOCSER) to transduce the outcome of the logical operation into a current. Positive attributes of this scheme are less molecular decomposition, less severe statistical fluctuations and an ability to interface with today's microelectronics. The MOCSER is a specially designed and gateless metal-oxide semiconductor field effect transistor. In place of the metal gate on the transistor, organic molecules will be chemically bonded to the device's gate oxide. By polarizing these organic molecules the current flow between the source and drain electrodes of the transistor can be modulated. The work will begin by demonstrating the MOCSER's response to a voltage-controlled, molecular polarization. With the success of this initial phase of work the proposed effort will include two parts: nanolithography and demonstrating olecular templating. To demonstrate the feasibility of a 'solid-state' device a new generation of the MOCSER, in which the gate oxide region is connected to metal pads through a molecule, will be fabricated and tested. The nanolithography will be performed at the Cornell Nanofabrication Facility, in collaboration with the expertise from the Weizmann group . In parallel, we will use the templating of complementary DNA strands, one which is tethered to the gate region of the MOCSER and the other to the AFM tip, to characterize the self-assembly of molecules and voltage-controlled polarization response through noncovalent contacts. Successful completion of this work should set the stage for using molecular polarization to perform logic functions and transducing the molecular polarization into current in a solid-state electronic device.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0102912</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beratan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.beratan@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Waldeck</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dave@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
