<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Microbial Biology for FY2001</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080308</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carter Kimsey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Microbial Biology for FY2001. The fellowship supports training and research on the basic biology of protozoan, microalgal, fungal, archaeal, bacterial and viral species that are not generally considered to be model organisms. Further, it provides opportunities for a recent doctoral recipients to obtain additional training in microbial biology, to gain research experience under the sponsorship of established scientists, and to broaden his/her scientific horizons beyond the research experiences during the undergraduate and graduate training. These fellowships are further designed to assist new scientists to direct their research efforts across traditional disciplinary lines and to avail themselves of unique research resources, sites, and facilities, including foreign locations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research and training plan is entitled "Effects of energy, environmental variation, and dynamic constraints on the structure of experimental microbial food webs." A lab-based microbial system, comprised of bacteria, autotrophic algae, heterotrophic protozoa, and rotifers, is being used to determine the effects of environmental variability and energy on the emergent structure of food webs. Webs of varying complexity are experimentally perturbed and changes in web structure are compared to stability measures to assess how perturbations and stability-complexity interact to generate community organization.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0102105</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Steiner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>04/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Steiner, Christopher F</Name>
      <CityName>Hickory Corners</CityName>
      <ZipCode>490609327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber></PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress></StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
