<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NER: Molecular Diode and Molecular Nonvolatile Memory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2001</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>S. Kamal Abdali</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL NO.: 0102765&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR: Choi, Jaewu&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION NAME: Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College&lt;br/&gt;TITLE: NER: Molecular Diode and Molecular Nonvolatile Memory&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research program addresses the challenges and opportunities&lt;br/&gt;available with molecular diode and molecular nonvolatile memory. The proposed&lt;br/&gt;molecular diode and molecular nonvolatile memory can be achieved with carbon&lt;br/&gt;nanotubes functionality and heterostructure of carbon nanotubes with a ferroelectric&lt;br/&gt;linear polymer.&lt;br/&gt;The carbon nanotube, itself, has many functional properties, such as quasi-one&lt;br/&gt;dimensionality, metal-semiconductor, mechanical stiffness, capillarity, high aspect ratio,&lt;br/&gt;large surface area, and chemical stability. In application of these carbon nanotubes to the&lt;br/&gt;electronic devices, one serious obstacle is handling the chiarlity, which plays an&lt;br/&gt;important role in determining the metallic-semiconducting behavior of the carbon&lt;br/&gt;nanotubes. The proposed research program allows us to overcome these difficulties by&lt;br/&gt;utilizing the carbon nanotubes as a backbone for a diode and a sensor for a nonvolatile&lt;br/&gt;memory.&lt;br/&gt;First of all, the proposed molecular diode consists of the differentially doped&lt;br/&gt;single carbon nanotube. This is based on our own research work on the electronic&lt;br/&gt;structure study of the modified carbon nanotubes by ion-bombardments, alkali metal&lt;br/&gt;doping, and atomic and molecular gas adsorption. These recent studies show that the&lt;br/&gt;density of states near Fermi level, work function, and band gap of the carbon nanotubes&lt;br/&gt;can be tunable. Therefore, it does not require any junction of two carbon nanotubes with&lt;br/&gt;different chirality to make a molecular diode, which has been suggested in a theoretical&lt;br/&gt;calculation by growth of a single carbon nanotube with different chiraity. To make a&lt;br/&gt;diode from a single carbon nanotube in this proposed research program, the half of the&lt;br/&gt;tube will be doped with p-type acceptor (like oxygen or fluorine) and the other half will&lt;br/&gt;be doped with n-type donors (alkali metals) using screening doping.&lt;br/&gt;Secondly, the proposed molecular nonvolatile memory is a heterostructure of a&lt;br/&gt;carbon nanotube and a ferroelectric linear polymer with a permanent dipole moment. The&lt;br/&gt;carbon nanotube has been studied as a gas sensor and a gas-storage. Adsorption of gas on&lt;br/&gt;carbon nanotube induces the conductivity change and band gap opening. In this proposed&lt;br/&gt;carbon nanotube-ferroelectric polymer heterostructure, we are going to detect the&lt;br/&gt;conductivity change of the carbon nanotube due to the electric dipole reorientation of the&lt;br/&gt;ferrolectric polymer by applying the normal TTL (transistor-tansistor logic) voltage.&lt;br/&gt;Therefore, the carbon nanotube-ferroelectric polymer heterostructure is the combination&lt;br/&gt;of the sensor and information storage. The interface between the carbon nanotube and the&lt;br/&gt;ferroelectric polymer, PVDF, of the proposed heterostructure systems is changed from&lt;br/&gt;the hydrogen or fluorine rich to the hydrogen and fluorine mixture across the&lt;br/&gt;conformational switching from all trans to gauch-trans-gauch bar with variation of&lt;br/&gt;temperature or applied voltage (a gate voltage). This is the working principle of the&lt;br/&gt;proposed molecular nonvolatile memory.&lt;br/&gt;Through this proposed program on molecular diode and molecular nonvolatile&lt;br/&gt;memory, graduate and undergraduate students will be involved and trained in the cutting-&lt;br/&gt;edge research area (an emerging area of nanoscale science and technology, in special&lt;br/&gt;molecular electronics) of science and technology with advanced synchrotron and&lt;br/&gt;microfabrication facilities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0102765</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jaewu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Choi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jchoi@ece.eng.wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/07/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>2878</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CCF</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1676</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
