<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symplectic, Contact and Low-dimensional Topology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>319309</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0102922&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Robert E. Gompf&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on constructing symplectic, contact and&lt;br/&gt;4-dimensional manifolds. The Principal Investigator has defined&lt;br/&gt;a topological structure called a "hyperpencil" on an&lt;br/&gt;even-dimensional closed manifold, generalizing a linear system of&lt;br/&gt;curves on a complex algebraic manifold. He has shown that any&lt;br/&gt;hyperpencil canonically determines a symplectic structure on the&lt;br/&gt;manifold. In dimensions less than 8, this correspondence maps&lt;br/&gt;the set of hyperpencils onto a dense subset of all symplectic&lt;br/&gt;forms on the manifold (up to isotopy and scale). A similar&lt;br/&gt;statement seems likely in higher dimensions, and would provide a&lt;br/&gt;complete topological characterization of those manifolds&lt;br/&gt;admitting symplectic structures. If the fibers of this&lt;br/&gt;correspondence can be topologically specified, the result will be&lt;br/&gt;a purely topological description of a dense subset of all&lt;br/&gt;symplectic structures on all closed manifolds. In addition to&lt;br/&gt;this investigation, Stein surfaces and their contact 3-manifold&lt;br/&gt;boundaries will be studied by methods such as Legendrian Kirby&lt;br/&gt;calculus. The topology of exotic R^4's and other smooth&lt;br/&gt;4-manifolds will also be investigated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An n-manifold is a space that in small regions looks just like&lt;br/&gt;n-dimensional Euclidean space. Points, curves and surfaces are&lt;br/&gt;manifolds of dimensions 0,1 and 2, respectively. The space in&lt;br/&gt;which we live is a 3-manifold, and the universe (space-time) is a&lt;br/&gt;4-manifold. Surprisingly, 3- and 4-manifolds are much less well&lt;br/&gt;understood than their higher-dimensional counterparts, although&lt;br/&gt;major progress has been made in recent years. Symplectic and&lt;br/&gt;contact structures on manifolds were discovered through classical&lt;br/&gt;physics (Hamiltonian mechanics and optics, respectively), but&lt;br/&gt;they are now seen to be important in such diverse areas as&lt;br/&gt;quantum physics, complex analysis, differential geometry and&lt;br/&gt;topology. For example, a rigid pendulum swinging in&lt;br/&gt;3-dimensional space determines a symplectic manifold. The bob&lt;br/&gt;moves on a spherical surface, so its position is specified by 2&lt;br/&gt;variables (latitude and longitude on this sphere). To completely&lt;br/&gt;specify the state of the system, one must also include the&lt;br/&gt;momentum of the bob. At any position, its momentum is tangent to&lt;br/&gt;the sphere and thus specified by two more variables. Hence, the&lt;br/&gt;set of states of the system is a 4-manifold (locally specified by&lt;br/&gt;4 variables). This 4-manifold has a special symplectic structure&lt;br/&gt;whose role is to link each position variable to the corresponding&lt;br/&gt;momentum variable. This linkage ultimately results in Hamilton's&lt;br/&gt;equations describing the motion of the pendulum under the&lt;br/&gt;influence of a specified force field. There are many other&lt;br/&gt;situations in which manifolds and their symplectic and contact&lt;br/&gt;structures arise. While our understanding of such structures has&lt;br/&gt;advanced enormously in recent years, some of the most basic&lt;br/&gt;questions remain to be answered. Which manifolds have symplectic&lt;br/&gt;or contact structures, and how many such structures are there on&lt;br/&gt;a given manifold? How many 4-manifolds (if any) are there&lt;br/&gt;satisfying a given description? Questions such as these form the&lt;br/&gt;basis of this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0102922</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gompf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gompf@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
