<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NER: Exploring A Novel Plasma-Based Copper Nano-Line Etch Method for Nano-Devices And Circuits</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>81161</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0103022&lt;br/&gt;Kuo&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal was received in response to NSE, NSF-0019. The goal of this proposal is to explore a novel method for etching copper nano-lines at room temperature, which is crucial for the fabrication of future nano-devices and circuits. The PI plans to study the key step in the process, i.e., a unique anisotropic plasma-copper reaction, in the nano-scale region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is an experimental research project. The PI is going to investigate a number of issues in the nano-line definition process, such as the critical dimension control, profile, sidewall surface, and residue formation, through fundamental studies of plasma-copper surface reaction, solid-state reactant transport and copper-halide reactions. This research involves the microstructure of the copper material, plasma chemistry, and directional solid-state reaction mechanisms. In addition to plasma process characterization, he will make extensive use of Transmission Electron Microscopy (TFM) as well as other thin-film analytical methods to probe the plasma-copper reaction phenomenon at the nano-scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The plasma reaction will he carried out in the principal investigator's (P1's) Thin Film Microelectronic Research Laboratory. All experiments will employ a simple parallel-plate reactive ion etching reactor with a 13.56 MHz RF generator. The nano-line pattern, e.g., sub-100 nm, will be prepared in the NSF National Nanofabrication Users Network (NNUN) facility located in the Pennsylvania State University using c-beam lithography. The industry sponsor AMD agrees to support this project by supplying thin film characterization service, technical consulting, and 6-inch wafers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0103022</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yue</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yuekuo@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1676</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
