<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Topology of Nonisolated Singularities and Scale-based Geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>84507</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0103862&lt;br/&gt;James N. Damon&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Professor Damon's research will apply infinitesimal and &lt;br/&gt;stratification methods from singularity theory to investigate&lt;br/&gt;the topology and deformation properties of a general class of &lt;br/&gt;highly nonisolated singular spaces. These spaces arise as &lt;br/&gt;nonlinear sections of certain natural universal varieties. &lt;br/&gt;For instance, geometric and deformation properties of mappings &lt;br/&gt;under various equivalences can be captured by such universal &lt;br/&gt;varieties. The structure of the tangent vector fields will be &lt;br/&gt;used to deduce algebraic formulae for certain fundamental &lt;br/&gt;topological invariants. These will be given in terms of &lt;br/&gt;certain natural algebraic and geometric multiplicities, &lt;br/&gt;measuring the singular behavior of mappings relative to &lt;br/&gt;associated geometric structures such as foliations Second, &lt;br/&gt;he will refine these ideas for questions in computer imaging &lt;br/&gt;by developing geometric structures associated to objects and &lt;br/&gt;features in images in terms of such highly singular spaces. &lt;br/&gt;The presence of discreteness, noise, and distortions in images &lt;br/&gt;require a "scale-based geometry" which is applicable to nondifferentiable functions, measures, and even distributions. &lt;br/&gt;Such a geometry will apply to "almost all" objects in a given &lt;br/&gt;type, and will yield stable geometric structures in scale space. &lt;br/&gt;This will allow the geometric analysis of images using functions &lt;br/&gt;and measures discriminating various features in images.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first part of Professor Damon's research will determine &lt;br/&gt;for specific types of systems of nonlinear equations, the &lt;br/&gt;qualitative properties of the set of solutions. These can be &lt;br/&gt;obtained from certain universal systems of equations. He &lt;br/&gt;proposes to use certain infinitesimal symmetries of the &lt;br/&gt;equations to deduce properties of the set of solutions &lt;br/&gt;in terms of algebraic invariants which reflect both properties &lt;br/&gt;of the universal equations and how the specific equations &lt;br/&gt;relate to the universal ones. Second, the research will be &lt;br/&gt;applied to problems in computer imaging. To objects and &lt;br/&gt;features in images, one may associate geometric structures &lt;br/&gt;capturing their properties for various imaging purposes. &lt;br/&gt;Such structures are defined using systems of equations as &lt;br/&gt;above. The presence of discreteness, noise and distortions &lt;br/&gt;in images interferes with identifying geometric features. &lt;br/&gt;The research will refine the methods described above via &lt;br/&gt;"scale-based" versions which introduce robust geometric &lt;br/&gt;structures overcoming these difficulties, which can then be&lt;br/&gt;used for a variety of computer imaging problems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0103862</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Damon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jndamon@math.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
      <CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
      <ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
