<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Problems in Fluid Dynamics and Elasticity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>104949</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Research is proposed on the following topics:&lt;br/&gt;1. Breakup of liquid jets: This research will mathematically analyze&lt;br/&gt; the capillary breakup of jets of Newtonian and viscoelastic liquids. The effect&lt;br/&gt; of polymer additives in suppressing breakup is well known and exploited both&lt;br/&gt; in nature (spider webs) and in technology (control of drops sizes in spraying&lt;br/&gt; of liquids). The research will concentrate on the asymptotics of breakup and&lt;br/&gt; compare various constitutive theories.&lt;br/&gt;2. Stability of viscoelastic flows: Elastic instabilities have been&lt;br/&gt; investigated extensively over the past ten years. Such instabilities often&lt;br/&gt; pose limits for polymer processing conditions. In the numerical investigation&lt;br/&gt; of instabilities in complex flows, continuous spectra which are poorly resolved&lt;br/&gt; pose a significant challenge. The research is aimed at using analytical &lt;br/&gt; techniques to determine the location of these continuous spectra.&lt;br/&gt;3. Shape control in elasticity: An elastic medium is controlled by&lt;br/&gt; actuators which can supply a stress of a given type. The research will &lt;br/&gt; investigate the question whether such controls can achieve a given shape of&lt;br/&gt; the medium.&lt;br/&gt;4. Numerical simulation of two-fluid flows: The research will continue&lt;br/&gt; work on simulation of flows of two liquids using a volume of fluid code. The&lt;br/&gt; following three problems will be investigated:&lt;br/&gt; a) Formation of ``staircase" structures on impacting drops due to&lt;br/&gt; capillary waves.&lt;br/&gt; b) Tipstreaming in drop breakup under shear when surfactants are&lt;br/&gt; present.&lt;br/&gt; c) Effect of normal stresses on breakup of viscoelastic drops under&lt;br/&gt; shear.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research addresses fundamental issues which arise in the processing and&lt;br/&gt;use of polymeric liquids, the control of deformations of elastic solids and the&lt;br/&gt;formation of emulsions by shear mixing. The proposed topics include a comparison of&lt;br/&gt;the qualitative behavior various models of polymeric fluids in jet breakup, the&lt;br/&gt;stability of polymeric flows, the question which shapes of an elastic medium can&lt;br/&gt;be achieved by a given type of control, and the development of numerical methods for&lt;br/&gt;two-fluid flows.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0103813</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Renardy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>renardym@math.vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
