<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Characterization of Unconventional Heavy Fermion Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>304416</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wendy W. Fuller-Mora</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This individual investigator award will support research focused on fundamental problems of strongly correlated 4f- and 5f-electron systems. The physical properties of this large class of systems challenge conventional theories of condensed matter based on a Fermi liquid theory. The aim of the proposed research is to; 1) investigate the non-Fermi liquid behavior of nearly magnetic heavy fermion metals; 2) investigate the role of crystal structure, crystalline and magnetic anisotropy in heavy fermions; 3) test various theoretical models; and 4) search for new materials with exotic properties. The project will involve both the synthesis and characterization of heavy fermion materials. Experimental techniques employed in this research will include transport, thermodynamic, and magnetic probes in a wide range of temperatures and magnetic fields, using the facilities of National High Magnetic Field Laboratory and the Microkelvin Laboratory, aided by international collaborations. The project addresses the widely recognized national shortage of qualified personnel able to synthesize novel materials of research quality by expanding graduate training in materials synthesis and characterization. Students involved in this project will receive training in synthesis and fundamental measurement techniques. They will be prepared for careers in fundamental and/or applied research.&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;Materials containing Lanthanum and the Actinide elements have been the source of many recent fundamental discoveries that have challenged our current understanding of matter. Due to strong electron correlations, these heavy fermion materials exhibit many exotic properties. They show extreme sensitivity to temperature, magnetic field, pressure, and frequency. Thus they may be a source of important technological applications. This individual investigator award will support a project focused on searching for new exotic states of matter as well as new heavy fermion materials, in addition it will test several theoretical models of these interesting materials. Samples prepared in-house, or obtained through international collaborations, will be studied by electric, magnetic, and thermal probes using state-of-the art facilities of National High Magnetic Field Laboratory and Microkelvin Laboratory. This project will address the widely recognized national shortage of qualified personnel able to synthesize novel materials of research quality by expanding graduate training in materials synthesis and characterization. Students involved in this project will receive experience in working at national facilities as well as in international collaborations. This training will prepare them for careers in fundamental and/or applied research.&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/16/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/03/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104240</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bohdan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Andraka</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>andraka@phys.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/16/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
