<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Metric Differential Geometry and Mathematical Gravity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>94858</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0104042&lt;br/&gt;Gregory G. Galloway&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research under this award will be conducted in the areas of&lt;br/&gt;Lorentzian and Riemannian geometry, with applications to General&lt;br/&gt;Relativity and String Theory. One of the specific aims of this&lt;br/&gt;project is to investigate the global structure of asymptotically&lt;br/&gt;locally anti-de Sitter spacetimes, especially in connection with&lt;br/&gt;the AdS/CFT correspondence. We continue investigations into the&lt;br/&gt;relationship of the topology of an asymptotically locally&lt;br/&gt;anti-de Sitter spacetime and that of its conformal&lt;br/&gt;boundary-at-infinity, and undertake a study of certain&lt;br/&gt;topological and geometrical properties of higher dimensional&lt;br/&gt;black holes, and related objects arising in string theory,&lt;br/&gt;including certain solitions conjectured to be least energy&lt;br/&gt;configurations. Another aim of this project is to continue&lt;br/&gt;investigations into spacetime rigidity phenomena associated with&lt;br/&gt;the occurence of timelike lines and null lines. Applications of&lt;br/&gt;the null splitting theorem will be considered, and a new&lt;br/&gt;approach to well-known conjectures concerning the rigidity of&lt;br/&gt;the singularity theorems is proposed for study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Modern theories of gravity are geometrical in nature. The&lt;br/&gt;gravitational field and other fields, black holes and related&lt;br/&gt;objects, may be described and analyzed using geometric methods.&lt;br/&gt;In more general terms, this project is concerned with the study&lt;br/&gt;of certain features of gravity of current scientific interest&lt;br/&gt;from this geometric point of view, utilizing the tools of&lt;br/&gt;Riemannian geometry, a mathematical theory of space, and&lt;br/&gt;Lorentzian geometry, a mathematical theory of spacetime. These&lt;br/&gt;theories provide a method for studying the relationship among&lt;br/&gt;three fundamental aspects of the spacetime universe: curvature&lt;br/&gt;(i.e., the bending of space or spacetime), topology (i.e., the&lt;br/&gt;global shape and complexity of space or spacetime) and causal&lt;br/&gt;structure (i.e., the large scale behavior of light rays and&lt;br/&gt;light cones).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104042</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Galloway</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>galloway@math.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami</Name>
      <CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
