<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Quantitative Genetics of Social Behavior</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>357785</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John A. Byers</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Title: Quantitative Genetics of Social Behavior&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Penelope F. Kukuk&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Social behavior is found in all types of organisms and is a characteristic&lt;br/&gt;of ecologically dominant species. The study of how social evolution came&lt;br/&gt;about has concentrated on selection. To date, theoretical and&lt;br/&gt;empirical work has focused on how group life and social cooperation influence&lt;br/&gt;survival and reproduction. This work began in the nineteen sixties and&lt;br/&gt;continues today. The other side of the evolutionary coin, the study of the&lt;br/&gt;genetic mechanisms underlying social cooperation, has been neglected. Even&lt;br/&gt;in the social Hymenoptera there is very little information concerning the&lt;br/&gt;most basic issues. It is not known to what extent differences in social&lt;br/&gt;behaviors among individuals in a species are based on differences in their&lt;br/&gt;genetic makeup. In species where females all have the potential to be&lt;br/&gt;competent reproductives, we do not know if there are enough genetic&lt;br/&gt;differences between individuals underlying any given social behavior to&lt;br/&gt;suggest that the behavior has the potential to evolve. Due to this lack of&lt;br/&gt;knowledge it is not possible to predict the evolutionary trajectory of&lt;br/&gt;social behaviors or to examine how inheritance of a suite of socially&lt;br/&gt;relevant traits may be correlated. This one-sided approach to social&lt;br/&gt;evolution is based on methodological constraints. Appropriate social&lt;br/&gt;species have neither the large reproductive output nor the ease in&lt;br/&gt;laboratory rearing needed to use the powerful methodology of quantitative&lt;br/&gt;genetic research, a methodology that can best address these questions. This&lt;br/&gt;limitation is changing. Due to new but well tested methods for obtaining&lt;br/&gt;information rich genetic fingerprints for individuals, based on multiple&lt;br/&gt;highly variable marker genes such as microsatellites, in combination with&lt;br/&gt;conceptual and statistical advances it is now possible to apply the methods&lt;br/&gt;of quantitative genetics to social behavior in a field setting for the first&lt;br/&gt;time.&lt;br/&gt; A collaboration between a quantitative geneticist (Allen Moore) and a&lt;br/&gt;behavioral ecologist (Penny Kukuk) will apply new methodologies in a field&lt;br/&gt;based quantitative genetic study of social behaviors for a group living&lt;br/&gt;halictine bee species Lasioglossum (Chilalictus) hemichalceum. This&lt;br/&gt;communal species, in which all group members reproduce, is an ideal species&lt;br/&gt;for such a study. In this species, individuals differ from one another in&lt;br/&gt;social behaviors and microsatellite markers are available to produce precise&lt;br/&gt;genetic fingerprints for individuals. Information on similarities&lt;br/&gt;between individuals in their microsatellite based genetic fingerprints&lt;br/&gt;and easily observed social behaviors will be used to determine components of&lt;br/&gt;inheritance for a suite of behavioral characteristics that are known to have&lt;br/&gt;important effects on survival and reproduction. The research will pioneer&lt;br/&gt;the quantitative genetic study of social behavior and pioneer the use of&lt;br/&gt;quantitative genetic methodology for behavioral traits in a natural setting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104937</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Penelope</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kukuk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>penny.kukuk@mso.umt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Montana</Name>
      <CityName>Missoula</CityName>
      <ZipCode>598120001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4062436670</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>32 CAMPUS DRIVE MAIN HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
