<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.- Sweden Cooperative Research: Photoelectron Microscopy Studies of Wide Band Gap Nitride Semiconductors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25260</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark A. Suskin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0104605&lt;br/&gt;Smith&lt;br/&gt;This award supports Kevin Smith and students from Boston University in a collaboration with Ralf Nyholm at the MAX-lab synchrotron radiation facility in the University of Lund, Sweden. The project will focus on the study of structural properties of wide band gap nitride semiconductors using photoelectron microscopy, in which area Professor Nyholm is an expert. The new collaborations will combine the skills of the two labs to address issues of fundamental importance in nitride semiconductors, and a high level of productivity is expected from combining the separate but complementary expertise of the U.S. and Swedish groups. Among the specific goals of the proposed work are an understanding of microscopic surface electronic properties of clean binary nitride semiconductors, understanding adsorption of simple gas molecules on well-characterized nitride surfaces, understanding growth, structure, and stability of metal contact overlayers, understanding the thermal decomposition of complex nitride alloy surfaces, and training of students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104605</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksmith@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
