<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Homotopy Theory of Classifying Spaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>72480</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0104318&lt;br/&gt;Jesper Grodal&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project consists of developing the homotopy theory &lt;br/&gt;of classifying spaces of compact Lie groups (including &lt;br/&gt;finite groups) and their generalizations. The goal of &lt;br/&gt;this is to solve central problems in homotopy theory involving classifying spaces, as well as to discover new relations&lt;br/&gt;to problems in group theory and representation theory. &lt;br/&gt;A further goal is to produce results in related fields &lt;br/&gt;such as in the theory of group actions, equivariant &lt;br/&gt;cohomology, and group cohomology. The project centers&lt;br/&gt;around developing the homotopy theoretic group theory &lt;br/&gt;of the classifying space BG, or rather of its p-completion. &lt;br/&gt;This involves examining the induction theory, p-local theory, representation theory as well as the more general actions &lt;br/&gt;of these objects. The methods used come from modern unstable &lt;br/&gt;homotopy theory, developed since the solution of the &lt;br/&gt;Sullivan conjecture, combined with ideas and techniques &lt;br/&gt;from modern group theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Forming the classifying space BG of a group of &lt;br/&gt;symmetries G is a way of geometrically or topologically &lt;br/&gt;encoding the "symmetries" present in G. Geometric spaces &lt;br/&gt;of this form and generalizations thereof are ubiquitous &lt;br/&gt;in topology, and hence form an important class of &lt;br/&gt;spaces to study. Furthermore, the less rigid structure &lt;br/&gt;of the classifying space BG, compared to that of&lt;br/&gt;the group G, makes certain techniques available in &lt;br/&gt;the study of the former which were not available when &lt;br/&gt;dealing with the later directly. Hence, studying the group&lt;br/&gt;theory of BG provides an interesting and useful way of &lt;br/&gt;studying the original group G.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104318</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jesper</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grodal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jg@math.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/11/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
