<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Complex Analysis and Geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>78600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexandre Freire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract NSF Proposal DMS-0104047&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Speaking more technically, the proposal aims to treat four research&lt;br/&gt;lines in complex geometry and analysis. We are studying the Grauert&lt;br/&gt;tube construction for its rigidity and uniquesness properties for&lt;br/&gt;large (maximal) radius or domain, and examining whether this point of&lt;br/&gt;view adds to old questions in representation theory and automorphic forms.&lt;br/&gt;Second, we will study a Kaehler-Einstein version of Min-Oo's rigidity&lt;br/&gt;theorem which we conjecture to hold. We will continue work with&lt;br/&gt;X. Gong on Levi flat hypersurfaces with singularities, especially&lt;br/&gt;algebraic ones with isolated singularities. Their importance is&lt;br/&gt;suggested by recent work of Siu and others proving the conjecture of&lt;br/&gt;Camacho on the non-existence of smooth, Levi-flat hypersurfaces in&lt;br/&gt;the complex projective plane. Finally we propose to study the rigidity&lt;br/&gt;of special classes of Schubert cycles on flag manifolds, following&lt;br/&gt;upon the work of the PI's former student M. Walters and,&lt;br/&gt;independently, R. Bryant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal addresses several questions in complex analysis and&lt;br/&gt;geometry. Most people are familiar with Descartes' analytic geometry&lt;br/&gt;from high school: in most respects, this line of investigation is the&lt;br/&gt;modern descendent of those early ideas. We will study the relationship&lt;br/&gt;between a geometric locus, sometimes defined by equations as in&lt;br/&gt;Descartes' original case, and its analytic properties, those&lt;br/&gt;properties influenced by the calculus of Newton and Leibniz. In&lt;br/&gt;particular we study a complexification of geometric locus, that is, we&lt;br/&gt;add "imaginary points" to the geometry, related to the imaginary unit&lt;br/&gt;"i", and study the influence of the imaginary points on the real&lt;br/&gt;points and their geometry. Another portion of the project seeks to&lt;br/&gt;understand the asymptotic, or long range properties of special metric&lt;br/&gt;geometries related to the Einstein equations. It is well known that&lt;br/&gt;both of these properties can be influential in physical applications,&lt;br/&gt;and there is recent work to lead one to hope that both this&lt;br/&gt;complexification construction and the asymptotics of Einstein metrics&lt;br/&gt;can be used to understand parts of the so-called Maldacena&lt;br/&gt;correspondence in theoretical physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104047</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Burns</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dburns@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
