<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Isospectral and isotonal metrics with different local geometries</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexandre Freire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract for DMS - 0104361&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main part of the project describes a new isospectral&lt;br/&gt;construction technique (Anticommutator Technique), which provides&lt;br/&gt;the first isospectral pairs of metrics on the most simple manifolds: on &lt;br/&gt;balls and spheres. The most striking examples are constructed&lt;br/&gt;on suitable spheres, where one of the members of an isospectral pair&lt;br/&gt;is a homogeneous metric, while the other is locally inhomogeneous. &lt;br/&gt;This demonstrates the surprising fact that no information about the &lt;br/&gt;isometries is encoded in the spectrum of the Laplacian acting on functions. &lt;br/&gt;These investigations also extend to the Laplacian spectrum of forms. &lt;br/&gt;Related questions are also considered. One of them is construction of &lt;br/&gt;Brownian-motion-equivalent spaces (Isothermal Metrics). &lt;br/&gt;This equivalence relation is much stronger then the isospectrality property,&lt;br/&gt; yet it does not determine the local geometry. The same statement is true &lt;br/&gt;regarding the metrics with equivalent density functions (Isodasyc Metrics).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The old argument between Relativity and Quantum Physics is easily discovered &lt;br/&gt;in the depth of these questions. In Relativity, the whole Physics is derived &lt;br/&gt;from a curved space. Actually, Physics is identified with the complete Geometry &lt;br/&gt;of this curved space. Einstein put his idea this way: "There is no such thing as &lt;br/&gt;Physics. Everything is Geometry." Contrary to Relativity, the Quantum Physics &lt;br/&gt;uses only particular aspects of Geometry such as the spectra of several operators &lt;br/&gt;or the Brownian Motion defined by a metric space. Einstein suggested, however, &lt;br/&gt;that the Brownian Motion may determine the complete local geometry. &lt;br/&gt;This reflects the extent of the confusion about the&lt;br/&gt;following question: "How much Geometry is used by the Quantum Physics?"&lt;br/&gt;The proposed investigations demonstrate, for the first time, how little&lt;br/&gt;information about Geometry is used by Quantum Physics. For instance,&lt;br/&gt;Quantum Physics completely ignores the isometries of the spaces, &lt;br/&gt;which otherwise form the central piece of a theory developed in Geometry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104361</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zoltan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Szabo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zoltan.szabo@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Herbert H. Lehman College</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104681589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7189608107</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>250 Bedford Park Blvd West</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
