<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Polygonal Knot Theory, Controlled Topology and Topology of Homology Manifolds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>93588</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0104111&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Heather M. Johnston&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Polygonal knot theory studies the isotopy classes of embedded&lt;br/&gt;polygons in three space where the number and length of edges are&lt;br/&gt;fixed throughout the isotopy. The PI and co-author have found&lt;br/&gt;the first examples of polygons which are topologically unknotted,&lt;br/&gt;but for which the isotopy class of embeddings is nontrivial. The&lt;br/&gt;PI and student collaborators will investigate questions such as&lt;br/&gt;whether or not there are any such examples for equilateral&lt;br/&gt;polygons. Surgery theory studies the set of manifold structures&lt;br/&gt;within a given homotopy type. The Bryant-Ferry-Mio-Weinberger&lt;br/&gt;surgery exact sequence for homology manifolds has been used by&lt;br/&gt;the PI to prove that up to s-cobordism many of the geometric&lt;br/&gt;properties of manifolds also hold for homology manifolds. The&lt;br/&gt;Novikov conjecture and related coarse Novikov conjecture are keys&lt;br/&gt;to our understanding of surgery theory. The PI has developed&lt;br/&gt;some techniques for attacking the coarse Novikov conjecture for&lt;br/&gt;unusual non uniformly contractible spaces. Controlled and bounded&lt;br/&gt;surgery theory will be used to further investigate homology&lt;br/&gt;manifolds and the coarse Novikov conjecture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Up to now, topologists have studied well-behaved spaces such as&lt;br/&gt;manifolds. Yet singular spaces arise more and more frequently in&lt;br/&gt;subjects such as analysis, algebraic geometry and physics. The&lt;br/&gt;non-resolvable homology manifolds studied in this project are so&lt;br/&gt;singular that they have no points whatsoever with Euclidean&lt;br/&gt;neighborhoods. Perhaps these strange spaces will someday account&lt;br/&gt;for the extra dimensions of the universe predicted by string&lt;br/&gt;theory. Coarse geometry, and the coarse homology of John Roe are&lt;br/&gt;ways of separating the large scale behavior of spaces from the&lt;br/&gt;local information. The invariants of coarse geometry and&lt;br/&gt;topology depend only on the large scale behavior of the&lt;br/&gt;space. Better understanding of these objects and their invariants&lt;br/&gt;will help topologists to classify the different types of singular&lt;br/&gt;spaces, which appear throughout modern physics. In polygonal knot&lt;br/&gt;theory, a new twist on the classical study of knots, a different&lt;br/&gt;type of singular spaces is studied. This new theory is modeled by&lt;br/&gt;sticks joined end to end by universally flexible joints (rubber&lt;br/&gt;tubing perhaps) to form a closed loop. The PI has produced the&lt;br/&gt;first examples of configurations which are stuck (cannot be&lt;br/&gt;unraveled), but only because they are made of sticks. If the&lt;br/&gt;same configurations were made of string they could be unraveled.&lt;br/&gt;Knot theory of strings has been applied to the study of protein&lt;br/&gt;and DNA molecules. For a small number of atoms each bond can be&lt;br/&gt;represented by a stick in the model discussed here, This is a&lt;br/&gt;richer and more appropriate model for small molecules than the&lt;br/&gt;string which has been used in the past.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104111</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnston</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hejohnston@vassar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vassar College</Name>
      <CityName>Poughkeepsie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>126040657</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8454377092</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>124 Raymond Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
