<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Second-order Cone Programming : Algorithms and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240018</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Large Second-order Cone Programming: Algorithms and &lt;br/&gt;Applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI. Donald Goldfarb and Garud Iyengar.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Second-order cone programs (SOCPs) are convex optimization &lt;br/&gt;problems in which a linear function is optimized over the &lt;br/&gt;intersection of an affine linear manifold with the Cartesian &lt;br/&gt;product of second-order (Lorentz) cones. Linear programs (LPs), &lt;br/&gt;convex quadratic programs (QPs), and quadratically constrained &lt;br/&gt;convex quadratic programs can all be formulated as SOCPs, as &lt;br/&gt;can many other problems that do not fall into these three problem &lt;br/&gt;classes. On the other hand, since a second-order cone constraint &lt;br/&gt;is equivalent to a linear matrix inequality, semidefinite &lt;br/&gt;programs (SDPs) include SOCPs as a special case. Computationally &lt;br/&gt;speaking, an SOCP falls between an LP or a QP and an SDP. Interior &lt;br/&gt;point methods solve all of these problems in polynomial time. &lt;br/&gt;Although, the computational effort required to solve an SOCP is &lt;br/&gt;greater than that required to solve an LP or a QP, it is &lt;br/&gt;substantially less than that required to solve an SDP of similar &lt;br/&gt;size and structure. However, in many ways, an SOCP is closer to &lt;br/&gt;an SDP than an LP or QP since its feasible set is non-polyhedral. &lt;br/&gt;The proposed research focuses on several aspects of SOCPs, &lt;br/&gt;including the development of numerically stable algorithms for &lt;br/&gt;SOCPs that take advantage of sparsity in the data, the study of &lt;br/&gt;SOCP-based approximation algorithms for hard combinatorial optimization &lt;br/&gt;problems, the study of computational aspects of cut generation methods &lt;br/&gt;for mixed 0-1 SOCPs and the applications of SOCPs in robust financial &lt;br/&gt;optimization. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SOCPs are excellent models for applications that arise in a broad range &lt;br/&gt;of fields from engineering, control, and finance, to robust and &lt;br/&gt;combinatorial optimization. The wide applicability of SOCPs and the &lt;br/&gt;need for efficient, numerically stable algorithms to solve them makes &lt;br/&gt;their study worthwhile.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104282</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goldfarb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>goldfarb@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Garud</FirstName>
      <LastName>Iyengar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>garud@ieor.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
