<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Variational Analysis in Problems of Optimization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>230377</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Pang, Jong-Shi&lt;br/&gt;From: Terry Rockafellar [rtr@math.washington.edu]&lt;br/&gt;Sent: Wednesday, June 13, 2001 3:59 PM&lt;br/&gt;To: jpang@nsf.gov&lt;br/&gt;Subject: proposal abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Jong-Shih, here's the abstract for my proposal "Variational Analysis &lt;br/&gt;in Problems of Optimization". &lt;br/&gt; Terry&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will apply the latest advances in variational analysis to &lt;br/&gt;a range of optimization problems and issues. Sensitivity and metric &lt;br/&gt;regularity in parametric dependence will be studied. Second-order &lt;br/&gt;optimality conditions will be devised for new purposes and from &lt;br/&gt;nonstandard perspectives. Connections between cost-to-go functions and &lt;br/&gt;feedback for certain kinds of optimal control will be explored along &lt;br/&gt;with the specialization to a control framework of recently generalized &lt;br/&gt;Euler-Lagrange equations and Hamiltonian equations. New risk models and &lt;br/&gt;splitting algorithms will be developed in stochastic programming, where &lt;br/&gt;decisions must be made optimally in advance of full information. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These efforts are needed because problems of optimization, which are &lt;br/&gt;of great importance in many applications from management to engineering, &lt;br/&gt;are not well covered by standard mathematics of the past and have &lt;br/&gt;required new ways of thinking. In such problems, centered on minimizing &lt;br/&gt;"cost" or maximizing "efficiency", for instance, there usually are very &lt;br/&gt;many side conditions that have to be satisfied, and moreover the number &lt;br/&gt;of decision variables to be coped with can be enormous---in the thousands &lt;br/&gt;or even millions. It is crucial to have a solid foundation for the &lt;br/&gt;development of numerical methods for finding solutions and understanding &lt;br/&gt;the effects that shifts in input data might have on those solutions. &lt;br/&gt;The work to be performed will further the progress in those directions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0104055</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>R. Tyrrell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rockafellar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rtr@math.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
