<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Instruction Set Architecture for Pervasive Security</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>256554</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pratibha Varma-Nelson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research investigates core architectural features for secure and private communications and computations over the public Internet and wireless infrastructures. It focuses on what instruction-set architecture (ISA) features general-purpose processors would have, if secure information processing is the default pervasive mode of operation, with non-secure processing the optional mode, rather than vice versa. It proposes ISA features for very fast, flexible, software cryptographic processing, not only for current algorithms but also to enable algorithm designers to create new cryptographic algorithms that are more secure and more efficient. Word-oriented, programmable processors can be radically more effective for cryptographic functions with new instructions for sub-word manipulations, as well as for multi-word arithmetic. Novel bit permutation instructions are proposed for providing superior diffusion capabilities for current and future symmetric key algorithms. Their performance, area and latency tradeoffs, and scalability with superscalar organizations are studied. Very fast table lookup and other ISA features are also studied for algorithms like Rijndael, the recent Advanced Encryption Standard winner, and for public-key algorithms like Elliptic Curve Cryptography. The research also investigates architectural features for secure key management, and other ISA features designed to enhance or enforce system security.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0105677</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ruby</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rblee@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
