<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Spectral Analysis for Data Mining</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen M. O'Hara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research is concerned with the development, analysis &lt;br/&gt;and empirical evaluation of algorithms for information &lt;br/&gt;retrieval and data mining, primarily using spectral analysis. &lt;br/&gt;A partial list of the fundamental questions&lt;br/&gt;being addressed are: How should data be stored,&lt;br/&gt;organized and processed so as to allow the most effective retrieval of&lt;br/&gt;information? How can ``important'' structure and ``meaningful''&lt;br/&gt;patterns be found within a large data-set? How and when can this&lt;br/&gt;hidden structure be used to facilitate determination of missing data&lt;br/&gt;or to ``clean'' data that is imprecise or partially incorrect?&lt;br/&gt;What are appropriate models for data generation, and how can&lt;br/&gt;these models be used to improve the design of data mining algorithms?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers are studying applications that have already &lt;br/&gt;received a great deal of attention and on which&lt;br/&gt;empirical success has been achieved, including object&lt;br/&gt;clustering and web site ranking. In addition, they are designing &lt;br/&gt;and analyzing algorithms, and developing and analyzing models &lt;br/&gt;for newer data mining problems, including collaborative filtering, &lt;br/&gt;topic distillation, spam detection and prevention, and hierarchical&lt;br/&gt;clustering. Matrix perturbation theory is the foundation for the &lt;br/&gt;development of theoretical results. The researchers are also studying&lt;br/&gt;new techniques for speeding up the computation of the SVD.&lt;br/&gt;The theoretical research is being complemented by&lt;br/&gt;experimental evaluation on real data sets.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0105406</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Karlin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>karlin@cs.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
