<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertations Initiative for the Advancement of Climate Change Research (DISCCRS)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>259462</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael A. Mayhew</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The DISsertations initiative for the advancement of Climate Change ReSearch (DISCCRS) program is an interdisciplinary, cooperative effort involving several professional societies including the American Geophysical Union (AGU), American Meteorological Society (AMS), and Ecological Society of America (ESA). Targeting recent Ph.D. recipients from across the spectrum of disciplines involved in climate change research, the program will quantify and characterize recent Ph.D. recipients interested in climate change to assess human potential and identify needs; consolidate and disseminate Ph.D. dissertation abstracts to highlight individual capabilities; establish electronic distribution lists to promote international, interdisciplinary communication; and organize an international "capstone" symposium for recent graduates to foster interdisciplinary understanding and interactions across disciplines. The program is structured to foster interdisciplinary understanding and accelerate research and insights in the vitally important and time-sensitive area of climate change and its impacts. It will foster international as well as inter-institutional networks, and favor participants from both developing and developed countries. Demographic data will facilitate the characterization and tracking of human resources across the climate-change research community. Tracking recent graduates through their first few years of professional development should tell us much about career progression and satisfaction during these early and most critical years of professional development. The on-line Dissertation Registry provides a comprehensive yet concise summary of new research for scientists, policy makers, and agency representatives and facilitate integration of this new generation of researchers into the broader community. Electronic distribution lists provide a mechanism to disseminate information and foster communication across disciplinary and international boundaries. The symposium will bring together individuals whose work transcends traditional boundaries and enable them to enhance understanding and perspectives and establish collegial, long-term associations to advance the field in new ways. In addition to presenting their research, participants would discuss emerging science and policy topics. Perspectives and recommendations will be published.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0105201</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>C. Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weiler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weiler@whitman.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Whitman College</Name>
      <CityName>Walla Walla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>993622067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5095275926</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>345 Boyer Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1575</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5209</Code>
      <Text>ENVIR SOCIAL &amp; BEHAVIOR SCIENC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5740</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5209</Code>
      <Text>ENVIR SOCIAL &amp; BEHAVIOR SCIENC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9278</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
