<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High-Resolution Optical Investigations of Layered Materials with Net Polarization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>472950</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Nelson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is aimed at studying physical properties of various soft condensed materials such as chiral-smectic liquid-crystal and bent-core compounds that display a large net electric polarization. In addition to experimentally determining the molecular azimuthal arrangements in the chiral-smectic variant phases, studies of physical properties of various new mesophases formed by bent-core molecules will be emphasized. Employing state-of-the-art optical systems, numerous important discoveries in these areas are now possible such as the characterization of mesophases formed by bent-core molecules. These experimental results will focus on fundamental studies of molecular packing in the various mesophases and provide theorists important physical parameters for theoretical modeling. Educational opportunities will be developed to train both undergraduate and graduate students in designing and constructing cutting-edge optical systems as well as acquiring, analyzing and understanding high quality experimental data. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The desire for high-speed liquid crystal displays and a new interest in special materials to be used in optic fiber networks makes the characterization of exotic liquid crystal phases for such applications has critically important. Students trained in these areas will be highly competitive in the job market.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0106122</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cheng-Cher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>huang001@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
