<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Late Cretaceous Vertebrates from Madagascar: Implications for Gondwanan Biogeography</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>280177</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030101</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>H. Richard Lane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;LATE CRETACEOUS VERTEBRATES FROM MADAGASCAR:&lt;br/&gt;IMPLICATIONS FOR GONDWANAN BIOGEOGRAPHY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;David W. Krause, Gregory A. Buckley, Catherine A. Forster, Raymond R. Rogers, and Scott D. Sampson&lt;br/&gt;EAR-0106477&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PIs previous NSF-funded research has established the Mahajanga Basin of NW Madagascar as having some of the most complete and spectacularly preserved specimens of Late Cretaceous vertebrates from the southern hemisphere. Their discoveries have quintupled the previously known species diversity of Late Cretaceous vertebrates from the island and now include specimens of fishes, frogs, turtles, snakes, crocodyliforms, dinosaurs, birds, and mammals. More broadly, investigators involved in the Mahajanga Basin Project have elucidated the anatomy, paleobiology, and phylogenetic relationships of several vertebrate higher taxa, documented the Upper Cretaceous stratigraphy and sedimentology of the basin, provided key insights into the biogeographic origins of both the extinct and extant vertebrate faunas of the island, and shed significant new light on Gondwanan plate tectonics during the Mesozoic. Much remains to be done, however, in the vast expanses of paleontologically and geologically unexplored Cretaceous rocks of the Mahajanga Basin. It is clear that, even in the primary study area, the diversity of vertebrates remains inadequately sampled when compared to more thoroughly studied areas elsewhere in the world. Furthermore, despite the exquisite quality and completeness of the specimens of some taxa, the vast majority of species are represented by only fragmentary and isolated specimens. Finally, the unconsolidated nature of the Upper Cretaceous strata and the high annual rainfall ensures that the supply of new localities and new specimens is replenished on an annual basis. With continued work, the PIs are confident that the Mahajanga Basin vertebrate fauna will become one of the best sampled faunas of Cretaceous age and one of the primary standards against which other Gondwanan faunas are compared. The primary goals of the current proposal are to expand preliminary efforts through additional discoveries of fossil vertebrates in the still under-sampled primary field area; investigation of new field areas discovered in 1999; anatomical, functional, and phylogenetic analysis of specimens already discovered but still unstudied or only partly studied; additional elucidation of geologic context, including paleoenvironment and paleoclimate; and testing of biogeographic and plate tectonic hypotheses related to the breakup of Gondwana.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0106477</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krause</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>David.Krause@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Forster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>forster@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/13/2002</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buckley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>buckley@fmnh785.fmnh.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sampson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ssampson@umnh.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rogers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rogers@macalester.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1571</Code>
      <Text>SCEC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5976</Code>
      <Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
