<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>De Novo Design of Helical Electron Transfer Metalloproteins</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph L. Templeton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Prof. George McLendon of the Department of Chemistry, Princeton University, is supported by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry program of the Division of Chemistry, National Science Foundation, for his work on developing a general protocol to synthesize de novo proteins of optimal stability. Kinetically inert metal/ligand systems will be used that allow stepwise resynthesis of the target assembly, and investigate the design by measuring thermodynamic folding parameters and by macromolecular structural analysis. The approach will be extended to select proteins that lend themselves to in vivo expression. Results from this study will lead to a greater understanding of the protein structure and folding through development of a novel technology, which will allow the design and expression of proteins of predictable function. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results from this study will have a broad societal impact in such areas as catalysis in industrial processes and synthesis of drugs. Students and post-doctoral research associates will receive excellent training in a novel developing area of bioinorganic chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0106342</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>McLendon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>glm@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Case</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcase@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
