<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Virtual Reality Modeling-based Inquiry: The Role of Isomorphic and Behavioral Modeling on Knowledge Construction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>724770</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregg E. Solomon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposed research project is designed to analyze the strengths of four theoretically grounded model-use conditions. The investigation focuses on the process through which understanding emerges, evolves and diffuses through modeling-based inquiry and pedagogy and 3D technologies. These investigators will use a data acquisition system that allows them to record data (video, audio, screen shots, and computer log files) in the classroom setting and analyze the data through activity "nodes" and "links" to track the "process" by which students engage in the modeling process. The group then proposes to explore the possibility of doing similar analysis through web-base resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fundamentally, the project builds on the existing foundation of experience, technology, and curriculum materials in Virtual Reality modeling-based inquiry. The basic design of the project is congruent with the approach advocated by Stokes labeled "use-oriented basic research." The findings will be used to develop a conceptual model of how learners learn under these modeling conditions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal is well written, detailed, and grounded in extant research on isomorphic and behavioral environments. The researchers, including the proposed subcontractor, have broad knowledge and experience in the areas of virtual reality, model building, and assessment. The work will have an influence on content areas beyond astronomy, providing insight into how students learn from modeling environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The panel generally viewed this project as having high potential. However, several issues were raised during the discussion:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. A significant portion of the proposal was devoted to the technology, and this technology-centered focus distracted from how the technology would be used to address the research questions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. The ROLE goals include integrating diversity into NSF programs, projects and activities. This proposal did not address this issue, and the panel felt that this detracted from the proposal.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0106968</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shaw</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jss@hal.physast.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kehay@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cohen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>proposals@cybernet.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1666</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH ON LEARNING &amp; EDUCATI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
