<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: The Evolution of Competitive Settlement Strategies in Fijian Prehistory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Under the direction of Dr. Terry Hunt, Ms. Julie Field will collect data for&lt;br/&gt;her doctoral dissertation. She will initiate new archaeological research in&lt;br/&gt;the Sigatoka Valley, located in the southwestern corner of the island of&lt;br/&gt;Viti Levu, Fiji. This research will investigate the evolution of competitive&lt;br/&gt;settlement strategies between related and non-related social groups in&lt;br/&gt;Fijian prehistory. Ms. Field's previous analyses of aerial photographs from&lt;br/&gt;the Sigatoka Valley have documented the location and character of over 700&lt;br/&gt;archaeological features, including fortifications, agricultural features,&lt;br/&gt;and unfortified settlements. Despite the quantity and richness of the&lt;br/&gt;archaeological record, no chronology exists for the establishment of the&lt;br/&gt;fortifications, or the arrival of the various patrilineal descent groups&lt;br/&gt;documented at the contact period. Ms. Field's doctoral dissertation&lt;br/&gt;research will examine the development of fortifications in the valley, and&lt;br/&gt;also trace the relationship between the environment and the frequency of&lt;br/&gt;conflict, as evinced by the occurrence of fortifications on lands&lt;br/&gt;traditionally held by patrilineal descent groups, known as mataqali and&lt;br/&gt;yavusa. Her research will incorporate an archaeological excavation and&lt;br/&gt;collection strategy, focusing on a sample of 15 sites from a variety of&lt;br/&gt;environmental zones. The acquisition of datable materials from such&lt;br/&gt;features as walls, ditches, and remote mountain outposts will allow for the&lt;br/&gt;first chronology of fortifications in this part of Fiji. Ms. Field will&lt;br/&gt;also couple the information gleaned from archaeological research to an&lt;br/&gt;environmental model generated within the framework of a geographic&lt;br/&gt;information system (GIS). Comparison of these data, as well as the&lt;br/&gt;distribution of land-holdings and hierarchical social relations that are&lt;br/&gt;known to exist between the patrilineal descent groups of the valley, will&lt;br/&gt;have the potential to indicate group fission, movement, and the various&lt;br/&gt;competitive stances that existed in prehistory. Archaeologists are&lt;br/&gt;interested in the development of conflict and warfare, and the examination&lt;br/&gt;of fortifications is a very direct method for the study of this phenomenon&lt;br/&gt;during the prehistoric period. NSF support will allow Ms. Field to conduct&lt;br/&gt;excavations in Fiji, and also provide for the dating of archaeological&lt;br/&gt;materials. This research is important because it will yield data of&lt;br/&gt;interest to both regional and international scholars, and it explores a&lt;br/&gt;topic that is of great interest to the discipline of anthropology. It will&lt;br/&gt;also support and assist in training a promising young scientist.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0106221</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hunt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thunt@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
