<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Barrett Lectures May, 2001 "New Directions and Developments in Computational Mathematics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9320</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Catherine Mavriplis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigator and his colleagues organize the 2001 John H. Barrett &lt;br/&gt;Memorial Lectures in the University of Tennessee at Knoxville from &lt;br/&gt;May 10-12, 2001. The Barrett Lectures have been held annually since 1972. &lt;br/&gt;Each year a different topic is chosen, representing the research interests &lt;br/&gt;of the mathematics faculty of the University of Tennessee. &lt;br/&gt;Since 1993, the lectures have consisted of three&lt;br/&gt;one-hour survey talks by each of three leading researchers&lt;br/&gt;representing different themes/directions in a single field. The topic of &lt;br/&gt;the 2001 Barrett Lectures is: ``New Directions and Developments in &lt;br/&gt;Computational Mathematics". The focus of the lectures is parallel &lt;br/&gt;numerical algorithms for partial differential equations and their &lt;br/&gt;implementations and applications. The main speakers of the 2001 Barrett &lt;br/&gt;Lectures are Jinchao Xu of Penn State University, David Keyes of &lt;br/&gt;Old Dominion University and ICASE, and Mary Wheeler of University of &lt;br/&gt;Texas at Austin. Each of them will deliver three one-hour survey lectures &lt;br/&gt;on recent developments on parallel numerical algorithms with three &lt;br/&gt;different emphases: theory (Xu), computer implementation (Keyes), &lt;br/&gt;and application (Wheeler). In addition to the main speakers, six&lt;br/&gt;speakers are also invited to give one-hour talks on topics related &lt;br/&gt;to one of the main lectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Barrett Lectures are partly funded by a grant from Tennessee Science &lt;br/&gt;Alliance, and have often received additional support from the National &lt;br/&gt;Science Foundation. They attract wide interest, with an audience of between &lt;br/&gt;40 and 50 participants from the whole country, in addition to faculty and &lt;br/&gt;students from Knoxville and the Oak Ridge National Laboratory. They represent &lt;br/&gt;one of the few long standing lecture series in mathematics in the southeastern &lt;br/&gt;United States. The main objective of the 2001 Barrett Lectures is to provide &lt;br/&gt;the participants with an exposition of parallel numerical algorithms for &lt;br/&gt;partial differential equations arising from various &lt;br/&gt;scientific/engineering/industrial applications, through in-depth survey&lt;br/&gt;lectures and informal discussions with the above three leading researchers &lt;br/&gt;in the field. Additional goals are to foster interdisciplinary collaboration, &lt;br/&gt;particularly with researchers in the Computer Science Department and in the &lt;br/&gt;College of Engineering at the University of Tennessee and several other &lt;br/&gt;southeastern institutions, and to generate a set of written surveys in the &lt;br/&gt;subject, which the organizing committee will endeavor to have published &lt;br/&gt;in book form. The fund being requested from the NSF will be spent&lt;br/&gt;providing partial support towards travel and accommodation for $20$ graduate&lt;br/&gt;students and recent Ph.D.'s who do not have research grants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107159</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ohannes</FirstName>
      <LastName>Karakashian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ohannes@math.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Collins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccollins@math.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaobing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xfeng@math.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
