<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Core Proposal for Federal Facilities Council</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Federal Facilities Council (FFC) is an element of the Board on Infrastructure and the Constructed Environment (BICE) of the National Research Council. Since 1953 the FFC and its predecessor organizations have provided its sponsoring agencies with a mechanism for jointly identifying and addressing mutual problems and concerns in the areas of building science and technology, management, and operations. Each year, the FFC formulates a Technical Activities Program to address the major concerns of the sponsor agencies. The 2001 Activities Program includes the following activities: initiation of an NRC advisory study of Capital Project Investment Decisions; information studies and workshops to address Performance Based Condition Assessments, Best Practices for Facility Advance Planning, Best Practices for Achieving Healthy Indoor Environments, and a Compendium of Best Practices for Facility Operations and Maintenance; conferences on Post-Occupancy Evaluations (POEs) for Facilities, Outsourcing of Management Functions for the Acquisition of Federal Facilities, and Emerging Technologies for Buildings of the 21st Century. The FFC program also supports approximately 35 meetings of FFC standing committee and maintenance of the FFC Internet Home Page. Reports resulting from the FFC program are prepared in sufficient quantity to ensure their distribution to the sponsors and to other relevant parties and made available electronically through the internet.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107614</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Little</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rglittle@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1635</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
