<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ROLE: Empirical Research on Critical Issues in Recruiting and Retaining the Mathematics and Science Teaching Workforce</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>857651</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Larry E. Suter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is intended to examine statistical data bases for the cities of Miami and Detroit to apply a statistical model of teacher hiring practices to seek improved strategies for attracting high quality teachers. It would focus on determining leverage points for maintaining a high quality instructional work force, providing the basis for selecting a policy from among options of changing wage compensation, working conditions, or district policies. The team will use econometric analysis and dynamic-system modeling. Teacher turnover will be analyzed with a statistical model that includes teacher attributes, compensation, and school factors. Then school effects will be decomposed into specific attributes that affect turnover and measurable attributes that can be observed. Finally, the researchers will build a data set that links teachers to students to examine the effect of teacher attributes to student outcomes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/28/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107014</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Burke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>burked@cna.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cavalluzzo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cavallul@cna.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The CNA Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Alexandria</CityName>
      <ZipCode>223111850</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7038242226</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4825 Mark Center Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
