<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Segmental Dynamics in Ultra-thin Polymer layers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>309000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests funds for continuation of studies of the segmental motion of polymers at solid interfaces. Since the interfacial regions are quite thin, spectroscopic techniques are required for their characterization. In this case, the technique to be used is primarily nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR). The NMR studies will be done with deuterium and specifically labeled polymers. Deuterium NMR has several advantages and the polymers will be studied with line shape, two-dimensional exchange, and relaxation time studies. These will give a picture of the motion of the polymer molecules at the interface. Of particular interest is the quantification of the molecular motion with the deuterium exchange experiment. The use of the deuterium label can also provide contrast so that the interface can be studied even in the presence of an overlayer of unlabeled polymers. The result of the successful completion of this work will be that knowledge of the structure and dynamics of interfacial materials will help researchers to design interfacial systems with enhanced properties for advance applications such as advanced composite structures, electronic devices, and particle stabilization.&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;Thin films made from polymers are important in a variety of applications including structural composites, sensors, and electronics. In these systems, the properties of the thin films are critical to the success of the devices that use them. Characterization of the properties of the polymers is crucial to an understanding of how the devices work. Ultimately, the properties of devices with polymers can be improved if the behavior and their roles are understood. These determinations become even more crucial as the size of the devices, and hence the thickness of the polymer films become smaller. For example, in electronic devices, some of the properties of the polymer layers change with the thickness of the polymer layer.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107670</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fblum@okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Rolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 W 12th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
