<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of a Standard Biostratigraphic Reference Section for the Silurian Cape Phillips Formation, Canadian Arctic</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100004</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030101</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>H. Richard Lane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Development of a Standard Biostratigraphic Reference Section for the Silurian Cape Phillips Formation, Canadian Arctic&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Paula J. Noble&lt;br/&gt;EAR-0107139&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study proposes to advance the status of Silurian radiolarian biostratigraphy through the collection and analysis of radiolarians from well-dated pristine sections of basinal marine strata in the Cape Phillips Formation, Canadian Arctic. Radiolarian data will be integrated with other useful biostratigraphic and geochemical datums with the goals of 1) generating a composite biostratigraphic standard for the Cape Phillips Basin, and 2) calibrating radiolarian datums that appear to have global biostratigraphic significance. This study should produce the most comprehensive and best calibrated data set ever generated for Silurian radiolarians and will be of fundamental importance in providing better age control for complexly deformed and poorly dated basinal sequences in orogenic belts around the world. Radiolarians and graptolites will be collected from at least three sections of Wenlockian - Ludlovian Strata on Devon and Cornwallis Islands and combined with six other Llandoverian-Ludlovian sections sampled by the PI and her collaborator, Dr. A. C. Lenz, during past field seasons. The graptolites are well studied and serve as the basis for biostratigraphic correlation and age control. A 1999 pilot study of carbon isotope geochemistry shows that there are at least two positive excursions that may serve as chemostratigraphic datums that may be integrated with the paleontologic data. Isotope geochemistry will be conducted on additional sections to further determine the reliability and extent of these chemostratigraphic datums.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107139</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Simon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Poulson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>poulson@mines.unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paula</FirstName>
      <LastName>Noble</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>noblepj@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
