<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Problems in Population Genetics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>243959</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Ann Horn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Sawyer&lt;br/&gt;0107420&lt;br/&gt; The investigator studies ways to estimate the average amount&lt;br/&gt;of selection for or against new mutations at a particular genetic&lt;br/&gt;locus using information contained in aligned DNA or protein&lt;br/&gt;sequences. If the estimated amount of selection is significantly&lt;br/&gt;negative, this is an indication that the region is under&lt;br/&gt;stabilizing selection and may have an important biological&lt;br/&gt;function. If the estimated average amount of selection is&lt;br/&gt;positive, then new variants in this region are favored, as is&lt;br/&gt;common for some immune system genes. Models that allow random&lt;br/&gt;variation of the amounts of selection over sites are also&lt;br/&gt;considered. The methods studied are computationally easy to carry&lt;br/&gt;out and have easily obtained significance levels, but assume&lt;br/&gt;statistical independence between polymorphic sites instead of the&lt;br/&gt;more usual assumption of tight linkage. Studies have shown in&lt;br/&gt;many cases that short-segment gene conversion and recombination&lt;br/&gt;act at a greater rate than point mutation, so that tight linkage&lt;br/&gt;is not always a reasonable assumption. Simulations are carried&lt;br/&gt;out to test the assumption that small to moderate amounts of gene&lt;br/&gt;conversion and recombination are sufficient to guarantee enough&lt;br/&gt;independence between sites so that the proposed estimators will&lt;br/&gt;have desirable statistical properties. The models are applied to&lt;br/&gt;aligned sequences from public databases. They are also applied to&lt;br/&gt;human SNP datasets, for which the assumption of sitewise&lt;br/&gt;independence is clearer.&lt;br/&gt; Recent advances in biology have made a vast amount of data&lt;br/&gt;available about the human genome and about the genomes of other&lt;br/&gt;species. Tools for understanding the significance of this data,&lt;br/&gt;and in particular the significance of variation in this data&lt;br/&gt;between individuals, have lagged behind. One question is whether&lt;br/&gt;new genetic variants at a particular genetic locus (or segment of&lt;br/&gt;DNA) have been favored on the average in the past, have rendered&lt;br/&gt;their owners less fit, or have had essentially the same effect on&lt;br/&gt;the fate of individuals with those DNA variants. Tests are&lt;br/&gt;proposed that give a computationally easy way of determining&lt;br/&gt;which of these three cases applies at a particular genetic locus.&lt;br/&gt;These tests are based on the configurations of variant sites in&lt;br/&gt;DNA from several individuals at that locus. The results of this&lt;br/&gt;test can give information about the function of this stretch of&lt;br/&gt;DNA. They can also give information about how a particular gene&lt;br/&gt;is affected by or is currently being affected by evolution.&lt;br/&gt;Information from related biological species can give further&lt;br/&gt;information. The difficulty of the proposed methods is that they&lt;br/&gt;assume that different portions of the genetic locus are evolving&lt;br/&gt;approximately independently. For some genetic data (for example,&lt;br/&gt;SNP for "single-nucleotide polymorphism" data) this can generally&lt;br/&gt;be assumed. The sensitivity of the proposed methods to this&lt;br/&gt;independence assumption for non-SNP data is tested.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107420</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stanley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sawyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sawyer@math.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
