<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Research Fellowship Program: River Metabolism Within the Amazon Basin: Constraints on the ROMBUS Model</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>57000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Parris</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0107270&lt;br/&gt;Aufdenkampe&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The International Research Fellow Awards Program enables U.S. scientists and engineers to conduct three to twenty-four months of research abroad. The Program's awards provide opportunities for joint research, and the use of unique or complementary facilities, expertise and experimental conditions abroad.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will support a twenty-four-month postdoctoral research fellowship for &lt;br/&gt;Dr. Anthony Aufdenkampe to work with Dr. Reynaldo L. Victoria and Dr. Alex V. Krusche of CENA and Dr. Ron Benner of the University of South Carolina. Support for this project is coming from the Ecosystem Studies Program of the BIO Division and the U.S.-Brazil Program in the Division of International Programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These experiments are designed toward two objectives: (1) Develop empirical relationships of river metabolism as a function of water composition, discharge hydrograph, and sub-basin characteristics, to be immediately applicable to the first parameterization of the ROMBUS model. (2) Interpret microbial organic matter transformations in rivers from the more detailed perspective of bioenergetics, which is the first step toward a more mechanistic parameterization of these processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposed research is to explore controls on rates of organic matter remineralization within the Amazon River system. The benefit of this project is that it will advance the knowledge of our understanding of Amazon River basin, and river ecology as well as provide us with a better understanding of river metabolism and water composition.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107270</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aufdenkampe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>07/11/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Aufdenkampe, Anthony K</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>22230</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510602</Code>
      <Name>Ecosystem Dynamics</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
