<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>5th Mississippi State Conference on Differential Equations &amp; Computational Simulations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NSF Award Abstract - DMS-0107783&lt;br/&gt;Mathematical Sciences: Fifth Mississippi State Conference on Differential Equations &amp; Computational Simulations&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;0107783 Shivaji&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports U.S. participants (invited speakers, young researchers, and graduate students) in the Fifth Mississippi State Conference on Differential Equations &amp; Computational Simulations on May 18-19, 2001. The objective of the conference is to provide a forum where mathematicians, scientists, and engineers from academia and industry can exchange ideas concerning theoretical, applied, and computational developments in differential equations and associated simulations. The conference is the fifth in a series of biennial meetings on the subject.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the rapid development of high performance computing and communication, and robust and efficient mathematical/numerical algorithms, computational simulation has emerged as an essential tool for engineering analysis and design environment. This has fundamentally&lt;br/&gt;changed the way underlying principles of science and engineering are applied to research,&lt;br/&gt;design, and development. These computational simulations involve (i) a system of differential&lt;br/&gt;equations representative of the physical phenomena (mathematical model); (ii) a numerical&lt;br/&gt;method to simulate the mathematical model; and (iii) an efficient sequential/parallel/distributed&lt;br/&gt;computing environment. Successful simulations require interdisciplinary collaboration between various scientific and engineering fields. This conference is an opportunity for workers in these fields to discuss important recent results.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0107783</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bharat</FirstName>
      <LastName>Soni</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bsoni@uab.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ratnasingham</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shivaji</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>r_shivaj@uncg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jianping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>j.zhu94@csuohio.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
      <CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
