<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Operation of a Trophic Cascade in Predator-free Forest Fragments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199958</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan James Tessier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The role of predation in regulating terrestrial ecosystems, and the related question of whether terrestrial ecosystems are subject to strong trophic cascades (effects which flow from predators through herbivores to plants) are topics of current debate in ecology. The proposed research takes advantage of a multi-billion dollar "experiment" that has created a large number of predator-free islands in a 4,300 square-kilometer impoundment associated with a hydroelectric installation in Venezuela. The proposed research generally tests the hypothesis that the predator-free status of islands should lead initially to a hyper-abundance of herbivores (seed and leaf eating species), and then to massive impacts on the vegetation as a consequence of trophic cascades. Primary activities include continuing rodent and ant removal programs on experimental islands and re-censusing plant plots to record the dynamics of vegetation change on both untreated and treated islands. This research may provide the most direct link yet to the important functional role played by large predators in tropical forests. This has enormous implications for conservation because human-induced loss of predators from tropical forests may drastically alter plant species composition of tropical forests resulting in significant declines in diversity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0108107</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Terborgh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>manu@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510102</Code>
      <Name>Role-Terrestrial Ecosystem</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
