<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Phylogeny, Development, and Taxonomy of Setaria and its Relatives</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>313800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patrick S. Herendeen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The cereal crops foxtail millet and pearl millet, and noxious weeds&lt;br/&gt;such as green foxtail and sandbur are all closely related members of the&lt;br/&gt;grass family, and are part of a group of 310 species descended from a&lt;br/&gt;single ancestor. These plants are all characterized by odd "bristles"&lt;br/&gt;interspersed among their flowers; the bristles are highly modified&lt;br/&gt;branches. This project will determine the precise relationships among as&lt;br/&gt;many species as possible in the "bristle group" using DNA sequences from&lt;br/&gt;the nucleus and the chloroplast. At the same time, the development of the&lt;br/&gt;seed head (inflorescence) and flowers will be studied for a precise&lt;br/&gt;description of how the species differ. Along with this, the graduate&lt;br/&gt;student supported on the grant will determine how many species are in the&lt;br/&gt;foxtail millet group, what the species look like, and will write&lt;br/&gt;identification guides to them. Because there is already information on&lt;br/&gt;the species in North and South America, this part of the project will focus&lt;br/&gt;on Asia and Africa.&lt;br/&gt; The information gained in this project will connect directly with&lt;br/&gt;other information already available on foxtail millet and the panicoid&lt;br/&gt;grasses. The genes that control morphological variation in foxtail millet&lt;br/&gt;are under active investigation, and some of these are similar to known&lt;br/&gt;genes in maize. It should soon be possible to describe morphological&lt;br/&gt;variation in the clade in terms of the genes involved. This will help&lt;br/&gt;answer questions about how species and larger groups are formed. The&lt;br/&gt;resulting study will provide a direct and explicit link between phylogeny,&lt;br/&gt;developmental morphology, and taxonomy, and will provide a framework for&lt;br/&gt;work on the evolution of development</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0108501</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kellogg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ekellogg@danforthcenter.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Saint Louis</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3145165897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ONE UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
