<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Ethnic Conflict in Guinea-Bissau, West Africa</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stuart Plattner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0109155&lt;br/&gt;Knauft / Davidson &lt;br/&gt; The contemporary world if full of cases of ethnic violence, where people who have been neighbors for years, if not generations, turn to violence. Theories explaining such conflict have addressed ancient animosities, political manipulation (especially during turbulent transitions to democracy), and competition for scarce resources. This dissertation research project by a cultural anthropology student will test these theories against the ethnographic reality of Guinea-Bissau, West Africa, where clashes between two groups, the Felupe and the Fula, resulted in violence and forced removal of families from the community. Through participant observation, structured interviews, household surveys and archival research, the student will explore the definition of cultural differences in inter-ethnic contexts; the modes of mobilizing ethnic solidarity; and the dynamics and trajectory of recent outbursts of ethnic violence. The relative importance of kinship, inter-ethnic marriage, land tenure, religious affiliation, initiation and socialization, and cross-national ethnic alliances will be studied. The new knowledge to be gained form this careful case study will be valuable to theorists of contemporary ethnic conflict and will advance our understanding of this important region of the world. In addition the project contributes to the training of a young social scientist.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0109155</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
      <LastName>Knauft</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>antbk@anthro.emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Emory University</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
