<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:Rare Earth-Aluminum Oxide Glass Photonic Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2001</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ritchie B. Coryell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will demonstrate photonic devices based on novel rare earth-aluminum oxide (REAl) glass. These devices exploit electronic transitions in rare earth doped and co-doped glass that potentially enable efficient laser action at wavelengths from 480 to 2250 nanometers (nm) when pumped by inexpensive diode lasers. Phase I will focus on the feasibility of devices having emissions at 1480 nm and possibly 1300 nm emission for telecommunications applications. The behavior of 480-490 nm emissions will be characterized with a view toward use in optical data storage applications. Phase I will also synthesize and characterize doped rare earth-aluminum oxide glasses, and establish protoype device performance. Measurements on the rare earth doped REAl glasses will include the spectral absorption coefficient at the pump wavelength, fluorescence cross section line shape, slope efficiency, fluorescence lifetime, single pass gain, and IR transmission.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Potential commercial applications include small laser or optical amplifier devices to extend the fiber telecommunication bandwidth for use in high-density optical data storage devices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0109441</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J.K. Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weber@containerless.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Containerless Research, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474672678</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>906 UNIVERSITY PLACE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
