<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Aerosol Radiative Forcing during Aerosol Characterization Experiment (ACE)-Asia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>93148</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jay S. Fein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research will use ACE-Asia (Aerosol Characterizations Experiment) aerosol and radiometric observations to determine the radiative effects of the polluted aerosol coming from the Asian continent through three objectives:&lt;br/&gt;1. Develop and validate an aerosol scattering model using the observed aerosol chemical, microphysical, and light scattering measurements.&lt;br/&gt;2. Determine the radiative forcing of the aerosol, using this model and observed radiative fluxes at the surface and top of atmosphere.&lt;br/&gt;3. Determine the context of these results by conducting a comparison of these forcing properties to those found for other regions, particularly during INDOEX (Indian Ocean Experiment).&lt;br/&gt;These studies will concentrate on the surface radiometric and aerosol properties measured from the R/V R. H. Brown, and will include satellite data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is important because of its potential to add new understanding and knowledge about aerosol chemistry and microphysics and the influence of aerosols on radiative forcing, and hence climate, over East Asia and the western Pacific.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0109135</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vogelmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>avogelmann@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0319000</Code>
      <Name>Climate Related Activities</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
