<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Quantitative Insight into Responses of Cell Populations to Radiation Exposure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>132000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Ann Horn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Hanin&lt;br/&gt;0109895&lt;br/&gt; The goal of the project is to gain a new quantitative&lt;br/&gt;insight, on the basis of advanced mathematical methods, into&lt;br/&gt;kinetics of biological processes in irradiated cell populations.&lt;br/&gt;The investigator formulates and analyzes a comprehensive&lt;br/&gt;mechanistic mathematical model of these processes, including&lt;br/&gt;formation of radiation-induced lesions and their repair,&lt;br/&gt;misrepair and fixation, cell cycling and cell death. Mathematical&lt;br/&gt;modeling techniques include general age-dependent branching&lt;br/&gt;stochastic processes, queueing systems, stochastic simulation,&lt;br/&gt;and modern methods of statistical inference. Parameters of the&lt;br/&gt;model are estimated from experimental data on kinetics and&lt;br/&gt;survival of cells in synchronized cultures of S3 HeLa and V79&lt;br/&gt;cells exposed to continuous irradiation at various dose rates.&lt;br/&gt;Parameter estimation is based on a comprehensive stochastic&lt;br/&gt;simulation model of the underlying biological processes and on&lt;br/&gt;methods of stochastic optimization in the maximum likelihood&lt;br/&gt;setting. The model is applied to stationary and exponential cell&lt;br/&gt;cultures that serve as experimental counterparts of tumor cell&lt;br/&gt;populations at different stages of tumor development. The&lt;br/&gt;distribution of the number of surviving clonogenic cells at the&lt;br/&gt;end of radiation exposure, obtained from the comprehensive&lt;br/&gt;simulation model of cell population kinetics, is compared with&lt;br/&gt;explicit formulas for this distribution within simpler birth and&lt;br/&gt;death Markov models that resulted from the preliminary studies.&lt;br/&gt;The most important biological outcome of this work consists of&lt;br/&gt;the set of estimates of unobservable model parameters, which are&lt;br/&gt;interpretable in biologically appealing terms of repair processes&lt;br/&gt;and cell kinetics. The project has a significant impact on&lt;br/&gt;evaluation, prediction and optimization of the efficacy of&lt;br/&gt;radiation cancer treatment and associated methods of cure rate&lt;br/&gt;estimation.&lt;br/&gt; A remarkable progress in cell biology and radiation biology&lt;br/&gt;since the 1920's has resulted in a prodigious amount of&lt;br/&gt;experimental data comprising all aspects of cell responses to&lt;br/&gt;ionizing radiation. These data represent an invaluable source of&lt;br/&gt;information for furthering our knowledge about intracellular&lt;br/&gt;processes in normal and irradiated cells. However, to a large&lt;br/&gt;extent, this gold mine of experimental findings amassed over&lt;br/&gt;years remains unclaimed. The investigator and his collaborators&lt;br/&gt;attempt to understand and describe mathematically the most basic&lt;br/&gt;processes in normal and irradiated cells. This is accomplished on&lt;br/&gt;the basis of advanced mathematical, statistical and computational&lt;br/&gt;methods applied to the original experimental data describing&lt;br/&gt;responses of several cell lines to radiation exposure at variable&lt;br/&gt;dose rate. The project was triggered by and has far-reaching&lt;br/&gt;implications for cancer radiotherapy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0109895</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hanin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hanin@isu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Idaho State University</Name>
      <CityName>Pocatello</CityName>
      <ZipCode>832090002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2082822592</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>921 South 8th Avenue, Stop 8046</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Idaho</StateName>
      <StateCode>ID</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
