<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Revitalizing Spectrofluorimeters with Cryogenic Fiber Optic Probes, Fluorescence Lifetime Capability, and Tunable Laser Sources</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>762000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will develop new instrumentation for fluorescence and phosphorescence spectral measurements. Phase I produced a customized spectrofluorimeter equipped with a tunable laser source, fluorescence lifetime capability, and fiber optic probe for cryogenic measurements. However, better methods are needed to analyze benzo[c]fluorene, which researchers now believe may be an environmental concern comparable to benzo[a]pyrene. Phase II will develop an upgraded new instrument, capable of retrofitting the low temperature probe, fluorescence lifetime, and tunable laser capabilities onto laboratory spectrofluorimeters. The emission monochromator, photomultiplier tube detector, and control/analysis computer can be retained from the spectrofluorimeter, and none of its functionality will be lost. Phase II is expected to produce several models of commercial spectrofluorimeters, test data for publication in technical journals and trade magazines, and instrument upgrade options as a commercial service.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The market for these upgrades presently has an estimated 30,000-40,000 spectrofluorimeters in service. An additional 4,000 individuals or institutions purchase new units each year. The new instrument upgrades will be used in research and development, analytical services, quality control, environmental studies and surveys, and teaching and other applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/26/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/03/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0110432</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gillispie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gillispie@dakotatechnologies.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>DAKOTA TECHNOLOGIES INC</Name>
      <CityName>FARGO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>581020000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7012374908</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2201 12TH ST N STE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>ND</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0118000</Code>
      <Name>Pollution Control</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
