<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP): Alabama Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation Phase III</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5194516</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dr. A. James Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The underrepresentation of minorities in the science, mathematics, engineering, and technology&lt;br/&gt;workforce is still a national problem, ten years after the National Science Foundation (NFS) initiated&lt;br/&gt;the Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) Program. By all accounts great&lt;br/&gt;progress has been made, but not enough to turn the problem around. As one of the six oldest National&lt;br/&gt;Science Foundation (NSF) Alliances in the nation, Alabama has been in the forefront of efforts to&lt;br/&gt;increase the quantity and the quality of underrepresented minorities receiving baccalaureate degrees in&lt;br/&gt;science, mathematics, engineering, and technology (SMET) fields. Many of the Alabama Alliance's&lt;br/&gt;programs have been replicated by other alliances. The Alabama Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority&lt;br/&gt;Participation (ALSAMP) began in 1991 with a baseline of 431 minority SEM undergraduate degrees&lt;br/&gt;and reached a peak of 979 in 1999, a 127% increase. The baseline minority SEM enrollment for&lt;br/&gt;ALSAMP is 3,301. The minority SEM enrollment for the 1999-2000 academic year is 5,876, a 78%&lt;br/&gt;increase. These are indicators of success for ALSAMP Phase I and Phase II.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ALSAMP Phase III proposal is designed to a) sustain the B.S. Degree production levels&lt;br/&gt;and student retention rates specified as Phase II goals and b) define a baseline level of and commitment&lt;br/&gt;to a significant increase in the number of previous, current, and future baccalaureate recipients entering&lt;br/&gt;either a SMET graduate program or a graduate program in teacher education. Thus, the project&lt;br/&gt;approach for LSAMP will involve sustaining and institutionalizing current LSAMP Phase II activities&lt;br/&gt;and the implementation of new LSAMP Phase III activities as given below.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Programs to be Sustained and Institutionalized New LSAMP Phase III Programs&lt;br/&gt;LSAMP Summer Bridge Program GRE Preparation for All Students&lt;br/&gt;LSAMP Scholars Program Undergraduate Research for All Students&lt;br/&gt;Summer Research Internship Program GRE Required for All LSAMP Students&lt;br/&gt;LSAMP Graduate Bridge Program&lt;br/&gt;SEM Student Mentoring Program Increase Number of SMET Students Entering Graduate School through Tracking Effort&lt;br/&gt;Drop-In Centers/Cooperative Learning Intensify Recruitment of Technology Students&lt;br/&gt;Summer Research Conference Increase Collaboration with Other Programs&lt;br/&gt;Publication of The National LSAMP Magazine National LSAMP Publication in Phase III Budget&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The major portion of the Phase III budget will support these new programs. Consequently, the&lt;br/&gt;Phase II programs will be sustained by cost sharing from participating institutions, support from&lt;br/&gt;private sources, and institutionalization. During the next five years, LSAMP will define a baseline&lt;br/&gt;level of and commit to a significant increase in the number of baccalaureate degree recipients entering&lt;br/&gt;either a SMET graduate program or a graduate program in teacher education. This effort will involve&lt;br/&gt;preparing students for success in graduate school and placement in a graduate school of choice.&lt;br/&gt;Students will be tracked through graduate school by means of the LSAMP Success Link Program&lt;br/&gt;and a graduate student database will be maintained by the Alliance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaboration with other NSF programs will be increased substantially, particularly with the&lt;br/&gt;NSF Alliances for Graduate Education and the Professoriate Program and the NSF Urban Systemic&lt;br/&gt;Program. Program activities will be disseminated through the publication of the National LSAMP&lt;br/&gt;Magazine and a full-time program evaluator will be appointed to oversee assessment and evaluation&lt;br/&gt;activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0110595</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dale</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ldale@uab.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Braswell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbraswell@uab.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</Name>
      <CityName>Birmingham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>352940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2059345266</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>AB 1170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
