<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Role of the PhosphoCTD in Spliceosome Assembly-</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>345220</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070800</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vicki B. Vance</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of the project is to investigate the structural basis for and functional consequences of tethering the splicing machinery to the transcription apparatus. In particular, features of a model proposed by Morris and Greenleaf (J. Biol. Chem. 275, 39935-39943 [2000]) will be pursued and tested. In this model the splicing factor Prp40, which binds to the phosphoCTD of RNA polymerase II, is postulated to recruit the U1snRNP to elongating RNAP II and to tether the developing commitment complex to the transcription machinery. This coupling to the transcriptase is proposed to cause early steps in the formation of spliceosomes to be more proficient. In the current project, three objectives will be pursued. One objective is to reveal a molecular basis for coupling spliceosome formation to transcription. To achieve this objective, the identity of the phosphoCTD-interacting domain of Prp40 will be ascertained. Then, the binding affinity and specificity of the newly-defined phosphoCTD-interacting domain will be measured. A second objective is to identify the steps in spliceosome assembly that are accelerated when there is coupling to RNAP II transcription. Toward this end, the rate of pre-commitment and commitment complex formation will be measured in an in vitro system in which splicing can be coupled to transcription (Ghosh, S., and Garcia-Blanco, M. A. (2000) RNA 6, 1325-1334). The third objective is to test a) whether phosphorylation of the CTD is required to tether the splicing machinery to RNAP II, and b) whether the CTD is sufficient for the tethering. The results of these experiments will contribute to an increased understanding of gene expression pathways in eukaryotes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The first step in gene expression is called transcription, a process by which the information in a DNA strand is copied into a long RNA strand. The second step is called RNA processing, wherein the long RNA strand is modified so that it can function as a messenger RNA, to direct the synthesis of a protein. A major event in RNA processing is that of splicing, during which segments of the RNA strand not meant to be in the messenger RNA are cut out and the flanking segments are spliced together. Splicing has usually been studied independently of transcription, but in cells the two processes are coupled. This project seeks to reveal how the two processes are coupled physically and to disclose how the coupling affects splicing events functionally. One objective is to characterize the molecular components that couple splicing to transcription; this characterization is necessary to understand how the two processes are physically linked. Another main objective is to identify the steps in splicing that are accelerated when splicing is linked to transcription. Defects in splicing can have severe consequences for an organism. The work described here will contribute new information that will lead to a better understanding of splicing mechanisms.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0110241</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arno</FirstName>
      <LastName>Greenleaf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>arno@biochem.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mariano A.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garcia-Blanco</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>garci001@mc.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
