<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Spinning Performance of Melt-Spun Fibers Containing Microencapsulated Phase Change Material</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499991</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>TIMOTHY J. RUDD</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project continues the development of the spinning performance of melt spun fibers containing microencapsulated phase change materials (microPCMs). In Phase I, polypropylene fibers less then 3 denier per filament were demonstrated with a good balance of physical properties (tenacity, percent breaking elongation, modulus, etc.) and thermal energy storage capability (latent heat content). Phase II will focus on process and materials variables that affect, in particular, the structure and properties of the as-spun fiber, and in general, the overall spinning process. A key objective is to convert the microcapsule wet cake into a well-dispersed microPCM/polymer concentrate devoid of volatilizing components for adding to virgin polymer and extruding into fiber. Innovative spinning concepts will be employed to improve the capture of microPCMs to maximize thermal energy storage properties. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial availability of melt spun fibers and resulting fabrics with enhanced thermal energy storage capabilities will enable products with superior performance for use in situations where comfort, endurance, or survivability in cold or hot environments is demanded. Thus, the perfection of this technology for the production of good quality fabric could be a major breakthrough in the textile industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0110499</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yvonne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bryant</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ygbryant@TRDCorp.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Triangle Research and Development Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Research Triangle Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277092696</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9198325959</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O Box 12696</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
