<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Launching Building Engineering and Scientific Talent (BEST)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01000000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathryn R. Rison</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Council on Competitiveness proposes to support the establishment of an independent, 501(c)3 organization, Building Engineering and Scientific Talent (BEST) to implement the recommendations of the Congressional Commission on the Advancement of Women and Minorities in Science, Engineering, and Technology Development. The Report of the Commission, released in September 2000, concludes that broadening the demographic base of the U.S. technical workforce is a national economic and social imperative.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Council will support the Report's call to action by framing a strategic vision and putting in place a structure that will enable BEST to engage national leaders at the highest level. If BEST can define itself as the nation's hub for strategic insights, proven methods, and actions plan of any community or institution in the country that wishes to meet the diversity challenge, it will gain the credibility to have the grass roots and policy impact intended by the Commission. The backing of this strategy by a prestigious board, a National Leadership Council, and a Federal Liaison Group will enable BEST to create strong nationwide, leadership networks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0110028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yochelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Johny@compete.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Council on Competitiveness</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200062515</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026824292</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>900 17th ST NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
