<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase II: Development of an Autonomous Equilibrating pCO2 Sensor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>495996</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase II project will develop and test an autonomous, low cost, robust, precise, and miniaturized partial and total carbon dioxide measurement system. This system will be able to characterize the carbon dioxide exchange between ocean surface waters and the atmosphere, thus helping to analyze the "greenhouse effect" and assess global warming on a worldwide basis. The partial and total carbon dioxide systems are miniaturized for deployment by the International SeaKeepers Society in ocean and atmospheric monitoring modules on cargo ships, cruise ships, and super yachts around the world as well as for use on piers, ocean buoys, and other platforms. The prototype partial carbon dioxide system, developed in Phase I, measures carbon dioxide in seawater that has been equilibrated with air using an infrared detector. It is sensitive to five parts per million and responds to rapid changes in carbon dioxide. The prototype miniaturized total carbon dioxide system has a precision of three parts per million. Phase II will miniaturize and test both systems in the laboratory and in the field. Based on these tests and any modifications required, final commercial partial and total carbon dioxide measurement systems will be produced.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The International SeaKeepers Society is expected to deploy hundreds of these carbon dioxide sensor systems. Other purchasers would include government agencies worldwide performing research and monitoring on the global warming phenomenon.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/26/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0110500</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Regis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cook</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>regis_cook@compuserve.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>GENERAL OCEANICS, INC.</Name>
      <CityName>MIAMI</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331699922</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress>1295 NW 163RD STREET</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0313000</Code>
      <Name>Regional &amp; Environmental</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
