<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>State-Resolved Spectroscopy and Dynamics of Chemical Transients</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>473130</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this proposal funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, David Nesbitt of the University of Colorado will pursue a program of research on the spectroscopy and dynamics of chemical transients using state-resolved techniques. The project will examine the spectroscopy of transient species, quantum state-selected reaction dynamics, and the development and exploitation of new methods to interrogate jet-cooled transient species. Jet-cooled radicals, molecular ions, and molecular ion clusters will be investigated in slit supersonic discharges using direct absorption infrared laser methods. High sensitivity overtone spectroscopy of clusters and reaction dynamics with aligned or oriented reagents will be studied using IR-UV-UV triple resonance methods. The ultrasensitive visible absorption spectroscopy of jet-cooled chemical transients will be examined using novel optical heterodyne/high finesse cavity methods combined with slit discharge sources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research program focuses on short-lived molecules and ions that are created under extremely energetic conditions, and thus they usually are not found in nature in stable forms. Besides being of fundamental interest, these studies have practical relevance to solving problems in combustion and atmospheric chemistry as well as in astrophysical chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0111251</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nesbitt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>djn@jila.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1962</Code>
      <Text>SPECTROSCOPY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9232</Code>
      <Text>RES OPPOR AWARDS(ROA) (SUPPLEM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
