<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Carbon Selenium Polymers and Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>405000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph L. Templeton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Advanced Materials Program in the Division of Chemistry makes this award to University of California San Diego. With the award, Professor William Trogler will study different methods such as photochemistry, chemical reduction, electro-polymerization and thermal polymerization to prepare new layered polymeric materials based on carbon diselenides, which will be free from elemental selenium. Doped thin films prepared from poly (carbonselenide)s will be studied for electrochemical, electronic conductivity and chemical redox properties. Complexation of cadmium with poly (carbondiselenide) at the surface would produce cadmium selenide nanoparticles and quantum dots with unique optical and electronic properties for potential applications in devices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;New polymeric materials based on carbon selenides and cadmium selenide quantum dots with electronic and photonic properties will be prepared. Synthetic methods to prepare poly (carbondiselenide)s free from elemental selenium and physical methods to characterize these materials would provide basic science knowledge for the future development of new electronic and photonic materials. Doped thin and flexible films of carbon diselenides would have unique electronic and photonic properties for applications in devices. The research, in addition, will provide training to graduate students in electronic and photonic materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0111376</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Trogler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wtrogler@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
