<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Grafts and Blends of Poly(alkyl/arylphosphazenes) of Organic and Inorganic Polymers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>348000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kenneth M. Doxsee</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Patty Wisian-Neilson in the Department of Chemistry at Southern Methodist University is supported by the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program for her studies on the preparation of a series of grafted poly (alkyl/arylphosphazenes) using anionic, ring opening, and atom radical transfer polymerization and characterization of their fundamental properties by NMR spectroscopy, elemental analysis, differential scanning calorimetry, thermal gravimetric analysis, and gel permeation chromatography. The number, length, and type of graft will be systematically varied and correlated to their physical properties. Gas permeability, flammability, and the ability to stabilize and organize inorganic nanoparticles will be closely examined by standard ASTM flammability tests, permeation studies involving gas chromatography, and transmission electron microscopy, respectively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program, Professor Wisian-Neilson will prepare a series of inorganic polymers and examine their fundamental properties such as thermal stability, solubility in common organic solvents, miscibility, gas permeability, and flame retardancy. The ability of these polymers to stabilize and organize metal and semiconductor nanoparticles (particles with nanometer dimensions) will also be investigated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0111325</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patty</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wisian-Neilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pwisian@smu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Methodist University</Name>
      <CityName>Dallas</CityName>
      <ZipCode>752750302</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2147682030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6425 BOAZ</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
