<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Pre- and Post-Decision Editing in a Risky and Complex Task Environment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>145000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This study focuses on the processes involved in the editing (memory) of past &lt;br/&gt;decisions. Our goal is to contribute to decision theory while expanding our &lt;br/&gt;collective understanding of how complex auditing decisions are made. The &lt;br/&gt;study builds on a well-known body of preceding work, notably Festinger's &lt;br/&gt;cognitive dissonance reduction theory, Fischhoff's hindsight bias, and &lt;br/&gt;Svenson's differentiation and consolidation theory. Festinger, for example, &lt;br/&gt;has shown that decision makers actively reevaluate the" worth" of the &lt;br/&gt;rejected alternative after a decision has been made--frequently to reduce the &lt;br/&gt;risk of post-decision regret. We focus on both pre- and post-decision &lt;br/&gt;attribute isolation and editing: on how expert and novice auditors make sense &lt;br/&gt;of complex and risky judgment/decision tasks, and on how feedback (or lack &lt;br/&gt;thereof) influences their memory of earlier supportive and counter-indicative &lt;br/&gt;signal ratings. Both pre- and post-decision sense-making (editing) processes &lt;br/&gt;are closely linked to both effective and biased learning. We hypothesize &lt;br/&gt;that there are significant differences in the type of data--qualitative vs. &lt;br/&gt;quantitative and positive vs. negative-- that the professionals and novices &lt;br/&gt;attend to. We also hypothesize that novices are more likely to behave in &lt;br/&gt;accordance with established decision theory than their professional &lt;br/&gt;counterparts; that domain knowledge gives rise to an interesting and largely &lt;br/&gt;unexplored set of mitigating factors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/20/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0111969</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lundberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lundberg@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nagle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nagle@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duquesne University</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152820001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4123961537</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Room 310 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
