<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Tribology Issues in Biology and Medicine, a Workshop (June 2001, Chicago, Illinois)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>60012</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Yip-Wah Chung</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0112199&lt;br/&gt;Bryant&lt;br/&gt;Support is provided for a multi-disciplinary workshop to identify important areas of research in tribology that involve biological, biomedical, and medical issues. This workshop willhave principal goals of providing an overview of the current state of the art and recommending new directions of research. The workshop will have approximately 40 to 50 participants, and feature several keynote speakers and participants from tribology, medicine, the biomedical implant community, and biology. The 2.5 day long&lt;br/&gt;workshop's format will consist of the following:&lt;br/&gt; Introductory session&lt;br/&gt; Presentations by keynote speakers&lt;br/&gt; Posters by attendees&lt;br/&gt; Breakout sessions&lt;br/&gt; Final half day wrap up session&lt;br/&gt;The workshop results will be documented to provide valuable guidance for future research directions in tribology. Results of the workshop will be released into the public domain by the workshop organizing committee, as a report to NSF, and as an article to be submitted to one of the Tribology and Biomedical Engineering periodicals and as web-based documents. Special efforts will bemade to facilitate communication between the various scientific communities involved and to identify areas for future cross-disciplinary research. Special efforts will also be made to bring new researchers and graduate students to the meeting and to attract attendeed from underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0112199</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bryant</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbryant@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
