<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR/SY(CISE): Why algorithms work well in practice: pertubation-based average-case analysis of the simplex algorithm and beyond</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>272040</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Du</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Computer Scientists have been challenged by the existence of&lt;br/&gt;remarkable algorithms that work well in practice, but whose&lt;br/&gt;theoretical analyses suggest that these algorithms should perform&lt;br/&gt;poorly or are inconclusive. The root of this problem is that&lt;br/&gt;traditional theoretical analyses measure the performance of&lt;br/&gt;algorithms on their worst inputs. This research analyzes the&lt;br/&gt;performance of algorithms using smoothed analysis, a new measure of&lt;br/&gt;the performance of algorithms that can better predict practical&lt;br/&gt;performance. Using smoothed analysis, this research aims to explain&lt;br/&gt;the good practical performance of some algorithms that are famous&lt;br/&gt;for outperforming pessimistic worst-case analyses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; In particular, algorithms that take real or complex inputs, such as&lt;br/&gt;those that usually occur in scientific and engineering applications,&lt;br/&gt;are examined under random perturbations of their worst-case inputs.&lt;br/&gt;The most famous of these, the simplex method for linear programming,&lt;br/&gt;was the subject of the paper introducing smoothed analysis. Yet, this&lt;br/&gt;work only investigated one rarely-used pivot rule. This research&lt;br/&gt;attempts smoothed analyses of the simplex method under more commonly&lt;br/&gt;used pivot rules. It also considers smoothed analyses of interior&lt;br/&gt;point methods and algorithms for convex programming. An attempt is&lt;br/&gt;being made to extend this analysis to algorithms that take discrete&lt;br/&gt;inputs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0112487</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spielman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spielman@cs.yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/23/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1686</Code>
      <Text>ITR SMALL GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
