<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR/SY (CISE): Verification and Supervisory Control of Hybrid Embedded Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>366698</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>D. Helen Gill</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Proposal #0113131&lt;br/&gt;Antsaklis, Panos&lt;br/&gt;U of Notre Dame&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of this project are to develop algorithms and prototype software for the verification and supervision of hybrid embedded control systems; also for the identification of hybrid system models. This project is developing supervisory processors to supervise and control in real time the operation of large number of control processors interacting with the outside world. The control processors interact with the physical world while the supervisory processors are responsible for monitoring and maintaining the health of the&lt;br/&gt;distributed control system in a highly autonomous and fault-tolerant manner. The innovative characteristics of this project are as follows: 1) the development and application of novel discrete event supervisory methods to supervise hybrid embedded systems; 2) the development and application of novel approaches to the verification and supervision of hybrid, piece-wise linear systems; 3) the development of theory and algorithms to extend these results to a class of nonlinear hybrid systems; and, 4) the development of novel&lt;br/&gt;model identification methodologies and algorithms for hybrid systems. The project's approach will improve the ability of hybrid embedded control systems to deal with high complexity, undecidability and nonlinearity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0113131</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Panos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Antsaklis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>antsaklis.1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lemmon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lemmon@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goodwine</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgoodwin@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
      <CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
      <ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
