<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Longitudinal Analysis of Internet-Based Research Communication in Developing Areas</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>505379</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project examines the effects of new information technology on science in developing areas over a five year period. The project team will study the impact of the Internet on research communication within the developing world and with the international scientific community through an analysis of the conditions associated with interpersonal networking and information search behavior. The study population consists of 360 scientists in three developing areas with different levels of research capacity (Ghana, Kenya, and the Indian state of Kerala) in two organizational contexts (universities, government research institutes). Each of these areas was the subject of a comprehensive 1994 study of research communication just prior to the rapid expansion of the Internet. These scientists are located in twelve organizational sites: two universities and two research institutes in each of the three areas (Ghana, Kerala, Kenya) for a total of 120 scientists in each country. Several kinds of data will be collected for each scientist (conventional survey, network survey, Internet usage data, and email data). The project will (1) enhance basic connectivity by providing local area networks to research organizations with point connections, (2) assess the professional relationships, information search behavior, and changes in research practice over a five year period, (3) train faculty and graduate students in the social analysis of science and technology. The results will have a direct impact on scientific capacity through increased connectivity and decreased isolation of scientists in developing countries, a direct impact through training of scholars in the social analysis of science and technology, and an indirect impact through increased understanding of the types of linkages that are most likely to be utilized and sustained.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0113545</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wesley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shrum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shrum@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1686</Code>
      <Text>ITR SMALL GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5976</Code>
      <Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1066</Code>
      <Text>SOUTH AFRICA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1657</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC IMPLICATIONS OF IT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1686</Code>
      <Text>ITR SMALL GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5928</Code>
      <Text>AFRICA AND ASIA,OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
