<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Dual-Track Masters Degree Program for Information Security Specialists</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3320314</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This program establishes a scholarship program for computer science graduate students specializing in information assurance. Upon graduation, the students participate in two years of federal service. The program of study is a dual-track masters program, leading to either a master's degree in computer sciences or an interdisciplinary master's degree with specialization in information security. Students in both tracks receive special attention in seminar and advising sessions to help them understand the context and role of information security in today's society. This includes regular presentations by leaders in commerce, academia, and government. Students have the opportunity to participate in leading-edge research projects conducted by faculty. Through this program students receive a valuable educational background in information security and assurance, obtain hands-on research experience, gain perspective on industry and research trends, and provide valuable service to the government while experiencing real-world problems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0113730</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eugene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spafford</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spaf@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
