<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Advanced Membrane Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas D. Frey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal number: CTS-0113116&lt;br/&gt;Proposal type: Investigator Initiated for International &lt;br/&gt; Conference&lt;br/&gt;Principal investigator: Andrew L. Zydney&lt;br/&gt;Affiliations: University of Delaware/ Engineering Foundation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ADVANCED MEMBRANE TECHNOLOGY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports partially the participation by 20 American faculty and researchers in the Engineering Foundation Conference, "Advanced Membrane Technology", being held in Barga, Italy, from October 14 to 19, 2001. The conference brings together leading researchers in the areas of new membrane synthesis and membrane-process applications. It highlights new developments in the field as well as research opportunities for the future. It brings together both academic and industrial researchers from throughout the world. Topics range from membrane synthesis through separation processes for liquids and for gases to membrane reactors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funding is provided to support partially participation costs of some invited speakers and particularly of junior-faculty, post-doctoral, graduate student attendees from the U.S. The impact of this award is not only its direct contribution to further development of effective membrane separation processes but also its stimulus in bringing academic U.S. researchers into productive contact with industrial and international colleagues.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0113116</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zydney</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zydney@engr.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>United Engineering Trustees, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>10017</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
