<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR/SI:Semiconductor Optical Amplifier Based High Capacity Optical Information Device Technologies and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence S. Goldberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this research project is to develop high speed optoelectronic devices based on semiconductor optical amplifiers, for applications in optical information technologies, networks, instrumentation and signal processing. The key devices will be novel ultrahigh speed multiwavelength semiconductor laser transmitters, modulators , nonlinear optical switches and optical clock recovery oscillators. These semiconductor optical amplifier based devices will then be configured together to demonstrate unique high-speed capabilities in next generation information technology applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An important feature of this research project is that the devices are based on an identical semiconductor layered structure and common device processing and fabrication techniques. This is significant because this philosophy allows for cost effective state-of-the-art device development, with the potential of the technology becoming readily available for commercial applications, owing to the ease of fabrication, from a manufacturing perspective. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, since each of the devices are realized by using a single common processing procedure on an identical semiconductor layered structure, the potential for demonstrating fully monolithic ultrahigh-speed information is great. These two features are critical in that the development of high-speed optoelectronic technologies are essential elements for commercial applications of information technology in the global economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1.1 Methods to be employed&lt;br/&gt;The research program will use standard optoelectronic device fabrication techniques to develop a set of 4 optoelectronic devices, e.g., transmitters, modulators, switches, and clock recovery oscillators, that will be used in three critical commercial information technology application areas: 1) high capacity optical links for both access and wide area networks, 2) high speed optical sampling for analogue to digital applications, and 3) wideband optical/rf analog information systems using arbitrary optical waveform generation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will exploit his latest findings on the fundamental physics of ultrashort pulse propagation in semiconductor optical amplifiers and the associated nonlinear optical effects, to demonstrate unique modes of operation of these devices, for high speed photonic functionality. As an example, he will exploit these novel effects to achieve both temporal and spectral control of ultrafast optical signals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, he will demonstrate:&lt;br/&gt;o multiwavelength modelocked operation of semiconductor diode lasers&lt;br/&gt;o ultra-stable, ultrahigh bit rate, single wavelength 160 Gb/s semiconductor laser sources&lt;br/&gt;o cost-effective semiconductor optical amplifier modulators and modulator arrays&lt;br/&gt;o novel high-speed optical clock recovery oscillators at 40 GHz&lt;br/&gt;o all optical switching and processing of WDM byte wide parallel data packets, showing the potential for ultrahigh speed parallel optical signal processing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The developed device functionality will be incorporated to demonstrate&lt;br/&gt;o hybrid WDM-OTDM links for a) access and b) wide area networks&lt;br/&gt;o optical sampling in optical analog to digital converters&lt;br/&gt;o arbitrary optical waveform generation for wideband optical &amp; microwave photonic applications&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Finally, he will use commercially available off the shelf components to realize prototypes that will facilitate technology transfer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1.2 Significance to the Advancement of Knowledge: Educational &amp; Scientific Impact&lt;br/&gt;From an educational perspective, the students trained in this research program will be exposed to a research environment that is vertically integrated. For example, the students will learn the physics and fundamentals of high speed optoelectronic device design and fabrication, the deployment of novel devices to realize unique high speed optoelectronic sub-system functionality, and finally, integrate several unique optoelectronic sub-system functions into a full ultrahigh speed optoelectronic system that will address needs in the information technology areas of networking, signal processing and instrumentation. This will allow the students to provide timely impact for prospective employers upon graduation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0113338</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Delfyett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>delfyett@creol.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078821120</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1686</Code>
      <Text>ITR SMALL GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1660</Code>
      <Text>ITR COMPETITION FOR UNDER $500K</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
