<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of Magnetometer for Magnetic Films Research and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>151300</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Instrumentation for Materials Research program and the Major Research Instrumentation program supports the acquisition of a highly sensitive magnetometer at Colorado State University at Colorado Springs. The magnetometer will have a profound impact on research program and teaching and training students. The instrument will be used to fully correlate the static and dynamic properties of studied magnetic structures. The system will significantly enhance materials characterization capability on magnetic structures in three research projects currently underway at the institution: (1) studies of the exchange biased ferromagnetic/antiferromagnetic structures, (2) studies of the exchange coupled Fe/Pd/Fe and Fe/Ag/Fe structures, (3) studies of the high frequency devices based on ferromagnetic metals. Furthermore, this new magnetometer will give graduate students but also undergraduate and high school students opportunity to work on research projects, further expanding their training. The interaction between students and postdoctoral fellows or faculty creates an atmosphere, which strongly stimulates education and training.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award from the Instrumentation for Materials Research program and the Major Research Instrumentation program allows Colorado State University at Colorado Springs to acquire the acquisition of a highly sensitive magnetometer. The magnetometer will have a profound impact on research program and teaching and training students. The instrument will be used to fully correlate the static and dynamic properties of studied magnetic structures. The system will significantly enhance materials characterization capability on magnetic structures in three research projects currently underway at the institution. Furthermore, this new magnetometer will give graduate students, but also undergraduate and high school students, opportunity to work on research projects, further expanding their training. The interaction between students and postdoctoral fellows or faculty creates an atmosphere, which strongly stimulates education and training.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0114189</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zbigniew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Celinski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zcelinsk@mail.uccs.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Colorado Springs</Name>
      <CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>809183733</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7192553153</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1420, Austin Bluffs Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
