<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Methods for Analyzing Lethal Gases of Endophytes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>56000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark E. Welker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this Small Grant for Exploratory Research (SGER) supported by the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program, Professor Gary A. Strobel of the Department of Plant Sciences at Montana State University, will trap, isolate and characterize the volatile substances produced by Muscodor alba, a new fungal genus and species isolated from the Honoduran rainforest. It has been demonstrated that at least one of the gaseous compounds produced by M. alba is lethal to virtually all other endophytic fungi and bacteria that are present in the stem tissues of its plant host. The separation and identification of the volatile components possessing antimicrobial activity will be pursued.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program, Professor Gary A. Strobel, of the Department of Plant Sciencs at Montana State University, will isolate and identify volatile organic compounds produced by a new fungal species, M. alba. This mixture of gaseous substances has been shown to be lethal to a range of other fungi and bacteria. Isolation of the bioactive product(s) may result in the identification of compounds with potential pharmaceutical applications, including antimicrobial agents.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0114469</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strobel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>uplgs@montana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Montana State University</Name>
      <CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
