<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Qualitative and Quantitative Methods for Longitudinal Research: Differences, Similarities, and Integration; at Brandeis University; December 6-7, 2001</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>65895</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stuart Plattner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports a workshop will bring together leading scholars with expertise on longitudinal studies in cultural and physical anthropology, epidemiology, economics, sociology, public health, and psychology. During the workshop they will highlight the importance and power of using longitudinal research designs for studying questions of social and biological change; identify areas of consensus and disagreement, develop practical guidelines that cut across disciplines and qualitative or quantitative methods of doing longitudinal studies; and identify how best to join qualitative and quantitative methods in longitudinal studies. The workshop will also assess the feasibility of designing a training workshop for graduate students of cultural and physical anthropology and other disciplines to teach qualitative and quantitative research methods for longitudinal research and techniques to analyze such information. This workshop activity has the potential to make a significant advance in the scientific capacity of cultural anthropology</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0114225</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leonard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>w-leonard1@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ricardo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Godoy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rgodoy@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brandeis University</Name>
      <CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7817362121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>415 SOUTH ST MAILSTOP 116</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
