<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Program for Gender Equity in Science, Mathematics, Engineering and Technology (PGE): DEM:Women on the Prairie: Bringing Girls into Science through Environmental Stewardship</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>875343</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jolene K. Jesse</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This demonstration project, a collaborative network of faculty, public school teachers&lt;br/&gt;and counselors, and professionals in both private sector/non-profit organizations will&lt;br/&gt;deliver and evaluate activities designed to bolster and reinforce the interest of &lt;br/&gt;middle-school girls in SMET disciplines and careers. These activities are based on &lt;br/&gt;research showing that access to role models, career information, and hands-on&lt;br/&gt;activities have beneficial effects. A hands-on summer workshop, industrial site &lt;br/&gt;tours, classroom activities, visits with women scientists and engineers, activities&lt;br/&gt;developed in conjunction with commercial and service organizations, and a web site&lt;br/&gt;characterize the intervention for the 6th and 7th grade girls who participate. &lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, in response to research showing that professional development for&lt;br/&gt;teachers, interactions between teachers and scientists, and implementation of &lt;br/&gt;methods to address diversity and gender equity issues are of paramount importance&lt;br/&gt;in creating more gender equitable classrooms, middle-school and high-school teacher&lt;br/&gt;in science and mathematics will be invited to partner with University faculty in &lt;br/&gt;developing the summer workshop activities. In addition, they will be invited to &lt;br/&gt;participate in a graduate-level course on gender equity in science and mathematics &lt;br/&gt;education and conduct action research projects that can be shared within the &lt;br/&gt;collaborative network. Finally, packets with information on both various SMET &lt;br/&gt;careers and on women who are currently employed in these fields, will be &lt;br/&gt;distributed to school counselors, the parents of girls in Girl Scout troops, and &lt;br/&gt;the parents of those girls who participate in the project activities. Summative &lt;br/&gt;evaluation will focus on the comparison of SMET course-taking patterns and course&lt;br/&gt;grades of participants in the project activities compared to a matched sample of &lt;br/&gt;girls who did not participate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/08/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0114723</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Douglas-Mankin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kdouglasmankin@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/08/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Beth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Montelone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bethmont@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spears</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdspears@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dolores</FirstName>
      <LastName>Takemoto</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dtak@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/21/2003</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ruth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdyer@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Freeman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Freeman@vet.k-state.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suzanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Franks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sefranks@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/08/2005</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kansas State University</Name>
      <CityName>MANHATTAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>665061103</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7855326804</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2 FAIRCHILD HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
