<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Program for Gender Equity in Science, Mathematics, Engineering and Technology (PGE): Dis: Science, Gender and After School: Creating a Research/Action Agenda</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100249</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Margrete S. Klein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Program for Gender Equity in Science, Mathematics, Engineering and Technology (PGE): Dis: Science, Gender and After School: Creating a Research/Action Agenda&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Educational Equity Concepts, Inc. (EEC), in collaboration with the Directorate for &lt;br/&gt;Human Resources and Education at the American Association for the Advancement&lt;br/&gt;of Science (AAAS), and the Academy for Educational Development (AED) requests &lt;br/&gt;$100,000 over 18 months from the National Science Foundation Program for Gender&lt;br/&gt;Equity for a dissemination project to create a research/action agenda around SMET&lt;br/&gt;programming for girls in the informal, out-of-school learning arena. The overall &lt;br/&gt;goal of the project is to use after-school programming as a vehicle to both engage &lt;br/&gt;and sustain girls= interest in pursuing education and careers in SMET. Specific &lt;br/&gt;objectives are to: (1) bring together a multi-disciplinary group of researchers and &lt;br/&gt;practitioners in a working conference setting; (2) develop a research/action agenda; &lt;br/&gt;(3) develop an action plan to carry out the agenda; and (4) disseminate the&lt;br/&gt;conference proceedings to researchers, practitioners, gender equity activists, &lt;br/&gt;policy-makers, and funders who are involved in informal and SMET education. &lt;br/&gt;Research focusing on girls at this juncture is critical because although there are &lt;br/&gt;a growing number of SMET programs, we do not know which programs are effective&lt;br/&gt;and which are not, especially with regard to engaging and supporting girls interest in &lt;br/&gt;SMET. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The out-of-school learning arena encompasses community and school-based after-&lt;br/&gt;school programs; summer camp and Saturday/weekend programs; museum programs; &lt;br/&gt;programs at community technology centers; college/university science programs; &lt;br/&gt;on-line science clubs and competitions; and programs offered by girl-specific&lt;br/&gt;organizations. After-school as an educational field (rather than child-minding&lt;br/&gt;or purely recreational) is both new and growing. Moreover, we are moving rapidly &lt;br/&gt;toward a technology-based economy where women are an increasing part of the&lt;br/&gt;workforce. This conference will take advantage of a ground floor opportunity &lt;br/&gt;to create a research/action agenda and inform the development of SMET programs&lt;br/&gt;that are free of gender and other forms of bias--race, ethnicity and disability &lt;br/&gt;that have traditionally contributed to educational inequality. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The agenda created at the conference will be distributed to a broad audience of &lt;br/&gt;researchers, practitioners, gender equity activists, policy-makers, and funders. &lt;br/&gt;In doing so, the conference will extend awareness and information about the &lt;br/&gt;participation of girls and women in SMET education; catalyze new thinking on&lt;br/&gt;the subject; and serve as a springboard for research and action. Dissemination&lt;br/&gt;will take place via journals, publications, web sites, listservs, and professional &lt;br/&gt;association conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0114741</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sprung</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bsprung@fhi360.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Merle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Froschl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mfroschl@fhi360.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Educational Equity Concepts Inc</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100116903</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2123674598</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 Fifth Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
