<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Advanced Methods of Mapping Surficial Processes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>61147</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Clifford J. Astill</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This workshop will bring together leading academic practitioners of Airborne Laser Swath Mapping (ALSM, LIDAR), Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR), Airborne Digital Imaging (ADI), Infrared (IR), and Hyperspectral Imaging (HI) with a cross section of both the engineering and scientific communities. The intent is to provide a forum to discuss how best to incorporate data collected by these powerful techniques into the monitoring and study of geo-surficial processes. The overall objective of the workshop is to increase the awareness of the potential uses of these advanced technologies and to obtain from the engineering and scientific communities research needs and activities that could benefit from their usage, both short and long term.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will take place over two and one half days. The first two days will contain a half-day each on ALSM technology, and a half-day on a mix of the complementary technologies, including SAR, ADI, IR and HI. Each of these sessions will open with invited papers to provide the participants a state-of-the-art update on each specific technology. The second day will begin with a session on current applications, new applications expected to emerge in the immediate future and the research needs of the engineering and scientific communities. After the invited summary papers, there will be panel led discussions to maximize the exchange of information between the particular experts and researchers that have ongoing projects utilizing these innovative technologies, as well as those considering the use of them in current or future research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the invited oral presentations, participants will be invited to submit poster presentations that will be on display for the attendees to view and discuss during breaks in the formal sessions. The UF/FIU ALSM aircraft will be available for viewing by the participants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The morning of the third day will be devoted to an open session with the Steering Committee serving as a panel to outline the final draft report and discuss the preliminary findings and recommendations to be included in that report. All participants will have the opportunity to provide input, and members of the Committee will be asked to draft specific sections of the final report to meet a schedule agreed to by the Committee.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0114135</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bloomquist</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dave@ce.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>carter4451@bellsouth.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ramesh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shrestha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rlshrestha@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0304000</Code>
      <Name>Disaster &amp; Natural Hazard</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
