<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Arabidopsis 2010: Development of Laser-Capture Microdissection for Plant Tissues</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan J. Lolle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Timothy Nelson&lt;br/&gt;Yale University&lt;br/&gt;IBN-0114648&lt;br/&gt;Development of laser-capture microdissection for plant tissues&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;The technique of laser-capture microdissection (LCM) will be developed and optimized for plant tissues. This is a method originally developed for animal tissues, whereby individual cells are harvested by tacking them to a plastic film with a low-power infrared laser that can be aimed at single cells while viewing the tissue slice under a microscope. Using this method, it should be possible to recover specific cell types or developmental stages from complex tissues consisting of many cell types. Cells recovered in this manner can be analyzed with regard to gene expression profiles, protein profiles, and other properties. Based on preliminary data, it will be necessary to test a variety of tissue fixation and sectioning methods to adapt the method to plants. This project will optimize the LCM technique, using a variety of plant tissue sources and purity markers for specific cells. Detailed protocols will be provided to the biological community at the website http://plantgenomics.biology.yale.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0114648</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>timothy.nelson@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
