<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-Egypt Workshop: Advanced Material Characterization and Metal Manufacturing Techniques, Cairo, Egypt, December 2001</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Osman Shinaishin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0115417 &lt;br/&gt;Elshall&lt;br/&gt;Description: This project supports a US-Egypt Workshop on Advanced Materials Characterization and Metal Manufacturing Techniques to be held in Cairo, Egypt, December 2001. The organizers are Dr. Hassan El-Shall, Department of Materials Science and Engineering, the University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida and Dr. Adel A. Nofal, President, Central Metallurgical Research and Development Institute (CMRDI), Helwan, Cairo, Egypt. The purpose of the workshop is to exchange information between the US and Egyptian sides on advances in materials characterization and manufacturing, and to discuss R&amp;D needs that may be met through cooperative research projects. Topics to be included are: fine particles preparation and surface coating, powder metallurgy, vacuum melting and coating, high pressure die casting, shell molding of chemically bonded sand, heat treatment of super-alloys, laser use in surface treatment, cutting and welding, and material characterization. Possible avenues for collaboration will be discussed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Scope: This project enables US and Egyptian scientists to participate in a workshop to discuss an area of importance to both countries and to identify potential collaborative research where the two sides can complement each others' capabilities. Dr. El-Shall is Associate Director for Research in the NSF-funded Engineering Research Center for Particle Science and Technology at the University of Florida. He has participated in past seminars and in cooperative research projects with scientists at the CMRDI. Dr. Nofal is the head of the main research center in materials science and engineering in Egypt. His institute is well equipped to organize the workshop and to secure participation from various academic and industrial research organizations in that country. Among the US participants are several junior scientists. The project meets INT objectives in supporting mutually beneficial joint workshops. This project is being supported under the US-Egypt Joint Fund Program, which provides grants to scientists and engineers in both countries to carry out joint scientific activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0115417</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hassan</FirstName>
      <LastName>El-Shall</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>helsh@mse.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
