<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 750 Hz Narrow-Band Argon Fluoride Laser</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>115339</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Kuczkowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) Program, the Department of Chemistry at Whitworth College will acquire a 750 Hz narrow-band argon fluoride laser. This equipment will enhance research in the following areas: 1) development of a laser-induced fluorescence (LIF) system to analyze wear on carbon-based ion thruster grids in situ; and 2) measurement of the dissociative resonance Raman spectra of several interesting molecules that photodissociate at 193 nm. Researchers from several area institutions (Gonzaga University, Eastern Washington University, New Light Industries) would also use this laser system to carry out studies on nonlinear materials, photoacoustic spectroscopy of bacteria and to develop high-spatial frequency gratings for templates in the growth of controlled orientation colloidal photonic crystals. Undergraduate students at Whitworth, Gonzaga and Eastern Washington will be heavily involved in the research efforts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A high repetition rate laser provides pulses of coherent visible or infrared light and enables researchers to obtain important information about fast occurring chemical reactions. Its use may enable breakthroughs in our understanding of the properties of reactive and nonreactive molecules. In particular, LIF is capable of detecting very small quantities of carbon atoms in the plumes of ion thrusters. This will allow for a rapid diagnostic test for wear in these advanced thruster systems. A switch to carbon-based thrusters will significantly increase the efficiency and lifetime of the ion thrusters, resulting in tremendous cost-savings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0115912</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stevens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kstevens@whitworth.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stevens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rstevens@whitworth.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Whitworth University</Name>
      <CityName>Spokane</CityName>
      <ZipCode>992182515</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5097773701</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 W. Hawthorne Rd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
