<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Taiwan Cooperative Research: Chemistry in Confined Spaces by EPR Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>147027</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard H. Nader</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0115082&lt;br/&gt;Lin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a three-year cooperative project between Dr Tien-Sung Lin, Washington University and Professor Chung-Yuan Mou, National Taiwan University, to study the chemistry of C60, tetracene pentacene, and gold nanocrystals within the confines of mesoporous solids such as MCM-41 and -48 using electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) Spectroscopy. This is an important research in nanotechnology. MCM-41 and -48 are interesting mesoporous materials with controllable tubular pore size. Such zeolite-type materials have been widely used in catalyst support and molecular sieve applications. Advances in this area may yield substantial societal benefits. This proposal also provides an opportunity for three U.S. postdoctoral scientists and three graduate students get valuable exposure to this field of mesoporous materials. This proposal addresses an important scientific question and meets the NSF objective of human resource development. The National Science Council of Taiwan and the NSF jointly support this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/30/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0115082</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tien-Sung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Lin@wuchem.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
