<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-India Cooperative Research: Investigation of Bubble Size Distribution Profiles in Gas-Liquid Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13208</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Lueck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0115297&lt;br/&gt;Ramkrishna &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Description: This award supports a US-India cooperative research project entitled Investigation of Bubble Size Distribution Profiles in Gas-Liquid Systems. The collaborators are Professor D. Ramkrishna, Department of Chemical Engineering, Purdue University and Professor J.B. Joshi, Department of Chemical Technology, Bombay University. They will make a systematic investigation of the effect that bubble population balance may have on prediction of computational fluid dynamics (CFD) calculations in gas-liquid flow. Such calculations are usually done with an assumed single bubble size and coalescence, and break-up phenomena and resulting bubble size distributions are ignored. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Scope: This collaboration will combine the US investigator's expertise on bubble dynamics, break-up and coalescence, and population balance with Professor Joshi's experimental facilities needed to measure model predictions. Together they can advance the current state of the art of gas-liquid flows significantly. The US and Indian graduate students involved in this project will have the advantage of exposure to the best available thinking in the field of gas-liquid bubbly flows. This research could have a profound impact on design and scale-up of gas-liquid contactors, which are common to numerous chemical processes and are of great technological and economic importance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0115297</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Doraiswami</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ramkrishna</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ramkrish@ecn.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
