<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Tracer Methodology and Fluorescent Microscopy in Faculty/Student Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>78633</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Helen G. Hansma</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A grant has been awarded to Dr. James E. Haley of the College of Mt. St. Vincent. Recent research in the biological sciences has taken on more sophisticated methods and instrumentation. One active current area involves the use of cell/tissue culture analyses of cell function especially for neurally derived cells from the rat brain including neurons and astrocytes as well as other glial cells. We are fortunate to offer such rare training experience at a small liberal arts college including a heavy emphasis on student involvement in faculty research activities. Most of our majors and graduates, about a total of 40 per year, are women and there is a growing enrollment of minority students who will have direct use and instruction with this sophisticated equipment. This type of training is critical for the preparation of future health science professionals. However, we are at present deficient in many state-of-the-art equipment necessary to expand the efficiency, skills, capacity, level of sensitivity, and potential for faculty/student research in the areas of neuroscience, plant cell biology, and pharmacology. The equipment requested include the following: 1) Liquid scintillation counter to be used in tracer methodology to examine proteins, nucleic acids, lipids, and other bio-active molecules made by cells. 2) A water purification system to produce ultrapure water necessary for cell culture. 3) A fluorescent microscope with photographic capabilities to examine cultured cells for specific proteins/molecules using indirect immunofluorescence staining and an efficient way to collect data. 4) An automated X-ray film processor to more proficiently develop film previously exposed to radiolabeled biomolecules resolved by gel electrophoresis to examine alterations after specific exposure to a variety of substances; for example drugs. 5) The research students as well as all graduating seniors are required to orally present their findings and conclusions or monographs at regional meetings and/or to the entire faculty. The purchase of a Polaroid Propalette would greatly facilitate the professional preparation of colored slides, an essential training for the students. In summary, this equipment would greatly facilitate the training and research experience of both our students and faculty.&lt;br/&gt;It is hoped that this undergraduate experience will more adequately train, prepare, and attract more students into the health professions as well as biology science teachers. The research area in neuroscience, specifically, may lead to a better understanding of the interaction between nerve cells and astrocytes, the later, which represents by far the most prominent number of cells in the central nervous system. It is thought that the formation of a glial (astrocyte) scar after damage to the brain prevents reformation of neuronal connections. This may lead to potential mechanisms for the treatment of brain injury.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0115758</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james.haley@mountsaintvincent.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>College of Mount Saint Vincent</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104711093</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7184053342</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6301 Riverdale Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
