<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Role of the Cia5 Gene in the Carbon Concentrating Mechanism in Chlamydomonas Reinhardtii</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>387000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gavin Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The carbon concentrating mechanism (CCM) plays a major role in the earth's&lt;br/&gt;photosynthetic productivity and its capacity to cycle carbon. The CCM is&lt;br/&gt;essential for photosynthesis at atmospheric levels of CO2 in Chlamydomonas&lt;br/&gt;and most other eukaryotic and prokaryotic algae. Knowledge gained&lt;br/&gt;regarding the CCM in C. reinhardtii through this three-year project,&lt;br/&gt;coupled with information from other laboratories, should allow a more&lt;br/&gt;complete understanding of how algal cells are able to survive and flourish&lt;br/&gt;in their CO2-limited, aqueous environment. The primary goal of this&lt;br/&gt;research project is to elucidate components and mechanisms of regulation of&lt;br/&gt;the CCM in Chlamydomonas reinhardtii. The focus of the project is the&lt;br/&gt;complete characterization of the Cia5 gene and its role as a master&lt;br/&gt;regulator of the cell's response to changes in environmental CO2 and HCO3&lt;br/&gt;concentrations. Based on the weight of present evidence, it appears the&lt;br/&gt;Cia5 gene encodes a transcription factor that is part of one or more signal&lt;br/&gt;transduction cascades that allow, or reverse, formation of a functional&lt;br/&gt;CCM. Experiments to fully characterize the Cia5 gene are outlined along&lt;br/&gt;with studies of the CIA5 protein, its subcellular location,&lt;br/&gt;post-translational modification(s), DNA binding specificities and other&lt;br/&gt;features required for its function in controlling assembly of the CCM. A&lt;br/&gt;model is proposed in which the CIA5 protein could act either as an inducer&lt;br/&gt;or repressor of transcription of genes whose expression is dramatically&lt;br/&gt;increased during a shift of cells from high to low CO2 levels. Experiments&lt;br/&gt;are outlined that will resolve the uncertainty of whether CIA5 acts as an&lt;br/&gt;inducer or repressor of gene expression. In the long term, an increased&lt;br/&gt;understanding of the CCM has the potential for practical application in&lt;br/&gt;agriculture. For example, certain crop plants have been demonstrated to&lt;br/&gt;produce higher yields under elevated levels of CO2. If appropriate&lt;br/&gt;portions of the CCM can be transferred to those crops, their resultant&lt;br/&gt;ability to increase internal CO2 concentrations could lead to substantially&lt;br/&gt;improved crop yields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0115626</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weeks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dweeks1@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 Vine St, 151 Whittier</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
