<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a Field Emission Scanning Electron Microscope</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330750</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark A. Farmer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A grant has been awarded to Dr. Andreas Holzenburg (PI) and Dr. Richard Crooks (Co-PI) at Texas A&amp;M University to acquire a state-of-the-art field-emission scanning electron microscope (FE-SEM) equipped for electron backscattered diffraction (EBSD), cathodoluminescence (CL), energy dispersive analysis (EDS), and tensile/heating stage testing, in addition to the more standard secondary electron (SE) and backscattered electron (BSE) imaging. The microscope as specified in the proposal will allow high resolution imaging using BSE, SE and CL, elemental microanalysis, orientation contrast imaging and automatic orientation analysis. The tensile heating/cooling stage will allow imaging during experiments in tension or compression, with heating functions to 1200 C. Another strength of the microscope is the geometric arrangement of the detectors and stage enabling CL, EDS, EBSD and tensile/heating stage testing in various simultaneous applications. The instrument will also support projects requiring imaging of uncotaed biological specimens. It therefore lends itself to uniquely support a wide range of diverse and interdisciplinary research activities in engineering as well as the biological, chemical, geological and physical sciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The imaging and analytical capabilities of the instrument as described above will enhance specific research projects in a number of areas including the following: development of novel chemical sensors and catalyst materials; semiconductors, high-temperature superconductors; micro-electromechanical systems; morphology and composition distribution in polymer systems; soil morphology; contaminants in near-surface geologic systems and hazardous waste sites; roles of fluids in rock deformation; evaluation of earthquake risks; creep compaction of reservoir sands; origin of magma; rheology of the Earth's crust and mantle; mechanical property-microstructure relationship of advanced materials; and phospholipid bilayers and integral membrane proteins; surface topography of biological specimens.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The exact configuration was chosen to effectively underpin interdisciplinary research and training needs existing on campus at Texas A&amp;M University (College Station) as well as within the region (Lamar University, Sam Houston Sate University and Prairie View A&amp;M University, USDA). The instrument will also enhance educational activities directed towards undergraduate and graduate studies. Research activities at Texas A&amp;M and other regional universities (including primarily undergraduate institutions) are intimately linked with teaching, and the FE-SEM will be used within coursework as well as to advance student research. Furthermore, ongoing educational outreach, through web-based activities, provides access to these technologies to K-12 students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0116835</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crooks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crooks@cm.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Holzenburg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>holzen@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
