<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improvement of Teaching and Research via NMR Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>57517</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wade N. Sisk</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) Program, the Department of Chemistry at DeSales University will acquire a 60 MHz NMR Spectrometer. This equipment will enable researchers to carry out studies on a) organic synthesis of ionic solvents and study of reactions using these solvents; b) aerosol preparation of metal oxides and organic polymer systems; and c) controlled-release kinetics of drug molecules from a microcrystalline cellulose matrix. This instrument will also be used in advanced undergraduate courses. Students will be heavily involved in the research projects at this primarily undergraduate institution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is the most powerful tool available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0116257</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mayville</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fcm0@desales.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>DeSales University</Name>
      <CityName>Center Valley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>180349568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6102821100</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2755 Station Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
