<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TQFTs in Spectra</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>170247</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0116288&lt;br/&gt;Jack Morava&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central idea of this proposal is a mathematical &lt;br/&gt;definition for the physicists' notion of topological &lt;br/&gt;gravity (analogous to Segal's mathematical definition of &lt;br/&gt;conformal field theory) as a representation of a monoidal &lt;br/&gt;category with manifolds as objects, using the geometric &lt;br/&gt;realization of a category of cobordisms between those &lt;br/&gt;objects as its morphism spaces; these spaces are unions of &lt;br/&gt;classifying spaces for the diffeomorphism groups of the &lt;br/&gt;cobordisms. In two dimensions, the resulting category &lt;br/&gt;is quite similar to that considered by Segal, but it &lt;br/&gt;generalizes very naturally, e.g. to four dimensions, &lt;br/&gt;where it has close connections with classical general &lt;br/&gt;relativity; but there is also a version for topological &lt;br/&gt;(i.e, non-smooth) four-manifolds, lacking any clear &lt;br/&gt;classical analog. Donaldson and Seiberg-Witten theory fit &lt;br/&gt;naturally into this framework, which predicts that such &lt;br/&gt;invariants should have higer-order `gravitational &lt;br/&gt;descendants', e.g. higher-codimension versions of the &lt;br/&gt;wall-crossing obstructions. In dimension two, this formalism &lt;br/&gt;fits in well on the one hand with work of Madsen and &lt;br/&gt;Tillmann on Mumford's conjecture, and on the other with the &lt;br/&gt;theory of a `large' quantum cohomology studied by Kontsevich, &lt;br/&gt;Manin, Witten, and others. One concrete goal of the project&lt;br/&gt;is to construct a cohomological theory related to the Atiyah-Patodi-Singer eta-invariant of a three-manifold, &lt;br/&gt;as Casson's invariant is related to Floer homology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Classical mechanics studies the trajectories of point &lt;br/&gt;particles in a smooth geometric background, and much &lt;br/&gt;recent work in string theory can be formulated in similar &lt;br/&gt;terms, with the background replaced by the &lt;br/&gt;(infinite-dimensional) space of smooth loops in some &lt;br/&gt;ambient manifold. However, the mathematics of these &lt;br/&gt;free loopspaces is quite challenging, and their topology &lt;br/&gt;(not to mention their geometry) is not yet well-understood.&lt;br/&gt;An added complication is that the models studied in &lt;br/&gt;quantum field theory involve topology change in a &lt;br/&gt;conceptually intrinsic way, and thus seem often to call, &lt;br/&gt;not for the free loopspace itself, but for a suitable&lt;br/&gt;completion with nice properties -- whose nature is still &lt;br/&gt;being worked out. This proposal suggests that the desired &lt;br/&gt;completion is an analog, for free loopspaces, of the dual &lt;br/&gt;of a finite-dimensional smooth manifold (as studied in the &lt;br/&gt;1960's by Whitehead, Spanier, Atiyah, and others). This &lt;br/&gt;point of view seems compatible with work of Chas and &lt;br/&gt;Sullivan on string topology, with work of Cohen, Jones, &lt;br/&gt;and Segal on Floer homotopy type, and with work of Ando &lt;br/&gt;and myself on the Witten genus.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0116288</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morava</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jack@math.jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
