<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of an Electron Beam Nanolithography System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence S. Goldberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This MRI Proposal involves the procurement of an Ultra-High Resolution Electron Beam (E-Beam) Nanolithography and Metrology System for research and education programs at Lehigh University. The E-Beam system offers a unique capability to university, industry and government researchers to fabricate novel device structures and to characterize the nanometric features of materials. This E-B earn system will provide an opportunity for researchers to realize nanolithographic features for the fabrication of mesoscopic and quantum devices, such as quantum-dot nonvolatile semiconductor memories, single electron transistors, biosensors, and nanoscopic-instrumented, microelectromechanical systems (MEMS). In addition, the E-Beam system will provide exceptional educational instruction into nanotechnology. The fabrication of devices requires the integration of processes where literally several hundred operations are needed to realize a final device structure. In order to accomplish this seamless integration of processes an E-Beam Nanolithograpy and Metrology System must be located literally within the same physical infrastructure. For example, the close coupling of nanoelectronics devices and MEMS with the preparation of biological samples is essential to accomplish tasks such as cell characterization and electronic sequencing of DNA. Finally, the E-Beam system will serve the surrounding community within the Lehigh Valley particularly the local colleges and K-12 students to excite students into the emerging world of nanotechnology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0116423</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marvin</FirstName>
      <LastName>White</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>white@ece.osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Miltiadis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hatalis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkh1@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lehigh University</Name>
      <CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
