<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Acquisition of Laboratory Equipment to Facilitate Micro and Nano Engineering at Michigan State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>272000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence S. Goldberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Recently within the College of Engineering at Michigan State University (MSU) faculty&lt;br/&gt;with research interests at the micro and nano dimensions have coalesced about a new College of&lt;br/&gt;Engineering Center research activity entitled the Micro and Nano Engineering Center (MNEC).&lt;br/&gt;MNEC builds upon the past strong research capabilities of faculty within the College of&lt;br/&gt;Engineering, such as carbon-based materials and plasma technologies and combines them with&lt;br/&gt;newly hired research faculty and their associated research initiatives in nano-device technologies,&lt;br/&gt;miniaturized millimeter wave and optical systems and micro/nano machine instrumentation.&lt;br/&gt;MNEC's mission is concerned with the application of frontier knowledge and techniques that&lt;br/&gt;synthesize, characterize, manipulate and modify materials in order to create integrated structures,&lt;br/&gt;electronic, and photonic devices and machines in the micro and nano environment. The emphasis&lt;br/&gt;of the Center's research activities is the development of novel devices, machines and systems in&lt;br/&gt;the micro and nano world. Faculty form synergistic interdisciplinary research teams which&lt;br/&gt;include cross-campus and multi-university collaborations. Notable among these are the NSF&lt;br/&gt;MRSEC Center for Sensor Materials and the NSF Wireless Integrated Microsystems (WIMS)&lt;br/&gt;ERC collaborations. Additionally, MNEC's research activities provide the university setting in&lt;br/&gt;which to train and educate both graduate and undergraduate students. Presently, the Center&lt;br/&gt;includes ten faculty and 40 graduate students of which over half are Ph.D. students. Of the ten&lt;br/&gt;faculty, five have been newly hired during the past five years and it is anticipated to expand to a&lt;br/&gt;total of 15-20 faculty over the next five years via additional faculty interest reorientation and new&lt;br/&gt;hires. MNEC's research activities have been and continue to be transferred to industry and&lt;br/&gt;commercialized into applications relevant to manufacturing, health care, the environment and&lt;br/&gt;national security.&lt;br/&gt;The rapid advance of micro/nano-fabrication technology requires continual reassessment of&lt;br/&gt;our facilities and capabilities. Micro-scale technology has been an important economic driver for&lt;br/&gt;the United States as well as the entire world. MSU's MNEC faculty have pioneered several&lt;br/&gt;important micro-fabrication technologies, including microwave plasma processing machines for&lt;br/&gt;etching and diamond deposition, IC-compatible diamond processing and fabrication techniques,&lt;br/&gt;and diamond micro electro-mechanical systems (MEMS). Now, as we enter a new millennium,&lt;br/&gt;nano-scale technology is becoming increasingly important to the center, the college, the&lt;br/&gt;university, and the nation. The instrumentation requested in this proposal will improve the&lt;br/&gt;Center's faculty ability to perform research activities and student training in nano-scale and&lt;br/&gt;micro-scale technologies.&lt;br/&gt;Specific, new long-term goals of the Center have been established over the past year through&lt;br/&gt;many strategic planning discussions amongst the Center faculty. Current and developing micro&lt;br/&gt;and nano-engineering research activities in MNEC can be described and organized into five areas&lt;br/&gt;including: (1) carbon-based technology, (2) microwave plasma technology, (3) nanodevice&lt;br/&gt;technology, (4) manipulation and probe technology for micro and nano applications, and (5)&lt;br/&gt;miniaturized millimeter wave and optical systems. The proposed equipment acquisition described&lt;br/&gt;below is part of the MNEC's multiyear strategy to improve its laboratory facilities, which will&lt;br/&gt;facilitate research activities and student training in these five areas. In developing our request, we&lt;br/&gt;have considered the availability of similar instrumentation on campus and the capabilities of such&lt;br/&gt;instrumentation. The equipment requested in this proposal will be housed in common facilities in&lt;br/&gt;the Micro and Nano Engineering Center (MNEC) cleanroom located on the MSU campus. The&lt;br/&gt;instrumentation requested in this proposal includes the following systems:&lt;br/&gt; Plasma Enhanced Chemical Vapor Deposition (PECVD) System&lt;br/&gt; Multisource Physical Vapor Deposition (PVD) System&lt;br/&gt; Scanning Probe Microscope&lt;br/&gt; Wet Chemical Processing Station&lt;br/&gt; Electrochemical Plating Station</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0116252</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jes</FirstName>
      <LastName>Asmussen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>asmussen@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fathi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Salem</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>salem@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aslam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aslam@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grotjohn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grotjohn@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ayres</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ayresv@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
