<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of Equipment for the Establishment of a Microbial Ecology Laboratory at Coastal Carolina University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>172296</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040101</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexander Shor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0116536&lt;br/&gt;Koepfler&lt;br/&gt;This award to Coastal Carolina University in South Carolina will provide support for acquisition of instrumentation for research on microbial ecology. It supports strong, ongoing efforts in integration of research and education at CCU, which has a large marine studies program and active programs involving undergraduates in research in environmental sciences. Specific instrumentation supported here includes a compound microscope with image analyzer, a data logging multiprobe, a multi-channel respirometer and incubators. The university will provide additional instrumentation under this project, including electrophoresis apparatus, gel documentation system, additional incubators, fluorometers, peristaltic pumps and computers for data logging and analysis. CCU is a non-Ph.D.-granting university; the university will contribute about 22% of the total cost of this project from non-federal funds. &lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0116536</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koepfler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eric@coastal.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Coastal Carolina University</Name>
      <CityName>Conway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>295286054</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8433492282</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O Box 261954</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
