<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanoscience and Engineering Center: Columbia Center for Electronic Transport in Molecular Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Nanoscale Science and Engineering Center award to Columbia University is co-funded by Divisions of Chemistry (MPS), Materials Research (MPS) and International Programs (IN). Columbia University Nanocenter will conduct research to establish the foundation for new paradigms for information processing through the development of fundamental understanding of charge transport phenomena unique to nanoscale molecular structures with special emphasis on crystalline organic conductors and carbon nanotube materials. Single-molecule structures will be fabricated by the Center through a fusion of advanced semiconductor technology and tailored molecular synthesis. The research will elucidate the control of charge transport through single molecules in terms of the chemical structure and also will examine underlying mechanistic questions. The research program will place strong emphasis on the modulation of charge transport through molecules, with the goal of developing a molecular transistor. Scientists from Canada, Germany, Japan and Switzerland will collaborate with the Center in solid state surface analysis, single crystal growth, and the determination of electron transport properties of crystalline nanomaterials. Nanoscale structures and devices will be fabricated and characterized in collaboration with Lucent and IBM research facilities. In addition to electronics, these studies of molecular transport in nanomaterials will have potential impact to other disciplines such as photonics, biology, neuroscience, and medicine. Through partnership with Barnard College, City College of New York, and Rowan University, the Center will incorporate an innovative educational program directed toward a wide variety of students at graduate, undergraduate, and high school levels. Educational and outreach programs will be designed to attract students to nanotechnology, with particular attention to groups, which have been historically underrepresented in science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Columbia University Nanocenter will conduct research to develop knowledge of charge transport phenomena unique to nanoscale molecular structures such as crystalline organic conductors and carbon nanotube materials. Single-molecule structures will be fabricated by the Center to elucidate the control of charge transport through single molecules in terms of the chemical structure and to examine underlying mechanisms, with the goal of developing a molecular transistor. Industrial collaborations with Lucent and IBM will be carried out to fabricate and characterize nanoscale structures and devices. In addition to electronics, these studies of molecular transport in nanomaterials will have potential impact to other disciplines, such as photonics, biology, neuroscience, and medicine. In collaboration with Barnard College, City College of New York, and Rowan University, the Center will incorporate an innovative educational program directed toward a wide variety of students at graduate, undergraduate and high school levels. Educational and outreach programs will be tailored to attract students to nanotechnology, with particular attention to groups, which have been historically underrepresented in science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0117752</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yardley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jy307@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
