<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Adaptive Protocol Suite for The Next Generation Wireless Internet</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1355070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gurudatta M. Parulkar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The technology and business of wireless communications systems have madespectacular progress since the&lt;br/&gt;first systems were introduced fifteen years ago. Currently proposed third generation (3G) systems offer roaming, higher capacity, and increased exibility for low bandwidth services, such as voice calls and messaging. While future wireless systems (fourth generation (4G) and higher) are envisioned to provide higher capacity, they are also expected to support heterogeneity in the following aspects: (i) physical environments (ranging from high-bandwidth low error-rate pico-cells to low-bandwidth high error-rate macro-cells); (ii) network architectures (cellular, peer-to-peer, or other hybrid network models); and (iii) applications (ranging from low-data rate non-real-time applications to high-data rate real-time applications). In this project, we will investigate several key elements that are necessary to realize a protocol stack for a mobile station in 4G wireless systems. The ultimate objective is to develop an adaptive protocol suite that would adapt itself to the different aspects of heterogeneity exhibited by the next generation wireless systems. In particular we willinvestigate the following problems:&lt;br/&gt;1. Application Layer&lt;br/&gt;Error-rate scalability: We propose an adaptive multiple description algorithm for error-rate scalability.&lt;br/&gt;Data-rate scalability: We introduce an optimal dynamic rate shaping technique to be utilized in the case of&lt;br/&gt;congestion or bandwidth variations.&lt;br/&gt;Jointly optimal real-time video streaming system: We propose a real-time video streaming system integrates the proposed unequal error protection mechanism, the multiple description coding technique, and the error-concealment method.&lt;br/&gt;2. Security&lt;br/&gt;An adaptive and scalable security protocols: We propose to employ finite-field wavelets to develop novel and&lt;br/&gt;innovative public key security techniques that address ubiquity, scalability, mobility, and usability.&lt;br/&gt;We propose efficient security protocols for mobile devices with limited processing power.&lt;br/&gt;3. Transport Layer&lt;br/&gt;Heterogeneous Packet Flows: We proposetoinvestigate transport protocols that can support a much richer&lt;br/&gt;set of semantics, adapting to the reliability semantics chosen by applications on a per-frame basis.&lt;br/&gt;Heterogeneous Network Characteristics: We propose to build a single transport protocol that will adapt itself&lt;br/&gt;to the characteristics of a variety of wireless network environments.&lt;br/&gt;Heterogeneous Network Architectures: We propose to explore transport layer adaptivity to the underlying&lt;br/&gt;network model (cellular, peer-to-peer, or hybrid).&lt;br/&gt;4. Network Layer&lt;br/&gt;Application Requirements: We will explore network layer constructs that enable heterogeneous applications&lt;br/&gt;to implement custom network layer policies.&lt;br/&gt;Heterogeneous Network Architectures: We will explore the use of novel state propagation schemes and virtual&lt;br/&gt;backbone approaches to enhance transport layer performance and help in adapting to heterogeneous network&lt;br/&gt;models.&lt;br/&gt;5. Data Link Layer&lt;br/&gt;Rate-compatible error control coding: We develop new types of rate-compatible convolutional codes using&lt;br/&gt;finite-field wavelet transforms.&lt;br/&gt; The protocol suite requires a new Protocol Suite Integration Plan. The project will consist of four phases. During the first phase we will design the details of all the proposed components/protocols/methods of the protocol suite. During the second phase we will assess their performance in a simulation testbed. During the third phase we will integrate the individual modules into the suite and finally in the fourth phase we willprototype the proposed protocol suite and we will assess its performance on a physical testbed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0117840</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Akyildiz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ian@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yucel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Altunbasak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yucel@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Faramarz</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fekri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fekri@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raghupathy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sivakumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>siva@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
