<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Algebraic and Geometric Constructions of Shannon Limit Approaching Codes and Turbo Decoding of Reed-Solomon Codes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>510000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sirin Tekinay</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>As the demand for error-free data transmission and data storage increases, &lt;br/&gt;error control becomes increasingly important in data communication and data&lt;br/&gt;storage systems. It has become an integral part in almost every data &lt;br/&gt;communication or storage system design. Today very sophisticated error &lt;br/&gt;control schemes are being used in a broad range of communication and data&lt;br/&gt;storage systems to achieve reliable data transmission and storage, such as&lt;br/&gt;wireless communication, satellite communication, optical communication, &lt;br/&gt;hard disc drives, compact disks and many others. The objective of this &lt;br/&gt;research is to devise methods for constructing good error control codes and &lt;br/&gt;to develop efficient error control schemes which have great potential to &lt;br/&gt;achieve error-free communication and data storage for the future generation&lt;br/&gt;of data communication and storage systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recently, there have been dramatic developments in error control codes and&lt;br/&gt;decoding algorithms. Two families of powerful codes, known as turbo and&lt;br/&gt;low density parity check (lDPC) codes, have been discovered and rediscovered.&lt;br/&gt;These two families of codes with iterative decoding have been shown to &lt;br/&gt;perform close to Shannon's theoretical limits with reasonable implementation&lt;br/&gt;complexity. As a result of their amazing error performance and practical&lt;br/&gt;implementation, it is anticipated that these two classes of codes will have&lt;br/&gt;an enormous impact on virtually all applications of error control coding over&lt;br/&gt;the next 10 years or so. This research involves in two important aspects&lt;br/&gt;of these two classes of Shannon limit approaching codes: construction of LDPC &lt;br/&gt;codes and turbo decoding of Reed-Solomon (RS) codes. The construction of &lt;br/&gt;LDPC codes is based on combinatoric appraches, such as finite geometries over&lt;br/&gt;finite fields, statistical experimental designs, permutation groups and&lt;br/&gt;graphs. In these approaches, points, lines, hyperplanes in finite geometries, &lt;br/&gt;balanced incomplete block designs, affine permutation groups, and paths&lt;br/&gt;and independent sets of graphs are used for constructing LDPC codes whose&lt;br/&gt;Tanner graphs do not contain short cycles. All the construction methods&lt;br/&gt;are systematic and codes constructed have good structural properties which&lt;br/&gt;simplify encoding and decoding implementations. Turbo decoding of a RS code &lt;br/&gt;is based on binary decomposition of the code into a set of simple binary &lt;br/&gt;component codes and formulating the code as a self concatenated code with the &lt;br/&gt;RS code itself as the outer code and the component codes as inner codes in a &lt;br/&gt;turbo coding arrangement. The decoding is carried out in two stages, turbo &lt;br/&gt;inner decoding and outer algebraic soft-decision decoding.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0117891</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shulin@ece.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Khaled A.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abdel-Ghaffar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ghaffar@ece.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
