<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: The February 28, 2001 Nisqually Earthquake: Juan de Fuca Slab Break-up, Viscoelastic Response, and Interplay with Crustal Faulting</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>61011</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robin Reichlin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Meghan Miller&lt;br/&gt;EAR-0119491&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PANGA consortium will install 8 continuously operating GPS stations in Puget Sound in a rapid response deployment to the Nisqually earthquake. This enhancement of PANGA is aimed at gathering basic data to answer opportune scientific questions. It also provides a demonstration of the ability of the Plate Boundary Observatory community to master the technical challenges of a post-earthquake response in a collaborative manner.&lt;br/&gt;The continuous GPS observations will further our understanding of these scientific issues:&lt;br/&gt;1. Is the series of slab deformation events recorded in 1939,1946 and 1949 a typical sequence, and will we observe a similar sequence in the 1999 Grays Harbor, 2001 Nisqually, and some near term future event(s)?&lt;br/&gt;2. How is deformation propagated from a down going slab through a viscoelastic lower lithosphere, to surface deformation? What are the rheologies that govern this complex scenario and how is deformation propagated or dissipated? &lt;br/&gt;3. How do these processes reveal the budget of seismic vs. aseismic slip? &lt;br/&gt;4. Is there a causal relationship between intra-slab earthquakes and deformation in the brittle upper crust?&lt;br/&gt;5. How does the concentration of deformation across the Puget Lowlands, where fore-arc migration ends in a zone of concentrated strain, relate to arching of the down-going slab and its consequent deformation?&lt;br/&gt;6. Is there an observable role between deeper, slab events with their broad deformation field, and teconomagmatic deformation?&lt;br/&gt;Page A&lt;br/&gt;011 9491</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0119491</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>M. Meghan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>meghan@cwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Central Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Ellensburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>989267500</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5099632111</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 E. University Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
