<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Tropical Cyclone Energy Dispersion and Self-Maintaining Mechanisms For Summer Synoptic-Scale Waves In The Northwest Pacific</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>294262</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jay S. Fein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The principal investigators (PIs) will investigate the mechanisms of tropical cyclone (TC) initiation and their roles in the maintenance of synoptic wavetrains observed in the Northwest Pacific. They hypothesize that the Rossby wave energy dispersion from northwest moving TCs induces equatorward and eastward synoptic wave disturbances. Through convective-circulation feedback, these disturbances have the potential of forming new tropical cyclones and repeating the cycle, thus maintaining the synoptic wavetrains. A three-dimensional, high-resolution tropical cyclone model, developed by one of the PIs, will be used to study this mechanism and related issues. An ocean model will be coupled with the TC model to investigate the effects of ocean feedback. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planned research holds promise for resolving a long-standing problem in tropical dynamics by identifying the processes responsible for the coexistence of tropical cyclones and wave-like disturbances. Resolution of the pertinent issues would expand our knowledge of tropical circulation systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0119490</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>timli@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuqing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yuqing@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
