<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Travel Support for Participation by young U.S. Scientists in Assemblies of the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics (IUGG)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150310</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Louis B. Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The American Geophysical Union (AGU) will provide partial support for travel of more than ninety students and young scientists from the United States to participate in the major international Assemblies of five international geosciences associations under the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics (IUGG): the International Association of Geodesy (IAG); the International Association of Geomagnetism and Aeronomy (IAGA); the International Association of Seismology and Physics of the Earth's Interior (IASPEI); the International Association of Hydrological Sciences (IAHS); the International Association of Meteorology and Atmospheric Sciences (IAMAS); and the International Association of the Physical Sciences of the Ocean (IAPSO). All of these Associations are members of the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics IUGG). This effort will promote and encourage international communication, collaboration and coordination in the geosciences, especially among scientists at an early point in their career. It is intended that this will lead to long-term international interactions among these scientists as they advance in their research careers in their respective institutions and countries. The five Assemblies will address a wide range of important geosciences problems. The AGU will advertise widely opportunities for applying for such support and will undertake a thoughtful and balanced review and selection process.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0120073</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Riordan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>coriorda@aip.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Geophysical Union</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200099123</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2024626900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2000 FLORIDA AVE NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1522</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICAL METEOROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1575</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1679</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5419</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
