<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>OEDG: Building Diversity in, and through, Environmental Journalism</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>253290</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jill L. Karsten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Building Diversity in, and through, Environmental Journalism&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award seeks to strengthen the understanding of the Earth and environment among populations underrepresented in geosciences by improving the quality and quantity of coverage of the environment in media that reach these communities. The Society of Environmental Journalists and the Earth &amp; Environmental Science Journalism Program at Columbia University will work with minority journalists, with journalists employed by minority-serving media organizations, and with the professional societies of minority journalists (the Native American Journalists Association, the National Association of Black Journalists, and the National Association of Hispanic Journalists) to raise interest in covering the Earth and environment among journalists of color and journalists who serve minority communities; raise awareness among non-minority journalists and editors of how minority audiences can be served through environmental reporting; exchange skills and information resources for better reporting on environmental issues of special interest to minority communities; foster grassroots collegial relationships and collaborations between individual journalists of color and environmental journalists; foster institutional partnerships between the professional societies of environmental journalists and minority journalists; showcase and reward exemplary environmental journalism by journalists who are members of underrepresented minorities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0120207</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kastens</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kkastens@edc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
