<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Sol-Gel Synthesis Methods for Organo-Ceramic Adsorbents for Separations of Cobalt, Chromium and Arsenic Ions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric S. Peterson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of the proposed work is to develop efficient metal-ion separation systems based upon the development of a new class of organo-ceramic hybrid materials which can be used as adsorbents for the extraction of toxic and valuable metal ions from aqueous streams. These organic-inorganic hybrid materials are designed at a molecular level to take advantage of desirable properties from both components such as a high reactivity of functional organic molecules for metal extraction and a high physico-chemical strength of the ceramic structure as well as fast metal transport in the pores. The development of these hybrid adsorbents is a multi-disciplinary work in which organic synthesis chemistry, nano-scale materials science, and engineering/technology of chemical and environmental applications are closely interrelated. In this project, over 10 functional organic compounds will be developed and tested for their affinity for the proposed target metal ions, chromium and arsenic. After prescreening, two or three functional organic compounds will be selected for further evaluation with each metal ion to develop the most desirable adsorbent materials. These materials will be used to demonstrate their applicability for separating the target metals in a variety of industrial and environmental fluid streams.&lt;br/&gt;Successful developments in the proposed project will lead to the understanding and advancement of the sol-gel processing technology and the identification of methodologies to produce and characterize organo-ceramic hybrid adsorbents for separation of toxic and industrially important metals. For example, a hybrid adsorbent developed for arsenic separation might be employed to produce safe drinking water from arsenic-contaminated ground water in many regions. Similarly efficient adsorbents for chromium separations could be applied to recycle this metal from contaminated effluent streams in the electroplating industry. In addition, the technology might be extended to other industrial applications to produce catalysts or new additives for polymers, flame-retardants, and lubricants. The project will also disseminate basic knowledge through research publications and novel industrial applications through patents, and it will provide training and education to students, including Native Americans concerned with contaminated lands.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/03/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0120204</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tavlarides</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lltavlar@ecs.syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/03/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
