<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BE/CNH: Interactions of Riparian Pattern, Policy, and Biocomplexity in Coupled Human/Riverine Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1950000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010209</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Martyn M. Caldwell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Complex patterns in river systems emerge because of the interdependence of biophysical and human processes, non-linearity in factors that shape process and pattern, and the unique behavior of linear patchwork mosaics within river networks. This research project combines field studies, biological models, complex systems techniques, and alternative future depictions to explore two interrelated aspects of biocomplexity: complexity of biotic communities and complexity of coupled human/natural resource systems. The investigators hypothesize that as biotic resources become scarce or impaired, a human/riverine system becomes more tightly coupled. This research will examine the ecological vulnerability of these emergent landscapes from the perspectives of likelihood and reversibility under different policies. The objectives are to explore system behaviors through a combination of field and model studies. These models apply complex systems approaches to explore coevolution of policies and landscape patterns, building on relationships identified through field studies of biotic complexity in large rivers and their floodplains. The 4-yr research project is focused on lowland rivers of the Pacific Northwest and is expected to develop of a set of transferable models of ecological and human interactions in river floodplains. The project will foster interactions between students, researchers, river guardians, and the Willamette Restoration Initiative to create a unique learning environment for students and the public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/26/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/26/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0120022</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stanley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gregory</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stanley.gregory@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bolte</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>boltej@engr.orst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hulse</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dhulse@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510602</Code>
      <Name>Ecosystem Dynamics</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
