<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITW - ITWF: Paths to Retention and Turnover in the IT Workforce: Understanding the Relationships Between Gender, Minority Status, Job and Organizational Factors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>699992</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Caroline E. Wardle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Information Technology Workforce (ITWF)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Information Technology Workforce (ITWF)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Id: EIA-0120092&lt;br/&gt;PI: Pascale Carayon&lt;br/&gt;Institution: U. Wisconsin&lt;br/&gt;Title: Paths to Retention and Turnover in the IT Workforce: Understanding the Relationships Between Gender, Minority Status, Job and Organizational Factors&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This ITWF award provides support for the University of Wisconsin to conduct a study that will identify the job, organizational and quality of working life (QWL) factors that influence turnover intention within the current IT workforce, and the way gender and minority status play a role in the relationships between job and organizational factors, QWL and intention to turnover. Two different models of the role of gender and minority status will be used and tested and compared in a sample of IT employees across a range of companies and jobs. The first research model postulates that gender and minority status have direct effects on job and organizational factors and both direct and indirect effects on QWL and intention to turnover. The second research model postulates that gender and minority status play a moderating role in the relationship between job and organizational factors and QWL and intention to turnover.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/26/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0120092</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pascale</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carayon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>carayon@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
