<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Albert Einstein Distinguished Educator Fellowship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>76802</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia M. James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Triangle Coalition for Science and Technology Education initiated the Albert Einstein Distinguished Educator Fellowship program in 1990. This program provides outstanding secondary mathematics and science teachers with an opportunity to serve in the national public policy arena. NSF funding will support an Einstein Fellow in the Informal Science Education (ISE) program. The Fellow will bring practical insight derived from being a classroom teacher to ISE and contribute to the program development and management. The ISE program supports large regional and national projects targeting informal learners that include linkages to formal education. The Einstein Fellow can contribute feasible suggestions on how those linkages can occur, while learning about the proposal development, submission, peer review and award process. The 11-month experience will enable the educator to learn about the field of informal science education from a national perspective through direct interaction with practitioners and participation in professional development. Collegial exchange occurs monthly as Fellows serving in other Federal agencies meet to discuss their experiences. Additionally, participants are required to submit three written reports to document their experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0120542</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>White</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whitep@triangle-coalition.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Triangle Coalition for Science and Technology Education</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>222013000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7035165960</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1840 Wilson Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
