<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Geosciences in Alaska - Field Explorations and Research for K-12 Teachers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40611</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jacqueline E. Huntoon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Geosciences in Alaska&lt;br/&gt;Field Explorations and Research for K-12 Teachers&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"Geosciences in Alaska" is a collaborative project among the University of Alaska Museum, the University of California Museum of Paleontology, and the West Contra Costa Unified School District. It provides a professional development opportunity for teachers that combines both field and research experiences and evaluates the impact of these experiences on their teaching. &lt;br/&gt;Working with faculty and staff associated with the University of Alaska Museum and the University of California Museum of Paleontology, teachers participate in an introductory local field trip, and four weeks of field experience in Alaska, followed by an additional excursion locally in which they will apply what they have learned. This comparison between two distinct yet similar geological settings, Alaska and California, reinforces the major concepts learned and allows for a better understanding of the Earth as a dynamic system. Using an inquiry-based approach, the field and research experiences focus on geologic processes, evidence for tectonics, and paleontology. Following the field experiences, teachers work with one another and their mentors throughout the school year to incorporate what they have learned into their classrooms, develop a rigorous course of study in the geosciences for the district, and expand the project to reach a total of 60 teachers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0121841</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lindberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drl@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
