<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Evaluating the Efficacy of a New Functional Imaging Protocol for Obtaining Data on Functional Connectivity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49996</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Breckler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With National Science Foundation support, Dr. Hampson will conduct a year-long investigation of techniques for using the covariation in activity of brain regions during periods of unconstrained cognition (without a psychological task) to build maps of the connected neural systems that support reading and understanding language. Recent advances in neuroimaging have led to the production of a plethora of new data on brain function. However, methods for deploying such data to develop models of interacting brain regions are presently limited. One new functional neuroimaging technique for studying brain interactions (or connectivity) examines low-frequency temporal correlations between resting state activity levels in different brain areas. This technique is used with functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). Dr. Hampson's project will apply this technique to the neural circuitry of reading in order to evaluate and refine the method. She will investigate the relationship between such maps of connectivity and psychological measures of reading performance. She will also assess whether resting state fMRI data can provide information regarding the existence and strength of interregional connections in individual subjects. The connectivity of this system has been previously investigated using imaging methodologies that examine across-subject correlations between brain areas. In the present project, the pattern of connections found between brain areas involved in reading will be correlated across individuals with their scores on a range of reading skills tests to determine which neural connections are most important for the different sub-processes of reading.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The techniques developed in this project are likely to lead to general methods that could be used to study relationships between brain connectivity patterns and psychological measures across subjects in many different high level cognitive systems. Such methods will be an important tool for investigating brain function at the systems level. Moreover, the findings will be incorporated into a new model of the neural substrate underlying reading ability. This model is intended to provide a framework for understanding reading disorders and to guide future experimental efforts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0121926</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hampson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>CHELL@BOREAS.MED.YALE.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1699</Code>
      <Text>COGNEURO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1699</Code>
      <Text>COGNEURO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
