<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ECS/EPSCoR, NSF Grantees Conference on Electronics, Photonics and Device Technologies, July 9-10, 2001, Univ. of Arkansas, Fayetteville, Ark.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>72417</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this proposal is to request funds to organize ECS-EPSCoR, NSF&lt;br/&gt;Grantees Conference on Electronics, Photonics and Device Technologies. The&lt;br/&gt;conference will be conducted during summer of 2001 at the University of Arkansas,&lt;br/&gt;Fayetteville, Arkansas. Arkansas is an EPSCoR state where significant progress has been&lt;br/&gt;demonstrated in the conference related topics through major NSF sponsored programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Another important objective is to establish an interactive platform of leading researchers&lt;br/&gt;from the states with leading as well as evolving research programs in the areas related to&lt;br/&gt;the conference. The meeting will invite grantees from EPSCoR states (over 60% out of&lt;br/&gt;the total number) and from non-EPSCoR states. This will be a singular opportunity to&lt;br/&gt;generate and discuss new academic concepts, research and education directions by&lt;br/&gt;establishing teams of leading researchers. The conference will provide a basis for&lt;br/&gt;discussing recent research findings as well as sharing first-hand-teaching experiences in&lt;br/&gt;interdisciplinary education across cultural, age and gender boundaries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The choices of conference venue is conducive for the subjects as well as inter and intra&lt;br/&gt;state teaming due to presence of outstanding research and education programs in the&lt;br/&gt;related areas on this campus. For example, this campus houses various leading NSF&lt;br/&gt;funded laboratories, centers, programs and projects including the Arkansas Center for&lt;br/&gt;Electronic-Photonic Materials Innovation (ACEMI), Materials Research Science and&lt;br/&gt;Engineering Center (MRSEC), Distributed seed Program at AR-NB-OK for Science and&lt;br/&gt;Engineering Research Center (SERC) for Durable Nano and Micro System, femtosecond&lt;br/&gt;laser microvias drilling at Materials and Manufacturing Research Laboratories (MRL),&lt;br/&gt;Integrative Graduate Education and Research Training (IGERT) in Microelectronics and&lt;br/&gt;Photonics, and MEMS packaging at High Density Electronics Center (HiDEC).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will result in promoting interaction among scientists and engineers&lt;br/&gt;leading to germination of new ideas and themes, team formation, new proposal&lt;br/&gt;submissions, student involvement and exchange, proceedings of extended abstracts, and&lt;br/&gt;generation of more fiscal and intellectual resources at EPSCoR states, K-12 and school&lt;br/&gt;teacher outreach, more technology transfer. The outcome of the conference will be&lt;br/&gt;disseminated through proceedings and related material on internet, recordable media, and&lt;br/&gt;at various related technical conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0121072</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ajay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Malshe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>apm2@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
      <CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
