<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF/CBMS Regional Conference in the Mathematical Sciences - "Numerical Methods in Forward and Inverse Electromagnetic Scattering" - June 3-7, 2002</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>27499</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lloyd E. Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This NSF-CBMS Regional Conference in the Mathematical Sciences on `Numerical Methods in Forward and Inverse Electromagnetic Scattering' at the Department of Mathematical and Computer Sciences, Colorado School of Mines will be held June 3 to June 7, 2002. The principal lecturer will be Professor Peter Monk of the Department of Mathematical Sciences at the University of Delaware. The theme of his ten lectures will be Maxwell's equations, and methods for their solution. This classical topic still offers many challenges today,&lt;br/&gt;especially as the need to solve Maxwell's equations has increased rapidly in recent years with applications including electromagnetic compatibility testing (to ensure different components like a car generator and&lt;br/&gt;electronic control unit do not interfere with one another) and safety (for example predicting the effects of cell phones on users), as well as familiar applications such as radar. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Topics covered will include: variational methods for cavity problems; finite elements and their application to cavity problems; coupling between finite elements and boundary integral equations; perfectly matched layers; adaptive methods; and methods for solving various inverse problems, such as locating obstacles.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/19/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0121301</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Graeme</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fairweather</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gfairwea@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pamartin@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
      <CityName>Golden</CityName>
      <ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
