<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Project Science: A Program in Education and Training in Management of Big Science Projects</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>338955</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>MARVIN GOLDBERG</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Efficient management of large science facilities requires experience and skills not usually found in the repertoire of research scientists. This proposal plans to address this need by establishing a program conducted by a cadre of knowledgeable project managers that includes workshops and summer schools to which mid-career research scientists, as well as other interested groups, with an interest in project management will be invited. The first steps will proceed through "prototype" activities that will identify the detailed needs as perceived by institutions and groups involved with major scientific projects. Training workshops and courses will then be developed through a series of such prototypes. The first prototype workshop will target a single emerging project and will involve leaders, middle level managers, individual scientists and students associated with the selected project. This workshop will yield a set of recommendations for the targeted project, and will begin the collection of tasks and solutions that will form the basis for the remaining work of this proposal. A week-long workshop will be planned using lessons learned from earlier prototypes. Attendance at this workshop is anticipated to be between 50 and 100 "students" , and would complete the definition of training and management materials to be delivered by this proposal. The proposers will author a set of materials and lecture notes for a university course in facilities management.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0121190</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sanders</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sanders@tmt.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marianne</FirstName>
      <LastName>De Laet</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>delaet@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
