<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>FSML: Improvements in Facilities and Equipment at Mpala Research Centre, Kenya</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>129200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080103</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gerald Selzer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Improvements in Facilities and Equipment at Mpala Research Centre, Kenya&lt;br/&gt;Daniel I.Rubenstein, P.I.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to enhance the quality of ecological research in the arid lands of East Africa by improving the physical infrastructure and the research capabilities of the Mpala Research Centre. The Centre, whose purpose is to advance research in the environmental, biological, and conservation sciences, lies at the heart of the Laikipia ecosystem, a diverse savanna maintaining prodigious wildlife populations, much of it not formally protected in National Parks or Reserves. This landscape is prone to severe environmental fluctuations that produce periodic droughts and floods which challenges the ability of indigenous peoples, commercial ranchers and the wildlife itself to survive. It is part of the Centre's mission to shape research programs that will provide scientific insights that help maintain the ecosystem while enhancing the quality of life of the people utilizing the ecosystem's resources. Fulfilling this mission requires melding institutionally driven mission-motivated research with applications emerging from fundamental research projects initiated by individual investigators. Improving the ability of scientists from all over the world, but mostly those from the US whose research is already supported by the National Science Foundation, to carry out these different types of research requires that the Centre enhance and enlarge its physical plant and provide additional common research support facilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In particular the Centre will improve its: 1) electrical system to provide uninterrupted electricity to run laboratory equipment and computers essential for data recording and analysis; 2) research space so that the large and integrated projects have adequate space for the teams to function coherently; 3) housing stock to accommodate the Resident Scientist who serves as the local research coordinator and the newly hired Geographical Information System specialist who will provide support for the analysis of spatial problems so important for the understanding of climate patterns and wildlife as well as livestock movements and population dynamics; 4) monitoring equipment both on the ground and in the air to provide the long-term data bases so essential for forecasting changes in environmental conditions, wildlife numbers and livestock levels so that rational and sustainable programs of management and conservation can be formulated; and 5) stock of shared and communal research, communication and computer equipment along with 4 x 4 vehicles for traveling over the rugged terrain. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research at Mpala Research Centre is intended to advance an informed and integrated approach to natural resource management and conservation within the Laikipia savanna ecosystem. In doing so the research provides the scientific background that is used by commercial ranches and the group ranches composed of indigenous peoples to better manage their lands, stock and wildlife in economically and ecologically sensible ways. Policies based on research are helping ensure that wildlife helps 'pay' for its protection by means of sustainable regimes of culling and consumption on some lands and ecotourism enterprises on others. In addition, outreach to these various communities on how to live with predators and wildlife competitors is helping maintain the dynamics of this harsh ecosystem. Courses taught with 'hands on' projects to wildlife professionals from governmental and non-governmental organization as well as student groups from Kenyan and international Universities are common and are helping transform the minds of the next generation of environmental leaders along with those who are making critical decisions today.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0122373</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rubenstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dir@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Georgiadis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ngeorg@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
