<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Visualization Learning Environments for Teaching Inquiry and Earth Science Concepts: A Model for Improving Earth Science Teaching (MODEST)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>80660</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jacqueline E. Huntoon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Visualization Learning Environments for Teaching Inquiry and Earth Science Concepts: A Model for Improving Earth Science Teaching&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project develops a pilot model for improving elementary teacher preparation in earth sciences, scalable for broader systematic change. The model consists of a framework for implementing visualization learning environments (simulations, modeling, and imagery of real data sets) in undergraduate science courses for the purpose of constructing inquiry-based learning. The pilot model is based on an eighteen-month longitudinal study on the use of visualization learning environments in an elementary teacher preparation science course taught at the University of Northern Colorado, Principles of Scientific Inquiry.. The longitudinal study is crucial in assessing the long-term impact of visualization learning environments on content literacy and inquiry skill development. The project contributes significantly to the evaluation section of the Digital Library for Earth System Education (DLESE) as a beta test site for DLESE's Evaluator Tool-kit, an instrument for methods and protocols for assessing activities and courses that utilize inquiry-based activities. Faculty teaching general education science courses could adapt the model created by this project for use in their classes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0122026</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mike.taber@coloradocollege.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Northern Colorado</Name>
      <CityName>Greeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>806396900</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9703511910</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
