<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Faculty And Curriculum Enhancement Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2388733</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael D. Fredenberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Statement of Objectives. The Fort Berthold Community College Technology and&lt;br/&gt;Instruction Enhancement Project is proposed to increase the numbers and persistence of&lt;br/&gt;American Indian SMET majors and potential majors&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;- The technology infrastructure of the college will be strengthened by expanded band width&lt;br/&gt; and high tech access for students, faculty and staff.&lt;br/&gt;- The SMET curriculum will integrate constructivist methods and technology applications&lt;br/&gt; to improve SMET student learning outcomes and persistence rates.&lt;br/&gt;- The college faculty and staff will build teaching and learning capacities through&lt;br/&gt; constructivist methodologies and techniques and technology applications.&lt;br/&gt;- American Indian SMET students persistence will be increased by 10% per year through a&lt;br/&gt; student retention model called Family Based Education.&lt;br/&gt;- SMET students will have expanded internships and community service placements,&lt;br/&gt; workforce placement and transfer opportunities through formal community outreach&lt;br/&gt; relationships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Methods to be Employed. The Technology and Instruction Enhancement Project of &lt;br/&gt;Fort Berthold Community College will focus on the recruitment and retention of American &lt;br/&gt;Indian Students toward graduation and transfer or workforce placement. First, the&lt;br/&gt;technology infrastructure will be expanded by improving the band width to speed up and &lt;br/&gt;broaden technology capacities. The student access to high tech equipment and applications&lt;br/&gt;will include the additionof high tech laboratories for student learning Web-conferencing &lt;br/&gt;capacities will be installed in theMentor Sites in three remote satellite campus locations. &lt;br/&gt;Second, constructivist teaching/learning methods and techniques that heightened student&lt;br/&gt;experiential learning and active discovery based activity; and increased technology &lt;br/&gt;applications will be integrated across the curriculum. The computer science networking &lt;br/&gt;program will deliver professional certificationsand two full time faculty members will &lt;br/&gt;make this a technology centerpiece in the curriculum. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Third, the curriculum and college services will be vastly improved through faculty and &lt;br/&gt;staff development opportunities in constructivist teaching/learning methods and technology &lt;br/&gt;applications. Faculty development opportunities will include individual professional &lt;br/&gt;conferences and mini-grants for research projects that involve SMET student interns as&lt;br/&gt;assistants. Fourth, to improve student retention rates, the student services division will &lt;br/&gt;acquire a full time retention officer to implement an aggressive, pro-active retention &lt;br/&gt;strategy called the Family Based Education Model. Pressure points in the family based&lt;br/&gt;American Indian students lives are identified and through a team analysis, referral and &lt;br/&gt;intervention strategies are prescribed to each student itat-risk.ln Community outreach &lt;br/&gt;will expand SMET student opportunities for internship and community service placements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Outcomes. The project outcome will be increased American Indian SMET&lt;br/&gt;student retention rates, 10% increases annually during the project period. The technology&lt;br/&gt;infrastructure will advance according to campus-wide plans. The faculty and staff will have&lt;br/&gt;long term capacities and skills reflecting constructivist methods and technology&lt;br/&gt;applications. The Family Based Education Model will have intervened with at-risk SMET&lt;br/&gt;students, to heighten retention rates. Broad-based community relationships will support&lt;br/&gt;SMET majors and graduates and the college as an educational institution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0123235</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Clarice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baker-Big Back</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbaker@fortbertholdcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Orion</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gillette</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ogilette@fbcc.bia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/06/2005</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fort Berthold Community College</Name>
      <CityName>New Town</CityName>
      <ZipCode>587630490</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7016274738</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 490</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>ND</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
