<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Fond du Lac Tribal Technology and Science Infrastructure Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2456041</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project was developed as a result of a technology and science planning process that&lt;br/&gt;Fond du Lac Tribal and Community College (FDLTCC) initiated in 2000 and is still&lt;br/&gt;continuing. This planning effort involved a large number of college and community&lt;br/&gt;stakeholder groups and provided both the underlying concepts for this proposal as well as the&lt;br/&gt;outline for specific curriculum programs and hardware/software infrastructure needs.&lt;br/&gt;The project proposed has several interrelated elements. High performance computing assets,&lt;br/&gt;including Internet2 hookup, cluster installation, and visualization panels, are put into place to&lt;br/&gt;support both curriculum and research agendas. The research agenda is centered in ongoing&lt;br/&gt;research efforts at the college in environmental science, soil mapping, computational science,&lt;br/&gt;and information technology (IT). The research effort is designed to provide students with&lt;br/&gt;experience in research, experience with the collaborative research environment, and&lt;br/&gt;experimential activities related to what they are studying. The grant also proposes to build a&lt;br/&gt;partnership with the University of Minnesota's Laboratory for Computational Science and&lt;br/&gt;Engineering, both to provide help with constructing the high performance infrastructure, as&lt;br/&gt;well as a research agenda that will involve students in computational science, physics, and&lt;br/&gt;other SMET-related curriculum areas. Other collaborative efforts will be implemented with&lt;br/&gt;current partners involved in FDLTCC research projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At the proposed project's heart are curriculum development and implementation activities&lt;br/&gt;designed to not only build on the enhanced research projects, but to also initiate new SMET&lt;br/&gt;degrees. Research with FDLTCC's target student population has indicated that these degrees&lt;br/&gt;and a one-year certificate program will increase the number of Native American students&lt;br/&gt;majoring in SMET-related programs. These degrees are all designed to launch a new&lt;br/&gt;curriculum track design, which provides a core of Information Technology courses that&lt;br/&gt;students can use to build either baccalaureate or associate degrees in a number of different&lt;br/&gt;disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The degrees and certificate initiated through the project will include: A GIS/GPS certificate&lt;br/&gt;which can be earned in conjunction with the environmental science, computer science, and&lt;br/&gt;law enforcement associate degrees; a baccalaureate in computer science with the IT core; an&lt;br/&gt;associate degree in E-Crime and Computer Security that can be earned with the IT core, the&lt;br/&gt;GIS/GPS certificate, and the college's current Minnesota Transfer or Law Enforcement&lt;br/&gt;associate degrees in order to complete the requirements for a baccalaureate. The new IT core&lt;br/&gt;will also be available to baccalaureate students in Elementary Education at FDLTCC. By the&lt;br/&gt;end of the grant, enrollment in these curriculum areas will support continuation of each&lt;br/&gt;program based on the timetable described in the grant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The last two elements of the grant include the plan to develop an associate degree online for&lt;br/&gt;students located at FDLTCC's Augsburg Offsite program that serves the Native American&lt;br/&gt;community in St. Paul/Minneapolis. This effort will also use the high performance&lt;br/&gt;computing resources built through the project. SMET related faculty and staff development&lt;br/&gt;activities are also included designed to increase IT sophistication at FDLTCC as well as to&lt;br/&gt;increase the number of MS and Ph.D.-qualified faculty in SMET-related areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0123121</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ted</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wetherbee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ted@fdltcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wold</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>awold@fdltcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gillespie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mgillespie@fdltcc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tom</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tdavis@lptc.bia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fond du Lac Tribal and Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Cloquet</CityName>
      <ZipCode>557202964</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2188790810</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2101 14th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
