<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Presidential Awards for Excellence In Science, Mathematics and Engineering Mentoring</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marilyn J. Suiter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The AAAS Project on Science, Technology, and Disability has played a leadership role in supporting the advancement of people with disabilities in science, mathematics and engineering since 1975, more than a decade before the mandate of the Americans with Disabilities Act. This program encourages scientists and engineers to self-identify and thus created the AAAS Resource Group of Scientists and Engineers with Disabilities, producing a group of about 1,000 scientists and engineers who serve as mentors. The AAAS Disability Project has become the most important resource for individuals and organizations seeking to encourage the entry and advancement of person with disabilities in science and engineering. The AAAS Disability Project, has a new program: Entry Point!, which has made more than 245 placements of students with disabilities in paid summer internships. The students are diverse in ethnicity, gender, and type of disability. All are mentored through the process of application, internship offer, relocation, research work, and follow up.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/23/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/23/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0123333</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stern</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rweibl@aaas.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/23/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Association For Advancement Science</Name>
      <CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200053928</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023266400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 NEW YORK AVENUE, N.W.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
