<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Expanding SMET Higher Education for Native Americans in the 21st Century</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute (SIPI) in partnership with the National Science&lt;br/&gt;Foundation will increase the number of Native Americans matriculating into science,&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, engineering and technology (SMET) baccalaureate programs and/or entering &lt;br/&gt;the science and technology workforce. This will be accomplished through a comprehensive&lt;br/&gt;program, irVision-21le which includes: a) curriculum development in calculus, physics and&lt;br/&gt;chemistry; b) standards-based faculty development in problem-solving instructional &lt;br/&gt;strategies and in the use of instructional technologies; c) two-year student experiences&lt;br/&gt;in research; and, c) an expanded program for networking professionals leading to&lt;br/&gt;industry certification to address the need for information technology workers in&lt;br/&gt;Native American communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is designed to improve student-learning outcomes in calculus, physics, and&lt;br/&gt;chemistry. Students will participate in inquiry-based learning strategies delivered through&lt;br/&gt;a technology-enriched curriculum that is delivered/facilitated by a skilled faculty. Native&lt;br/&gt;American undergraduates will also participate in meaningful research experiences that &lt;br/&gt;will lead to improved diverse career opportunities, particularly in the SMET fields. &lt;br/&gt;Students will learn and write about the research process, and develop presentations&lt;br/&gt;for professional student forums. This is a learning experience that is rarely afforded &lt;br/&gt;to two-year undergraduates. Finally to address the need for certified information &lt;br/&gt;technology professionals in the U.S., and especially among Tribal Nations, SIPI will&lt;br/&gt;expand its networking training program, allowing for industry certification.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project staff in collaboration with faculty will develop an extensive evaluation&lt;br/&gt;and assessment program. Staff will encourage and monitor student enrollment &lt;br/&gt;and success in college courses that will prepare students for science, mathematics,&lt;br/&gt;engineering and technology careers. Curricula products will be packaged and shared &lt;br/&gt;with Native serving institutions, and evaluation and assessment results will be &lt;br/&gt;electronically disseminated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0123131</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jerry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Simmons</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jsimmons@sipi.bia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lujan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlujan@sipi.bia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hooks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rhooks@sipi.bia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871203101</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5057922976</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9169 Coors Road NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
