<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ANTEC - U.S.: Workshop and Science Planning Activities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>65068</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexandra Isern</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award, provided by the Office of Polar Programs (OPP) of the National Science Foundation (NSF), provides support for U.S. participation in an international workshop and associated planning activities of the Antarctic Neotectonics (ANTEC) initiative. The goal of the ANTEC program is to improve understanding of the unique character of the neotectonic regime of the Antarctic plate, including measurement of, and discrimination between, glacial and tectonic kinematic signals, mapping the structure of the Antarctic lithosphere and asthenosphere, investigating the stress field and seismotectonic features of the Antarctic plate, and understanding the nature of coupling between tectonics, climate and erosion. A workshop at the Certosa di Pontignano, Siena, Italy, will bring together scientists active in Antarctic neotectonics research to assess the current status of neotectonic research programs, and to develop a detailed science plan for future research. Nearly 45% of the research projects currently funded by the Antarctic Geology and Geophysics Program of NSF-OPP are either focused directly on, or are pertinent to, Antarctic neotectonic science themes. Consequently, broad representation of the U.S. research community at the ANTEC workshop is important. Funds provided by this award will support U.S. participation in the workshop and will cover costs associated with dissemination of the workshop results through publication of a workshop report, a brochure summarizing the ANTEC initiative, and via the ANTEC web site.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0123184</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>twilson@mps.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6142923732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0311000</Code>
      <Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
