<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ACS Polymer Division Symposium "Nobel Laureates in Polymer Chemistry"; Chicago, IL; August 27, 2001</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support of the ACS Polymer Division symposium Nobel Laureates n Polymer Chemistry, to be held on Monday, 27 August 2001 at the National ACS Meeting in Chicago, Illinois. These funds will be used to facilitate attendance of 1 young faculty member and 3 graduate students/postdocs.&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;The 2000 Nobel Prize in Chemistry was won by Professors Hideki Shirakawa (Tskuba University), Alan MacDiarmid (University of Pennsylvania), and Alan Heeger (UC California, Santa Barbara). In the Nobel laureates in Polymer Chemistry Symposium, the winners of the 2000 Nobel Laureates in Polymer Chemistry Symposium, the winners of the 2000 Nobel prize in Chemistry will give lectures in the exact order of their Nobel addresses that were given in Stockholm in December 2000. This Symposium is scheduled for Monday, 27 August 2001 at the Chicago ACS Meeting. To recognize the importance of international interdisciplinary research in polymer science and the longstanding research collaborations with Japanese polymer scientists, The Society of Polymer Science of Japan (SPSJ) was asked to "cosponsor" the "Nobel Laureates in Polymer Chemistry symposium" and has responded enthusiastically. The President of SPSJ, Professor Tisato Kajiama (Fukuoka University), will give opening remarks highlighting the close friendships and research collaborations of U.S. and Japanese polymer scientists. Industrial participation in this symposium includes a talk by a research leader and session chairing by key industrial technology managers who are involved in transitioning basic research into conducting polymer and optoelectronic technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0124013</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wynne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kjwynne@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
      <CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
