<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Teaching Bioinformatics through the Lynx Genome Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>52165</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jeanne Small</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological Sciences (61)&lt;br/&gt;The recent sequencing of the human genome and continuing efforts to sequence and analyze genetic sequences of many species demonstrate the need for effective pedagogies in genomic studies. This project acquires the equipment and develops the materials necessary to engage undergraduate students in a novel genome project adapting and implementing materials from James Madison University. A DNA sequencer and sequence analysis software are being used to initiate the Lynx Genome Project as a unit in the Molecular Biology Laboratory course. Students are sequencing cDNA clones from lynx species (the Rhodes College mascot) and using the resulting data in evolutionary and functional prediction analyses. Results are expected to lead to insights in efforts to conserve these threatened species. High school students and teachers, a significant number of whom are members of groups underrepresented in the sciences, are participating through a Summer Scholars Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0124866</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lindquester</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>glindquester@rhodes.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rhodes College</Name>
      <CityName>Memphis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>381121624</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9018433958</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2000 North Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
