<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Transport and Transformations of Carbon and Nitrogen in the Western Arctic Ocean: A Contribution to the SBI Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>515030</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Neil R. Swanberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project contributes to Western Arctic Shelf-Basin Interactions (SBI) by focussing on a) biogeochemical modifications of Pacific water over the Beaufort and Chukchi shelf and slope regions,&lt;br/&gt;with emphasis on carbon and nitrogen; and b) comparative analysis of the findings over the broad Chukchi shelf and narrow Beaufort shelf and adjacent slopes to facilitate integration of the Western Arctic into a Pan-Arctic perspective. The project will evaluate the processes of carbon and nitrogen transport, exchanges and transformations in the regions of interest. Specific objectives are: a) determination of mass transport and fate of carbon and nitrogen associated with the volume transports calculated by SBI collaborators; b) interpretation of carbon and nitrogen spatial distributions and temporal variability relative to biological&lt;br/&gt;and physical conditions; c) evaluation of partitioning of organic matter between dissolved and particulate phases; d) determination of net community production and it's fate; e) determination of C:N stoichiometry as a complement to biological studies, particularly in relation to community structure and seasonal progression of intense phytoplankton blooms in the Chukchi and Beaufort Seas; and f) evaluation of the contribution of dissolved and particulate organic material to apparent oxygen utilization development in the Arctic halocline and export from the shelf.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/27/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0124900</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hansell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dhansell@rsmas.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami Rosenstiel School of Marine&amp;Atmospheric Sci</Name>
      <CityName>KEY BISCAYNE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331491031</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3054214089</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4600 RICKENBACKER CSWY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5219</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SYSTEM SCIENCE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5205</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESRCH SUPPRT &amp; LOGISTI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5219</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SYSTEM SCIENCE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
