<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Program for Persons with Disabilities - PPD: RASEM Squared: Advanced Regional Alliance of Science, Engineering, and Mathematics for Students with Disabilities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4141269</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark H. Leddy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal # HRD-0124198&lt;br/&gt;Institution: New Mexico State University&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigators: William McCarthy and Ed Misquez&lt;br/&gt;Title: RASEM Squared&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;New Mexico State University will be the lead institution for a Regional Alliance for Students with Disabilities in Science, Mathematics, Engineering, and Technology (SMET). The project, entitled RASEM Squared (or RASEM 2), is based on the successes of an earlier project named RASEM (Regional Alliance For Science, Engineering, and Mathematics for Students with Disabilities) funded by NSF. The project's primary goal over the five years of the program is to increase the number of students with disabilities who graduate with baccalaureate degrees leading directly to graduate training or to employment in their desired fields. To achieve these goals, RASEM 2 is instituting a comprehensive educational approach composed of six innovative actions, five previously field-tested by RASEM and an additional one that prepares faculty for full participation of students with disabilities in SMET curricula. The actions will affect students throughout the education continuum from K-12, through community colleges, and to universities in New Mexico and far west Texas. The six actions are: 1. Hands-on science experiences in pre-college science education environments. 2. Formal research experiences as undergraduates and graduates. 3. Preparation of faculty for full participation of students with disabilities in a SMET curricula. 4. Bridge programs between academic levels. 5. Mentoring by successful SMET professionals and SMET students with disabilities. 6. Securing co-op, summer internships, and professional employment. Each of the six actions will be evaluated using outcome measures that provide evidence of the program's efficacy. &lt;br/&gt;The RASEM 2 Alliance is made up of numerous entities in New Mexico (seventeen 2-year community colleges, six 4-year colleges and universities, and nine school district regional center cooperatives) and West Texas (two universities and two educational service centers representing school districts). The Alliance also includes two national laboratories, the statewide agencies serving people with disabilities, and a national organization for the advancement of science. These entities are located in a region that has a broad spectrum of culturally diverse, economically impoverished constituencies of students with disabilities and student families. RASEM 2 project coordinators in three sub-regions will work to strengthen existing ties (or develop new ones) with public schools in their areas. They will facilitate efforts to provide a bridge between public schools and higher education institutions and promote summer programs in their geographical areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/27/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0124198</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCarthy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wmccarth@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Misquez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>emisquez@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
      <CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
      <ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
