<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-France Cooperative Research: Disorder-Driven Quantum Phase Transitions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13966</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0124350&lt;br/&gt;Scalettar&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This two-year award supports U.S.-France collaboration in materials research between Richard T. Scalettar, University of California, Davis, and George Batrouni of the University of Nice. The project addresses the problem of interacting, disordered electron systems. The objective is to determine quantum phase transitions in disordered superfluids and superconductors using Quantum Monte Carlo (QMC) methods. The investigators will conduct numerical simulations of the Boson-Hubbard model for superfluids and of supersolid formation in the Fermion-Hubbard model. The US investigator brings to the collaboration expertise in fermion determinant QMC methods. This is complemented by French expertise in dual algorithm bosonic QMC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Disordered electron systems exhibit remarkable properties including universal conductivity, two-dimensional metal-insulator and superconductor insulator phase transition, zero temperature liquid behavior and novel glassy phases. These systems represent fundamental problems in solid state physics and have important technological applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award represents the US side of parallel proposals to the NSF and the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS). NSF will cover travel funds and living expenses of the US investigator and student. The CNRS will support the visits of the French researchers. The collaboration will advance fundamental understanding of disordered electron systems in solid state physics and provides an international research training opportunity for a US student.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/13/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0124863</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scalettar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scalettar@physics.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
