<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Power-Autonomous Wireless Networks: Controlling CPU and Transmission Power with Rechargeable Capabilities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>206250</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project focuses on new approaches to maximizing power consumption in handheld and other wireless devices by combining a network-centric view of the power-consumption issue (aximizing longevity for the network rather than device by devic) with the more traditional device-centric view (power management capabilities for the individual device). The project will model and evaluate new architectures and algorithms that allow the operating system to accept input from the applications and interact closely with the network for minimizing overall energy in the wireless system. The focus of the research is: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) power-management of individual nodes &lt;br/&gt;2) power-aware routing, in the sense that the power is minimized for the overall network and not only for individual messages or streams. &lt;br/&gt;3) a combination of the variable voltage scheduling with the power-aware routing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is anticipated that through algorithm development and analysis, simulation and testbed implementations, the results of this project will lead to a better understanding of how to provide more efficient power management to nodes with rechargeable batteries, and how to integrate CPU and network power management under one paradigm.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0125704</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rami</FirstName>
      <LastName>Melhem</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>melhem@cs.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mosse'</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mosse@cs.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
