<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integrating Calculus and General Physics Using a Workshop and Peer-Leader Approach</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98145</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan H. Hixson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Interdisciplinary (99) Mathematics (21) Physics (13)&lt;br/&gt;We are implementing an integrated physics and mathematics laboratory and classroom in which we extend cooperative learning models into a unified introductory physics and calculus course. We address several persistent problems in student learning: poor conceptualization and retention of material, underdeveloped problem-solving skills, and difficulty actively applying knowledge across disciplines. We are integrating and adapting materials and methods from several NSF funded projects (including Workshop Physics, integrated calculus and physics at University of New Hampshire, and peer-led team learning) and are building on successful projects at the University of Portland that use cooperative learning models. We are teaching a unified introductory math/physics course that encourages students to make connections across disciplines in the same environment using the same set of tools. Instructors in this course have greater flexibility in the timing of topics, at times focusing on building strong foundations and at others, establishing connections between the subjects. New equipment allows students to work in small groups on investigative activities with a supervising peer-leader and a faculty member overseeing the entire class. The design of the classroom allows faculty to unify lecture with hands-on learning and to integrate computer usage with group activities such as experimentation and joint problem-solving. The laboratory also is used in our education of math and physics students interested in K-12 teaching.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0125614</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tamar</FirstName>
      <LastName>More</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>more@up.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hillg@up.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Portland</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972035743</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5039438004</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 N Willamette Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
