<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH/CRI: Children's Digital Media Centers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>579834</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amy L. Sussman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>American children spend many hours with media each day. Although much of this time involves television viewing, an increasing amount involves participation with digital interactive entertainment technologies, including the Internet. Even television as we know it will soon change dramatically, with digital television adding improved clarity of images and the opportunity for interactivity. Knowing how to use these interactive technologies will be a necessary skill for an educated workforce in the 21st century and may be a gateway to studying science and technology. Therefore, knowing how children use and learn from these digital technologies is an important step in ensuring that children will develop these basic skills. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although children invest their free time heavily in electronic entertainment media, relatively little is known about how new interactive media impact children's learning in informal learning contexts. One problem is that the field is interdisciplinary. Researchers examine diverse issues rather than examine specific areas of interactive digital media systematically and then consolidate that knowledge into a central information base. Another problem is the rapid change in digital technologies, making researchers one step behind the latest developments. One outcome of these problems is a poor knowledge base for understanding of how new digital entertainment technologies influence children's learning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the next 5 years, this Center will advance theory and method in how children learn through digital interactive entertainment media. Using an interdisciplinary team of researchers from the fields of psychology, human development, communications, sociology, anthropology, and medicine, researchers will explore multiple levels of analysis in order to explicate the role that dialogue, in the form of interactivity and identity, play in children's learning from entertaining interactive digital technologies. At a macro level, two types of survey will be conducted to document patterns of change and similarity over time in children's access to, and use of, new and emerging digital platforms. These macro level studies will guide the direction of micro level experimental, observational, and ethnographic studies that will examine what interactivity is and how and what children learn from online digital experiences. Parallel research activities will examine children at different age groups, providing both cross-sectional and longitudinal findings on children's uses of media and the impact of media on their development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Overall, these research activities will expand the knowledge base about: 1) the kinds of digital media that are emerging; 2) the kinds of interactive digital media experiences children choose to have; 3) the impact of these interactive experiences on children's long-term social adjustment and academic achievement; 4) how specific kinds of interactions with digital technologies impact children's learning; 5) how interacting with each other online influences children's learning and identity construction; and 6) how observational and interactive experiences are represented in the developing brain. This knowledge base will be disseminated in published form in professional journals, through presentations at national and international conferences, and via interconnected websites to create synergistic activities among the researchers, policy makers, child advocacy groups, and creators in the children and digital media field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Children's Digital Media Centers, based at Georgetown University, will also include the University of Texas at Austin, Northwestern University, and the University of California Los Angeles. Centers will include a Steering Committee and an Advisory Board of distinguished colleagues.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0125446</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Greenfield</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>greenfield@psych.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
