<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: Time-Averaging in Mixed Brachiopod-Mollusk Assemblages along a Depth Gradient across a Modern Tropical Shelf</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99172</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030101</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The limits to temporal resolution imposed by processes of time-averaging (i.e., age mixing of fossils that determines the temporal resolution of the fossil record) have broad implications for interpretation of the fossil record in a wide variety of types of studies. Almost no information on time-averaging is currently available for brachiopods, the predominant organism comprising Paleozoic and many later marine shell assemblages. We propose to use a combination of amino acid racemization and radiocarbon dating to document time-averaging in surficial accumulations of mixed brachiopod-mollusk shells on the southern Brazilian shelf. The resulting data will provide quantitative estimates of age structures of dated shells of brachiopods and mollusks from seven sites along a depth gradient. The study is expected to produce (1) the first quantitative estimates of time-averaging for brachiopod shell accumulations, (2) the first comparative data on time-averaging for two groups of biomineralized organisms (brachiopods vs. mollusks), and (3) the first estimates of time-averaging along an onshore-offshore bathymetric gradient. By adding taxonomic and environmental dimensions to the current knowledge of time-averaging, this study will provide a significant contribution to our understanding of the temporal resolution of the fossil record.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0125149</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kowalewski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkowalewski@flmnh.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/05/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
