<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Potential Vorticity Diagnosis of African Easterly Waves and Tropical Cyclones</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>349079</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jay S. Fein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Potential vorticity (PV) diagnosis has been used as a powerful tool in studying midlatitude cyclone developments. The PIs will use this tool to study the downstream evolution of African easterly waves (AEWs), their interactions with the large-scale flow, and their subsequent development into tropical cyclones (TCs). Specific studies include: 1) to reexamine whether AEWs are, in fact, wave-like disturbances, 2) to determine whether the deformation and concomitant superposition of AEW PV by the large-scale environmental flow is a viable mechanism alone to trigger tropical cyclogenesis, 3) to understand more completely the three-dimensional structure and evolution of TC PV, 4) to relate the steering layer of TCs to the depth of the PV column, and 5) to examine the sensitivity of TC steering to various microphysical parameterizations in NWP models. The hypotheses associated with the tasks are: 1) the intensification of the AEWs is related to their change in shape (from elongated to more circular) associated with appropriate deformation and 2) the intensity and track of a cyclone is related to its depth. Global analyses from European Center for Medium-range Weather Forecast (ECMWF), in conjunction with satellite data and satellite-derived winds and aircraft data, will be used to analyze the portrayal of AEWs. Investigation on TCs' development and structure will be carried out with high-resolution non-hydrostatic research models. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tropical cyclone formation remains one of the largely unsolved problems in dynamic meteorology. This research using PV analysis has the potential to provide greater insight into the mechanisms of the transformation of African easterly waves into tropical depressions and provide guidance in tropical cyclogenesis prediction. The project provides good opportunities for training graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0125169</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morgan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcmorgan@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1527</Code>
      <Text>LARGE-SCALE DYNAMIC METEOROLOG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
