<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integrating Biochemical Topics into the Analytical Lab Using HPLC and UV-Visible Spectrophotometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>38002</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph Grabowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objectives of this project are (1) to integrate selected biochemical concepts and methods and (2) to introduce project-oriented, student-designed laboratories into the analytical course. An HPLC system and a UV-Visible spectrophotometer are making this possible. Specific experiments and the project laboratory approach are being adapted from the chemical education literature, the primary chemistry literature, and application notes provided by manufacturers. The proposed changes are correlated with a Departmental goal to integrate biochemical concepts across the chemistry curriculum and toward a college-wide effort for student-directed, individualized learning opportunities. By incorporating biochemical concepts and group project experiments into the analytical laboratory, student understanding of selected biochemical topics, student ability to apply an analytical approach to biochemical problems, and student capacity for working with other members of a group toward the solution of a problem are being increased.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126921</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cstrong@cornell-iowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell College</Name>
      <CityName>Mount Vernon</CityName>
      <ZipCode>523141098</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3198954000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>600 First Street West</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
