<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Introducing Indivisibles into Calculus Instruction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399954</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lee L. Zia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI's Bronislaw Czarnocha and Vrunda Prabhu, will conduct two year-long cycles of&lt;br/&gt;teaching experiments to introduce the intuition of "indivisibles" into calculus instruction and&lt;br/&gt;integrate it with standard ways of instructing via Riemann construction. They plan to study&lt;br/&gt;closely the conceptual and computational development of students who receive this instruction. It&lt;br/&gt;As part of this project, the PI's will investigate:&lt;br/&gt;(1) What is the process of transformation and development of the intuition of lines (the&lt;br/&gt;indivisibles) into a precise, mathematical concept?&lt;br/&gt;(2) Does the introduction of the W-C construction based on indivisibles, the interplay of that&lt;br/&gt;construction with the standard Riemann construction, and the instruction that integrates both,&lt;br/&gt;strengthen students' understanding of the concept of the definite integral?&lt;br/&gt;In the proposed project, they will conduct and coordinate Calculus instruction at six&lt;br/&gt;institutions, assess students' performance via tests, essays and clinical interviews, collect data&lt;br/&gt;resulting from the different assessment and analyze the data in preparation for a refinement of the&lt;br/&gt;teaching strategy. As a general framework they will adopt Vygotsky's theory with its emphasis&lt;br/&gt;on the cognitive processes in the zone of proximal development, which dictates important&lt;br/&gt;consequences on the instruction and assessment. Students will be guided by the activities of the&lt;br/&gt;class to enable them to experience the process of mathematical thinking and to reveal its content&lt;br/&gt;to the teacher. The role of the instructor will be to provide systematization of their spontaneous&lt;br/&gt;development grounded in the precise mathematical understanding of the concept in question. The&lt;br/&gt;directions their spontaneous thought processes take, will be under investigation during the course.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is a balance between various aspects: (1) the natural intuition of the learner vs.&lt;br/&gt;the academic instruction, (2) computational mastery vs. conceptual understanding, (3) teaching&lt;br/&gt;and research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126141</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bronislaw</FirstName>
      <LastName>Czarnocha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bczarnocha@hostos.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vrunda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prabhu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vrunda.prabhu@bcc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Hostos Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104515307</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7185186660</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>475 Grand Concourse</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
