<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Discovering Science through Microbiology: Biology for Majors, Non-science Majors, and High School Students</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>144813</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jeanne Small</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological Sciences (61)&lt;br/&gt;Through implementation of investigative and collaborative learning, using&lt;br/&gt;pedagogy established by BioQUEST, our goal is developing critical thinkers in three&lt;br/&gt;populations: biology majors, and non-science majors at the University of Richmond, and&lt;br/&gt;high school students from the Richmond area, particularly underrepresented minorities.&lt;br/&gt;To realize these goals, we are using microbiology as the subject with the laboratory&lt;br/&gt;component focused on antibiotic resistant bacteria isolated from freshwater sources. We&lt;br/&gt;are teaching not only what we know from science (i.e., content), but more importantly how&lt;br/&gt;that knowledge is acquired (the process of science) and its relevance to real-world&lt;br/&gt;problems. We are adapting BioQUEST's inquiry-based model for our Biology major's&lt;br/&gt;Microbiology course, the development of two new courses, Unseen Life (non-science&lt;br/&gt;students) and Microbes: Life's Small Beginnings (high school students), and a research-based&lt;br/&gt;course, Exploring the Basics of Biotechnology: Teaching Investigative and Deductive Experimentation (EBBTIDE), which is an investigative experience designed for high school students. The goals of these microbiology courses, regardless of the student population, differ only in regard to science literacy (e.g., understanding primary literature versus review articles). Through investigative and collaborative learning experiences, using currently available technology, we are teaching students critical thinking, how to: (1) ask questions, (2) solve problems, and (3) articulate their findings. These courses culminate in opportunities for scholarly activities for undergraduates and some high school students. By engaging students in independent investigations with connection to current events, students should leave the academic setting as life-long learners, excited about science and their environment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/28/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/28/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126955</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Debra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wohl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wohld@etown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paula</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lessem</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>plessem@richmond.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reed</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbreed@grahec.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Richmond</Name>
      <CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>231730001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8042898100</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 MARYLAND HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
