<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Science Achievement and Health Behavior: High School Curriculum, Social Context, and Opportunity to Learn</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1752756</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Larry E. Suter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A three-year research project is proposed with the following goals:&lt;br/&gt;1. To fully describe the science and mathematics curricular exposure of high school students and&lt;br/&gt;differences resulting from curricular variations, social context and opportunities to learn, and&lt;br/&gt;students background.&lt;br/&gt;2. To analyze how curricular exposure and social structure influence students persistence through&lt;br/&gt;the science and mathematics pipeline.&lt;br/&gt;3. To analyze how curricular exposure and academic progress through the science pipeline affect&lt;br/&gt;students choice to major in science-related fields, including teaching.&lt;br/&gt;4. To analyze how science curricular exposure shapes students health behavior and health-related&lt;br/&gt;science literacy.&lt;br/&gt;Three major areas that influence students progress through the science and mathematics&lt;br/&gt;pipeline and their health choices and literacy even if they leave the pipeline are identified and&lt;br/&gt;analyzed: (1) curriculum content, performance expectations and perspectives (2) formal,&lt;br/&gt;structured opportunities to learn and (3) the informal social contexts of students learning&lt;br/&gt;environments.&lt;br/&gt;Quantitative methods are employed. This study takes advantage of a unique and timely&lt;br/&gt;opportunity to analyze nationally representative, longitudinal data from the 1990s, the National&lt;br/&gt;Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health (Add Health) and its transcript supplement. A third&lt;br/&gt;wave of Add Health is currently being gathered, and students high school transcripts and&lt;br/&gt;supporting school documents (course catalogues, syllabi, textbook lists) are being collected and&lt;br/&gt;coded. For this study, course curriculum (content, performance expectations, and perspectives)&lt;br/&gt;will also be coded and analyzed along with the transcript data and longitudinal survey data from&lt;br/&gt;approximately 19,000 respondents who were in grades 7 through 12 in the1994-1995 school year.&lt;br/&gt;This data set contains extensive measures of many sources of influence from the contexts of&lt;br/&gt;students lives that can be linked to adolescents health behavior, academic performance, and&lt;br/&gt;science and teaching aspirations.&lt;br/&gt;This study is set within Quadrant III of the ROLE program: irResearch on SMET learning in&lt;br/&gt;formal and informal educational settings,ll and has major implications and links to Quadrants II&lt;br/&gt;and IV. The study directly targets the question of how recent mathematics and science&lt;br/&gt;educational reforms in approaches and curriculum materials affect students academic progress&lt;br/&gt;and learning. It explicitly distinguishes between formal and informal processes to assess the&lt;br/&gt;effects and interactions of each. The study addresses the concentration of Quadrant II since the&lt;br/&gt;research questions are framed to recognize how the complex, multilevel aspects of students&lt;br/&gt;backgrounds and lives interact with the structure and social context of schools to affect learning.&lt;br/&gt;The concentrations of Quadrant IV are also addressed by the multilevel approach to analysis of&lt;br/&gt;longitudinal, nationally representative data. The data sets depth allows for analysis of how&lt;br/&gt;reforms in curricular content (including textbook adoptions) and structure are related to students&lt;br/&gt;progress within the context of schools and curriculum-based subsets of students (such as tracks).&lt;br/&gt;Consistent with common themes across ROLE concentration areas, this study will model these&lt;br/&gt;processes and analyze large-scale effects of curricular and social structuring inherent in&lt;br/&gt;mathematics and science reform efforts. Finally, it assesses how science education is related to&lt;br/&gt;the everyday lives of the U.S.s diverse population by examining how exposure to science in&lt;br/&gt;high school is related to health choices and behaviors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/26/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126167</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chandra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cmuller@prc.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pedro</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reyes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>preyes@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1666</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH ON LEARNING &amp; EDUCATI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
