<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improving Item Construct Validity by Illuminating Student Cognitive Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>752177</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Larry E. Suter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal 0126088&lt;br/&gt;PI: Steve Ferrara and Marianne Perie&lt;br/&gt;Institution: American Institute for Research, Washington &lt;br/&gt;Title: Improving Item Construct Validity by Illuminating Student Cognitive Processing&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a study of middle school science assessment test items. It intends to develop test items that have high levels of validity. The investigators would create a framework to guide writing valid science items that elicit intended knowledge, skills, and cognitive processes that are valid for women, men, and minority groups. The goal is to develop a strategy that can be used by other test developers to develop such tests rather than develop the test itself. They are seeking items that require the students to use the same knowledge and skills as intended by test developers and that work the same way regardless of ethnicity or gender. The framework also involves attention to student motivation, content exposure, and attitude toward response strategies and uses a taxonomy developed by Richard Snow as the basis for their study. The product will be a series of reports that will serve as a guide for middle school science assessment developers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126088</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marianne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Perie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mperie@air.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ferrara</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sferrara@air.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200073835</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2024035000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Thomas Jefferson Street, NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
