<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Enhance Heterologous Protein Production in High-Density Plant Suspension Cultures using Cell-Cycle Engineering and GFP-based On-line Optimization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249717</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Fred G. Heineken</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The overall goal of this project is to develop plant cell bioreactor cultures into a more effective system for producing high-value recombinant proteins. The specific objectives of the present research are as follows: 1) Test inducible cell-cycle control to maximize the useful culture life and yield of the target protein; 2) Employ tested molecular strategies that complement the cell-cycle control to further enhance the level of target protein expression; 3) Optimize protein production using on-line GFP-fusion monitoring and dynamic process optimization in high-density cultures. To accomplish these objectives, the Principal Investigators (PIs) will embark on the following research tasks: (1) examine the effect of expressing a cell-cycle inhibitor on cell proliferation in plant suspension cultures; (2) study coordinated expression of the target gene and the cell-cycle gene to enhance the target protein production; (3) exploit suitable targeting and endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-retention signals to promote secretion and to stabilize the target protein; (4) engineer GFP as a dual function fusion tag for process monitoring and protein purification; (5) investigate signal processing of on-line detected fluorescence of GFP-fusion proteins; (6) devise an effective dynamic process optimization scheme that draws on the on-line fluorescence data; and (7) develop high-density perfusion and fed-batch cultures integrated with the controlled proliferation technology and the fusion protein monitoring/optimization schemes. Tobacco will be used as the model host system. Human granulocyte macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GMCSF) with GFP fusion is chosen as a model protein in this research. The proposed research should lead to development of a more effective plant cell culture process for recombinant protein production. It should also shed light on regulation of the plant cell cycle and cell-cycle dependence of foreign gene expression in plant cells.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126191</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wei Wen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Su</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wsu@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ning-Shou</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ningshou@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Henrik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Albert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>halbert@harc-hspa.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
