<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Applying Science to Sustainability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149615</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Terry S. Woodin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological Sciences (61) Ithaca College and EcoVillage at Ithaca, in partnership, are developing a science-intensive curriculum in environmental sustainability. Drawing on models of college/community affiliation successful on other campuses, such as Pennsylvania State University, the project adds four new laboratory courses (Ecologically Sustainable Communities, Sustainable Land Use, Energy Systems and Sustainable Energy, and Ecological Footprinting) and faculty sponsored summer research. The new courses are sequenced such that students are introduced to the approach of sustainability science in the first course, master the analytical tools involved in energy efficiency (combustion analyzers, watt and light meters, thermal submetering systems, as well as computerized building models) and land use (field surveys, and GPS/GIS) in the second and third courses, and unify their knowledge and apply it using the ecological footprinting approach in a final capstone course. Furthermore, all the core courses in the Environmental Studies Program are being modified to incorporate the curricular theme of environmental sustainability such that students are trained in all aspects of sustainability and are fully equipped to pursue careers at the science-policy interface with a solutions-oriented approach.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126792</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Allen-Gil</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sallen@ithaca.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shevory</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shevory@ithaca.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ithaca College</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148507000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072743111</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>953 Danby Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
