<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Workshops in the Human Sciences: Understanding Socialization and Adolescent Development in Multi-cultural Contexts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14992</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jasmine V. Young</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding Socialization and Adolescent Development in Multi-cultural Contexts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Andrew Supple&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Communities in the southeastern United States have experienced rapid increases in proportions of foreign-born individuals over the last decade. Demographic changes have been especially dramatic in No. Carolina and Georgia, two states among the top ten in terms of percentage increases in foreign-born populations during the 1990s. Changes in the demographic composition of local communities in these states have created an acute need for a sound knowledge base regarding the socialization influences and outcomes in these populations. Moreover, community leaders, outreach service providers, and educators will need reliable data and culturally relevant theoretical frameworks to disseminate knowledge about socialization processes among children and adolescents from immigrant families. The purpose of this project is to create a multidisciplinary and cross-institutional research team from three universities in the southeastern United States through a series of workshops. The workshops are designed to develop a strategic plan for research on the socialization of children and adolescents in immigrant families.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126473</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Supple</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ajsupple@uncg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina Greensboro</Name>
      <CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>274125013</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3363345878</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1111 Spring Garden Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
