<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Promoting Undergraduate Research through the Development of Two Interdisciplinary Research Methods/Statistics Courses and Increased Support of Student Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>197975</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniel P. Maki</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Interdisciplinary (99)&lt;br/&gt;This project increases students' involvement in undergraduate research by developing two team-taught interdisciplinary research methods statistics courses. The interdisciplinary team approach is adapted from the approaches developed by Donovan at Kean University and Peaslee at Hope College. The project also provides faculty development opportunities to foster greater inclusion of active learner methodologies in courses, and creates a centralized program to promote and support undergraduate research activities. The unique configuration of the nine basic and applied sciences and health sciences programs in the College provides team-teaching and student-faculty research opportunities across disciplinary boundaries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project activities include: (1) Development of a team-taught interdisciplinary two-course sequence on research methods/statistics courses that is offered for sophomore students majoring in Biology, Nursing, Mathematics, Computer Science, Environmental Science and Geography, and Exercise and Movement Sciences. During the first course, students working in interdisciplinary research groups complete the first two sections of a research report including the introduction and review of literature. Labs are conducted and instructions on statistical computer programs are also provided. The second course covers additional statistical procedures and computer applications in addition to writing the method, results, and discussions sections of a research report. Labs and research presentations provide student-active learning opportunities. The proposed courses are adapted from undergraduate research courses at several institutions (such as Hampshire College, Portland State University Samford University and Spellman College among others). (2) Faculty development activities include workshops and seminars on student-active learning and the effective use of students in research. (3) The promotion of student involvement in research includes the tracking and encouragement of students who complete the two-course sequence, expansion of paid summer research opportunities, and development of a part-time position to oversee and promote student involvement in research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126435</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vishwa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bhat</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bhatv@wpunj.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Silgailis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>silgailisk@wpunj.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Paterson University</Name>
      <CityName>Wayne</CityName>
      <ZipCode>074702103</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9737292852</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 Pompton Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
