<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Advanced Microscopy Center for Undergraduate Course Development and Improvement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>121388</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nancy J. Pelaez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological Sciences (61)&lt;br/&gt;Recent advances in microscopic techniques have provided scientists with new tools to understand cells and the tissues they comprise. A wide variety of fluorescent labels are now available to study cellular structure and function in both living and preserved cells. In addition, contrast enhancing optics and computerized image analysis provide advanced microscopy tools needed to prepare, observe and analyze the organization and function of tissues and cells. These techniques provide the opportunity to completely reinvent undergraduate courses that involve microscopy (e.g. Functional Histology) in such a way that will provide for cooperative, inquiry-based, learning and critical thinking among all students while giving them an experience in discovery-learning. The knowledge of tissue and cellular architecture thus gained will be particularly important to students planning to enter medical school, graduate school, or work as technicians in most biological laboratories. This project is incorporating these teaching techniques in a centralized advanced microscopy center that provides students with the facility and, through training in microtechniques and image analysis, the skills needed for more critical observation of biological phenomena by using the microscope as a tool of inquiry. In this way students are encouraged to develop research interests and are able to design and evaluate experiments in a scientifically meaningful way. This is being accomplished by incorporating experimentally advanced microscopic techniques across the undergraduate curriculum and in our undergraduate research programs for biology majors. The techniques are adapted from successful programs established at Kent State University (DUE grant # 9551341) and Fort Lewis College (DUE grant # 9980815), both of which have been established through NSF funding. These exemplary programs are being adapted so as to integrate these powerful teaching techniques with advanced microscopy technologies into our curriculum which is being modified for: 1) the establishment of a new "functional histology" course; 2) specific laboratory exercises across the biology curriculum; 3) two faculty workshops on advanced microscopy techniques and modern image analyses; 4) our pre-college teacher training programs and; 5) our academically talented minority high-school program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126505</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reinking</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>larry.reinking@millersville.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cosentino</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james.cosentino@millersville.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Millersville University</Name>
      <CityName>Millersville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>175510302</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7178723820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 1002</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
