<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Undergraduate Experiments in Electron Diffraction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>21741</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Duncan E. McBride</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Physics (13) The Department of Physics &amp; Astronomy has added a laboratory component to its Modern Physics course and moved some experiments from the Experimental Physics Laboratory course to the&lt;br/&gt;Modern Physics course. A capstone research project has also been added for senior physics majors.&lt;br/&gt;As part of these course modifications, the department is adding high-energy&lt;br/&gt;electron diffraction (RHEED) equipment to be used by undergraduate students in a wide variety of&lt;br/&gt;experiments. Experiments adapt and draw from undergraduate labs on diffraction and on research techniques using RHEED to make measurements on materials.&lt;br/&gt;Students who work with the electron diffraction equipment &lt;br/&gt;demonstrate for themselves the wave-like behavior of electrons and also gain valuable hands-on&lt;br/&gt;experience using particles as a probe of the structure of matter. Other more advanced topics that are &lt;br/&gt;covered include the concepts of diffraction and reciprocal space, surface symmetry and order,&lt;br/&gt;and structural differences between amorphous and crystalline solids.&lt;br/&gt;The diffraction equipment complement the real space imaging capabilities of two&lt;br/&gt;scanning probe microscopes already owned by the department. Together the electron diffraction&lt;br/&gt;and scanning probe microscopy experiments make a powerful combination that enable &lt;br/&gt;students to gain a deeper understanding of important fundamental physical ideas like diffraction,&lt;br/&gt;tunneling, and the wave-like nature of matter. Laboratory manuals and supporting materials&lt;br/&gt;developed under this project are shared at regional meetings of the AAPT in addition to being&lt;br/&gt;posted on web sites. Results stemming from undergraduate research is published&lt;br/&gt;separately in appropriate peer-reviewed journals and presented at scientific meetings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0126105</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rioux</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rioux@uwosh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Umlor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>umlor@uwosh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Oshkosh</Name>
      <CityName>Oshkosh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>549013551</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9204241415</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 Algoma Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
