<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CCLI-EMD: Virtual Collaborative Engineering for the Freshman Curriculum</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>74778</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kenneth Lee Gentili</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Engineering - Other (59)&lt;br/&gt;Our project involves the design, implementation, and assessment of a multidisciplinary freshman engineering course. Experience in distributed virtual collaborative engineering is becoming more and more important as the use of advanced communication and information technologies is transforming engineering companies. Our course incorporates e-engineering technologies that model a virtual collaborative engineering environment. Although such e-engineering technologies may be found at the corporate level, graduating students often lack skills and knowledge needed to take advantage of these technologies and this emerging environment. There exists a unique opportunity to create a virtual collaborative engineering course model which leverages on-going academic industry and government initiatives. The goal of our work has been to create a multidisciplinary, project-oriented freshman engineering course. Our course covers the fundamentals of project management, engineering team organization techniques, and problem solving, e-engineering technologies, and application of the above concepts and methodologies to a multidisciplinary project. This project will include design, rapid prototyping, and testing of a product, and is designed to challenge students to move beyond traditionally conceived engineering team toward a virtual collaborative engineering approach by employing the use of e-engineering technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127397</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Derya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jacobs@rmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wswart@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dryer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddryer@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
