<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Network-Based Interactive Laboratory Modules for the Study of Movement Biomechanics, and Coordination and Control</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>131704</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniel Udovic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological Sciences (61)&lt;br/&gt;In science education, laboratory sessions are valuable for reinforcing concepts introduced in&lt;br/&gt;lectures. However, it has become increasingly difficult to acquire equipment, space, and&lt;br/&gt;personnel resources to manage laboratory classes in higher education. The objective of the&lt;br/&gt;project is to develop a set of interactive laboratory modules utilizing a previously developed&lt;br/&gt;Internet-based video digitizing system. The developed modules will allow students to quantify the motion of an object or the human body by acquiring coordinate data from video images. The kinematic parameters resulting from the processing of coordinate data can be used for the learning of basic mechanical concepts and the study of movement coordination and control. Specifically, laboratory modules will be developed for the learning of basic mechanical concepts (e.g., linear and angular kinematics, muscle mechanics) that are usually taught in undergraduate level biomechanics and physics courses. The modules for the learning of concepts in motor coordination and control (e.g., inter-limb coordination, postural control) utilize a multidisciplinary approach, integrating concepts from biology, psychology and engineering. The use of the Web provides students unlimited accessibility in terms of both time (when) and location (where) to complete the laboratories. The modules have applications for distance learning courses and for educational settings where resources for specialized undergraduate laboratories are limited or unavailable. The project provides a unique integration of information technology and education for laboratory environments and the laboratory modules developed will be made available to the public. Teachers/Professors can selectively incorporate some or all of the modules in their courses. This is a collaboartive effort with the University of Florida (DUE 0127338).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127221</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Les</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carlton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lcarlton@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7427</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7427</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
