<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integrating Discrete Mathematics via CS-Complete Examples in a Model CC2001 Curriculum</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>74026</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ernest L. McDuffie</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Computer Science (31)&lt;br/&gt;We are addressing a major issue facing many computer science students, i.e., that they are deficient in mathematics in general and that they do not see the relevance of mathematics to computer science, by integrating discrete mathematics into the first-year computer science curriculum via CS-Complete examples. A CS-Complete example is a problem that covers the topics of representation, problem solving, algorithms, recursion, induction, and data structures. In order to further help with the integration of discrete mathematics into the first year computer science sequence, we are constructing software tools that provide students with an enhanced integrated development environment for Java that enables them to analyze their computer programs (in terms of their correctness and time complexity) while they are creating them.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are two primary goals of this project. First, we are producing a useful software development tool that enhances instruction in the introductory computer science curriculum and is useful for practicing software developers as well. Second, we are producing model first and second course syllabi that cover all of the core topics of the Programming Fundamentals plus over 25% of the core topics of the Discrete Structures, Algorithms and Complexity, and Software Engineering areas of the Computing Curricula 2001 proposal for Computer Science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127483</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bunce</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gbunce@vax2.winona.msus.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gegg-Harrison</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tgeggharrison@winona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oberlin College</Name>
      <CityName>Oberlin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>440741090</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4407758461</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 N. Professor Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7427</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7427</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
