<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Novel Laboratory Based Introduction to Electrical and Computer Engineering for Sophomores</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>304643</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell L. Pimmel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The reviewers found this project to be meritorious. I have read the summary and individual reviews and concur with their assessment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a full development proposal that will develop, evaluate, and disseminate material for an alternative first-course in electrical engineering. In addition to teaching some of the fundamental concepts, the course introduces the discipline and provides a set of experiments in various areas tied to real applications. The applicant has tested a pilot version of the course material with good results and asks for funds to continue their work. The assessment plan is excellent and will address learning outcomes. The dissemination plan involves textbook publishers, letters to other departments, on-line material, and a faculty workshop. He also arranged to have the material tested at North Carolina A &amp; T, a minority institution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The reviewers rated this proposal very highly. They indicated that the existing parts of the new course and labs looked very good and were impressed by the institutional support in the initial development. They noted that the breadth of the material provided an excellent overview and that the labs would be fun for the students. The low cost of the lab modules, the objective nature of the assessment plan, and the quality of the assessment consultants impressed them. They listed the following minor weakness: (1) The applicants should consider adding a minority or open enrollment institution to the project to pilot the material as a way of broadening the user population and increasing diversity in engineering. (2) A seminar or workshop could easily be added to the dissemination plan to facilitate adoption at other universities. (3) A commercial educational equipment supplier should be approached concerning offering the experimental modules fabricated at a reasonable cost, but the publication of the documentation for do-it-your-selfers should not be sacrificed. I contacted the PI and suggested that he consider modifying his project to include work with a minority institution, a faculty workshop, and a possible commercial supplier (see my email dated 10/12/01). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI did followed through on each of the three suggestions as indicated in his email dated 11/27/01 and his FAX dated 11/28/01. He arranged to have North Carolina A &amp; T participate by offering a version of the course in their EE program with a small increase in the budget to support this effort. He added a faculty workshop, again with an increase in the budget to support the participants' travel and so on. Finally, he made arrangements with TCI Works, a nonprofit agency that provides work oriented rehabilitation services for disabled and disadvantaged individuals by providing light, short run electronic assembly, to produce the modules.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a well-written proposal that addresses the nature of the first course in electrical engineering. In place of a rigorous course on circuit theory, the applicants have developed and offered a course that provides an overview of the discipline and laboratory experiences related to several applications. Evaluation results of several pilot offerings were very positive and they want to refine and expand the course material and develop a web-based virtual lab for off-campus use. The evaluation study of the pilot offering was excellent and planned future assessment work is solid. The dissemination plan will be effective.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I recommend funding at the revised level.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127348</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mehmet</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ozturk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mco@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
      <CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7427</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7427</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
