<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Enhancing Mathematics Communication: Creating and Delivering Web-based Homework Problems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149982</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lee L. Zia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Mathematical Sciences (21). This project is adapting and implementing a web-based homework delivery system, WQS, created at the University of Kentucky (UK) under NSF funding (DUE-99542436). First, WQS is being used to deliver extensive sets of homework problems in college algebra, first term calculus, first term calculus lab, and business calculus. The materials are providing assistance for students with weak skills in certain prerequisite topics, as well as help on new course topics. Second, the project is adapting a problem-solving course developed at UK for prospective high school mathematics teachers in which students use the Maple to design web-based problems, posting them on the web via WQS. Finally, the PIs are conducting academic year and summer workshops for college faculty and current high school teachers to design web-based problems and use WQS with their own students. Assessment includes multiple student and faculty surveys and comparative studies to determine the value of WQS for students in university courses by measuring communication between faculty and students, collaboration among students, and improvements in student performance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/10/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127007</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walters</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Terry-Walters@utc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuhn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stephen-kuhn@utc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Chattanooga</Name>
      <CityName>Chattanooga</CityName>
      <ZipCode>374032504</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4234254431</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>615 McCallie Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
