<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Affordable Model Laboratory for Undergraduate Mechanical and Civil Engineering Programs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>74963</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Krishna Vedula</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Engineering - Mechanical (56)&lt;br/&gt;This project is developing fourteen experiments and building seventeen apparatuses for an undergraduate laboratory designed for conducting experiments in Mechanics of Materials and Dynamics of Machinery. The experiments and the apparatus being developed through this project may be utilized as starting points for the new laboratories or used to strengthen the existing laboratories. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Undergraduate students are participating in research, design and development stages of the project in materializing all components of a "Model Laboratory". The project is helping them to improve their skills in working in teams, and their appreciation for cost-effective and superior designs. The outcomes of the project consist of:&lt;br/&gt;1. Developing blueprints for fabrication of apparatuses necessary for precision experimentation in the areas of Mechanics of Materials and Dynamics of Machinery.&lt;br/&gt;2. Creating detailed laboratory manuals for distribution to students.&lt;br/&gt;3. Building a comprehensive plan for putting together an affordable model laboratory that successfully addresses the fundamental requirements of undergraduate laboratories in civil and mechanical engineering as well as engineering technology programs.&lt;br/&gt;4. Enhancing the capabilities of future engineers/educators by involving them in the process of research, design, and development of experiments and equipment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127753</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bijan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sepahpour</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sepahpou@tcnj.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The College of New Jersey</Name>
      <CityName>Ewing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>086280718</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6097713255</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 7718</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
