<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Paleoanthropology of the northern Afar (Danakil) Depression, State of Eritrea</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4950</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark L. Weiss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The anthropologically rich Afar region of East Africa has been a prolific area of research for human origins. The northernmost reaches of the Afar in the newly founded State of Eritrea have been untapped to this point. This award is to undertake fieldwork in the northern Afar. It is important for, 1) understanding the earliest history of humankind in Africa 2) understanding the northernmost range of early human ancestors on the African continent, 3) understanding when and where our species, Homo sapiens left Africa, and 4) understanding the biogeography of humans and our ancestors in one of the worlds most geologically active areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will survey, map and surface collect sites in the northern Afar (Danakil depression) four to five weeks. All specimens will be catalogued and deposited in the National Museum of Eritrea. Description and analysis of fossils and artifacts will take place in Asmara. Rock samples for petrographic and isotope analysis will be transported to the United States and South Africa for analysis. The research team will consist of scientists from the United States, Eritrea and South Africa.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127853</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
      <LastName>Susman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rsusman@uhmc.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1392</Code>
      <Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
