<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Cooperative Research-based Course on Genes and Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>82786</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>V. Celeste Carter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological Sciences (61)&lt;br/&gt;This project is supporting an advanced Laboratory Course in Developmental Genetics. The course provides a cooperative, research-based learning experience that complements upper level lecture courses in genetics, cell biology and developmental biology. The critical reasoning and problem-solving strategies that student are exposed to in this laboratory course are expected to have a broad impact on their overall intellectual development. This laboratory course uses Drosophila and Xenopus, two important model systems for current research, to explore a number of fundamental principles in developmental biology and genetics. Research grade microscopes are used to enhance the students ability to obtain hands-on experience with embryological experimentation in these two biological systems. Digital-imaging equipment is being used for both the purpose of demonstration and for student collection and analysis of experimental results. This laboratory course is adapting exercises in vertebrate experimental embryology from Harvard University (MCB116) and from an EMBO Practical Course in Drosophila Embryology. An important feature of the course is an inquiry-based approach that strongly encourages cooperative learning by the students. This laboratory course is an innovative addition to the curriculum and is helping to formalize a new paradigm for integrating research and education at Stony Brook.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/25/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0127070</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gergen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pgergen@life.bio.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thomsen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gerald.h.thomsen@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
