<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: UNiCAP--Universal Combinatorual Auction Platform</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>105600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jean C. Bonney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is aimed at developing a general platform for conducting combinatorial auctions. It is proposed to develop a bidding language and user interface, along with a system architecture for an integrated combinatorial auction platform that can be used to facilitate combinatorial auctions. The system will provide a wide degree of flexibility in terms of the number of rounds, stopping rules, and bidder and/or object-specific constraints that can be implemented. If successful, this project will lead to a development of a combinatorial auction system that will become a standard part of Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP) systems and will greatly enhance electronic procurement in business-to-business environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Some examples of industries that can benefit from combinatorial auctions include: airport time slots for flights; shipping and transportation companies, as well as the retailers and manufacturers who use these shippers; computer hardware manufacturers, as well as auto manufacturers who can use combinatorial auctions for material procurement; and television networks who can use combinatorial auctions to sell advertising space in TV shows.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/09/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0128588</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Katok</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ekatok@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/09/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Active Decision Support, Ltd.</Name>
      <CityName>Port Matilda</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168709467</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8147775836</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 W. Willowood Ct.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0522400</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
