<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Fabrication of High Temperature/Low RH Catalyst Coated Fuel Cell Membranes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99580</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project is aimed at optimizing the mass-transport properties of the cathode electrode for high temperature (120C), and dry air operation. The overall objective is to fabricate complete catalyst coated membranes utilizing the newly engineered cathode electrode layer, and test the improvements in a high temperature(120C) fuel cell. A second objective is to understand the water and reactant transport mechanisms occurring in the cathode electrode that are limiting the operating temperature and requiring high levels of cathode humidification. &lt;br/&gt; Major benefits could be realized if proton exchange membrane fuel cells could be operated under hotter (&gt; 90C) and drier conditions on the air electrode. Higher operating temperatures allow for an easier system heat rejection and a greater anode tolerance to CO contaminants typically found in reformed hydrocarbon fuel streams. Similar benefits can also be realized in building co-gen applications where a higher temperature.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/08/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/09/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0128026</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grot</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>s.grot@ion-power.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/08/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ion Power, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Bear</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197010000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028329550</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Glasgow Pines Industrial Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
