<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Direct Manufacturing Method for Miniature Medical Components</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99952</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>TIMOTHY J. RUDD</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project will develop a hybrid, co-flow laser material deposition system in order to enhance the ability to fabricate materials with nanocrystalline microstructures and to produce miniature, three dimensional structural components such as dental implants and stents directly from a CAD (Computer Aided Design) solid model. This work will leverage two technologies previously developed by the researchers : (a) Laser Engineered Net Shaping (LENS), and (b) Direct Write Electronics (DWE). The LENS process provides the ability to fabricate large structures directly from a CAD solid model, whereas the DWE process provides the ability to fabricate microelectronic components directly from a CAD representation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal commercial application of this project will be in the field of miniature biomedical components. Additional applications are expected in the field of electronics and defense.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0128606</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Keicher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dkeicher@optomec.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Optomec Design Company</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871095841</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5057618250</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3911 Singer Blvd NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
