<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Germany Cooperative Research: Representation Rings of Finite Groups</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0128969&lt;br/&gt;Boltje&lt;br/&gt;This award supports Robert Boltje and students from the University of California-Santa Cruz in a collaboration with Burkhard Kulshammer of the Department of Mathematics at the University of Jena, Germany. The aim of the international project is to study the structure of various representation rings of finite groups, viz., the ring of monomial representations, the trivial and linear source ring, the Green ring, and other viariants. The results are expected to have applications to generalizations of Brown's theorem on Euler characteristics and to invariants in algebraic number theory, and might also uncover connections to algebraic topology. The work plan provides for extensive participation by graduate students in the international travel and research, and the exchange is intendedto let them benefit from the complementary strengths of both collaborators and to introduce them at an early stage to international collaboration to stimulate further exchange of ideas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0128969</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boltje</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>boltje@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
