<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-France Cooperative Research: Passivity Based Control of Networked Control Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0128656&lt;br/&gt;Spong&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year award supports US-France collaboration in control systems between Mark W. Spong of the University of Illinois and Romeo Ortega of the Signal and Systems Laboratory at SUPELEC, a French center for research in electrical engineering. The objectives are to investigate passive nonlinear control of networked control systems, in particular, systems involving bilateral remote operation (teleoperation) over unreliable communication networks. The problem is motivated by interest in wireless communication in embedded real time control systems and the use of the Internet as a communication medium in teleoperated and networked control systems. The research will advanced understanding of how to design and utilize mobile, intelligent robotic systems with local intelligence for communication over unreliable networks with other robots and human operators. The researchers plan to answer: How sensory, command and control information are shared over such networks and how much local intelligence is needed to guarantee performance and stability when network communications are degraded. The US investigator brings to this collaboration expertise in passivity-based networked control systems. This is complemented by French theoretical expertise in nonlinear control and robotics. Potential applications of their results include work in hazardous and remote environments, surveillance, search, and rescue robots, autonomous vehicles and autonomous locomotion systems, haptic devices, remote construction, and remote surgery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award represents the US side of parallel proposals to the NSF and the CNRS. NSF will cover travel funds and living expenses for the US investigator. The CNRS will support visits by French researchers and graduate students to the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0128656</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mspong@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0107000</Code>
      <Name>Operations Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1518</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL, NETWORKS, &amp; COMP INTE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5980</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5918</Code>
      <Text>FRANCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9196</Code>
      <Text>NATURAL DISASTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
