<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Exploring Complex Biological Concepts in an Interactive 3-D Learning Environment over the Internet</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will catalyze the creation of interactive worlds accessible over the Internet where students, professionals, and consumers can experientially learn scientific concepts not readily accessible to human physical interaction. The specific focus is the construction of a cellular world where University students can explore complex cellular mechanisms, and through customized versions, corporations can educate physicians, researchers and patients on the cellular basis of their products. As a proof of concept, Voyager Interactive has created a demonstration of 3D content delivered over the Internet using narrowband connectivity. This demostration allows students to become" a virus particle and if successful, infect a cell. The student moves within a 3D cellular world, activates viral functions, interacts with objects, and triggers events in the world. A Cellbot companion interacts by voice and by uploading text and figures to assist the student. The content and functionality requirements described in the proposal will be translated into a comprehensive software development plan, which will serve as the blueprint for success in the phase of the research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BioMachine Cellular World proffers a significant contribution to science education and an excellent launch point for custom commercial collaborations. It has prospects for science publishers interested in immersive 3D cellular educational software for use by electronic texts as well as indirect benefits associated with the identification of functional requirements for promoting student active learning in these highly interactive environments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0128213</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seifert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>douglas.seifert@syandus.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syandus, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Exton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>193411149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6103212500</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>760 Constitution Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0108000</Code>
      <Name>Software Development</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1666</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH ON LEARNING &amp; EDUCATI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7256</Code>
      <Text>RSCH IN EDUCATION, POLICY, PRA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7355</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUCTIONAL MATERIALS DEVELP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9180</Code>
      <Text>PUBLIC SCIENCE LITERACY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
