<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Endophyte Mediation of Tri-Trophic Interactions in the Quercus Gambelii</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400006</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan James Tessier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: DEB-01-29630&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: Endophyte Mediation of Tri-Trophic Interaction in Quercus gambelli&lt;br/&gt;PI Name: William J. Boecklen&lt;br/&gt;Institution: New Mexico State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The importance of endophytic fungi (fungi that live within the leaves of plants) in mediating interactions between host plants, insect herbivores, and the natural enemies of herbivores (predators and parasitoids) is poorly understood in natural systems. The proposed research will examine both direct and indirect effects of endophytic fungi on plant herbivore interactions in a southwestern oak (Quercus gambelii) by using a combination of field sampling, chemical analyses, and controlled field experiments. In addition, the influence of environmental variation on the outcome of antagonistic interactions between endophytic fungi and interactions between endophytes and herbivores will be tested using field inoculations of fungal species onto oak hosts. The proposed research will contribute to our understanding of plant-herbivore interactions, and will help identify factors that influence plant susceptibility to herbivore attack. By understanding how herbivores respond to plants bearing endophytic fungi, results of this research will provide important insights into developing new strains of pest-resistant crop plants. In addition, the results of this research will provide background data on the potential use of endophytic fungi as biocontrol agents against insect herbivores.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0129630</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boecklen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wboeckle@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
      <CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
      <ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510102</Code>
      <Name>Role-Terrestrial Ecosystem</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
