<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Germany Cooperative Research: Real-Time Sintering and Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0129176&lt;br/&gt;Groza&lt;br/&gt;This award supports Joanna Groza and students from the University of California-Davis in a collaboration with Eberhart Burkel of the Department of Physics at the University of Rostock, Germany. The aim of the international project is to study field-activated sintering of nanopowders, which occurs under exposure to microdischarges. Technologically, electric field application has distinct benefits, such as enhanced sintering rates, sontrol and production of novel microstructures, and fewer processing steps. The US group has an ongoing research program which has already achieved results on difficult-to-sinter materials. The German group is a leader in the development and improvement of new synchrotron radiation ingvestigation using inelastic scattering of synchrotron radiation with very high resolution. The research will advace our knowledge of field-assisted sintiering, particularly as applied to nanosized powders.. The work plan provides for extensive participation by graduate students in the international travel and research, the work is intended to offer insights into science and engineering education and prepare the students to work in an increasingly interdependent global economy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0129176</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joanna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Groza</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jrgroza@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
