<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Assembly of Wetland Plant Communities along Gradients: An Experimental Study</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>363846</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan James Tessier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: DEB-0129024&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: Assembly of Wetland Plant Communities Along Gradients: An Experimental Study&lt;br/&gt;PI Name: Paul Keddy&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Southeastern Louisiana University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most basic questions in ecology relates to the rules or mechanisms that determine the assembly of species into local communities. Although some hold that physiological limitations of species along environmental gradients determine community composition, others argue that interspecific competition plays a pivotal role in determining the identity of coexisting species. This research addresses such questions through a suite of manipulative experiments. Twelve species of wetland plant, many used in restoration projects, will be combined in controlled experiments along a gradient of water depth. By comparing aspects of growth in the presence or absence of competitors, this research will address two broad topics. First, how much does competition suppress the ecological range of species, and to what extent is it variable and species-specific? Second, is competitive displacement one-sided, and if so what are the quantitative characteristics of this asymmetry? Because this work will take place in a new outdoor classroom that is accessible by K-12 students, it will provide a concrete platform for illustrating the importance and role of research in understanding the ecology and conservation of wetlands.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/18/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0129024</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Keddy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pkeddy@selu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southeastern Louisiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Hammond</CityName>
      <ZipCode>704020001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9855495312</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SLU 10508</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510602</Code>
      <Name>Ecosystem Dynamics</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
