<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Czech Republic Research on Microarray-Based Analysis of Plant Genome Structure.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40448</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cassandra M. Dudka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This U.S.-Czech research project between David Galbraith of the University of Arizona and his counterpart, Jaroslav Dolezel from the Czech Academy of Sciences' Institute of Experimental Botany in Olomouc, features use of flowsorting to selectively enrich populations of individual barley chromosomes. Their intent is to produce fluorescent genomic DNA targets for hybridization of barley DNA microarrays and for fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) analyses of metaphase chromosomes. The total effort benefits from the Arizona team's extensive expertise with microarray technologies and the Czech's expertise in both fluorescence-activated sorting of plant chromosomes and plant chromosome cytology. Research experiences for undergraduate students are an integral part of the research plan. If successful, this work my yield new techniques for mapping single copy genes (i.e. ESTs) on specific plant chromosomes using barley as a model. The researchers also anticipate using the sorted chromosomes for the production of chromosome-specific DNA libraries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This international project in plant genome research fulfills the program objective of advancing scientific knowledge by enabling experts in the Untied States and Central Europe to combine complementary talents and share research resources in areas of strong mutual interest and competence.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0130671</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Galbraith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>galbraith@arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0521400</Code>
      <Name>Plant Productivity</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>CENTRAL &amp; EASTERN EUROPE PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5930</Code>
      <Text>U.S.-CZECHOSLOVAKIA PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9109</Code>
      <Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
