<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Purchase of an HPLC ESI Mass Spectrometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>225242</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090002</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan M. Frye</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With this award from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation and Facilities (CRIF) Program, the Department of Chemistry at the University of California in Irvine will acquire a High Performance Liquid Chromatograph-Electrospray Ionization Mass Spectrometer. This equipment will enhance research in a number of areas including a) the separation and analysis of diastereomeric polysiliconates and the evaluation of affinity supports for the separation of oligonucleotides and small peptides (Shea); b) the synthesis of beta-sheet mimics for protein recognition and function research (Nowick); c) novel strategies and mechanistic studies for natural product synthesis (Overman); d) the synthesis of highly oxygenated macrolide natural products with potential cytotoxic and anti-fungal applications (Rychnovsky); and e) the synthesis of dityrosine and ditryptophan crosslinked peptides as protein structure probes (Van Vranken). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Liquid chromatography with mass spectrometric detection (LC-MS) is an extremely powerful technique used for the separation and analysis of complex mixtures. The research that this instrument will enable will have a significant impact in the areas of biochemistry and pharmaceutical chemistry, among others.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/27/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/27/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0130980</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shea</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kjshea@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/27/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498244768</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5171 California Avenue, Ste 150</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
