<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>National Information Service for Earthquake Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>183541</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project provides for continued development and public access to the national Information Service for Earthquake Engineering (NISEE) at the University of California, Berkeley. The Earthquake Engineering Abstracts database, which will soon reach 100,000 citations of the technical literature, is the premier source of earthquake engineering research literature in the world. The NISEE Software Library of 114 programs in source code has successfully turned a long-term investment in NSF engineering research at universities into an affordable public good for engineering analysis and design. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The grant also supports a workshop designed to review the needs and directions within NSF's evolving George E. Brown, Jr. Network for Earthquake Engineering Simulation (NEES) program. In conjunction with management of NISEE, the PIs will conduct the workshop to identify needs and opportunities in the information environment created by the formation of the NEES collaboratory. The workshop will include representatives from the Science and Engineering Digital Library project at Cornell University, and also managers of curated databases in the physics community (e.g., Lawrence Livermore Laboratory) and industry representatives. The proceedings will include recommendations on needs and future directions in information services in the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0130551</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moehle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>moehle@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fenves</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fenves@ce.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
