<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Role of LEAFY in Reproductive Development in Arabidopsis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350396</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jacqueline Banks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0130804&lt;br/&gt;Wagner&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Role of LEAFY in Reproductive Development in Arabidopsis&lt;br/&gt;The switch from juvenile to reproductive phase occurs in all higher organisms. Control of the proper timing of this switch is vital. In plants the transition from vegetative to reproductive development is also of agronomical importance as seeds, the storage reserves which human sustenance largely depends on, are the product of the reproductive phase. &lt;br/&gt;The transcription factor LEAFY (LFY) is a key regulator of the floral transition, a central step in the switch from vegetative to reproductive development. Later in the reproductive phase LFY controls flower patterning. Despite its central role in these processes, events downstream of LFY are poorly understood. Only two direct targets of LFY are known. Genetic evidence indicates that additional LFY-controlled target genes play critical roles in reproductive development. We will employ genomic molecular approaches to identify these unknown LFY-regulated target genes. The proposal is based on posttranscriptional activation of a LFY fusion protein that allows identification of genes whose expression change rapidly in response to LFY activation. Biological significance of the identified novel LFY-regulated target genes will be investigated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/12/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0130804</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Doris</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wagner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wagnerdo@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
