<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Collaboration and Negotiation in Supply Chain Management and Electronic Commerce; Gainesville, Florida, February 26-27, 2002</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Janet M. Twomey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides partial support for a workshop organized by the University of Florida focusing on research on negotiating strategies and mechanisms in extended enterprises which are spatially and organizationally distributed. The workshop will include a mini-symposium of research papers on the topic, coupled with breakout sessions to identify a future research agenda. The primary goals of the mini-symposium are to bring academic researchers and industry practitioners together to: (1) Characterize the problems and challenges facing leading-edge manufacturing and service firms in the areas of electronic commerce (eCommerce) and supply chain management; (2) Define the state-of-the art technological and decision support capabilities currently available to industry; (3) Identify the new technological and decision support solution capabilities needed for both meeting newly arising challenges faced by industry and for driving new sources of strategic and competitive advantage; and (4) Identify and define academic research opportunities and challenges for developing new technological and decision support solution capabilities sought by industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0131527</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sherman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbai@ise.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Geunes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>geunes@ise.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
