<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Learning From Earthquakes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2796541</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dennis Wenger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>For nearly 30 years, the National Science Foundation has provided support for EERI's Learning from Earthquakes (LFE) Program. These funds have enabled dozens of &lt;br/&gt;multidisciplinary teams of researchers to carry out field investigations of significant &lt;br/&gt;earthquakes throughout the world, to observe and document effects on the natural and&lt;br/&gt;built environment and resulting social, economic and policy impacts. Over the years the&lt;br/&gt;program has generated much new knowledge, leading to changes in practice and stimulating new research in each of the related fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the US leader in post-earthquake investigations, EERI proposes significant&lt;br/&gt;revisions to the LFE program to improve the overall coordination of NSF funded post-earthquake research efforts and to incorporate new technologies to improve the collection and management of perishable data. During the duration of this award, EERI will coordinate post-earthquake investigations and improve the collection of perishable data in the first weeks after the earthquake. Equipment will be acquired to enhance data collection and dissemination, training will be provided to team members, and a new program of small grants for follow up research in each of the disciplines that contribute to fundamental understanding of earthquake impacts will be initiated. The LFE program will be integrated into the new Network for Earthquake Engineering Simulation (NEES). The LFE program will work with other agencies, organizations and NSF funded centers to reach diverse population of young people and students to stimulate their interest and involvement in science and engineering. These and other activities during the five year duration of this award will contribute to a fundamental understanding of the science and practice of earthquake engineering and the reduction of future earthquake losses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0131895</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tubbesing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>skt@eeri.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Earthquake Engineering Research Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Oakland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>946121934</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5104510905</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>499 14th St Suite 220</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
