<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Elementary, Secondary and Informal Education: Research News for Local NBC Newscasts -- A Planning Grant</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49687</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Hyman H. Field</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ScienCentral, with major support from NSF, has been developing and distributing short science stories for inclusion in local ABC news broadcasts. They are now developing a plan, in cooperation with NBC News Channel, to produce stories about cutting edge research to be carried on local NBC stations during their local news broadcasts. During this planning phase, ScienCentral will produce, distribute and evaluate three stories about current research in the area of global climate change. Specific planning tasks include: &lt;br/&gt;determining the technical and editorial processes for working with NBC News;&lt;br/&gt;conducting formative evaluations for topics, format and desired frequency of stories; &lt;br/&gt;and developing an auditable cost sharing process. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Editorial Board for the project includes Eliene Augenbraun, PI/Executive Producer and former research scientist; Besty Rosenfield, Vice President of ScienCentral; Jack Penland, News Director; and Curt Epstein, Senior Producer. They will work closely with an advisory panel consisting of Greg Kohler, Senior Producer, NBC News Channel; Leon Lederman, Office of Strategic Initiative, Illinois Institute of Technology; Jane Lubchenco, Environmental Scientist, Oregon State University; and Danielle Gray, Deputy Director for Emory University Integration of Education and Research, Center for Behavioral Neuroscience. Members of the advisory board will review scripts and roughcuts of all segments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0131424</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eliene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Augenbraun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ea@sciencentral.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Betsy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rosenfield</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>br@stn2.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>ScienCentral Incorporated</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100012505</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2122449577</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>248 W35th St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
