<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>E-Print Archive</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>958798</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Beverly K. Berger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The e-Print Archive has been a major advance in the dissemination of scientific research. It has effectively transformed the research communication infrastructure of multiple fields of physics and other scientific communities. It has been in operation since 1991 and has recently moved its base from Los Alamos National Labs to Cornell University. It has experienced continuous growth and has become in such general use that the APS and the University of California Digital Library have become mirror sites. Other scientific research areas are utilizing the archiving system as well. The number of submissions are over 20,000 per year and the site processes about 3 million transactions per month. The project has positively influenced the process and progress of scientific research and can be credited with many of the innovations in the electronic transfer and sharing of scientific information. It provides rapid access to current research at both larger and smaller research institutions and allows fuller participation in research by developing countries. It represents research at the leading edge of electronic dissemination of scientific information and continues to provide a service of great value to a number of scientific disciplines. Its continued development will have a strong influence on scientific advances in many disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132355</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ginsparg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ginsparg@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
