<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Studies in Physical Organic Chemistry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>242000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With the support of the Organic Dynamics Program in the Chemistry Division, Professor Kenneth B. Wiberg, of the Department of Chemistry at Yale University, will study the nature of the intramolecular interactions that control the structures, energies, spectra and other properties of organic molecules. Through a combination of experimental and theoretical approaches, Professor Wiberg will examine the intramolecular interactions that control the preferred conformations of molecules. Electrostatic interactions in organic molecules will also be studied making use of calculated group dipoles and examining the question of the effective dielectric constant both experimentally and computationally. Studies will also be done examining the nature of electronically excited states for cyclic and open chain alkenes, factors that control optical rotation and, hence, optical activity, and comparing the permanganate oxidation of alkenes with the reaction of alkenes with Cr(IV).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kenneth B. Wiberg, of the Department of Chemistry at Yale University, with the support of the Organic Dynamics Program, studies the properties of organic molecules using the synergistic interaction between experiment and theory to garner a richer detail of information than would be possible using either approach by itself.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132678</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wiberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kenneth.wiberg@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
