<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase II: Autonomous Undersea Systems Network (AUSNET)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>725000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This STTR Phase II project will result in the creation of an advanced network capability to enable ad-hoc networks to operate in a low bandwidth undersea environment. The specific application of the resultant capability will be to support Autonomous Undersea Systems Networks (AUSNET), which are fleets of unmanned robotic vehicles that can provide survey, search, and monitoring functions for customer bases including the oil industry, environmental monitoring, undersea communications infrastructure, search and rescue, and military applications. The capability will build upon the emerging standard Dynamic Source Routing (DSR) protocols to create a network that is entirely self-configuring, bandwidth conserving, and tailored to the unique requirements of cooperative undersea robotic operations. The two technical thrusts of the effort include AUSNET low-level protocol development, and higher level Application Programmer Interface specification and development.&lt;br/&gt; The cooperative Autonomous Undersea Vehicle (AUV) market is emerging and substantial. There are currently 17 companies selling undersea communications devices, each of which is a candidate licensee for AUSNET technology. Near term application of Phase II results is anticipated in Naval applications. Even greater application is to be found in support of offshore undersea operations addressing requirements of the oil industry, communications (undersea cable) installation and maintenance, environmental survey and monitoring, search and rescue operations, and exploration/scientific research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132084</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Benton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbenton@tsinc.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Technology Systems, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Brunswick</CityName>
      <ZipCode>040110000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2077984646</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>14 Maine Street - PMB 41</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maine</StateName>
      <StateCode>ME</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
