<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>New Mexico EPSCoR Infrastructure Award</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6259280</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01120000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>EPSCoR</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Denise M. Barnes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The New Mexico EPSCoR project focuses on natural resource analysis and management and nanoscience. The goal is to strengthen the infrastructure in these two focal areas and remove the barriers to competitive research and to related educational and economic development. Improved computer connectivity and communication among New Mexico's institutions undergirds both focal areas. Six institutions will be participating: University of New Mexico, New Mexico State University, New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology, Eastern New Mexico University, Western New Mexico University, New Mexico Highlands University, San Juan College, and Dine College. In the Natural Resource Analysis and Management area, new faculty in remote sensing/hydrology and forestry in addition to new labs in environmental chemistry and spatial analysis will be featured in the new Institute for Natural Resource Analysis and Management. In Nanoscience, the purchase of high-resolution microscopes and increased connectivity will contribute to the collaborations among the New Mexico campuses and between the campuses and the national laboratories. The Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies, designed as a collaboration between Sandia and Los Alamos National Laboratories and the University of New Mexico, will participate in fostering research collaborations and providing nanoscience education. The Master of Science for Teachers program at New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology will introduce nanoscience and nanotechnology into the curriculum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132632</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gosz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgosz@idaho.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
