<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Brain and Cognitive Effects of Learning a String Instrument</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher T. Kello</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Research has demonstrated structural differences in the brains of musicians compared to non-musicians. However, it is not yet known whether these differences are inborn or develop through long-term stimulation during critical periods of brain development. On the one hand, the brain may be capable of changes not only in functional brain networks, but also in structural components as a response to increased use. On the other hand, the brains of musicians may be atypical prior to training, both anatomically and functionally. If so, becoming a professional musician may be partly genetically predetermined. Research has also demonstrated that music training in children results in long-term enhanced visual-spatial and mathematical performance. The underlying neural basis of such enhancements is unknown. Possible explanations include changes in arousal, mood, and priming of particular brain regions. However, long-term changes in brain function or structure, such as strengthening of existing brain connections or the formation of new connections or even new cells and a more elaborate system of connections, might be induced by learning and practicing on a musical instrument. This pilot longitudinal study will follow young children at the beginning of their music training over a period of three years and compare them to a control group of children matched in gender, SES, handedness, age, and overall IQ.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using high-resolution MR images within subjects over time, the research will begin to answer questions such as the following: Does the amount of instrumental practice correlate with structural brain differences and/or do levels of musical talent/skill predict structural brain differences either prior to or as a consequence of training? Is visual-spatial and mathematical reasoning enhanced by music training? If so, are these non-musical cognitive outcomes related to amount of time spent practicing, degree of improvement in reading music notation, and/or level of musical talent/skill? Do gains in visual-spatial and mathematical reasoning, if found, correlate with structural brain enhancements over the course of musical training?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research has potential far-reaching implications. First, children often begin music study at an age when the brain is at a critical phase of development and maturation. If structural brain changes or use-dependent brain growth occur, it would have important implications for early childhood education. Second, the results might help to explain why certain children succeed and others fail in mastering musical instruments. Third, demonstrating improvements in domains other than music as a function of music training would have strong implications for both general and music educational practice. Fourth, this research will provide testable hypotheses about the neural basis of transfer effects. Transfer is a key issue in educational theory, and has not only applied value but also theoretical value, since a demonstration of transfer helps us to understand how mental capacities are organized and related to one another.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132508</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Winner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>winner@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gottfried</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schlaug</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gschlaug@bidmc.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</Name>
      <CityName>Boston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>022155491</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6176674208</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>330 Brookline Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
