<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: A Source for High Rate Growth of Gallium Nitride Films</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>493649</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II Project will develop a neutral, high flux/fluence nitrogen atom beam source for application to the high rate growth of III-V nitride semi-conducting materials over large areas. The proposed source is based on proprietary MID-JET technology. This technology employs an electrode-less discharge contained by vortex flow, rather than a dielectric tube commonly used in traditional sources. MIDJET technology utilizing a temperature of 5000 C to produce1021 nitrogen atoms has been demonstrated. This is 2-3 orders of magnitude higher than that generated by currently available sources. It is particularly applicable to Metal Organic Chemical Vapor Deposition (MOCVD) systems, where it will allow both high growth rate and the elimination of the use of ammonia. The MIDJET will be adapted for use in a MOCVD reactor and a demonstration made of the system's ability to grow gallium nitride at a rate of at least 10 microns per hour. &lt;br/&gt; This project will develop a charge-free, high flux/fluence nitrogen atom beam for the growth of III-V nitride materials which can replace existing plasma-based tools. With higher growth rates of high quality material over larger areas, systems based on the MIDJET will have with application to the fabrication of high power/high temperature semiconductor devices and blue illumination sources (including those for flat panel displays).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132055</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Read</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>read@psicorp.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/07/2004</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Willi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schwarz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schwarz@psicorp.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Physical Sciences Incorporated (PSI)</Name>
      <CityName>ANDOVER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>018101077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5086890003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>20 NEW ENGLAND BUS CTR DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
