<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: INVESTIGATING ELECTROSTATIC DISCHARGE PROTECTION IN ULSI ICs DOWN TO NANO-SCALE: SIMULATION, MODELING &amp; EXPERIMENTS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>404184</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pradeep P. Fulay</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Electrostatic Discharge (ESD) failure is a devastating reliability problem &lt;br/&gt;to VDSM (very-deep-sub-micron) and nano-scale Si ULSI IC technologies. &lt;br/&gt;It is imperative to investigate ESD failure fundamentals and on-chip ESD&lt;br/&gt; protection theories focusing on the following challenges: 3D mixed-mode &lt;br/&gt;ESD simulation methodology; accurate high-current ESD modeling; whole-chip &lt;br/&gt;ESD design synthesis, advanced ESD protection solutions for ULSI ICs, ESD&lt;br/&gt;protection for super-GHz RF ICs, ESD protection for nano-scale as well &lt;br/&gt;as wide-bandgap semiconductor IC technologies. The PI proposes a &lt;br/&gt;career development plan that addresses these challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposed research activities consist of six tasks: to investigate &lt;br/&gt;advanced on-chip ESD protection phenomena in ULSI ICs by developing a novel &lt;br/&gt;3D mixed-mode ESD simulation methodology; to investigate ESD &lt;br/&gt;protection fundamentals by developing accurate high-current ESD device &lt;br/&gt;models; to develop a full-chip ESD design verification CAD tool called &lt;br/&gt;ESDcat; to explore novel ultra-fast ESD protection solutions for &lt;br/&gt;sub-100nm ULSI ICs, to explore ESD protection for future nano-technologies, &lt;br/&gt;and to extend ESD research to super-GHz RF ICs and wide-bandgap &lt;br/&gt;semiconductor, GaN. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since ESD phenomena are geometry-dependent involving complex&lt;br/&gt; electro-thermal-process-device-circuit coupling, the proposed &lt;br/&gt;research procedures take full-scale mixed-mode approaches that investigate &lt;br/&gt;ESD fundamentals in a fully-coupled process-device-circuit-electronic-thermal&lt;br/&gt; closed-loop in 3D format. A 3D parallel ESD model network is proposed &lt;br/&gt;for accurate high-current ESD modeling. ESDcat enables chip level ESD &lt;br/&gt;synthesis and verification at both schematic and layout levels. Nano-scale &lt;br/&gt;ESD research will take into account the ballistic phonon scattering &lt;br/&gt;effect. ESD for wide-bandgaps will focus on Si-compatible GaN ICs. &lt;br/&gt;End results include insights into ESD mechanisms, CAD tools for further &lt;br/&gt;investigation and design of ESD protections for various IC technologies, &lt;br/&gt;e.g., CMOS, BiCMOS, SOI, SiGe, GaN, RFIC, and Cu interconnects. Both &lt;br/&gt;new ESD theory and immediate industrial applications are expected.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The education plan centers on: new curriculum development; integration &lt;br/&gt;of microelectronics research and education; student mentoring and &lt;br/&gt;community services; and university-industry collaboration. Specifically,&lt;br/&gt; activities include: develop five courses/labs in a five-year period; &lt;br/&gt;pursue an improved microelectronics teaching approach; establish an &lt;br/&gt;Integrated Electronics Laboratory, a Virtual IC Fab facility, and &lt;br/&gt;TCAD/ECAD Design Studios; advising students in conducting &lt;br/&gt;inter-professional projects; develop a undergraduate industrial &lt;br/&gt;co-op program; and involving minority/women students in microelectronics&lt;br/&gt; research. This five-year education proposal is integrated into &lt;br/&gt;the departmental redevelopment plan in microelectronics</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/13/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/12/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132869</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Albert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aw@ee.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
