<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Development of New Olefin Metatheses-Based Processes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>369000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kenneth M. Doxsee</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this work is to expand the scope and utility of olefin metathesis reactions. In an expansion of the PI's prior work, the types of olefins that can be used in cross metathesis reactions will first be investigated. Intermolecular cross metatheses of functionalized and cyclic olefins will be studied and the incorporation of allenes and alkynes into ring opening metatheses will be investigated. Secondly, metathesis based isomerization reactions will be developed and novel skeletal rearrangements of polyolefinic ring systems using this approach will be effected. Ruthenium catalyzed enantioselective metathesis isomerizations will be explored in addition to the sequential coupling of metathesis reactions with Kharasch reactions to build more complicated structures in a single reaction flask.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Dr. Marc L. Snapper of the Department of Chemistry at Boston College. Dr. Snapper will explore the scope and utility of olefin metathesis reactions. Olefin metathesis is an industrially important process used to make a number of specialty chemicals and starting materials for pharmaceutical syntheses from petroleum feedstocks. Developing shorter, more environmentally friendly routes to specialty chemicals (which are catalytic in metals used to effect the bond forming metathesis reactions) is one likely outcome of the proposed work. Students trained during the course of this work will gain skills needed by the pharmaceutical as well as specialty chemical industries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0132221</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Snapper</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Snapper@BC.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Boston College</Name>
      <CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
