<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Third U.S.-Japan Workshop on Design for Wind and Wind Hazard Mitigation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36342</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas A. Foutch</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is for the support of the third joint workshop of Task Committee D (Wind Engineering) of the U.S.-Japan Cooperative Program on Natural Resources (UJNR). This workshop is an ongoing effort of the UJNR Panel on Wind and Seismic Effects to bring together U.S. and Japanese researchers from academic institutions, government laboratories and industry to discuss the state-of-the-art of wind effects on civil engineering structures and develop strategies and collaborative efforts that will benefit both countries. The theme of this workshop is "Reducing Losses from Wind: Collaborative Opportunities for the 21st Century" and it will be held in Seattle, U.S. on October 2-5, 2002. The purpose of this workshop is to (a) discuss previous collaborative research efforts, (b) continue mutual exchange of technical information on ongoing research, (c) identify collaborative opportunities for the 21st century and develop strategic planning that will benefit both the countries, (d) identify specific projects for collaborative research, and (e) visit selected sites in the Seattle area related to wind effects on structures.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0133410</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Partha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sarkar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ppsarkar@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
