<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Systematic Design Space Exploration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375130</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Chitaranjan Das</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project involves the research, development, and dissemination of techniques and tools necessary to perform rigorous, systematic processor design-space exploration. The key element is a framework in&lt;br/&gt;which architectural simulators and targeted compilers are automatically derived from a common architectural description, providing architects, microarchitects, and compiler developers with a&lt;br/&gt;dynamic, yet coherent, environment within which to design processor systems. Such a system would enhance productivity and design quality by tightening the loop between architectural decision-making and&lt;br/&gt;realistic performance feedback and by allowing for more productive collaboration among the members of a prototyping team. The resulting reduction in design cycle times will counter increasingly restrictive&lt;br/&gt;market pressures, safeguarding the practicality of designing both new general-purpose microprocessors and application-specific processors (ASIPs), such as those found in networking hardware, cellular&lt;br/&gt;telephones, and next-generation digital devices. Additionally, this research will provide invaluable experiences for both undergraduate and graduate students in computer architecture and compilers. This&lt;br/&gt;same system is an ideal mechanism by which students can interact with tangible examples of computer architecture and compiler concepts -- it will allow them to rapidly prototype systems, experiment with new ideas, and thereby build intuition about computer systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/15/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0133712</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>August</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>august@cs.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
