<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Practical Language-Based End-to-End Security</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>349999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Almadena Y. Chtchelkanova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Increasingly, confidential information is placed on network-accessible&lt;br/&gt;computers by organizations and individuals, yet neither the current&lt;br/&gt;practice nor theories of computer security are adequate to ensure that&lt;br/&gt;this information remains confidential. The lack of sound mechanisms&lt;br/&gt;for protecting confidential information, especially in the presence of&lt;br/&gt;malicious code or hosts, creates serious privacy, liability, and even&lt;br/&gt;national security concerns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research explores new security mechanisms that provide stronger,&lt;br/&gt;end-to-end assurance that data remains confidential. The focus is on&lt;br/&gt;three important areas where existing models are inadequate and existing&lt;br/&gt;enforcement methods are impractical. First, confidentiality must&lt;br/&gt;be protected even in systems that include both mutually distrusting&lt;br/&gt;principals and untrusted, possibly malicious hosts. Second, concurrent&lt;br/&gt;and distributed systems create new challenges for information flow&lt;br/&gt;control. Third, new techniques are needed for verifying that binary&lt;br/&gt;code, including legacy code, protects confidential information.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this work is fast, practical, end-to-end assurance of&lt;br/&gt;confidentiality for decentralized systems with mutual distrust. This&lt;br/&gt;kind of assurance promises to significantly strengthen the security of&lt;br/&gt;the emerging computing infrastructure.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/28/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/12/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0133302</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Myers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>myers@cs.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
