<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Automatically Generating Specifications to Improve Program Correctness and Maintainability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CCR-0133580&lt;br/&gt;CAREER: Automatically Generating Specifications to Improve Program Correctness and Maintainability&lt;br/&gt;Michael D. Ernst&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ensuring software correctness, modifying software, and many other software&lt;br/&gt;engineering tasks are greatly eased by the presence of specifications that&lt;br/&gt;document program behavior. Unfortunately, specifications are usually&lt;br/&gt;absent, leading to problems with program understanding and maintenance.&lt;br/&gt;This research extends work in automatically generating (inferring) partial&lt;br/&gt;program specifications from program executions. The research goals are to&lt;br/&gt;detect conditional invariants (implications) that are true only sometimes,&lt;br/&gt;to scale the technology, to enable online processing, to investigate new&lt;br/&gt;inference strategies, to improve usability, to evaluate via experiments and&lt;br/&gt;case studies, to integrate the techniques and tools into education, and to&lt;br/&gt;transfer technology to industry. The research has three broad impacts: (1)&lt;br/&gt;it explains, advances, and evaluates the theory and practice of automatic&lt;br/&gt;generation of program specifications; (2) it enables easier, more&lt;br/&gt;effective, and broader use of specifications, by automating generation of&lt;br/&gt;partial specifications and by extending their scope to likely (as opposed&lt;br/&gt;to guaranteed) properties; and (3) it applies specifications to specific&lt;br/&gt;program tasks via new techniques and tools for program modification,&lt;br/&gt;testing, reuse, and documentation. Evaluation includes theoretical&lt;br/&gt;evaluations of the accuracy of the underlying techniques, case studies of&lt;br/&gt;substantial software projects, and controlled experiments to determine the&lt;br/&gt;efficacy of the resulting tools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0133580</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ernst</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mernst@cs.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>2880</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE ENGINEERING AND LANGU</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
