<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Scaling Plant Life History, Ontogeny, Diversity, and Ecology: Elaboration of a General Model</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>520000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan James Tessier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>One of the central problems facing biology is to identify the general&lt;br/&gt;principles that govern the evolution of form, function and diversity.&lt;br/&gt;Adding to this problem is the complexity of connecting pattern and process&lt;br/&gt;across several scales of biological organization. The career development&lt;br/&gt;plan will allow for the development of a rigorous integrative training&lt;br/&gt;program in biological scaling at the University of Arizona. The proposed&lt;br/&gt;research program consists of two parts: 1) Expand a general allometric&lt;br/&gt;framework to account for patterns of ontogenetic growth across vascular&lt;br/&gt;plants. This focus will provide theoretical extensions and empirical&lt;br/&gt;assessments of allometric theory to account for patterns of ontogenetic&lt;br/&gt;growth and allocation across vascular plants; 2) Extend theoretical&lt;br/&gt;framework to quantitatively predict how physiological aspects of plants&lt;br/&gt;and variation in allocation and growth rate ramify to influence numerous&lt;br/&gt;attributes of large-scale dynamics in ecological communities and&lt;br/&gt;ecosystems. This line of investigation is geared toward: (i) documenting&lt;br/&gt;prominent scaling laws associated with the production and allocation of&lt;br/&gt;biomass across ecological communities; (ii) elucidating how the&lt;br/&gt;constraints of plant allometry influences the size structuring and&lt;br/&gt;dynamics of ecological communities; and (iii) highlighting a novel theory&lt;br/&gt;for the movement of resources and energy through ecosystems. The&lt;br/&gt;multifaceted research proposed will combine elaboration of allometric&lt;br/&gt;theory, the compilation of large global datasets, and experimental&lt;br/&gt;greenhouse manipulations to assess the quantitative predictions of new&lt;br/&gt;theoretical insights. The proposed research will contribute to a&lt;br/&gt;significant advancement in our ability to mechanistically predict the&lt;br/&gt;scaling of pattern and process in biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0133974</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Enquist</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>benquist@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510203</Code>
      <Name>Model Validation</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510301</Code>
      <Name>Structure &amp; Function</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1128</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL CLUSTER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1196</Code>
      <Text>LONG-TERM RSCH IN ENVIR BIO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1196</Code>
      <Text>LONG-TERM RSCH IN ENVIR BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
