<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Intelligent Based Performance Enhancement Control of Micropower Energy Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>380997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dagmar Niebur</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An advanced renewable based distributed power generation system is required for&lt;br/&gt;the next age of the alternative energy market. Improved and dependable systems&lt;br/&gt;for energy conversion, energy storage requires power quality demands and&lt;br/&gt;compatibility with distributed energy systems, also called by microgrid or&lt;br/&gt;micropower energy systems. An intelligent-based control methodology must be&lt;br/&gt;developed to optimize the microgrid system requirements, aiming convergence of&lt;br/&gt;adaptive, parameter insensitive and on-line learning capabilities. This research&lt;br/&gt;project is concerned with three main issues (1) small distributed generation&lt;br/&gt;prototype development of a high frequency ac link (HFAC) microgrid system, (2)&lt;br/&gt;analysis and modeling of behavior interactions and architecture management and&lt;br/&gt;(3) intelligent control applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Power electronic systems will be designed to connect distributed sources to the&lt;br/&gt;HFAC. Intelligent control techniques will be developed to implement capabilities&lt;br/&gt;of learning by sensing the environment in order to reach its objective of&lt;br/&gt;optimum power operation, automatic functioning, self-monitoring and&lt;br/&gt;self-checking of failures and detection/recovery for efficient user interface. A&lt;br/&gt;behavior based hierarchic control capable to generate set-points for optimal&lt;br/&gt;neural network controllers based on Adaptive Critic Design will be developed.&lt;br/&gt;An educational plan is focused to leverage the interdisciplinary mission of the&lt;br/&gt;Engineering Division at Colorado School of Mines. It is proposed the development&lt;br/&gt;of educational material will be developed to allow students to have experience&lt;br/&gt;in studying theoretical foundations of intelligent control systems,&lt;br/&gt;understanding their functional operation through the use of computer for&lt;br/&gt;simulation in promising research directions. The five-year, integrated&lt;br/&gt;development plan encompasses research, education and outreach activities in&lt;br/&gt;order to incorporate intelligent control techniques for performance improvement&lt;br/&gt;of distributed energy systems used in residential and small business&lt;br/&gt;applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134130</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marcelo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Simoes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>msimoes@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
      <CityName>Golden</CityName>
      <ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0306000</Code>
      <Name>Energy Research &amp; Resources</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
