<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Mechanics of Microstructural Development at Crystal Surfaces: Micro- and Nano-scale Modeling and Simulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Clark V. Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This CAREER project develops a multiscale approach to modeling and simulation of microstructural development in epitaxial thin films. The energetics and kinetics of surface steps and their interactions with lattice dislocations will be investigated. To capture features&lt;br/&gt;over a wide range of length scales, three modeling methodologies, atomistic, micromechanical, and continuum, will be utilized. Models suited for larger length scale simulations will be built from their smaller length scale counterparts, while retaining relevant physics. This approach is critical to engineering structures of interest for current and emerging micro- and nano-technologies, which are too large to model directly using atomistic approaches, but small enough that atomic-level phenomena have a large role in determining behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The education component builds on the PI's current activities to address the needs of high school, undergraduate, and graduate students and local industries. Specific initiatives include&lt;br/&gt;instruction and assistance to high school teachers on the principles of engineering and developing events and programs designed to promote participation and inclusiveness in the ASME student section at Stony Brook. A high school outreach program to underrepresented minority students will be developed together with the students of ASME and the minority engineering student organizations at Stony Brook. In addition to attracting minorities to engineering, the program is intended to teach leadership and organization skills to participating&lt;br/&gt;students and to convey a sense of duty for community service.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134123</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kukta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robert.kukta@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1633</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
