<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Elementary, Secondary and Informal Education: Behind the Screen Traveling Exhibition Tour Extension</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>219510</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Valentine H. Kass</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The American Museum of the Moving Image is refurbishing the traveling exhibit, "Behind the Screen: Making Motion Pictures and Television." The exhibit, which focuses on the science and technology underlying movies and television, opened at the World Financial Center in New York City and subsequently traveled to the Kulturhuset in Stockholm, Sweden and the Technisches Museum in Vienna, Austria. It currently is at the Exploratorium in San Francisco and is scheduled to travel to COSI Toledo, Ohio in October 2001. The American Museum of the Moving Image has requests for the exhibit from the Science City, Kansas City; the Franklin Institute, Philadelphia; and the Museum of Science, Boston. However, in order for the exhibit to travel to venues beyond the Exploratorium, it needs to be refurbished and upgraded. This grant provides the funds for the exhibit to remain viable and to travel to additional venues.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134680</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rochelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Slovin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rslovin@movingimage.us</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Museum of the Moving Image</Name>
      <CityName>Astoria</CityName>
      <ZipCode>111061226</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7187844520</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>36-01 35th Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
