<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Systematic Multiscale Modeling of Directed Assembly in Semiconductor Materials Processing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patrick E. Phelan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: CTS-0134418&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Talid Sinno&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Affiliation: University of Pennsylvania&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: CAREER: Systematic Multiscale Modeling of Directed Assembly in Semiconductor Materials Processing&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to develop a synergistic modeling framework, from continuum level through atomistic simulation, to improve the understanding of diffusion reaction, and species aggregation during electronic materials processing. The creation of novel structures at length scales smaller than those available from traditional top-down fabrication methods requires a detailed atomistic understanding of the physics and chemistry governing multicomponent processes. This understanding must be linked also to macroscopic scale process operating conditions. Potential application areas that can benefit from such a paradigm include atomistic scale control of bulk dopant and defect distribution in silicon microelectronics, defect control in other electronic materials such as SiC, SiGe, and GaAs, and controlled deposition of multilayered structures for advanced optoelectronic materials. A close coupling of the analytical framework against available experimental results will be included in the research program. A primary goal of the educational component of the project will be to introduce electronic materials processing into the curriculum choices for chemical engineering majors, particularly at the University of Pennsylvania, to increase the number of those graduates who move into this important industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134418</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Talid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sinno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>talid@seas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
