<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Variable Temperature Electric Force and Magnetic Resonance Force Microscopy Studies of Organic Electronic Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499405</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project aims to develop new leading-edge instrumentation as tools for advancing the understanding of chemical and physical mechanisms of doping and charge conduction in organic conductors and semiconductors. The goal is to enhance the ability to quantify and image surface charge since the detecting charge with better than single electron sensitivity over a wide range of temperatures and pressures will significantly advance the science and engineering of organic device fabrication. Another goal is to explore the possibilities for measuring sub-femto Newton forces and ultimately single-molecule nuclear magnetic resonance imaging by force microscopy. The educational goals include exploring the integration of this research with chemistry-based materials science directed to training undergraduates, particularly engineers, and for outreach to Kindergarten through grade 12 students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The development of all silicon technology hinges upon the inherently low charge trap density at the silicon / silicon dioxide interface. The presence of interface charge traps in organic devices has seriously retarded the development of high-efficiency organic transistor type devices. Designing and using tools that can be used to characterize and remove these charge traps will be crucial to the commercialization of organic based devices. Students trained in these areas will compete very effectively for job opportunities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134956</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marohn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jam99@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
