<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Enabling Nanoscale Science and Devices Using Selective Biomolecular-inorganic Interactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>94671</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Advanced Materials Program in the Division of Chemistry makes this Career award to University of Central Florida. With this award, Professor Deron Walters will study interaction of peptides with carbon nanotubes (CNT) and will build nanomaterials from bottom up. These studies will involve selecting nanotube-binding peptides, studying electronic effects of peptide binding to individual tubes, and linking tubes together with bifunctional binding/structural peptide units. Modification of electronic properties and nanopatterning of CNT surfaces by Atomic Force Microscopy will also be carried out with this award. Two- and three-dimensional assembly and chiral separation of CNT-peptide complexes planned with this award will be helpful for successful development of electronic devices, circuits and sensors. The PI, with the departmental support, will provide innovative approaches to teach quantum mechanics courses to undergraduate students at University of Central Florida. In addition, principles and behavior of the nanoscale world will be made available to the public, and precollege teachers and students through the Orlando Science Center. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Interaction of peptides with carbon nanotubes (CNT) and nanopatterning of CNT surfaces by Atomic Force Microscopy will be carried to build nanomaterials from bottom up. These studies will involve selecting nanotube-binding peptides, studying electronic effects of peptide binding to individual tubes, and linking tubes together with bifunctional binding/structural peptide units. Modification of electronic properties and nanopatterning of CNT surfaces, two- and three-dimensional assembly and chiral separation of CNT-peptide complexes will be helpful for successful development of electronic devices, circuits and sensors. Innovative approaches will be used to teach quantum mechanics courses to undergraduate students at University of Central Florida. In addition, nanoscale science will be made available to the public, and precollege teachers and students through the Orlando Science Center.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134950</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walters</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dwalters@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078821120</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1984</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS SYNTHESIS &amp; PROCESSN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1984</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS SYNTHESIS &amp; PROCESSN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9239</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
