<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Glycolipid Interactions In Myelin</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>464000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Amit Basu, of the Department of Chemistry at Brown University, is supported by the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program for his studies of glycolipid interactions in myelin. In the research portion of the career plan, carbohydrate-carbohydrate interactions between glycolipids are identified as the object of exploration. Interactions between the carbohydrate portions of membrane glycolipids mediate the compaction of the myelin sheath, adhesion of a variety of cancer cells, and also initiate signal transduction pathways in certain instances. This proposal outlines a new approach for detailed characterization of carbohydrate-carbohydrate recognition using the interaction present in myelin as a model system. Professor Basu will prepare carbohydrate containing liposomes as well as self-assembled monolayers as cell surface mimics of glycolipids. The monolayers will be used to obtain information about how carbohydrate structure affects monolayer morphology and its recognition properties. The second stage of the project will use chemical mutagenesis to identify individual binding interactions in the associated carbohydrates. Each type of mutation provides a unique probe of the nature of the native binding interaction. These mutants will be incorporated into monolayers and their effect on monolayer architecture and recognition will be examined. Finally, detailed experiments are designed to correlate glycolipid structure with membrane morphology and recognition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The teaching portion of this proposal focuses on methods for introducing research into the undergraduate curriculum. The class will be introduced to research through the exclusive use of the primary literature for course readings. Students will develop the skills necessary to interpret and critically evaluate information that is presented in research articles. In the course of doing so, they will begin to identify key features and limitations in experimental methods and design. This will lead them to consider new experiments that might be performed. Therefore, with the support of the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program, Professor Amit Basu, of the Department of Chemistry at the Brown University will use an integrated approach to teaching and research, that is, the methodology of research will be incorporated into the undergraduate curriculum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/29/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134908</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amit</FirstName>
      <LastName>Basu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amit_basu@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1944</Code>
      <Text>BIMOLECULAR PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
