<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: The Coordinated Theory and Experiments of the Fundamental Metal Oxidation Kinetics As Visualized By In Situ UHV_TEM</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>506250</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Harsh Deep Chopra</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project aims in applying in-situ transmission electron microscopy under ultra high vacuum conditions to develop a fundamental understanding of the oxidation processes at the nanoscale. Major objectives of the proposed study is to develop better understanding of the nanoscale stages of oxidation from the nucleation of the metal oxide to the formation of thermodynamically stable oxide. Systematic experimental studies will be made on thin films of copper and aluminum. The project involves collaborations with the Materials Research Laboratory at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC), Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory (LLNL) and the Institute for Materials Research and Engineering (IMRE), Singapore where a specialized in situ chamber for Al thin film deposition inside the UHV-TEM exist. This research has technological relevance where surface oxidation processes play critical roles in environmental stability, high temperature corrosion, electrochemistry, catalytic reactions, gate oxides and thin film growth as well as fuel reactions. The educational component incorporates the research tools developed in the project in the development of new courses at both the undergraduate and graduate levels in materials science and engineering (MS&amp;E) curriculum as well as a new web site accessible for public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research develops a new understanding of the fundamental processes involved in nanoscale oxidation on thin metals that would have direct relevance in technologies where corrosion is the limiting factor.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/15/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134719</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>judyyang@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
