<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Integration of Research and Education in the Study of Analysis and Partial Differential Equations in Carnot-Caratheodory Spaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joe W. Jenkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;--------&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research component of this proposal deals with the study of &lt;br/&gt;solutions to certain non-linear systems of Partial Differential&lt;br/&gt;Equations which arise in connections with the geometry of &lt;br/&gt;Carnot-Caratheodory spaces. More precisely, we will study the &lt;br/&gt;sharp regularity of solutions to quasilinear subelliptic &lt;br/&gt;systems, and apply the results to the theory of quasi-regular &lt;br/&gt;maps in Carnot groups and in more general spaces. &lt;br/&gt;We will study critical points of the energy for maps with &lt;br/&gt;target in the Heisenberg group and with domain in a Riemannian &lt;br/&gt;manifold or in the Minkowski space.&lt;br/&gt;The analysis of boundary value problems for sub-elliptic &lt;br/&gt;operators, and the study of qualitative and quantitative &lt;br/&gt;properties of solutions of some non-divergence form non-linear &lt;br/&gt;equations, are also part of this proposal.&lt;br/&gt;The educational component of this proposal is centered around &lt;br/&gt;the creation of Integrated Research Groups, in which &lt;br/&gt;undergraduate and graduate students work on basic research &lt;br/&gt;projects supervised by the PI. One of thegoals of this &lt;br/&gt;activity is the dissemination of information, through a &lt;br/&gt;web-based data-base, seminars, and publications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partial differential equations are used to provide a &lt;br/&gt;mathematical model for real-life phenomena, such as &lt;br/&gt;chemical reactions, force-fields or conductivity. Such models&lt;br/&gt;allow both to better understand the phenomena and to try to &lt;br/&gt;forecast the future behavior of the system under study. &lt;br/&gt;Roughly speaking, smooth solutions to PDE's correspond to &lt;br/&gt;systems which can be well understood and modeled. The study &lt;br/&gt;of regularity of solutions consists in finding smooth solutions.&lt;br/&gt;The equations described in this proposal appear in the study of&lt;br/&gt;motion under constraints (as in Robot arms motion),&lt;br/&gt;and in the study of diffusion in a non isotropic media.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0134318</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Capogna</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lcapogna@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
      <CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
