<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research Symposium: Some Next-Generation Leaders in Science and Technology Policy Workshop (November 2002)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49188</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rachelle D. Hollander</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A symposium gathers together outstanding scholars, analysts, and practitioners in science and technology policy who are within seven years of their PhDs. It provides an opportunity to meet and exchange ideas and to present their work to a high-level (senior) audience. This research symposium is oriented toward eight theme tracks in science and technology policy: &lt;br/&gt;New history of science and technology policy.&lt;br/&gt;R&amp;D program analysis and evaluation &lt;br/&gt;Expertise, advice, assessment, and evaluation&lt;br/&gt;Science, technology, and human needs and values&lt;br/&gt;Science, technology, and international issues&lt;br/&gt;Science education, human resources, and workforce&lt;br/&gt;Science and technology policy institutions and processes&lt;br/&gt;Science, technology, and the public. &lt;br/&gt;Proposals for these tracks were broadly solicited and peer reviewed for acceptance. Accepted authors were funded to attend the workshop held in Washington, DC. Senior scholars and practitioners served as discussants. The new scholarship presented and the interaction among academics and practitioners have the potential to improve policy and programs and to benefit education in science and technology policy in a variety of ways. An edited book containing the presented papers will be published.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0135170</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guston</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.guston@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7915</Code>
      <Text>Ethics &amp; Values of SET</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9139</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
