<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Informatics of Human and Monkey Brain Atlases</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Interagency Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosanna Guadagno</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Jones, Edward G.&lt;br/&gt;0135396&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Human Brain Project will extend our previous efforts in developing an information system that can store, manipulate and retrieve large datasets compiled by the collaborating investigators. The project is built around and designed to manage data obtained from high resolution human and monkey brain atlases, molecular and cellular mapping studies, morphometry and physiology of retinal and thalamic cells, and studies of brain connections. There is an Administrative Core responsible for oversight, evaluation and dissemination and 4 Research Projects that will collect data and interact in visualization and databasing. Project 1 will design and integrate informational methods that integrate graphical and non-graphical datasets derived from Projects 2-4 and, using the lateral geniculate nucleus as a model, will develop software tools for building and maintaining neuroscience specific databases, for linking the diverse information sets derived from Projects 2--4 to one another, and for network retrieval and interchange of information from these and other neuroscience datasets. Project 2 will use computer assisted microscopy to build high resolution digital atlases of human and monkey brains, extending cytoarchitecture to quantify neuronal populations in the major nuclei of the thalamus (including in normal, schizophrenic and manic depressive human brains), and their profile of receptors and chemically defined cells and afferent fiber systems. This project incorporates a strong Visualization Component made up of computer scientists who have expertise in storage, manipulation and display of large datasets. It will populate a central NeuroImage Repository and, working in close conjunction with the other projects, will develop software tools for manipulating, graphically displaying and browsing the high resolution histological and neurochemical brain atlases, starting with the lateral geniculate database, and for distributing simplified images using Internet methodologies. Project 3 will expand a database of retinal cells characterized by morphology, chemistry, physiology and connectivity that provides the model for, and input to the lateral geniculate database. Project 4 will develop a database of monkey visual thalamo- and cortico-cortical connections for integration with the lateral geniculate database, using a newly developed pulvinar database as a model.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0135396</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koslow</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>5173533287</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Institutes of Health Office on Neuroinformatics</Name>
      <CityName>BETHESDA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>208920000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber></PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9000 ROCKVILLE PIKE, BLDG 31</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
