<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>'Dreamers with Shovels': Science and Technology in the New Deal Political Imagination</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fixed Price Award</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Abstract&lt;br/&gt;SES Proposal 0135333&lt;br/&gt;"Dreamers with Shovels:" Science and Technology in the New Deal Political Imagination Jessica Wang, University of California, Los Angeles&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project investigates, through a series of biographically-based historical case studies,&lt;br/&gt;the role of science and technology in political thought and action during the New Deal period in&lt;br/&gt;the United States. Within science and technology studies, many observers of technocratic&lt;br/&gt;political thought have emphasized its hegemonic, instrumentalist, and undemocratic character.&lt;br/&gt;In recent years, however, scholars have recognized that while this approach has contributed much&lt;br/&gt;toward understanding the nature of technological society, it needs to be revised and augmented.&lt;br/&gt;A study of the New Deal provides an important opportunity to reconsider prevailing assumptions&lt;br/&gt;and scrutinize the complex nature of technocratic politics as a set of beliefs and practices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study centers on three main subjects -- planning, electrification, and state-building -- and&lt;br/&gt;discusses how science and technology affected policymaking in each of these areas during the&lt;br/&gt;New Deal years. The section on planning illuminates how Rexford Guy Tugwell, Frederic A.&lt;br/&gt;Delano, Wesley C. Mitchell, and Charles E. Merriam sought to translate technocratic ideology&lt;br/&gt;into action. With electrification, the study turns to technology itself and investigates the conflicts&lt;br/&gt;within the Tennessee Valley Authority and the Rural Electrification Administration over the&lt;br/&gt;proper relationship between technology and human values, and the appropriate political&lt;br/&gt;structures for technological development. The discussion of state-building examines how Jerome&lt;br/&gt;N. Frank and William M. Leiserson used ideas about science to legitimize the New Deal state&lt;br/&gt;and justify its expansion of state power via the new administrative agencies of the 1930s. The&lt;br/&gt;final part of the project probes the postwar experiences of Henry A. Wallace and David E.&lt;br/&gt;Lilienthal, examines the transformation of technocratic politics wrought by the cold war, and&lt;br/&gt;explores how cold war instrumentalism replaced the technocratic liberalism of the New Deal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By examining how the New Dealers understood science and technology as a resource for&lt;br/&gt;politics, the project contributes to a renewed debate within STS over the nature of technocratic&lt;br/&gt;ideology and its political ramifications. The New Deal reveals the full complexity behind&lt;br/&gt;technocratic politics. Some of the New Dealers adopted subjectivist beliefs about the nature of&lt;br/&gt;knowledge, some brought a nostalgic, agrarian dimension to their version of technological&lt;br/&gt;progress, and most took seriously the problematic relationship between experts and democratic&lt;br/&gt;society and struggled over the question of whether technocratic politics could be made consistent&lt;br/&gt;with democratic values. The diverse range of thought and experience among the New Dealers&lt;br/&gt;suggests that an image of technocratic politics as naively positivist, dedicated to an unwavering&lt;br/&gt;faith in technological progress, and overly willing to subordinate democratic values to a cult of&lt;br/&gt;expertise requires refinement and reevaluation. The project will reinforce STS's current efforts&lt;br/&gt;to readdress the relationship between expertise and democracy and explore the full meaning of&lt;br/&gt;science and technology as forms of political thought and practice.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0135333</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jesswang@mail.ubc.ca</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
