<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developing a Long-term Research Agenda for the Network for Earthquake Engineering Simulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>290000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter Chang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The National Research Council (NRC) through its Division on Engineering and Physical Sciences, will conduct a study to assist the National Science Foundation in the formulation of a comprehensive, long-term agenda for the earthquake engineering research that fully utilizes the capabilities of the George E. Brown, Jr. Network for Earthquake Engineering Simulation (NEES). This effort will result in a report that articulates a dynamic, stakeholder-inclusive process for determining research needs, identifies the principal issues in earthquake engineering amenable to an integrated research approach that incorporates analysis, computational modeling, simulation, and physical testing; and assesses and comments on the possible roles of information and communication technologies for collaborative on-site and remote research. It will produce a long-term research plan based on short-, intermediate-, and long-term needs, general program to address them, and the estimated costs and benefits of the research program</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0135915</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Little</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rglittle@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1637</Code>
      <Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
