<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Board on Atmospheric Sciences and Climate Core Support</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>820000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jay S. Fein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a grant to support the continuation of the core activities of the Board on Atmospheric Sciences and Climate (BASC) of the National Academy of Sciences. The objectives of the effort include:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(i) providing a national and international forum for the atmospheric sciences, focusing on research needs, policy issues, educational implications and issues and the resources required to improve understanding of the atmosphere and its interaction with human societies and other components of the Earth System;&lt;br/&gt;(ii) coordinating and overseeing the BASC study units involved in developing and publishing disciplinary assessments that probe the frontiers articulated in the Atmospheric Sciences Entering the Twenty-First Century report, and other studies requested by agencies on specific issues;&lt;br/&gt;(iii) serving as a continuing resource to inform and provide advice from the atmospheric sciences community to federal agencies and other relevant decision-makers, and to serve as a linkage to the entire cross-section of the atmospheric sciences community. To this end, BASC proposes to initiate annual forums to discuss the Federal plans and budgets for the atmospheric sciences and climate related research. The resulting forums will serve as major mechanisms for improving the coordination of the entire Federal program in these vital areas.&lt;br/&gt;(iv) coordinating atmospheric science expertise for other National Research Council (NRC) units (most frequently with Ocean Studies Board, Polar Research Board, Board on Earth Sciences and Resources, Board on Environmental Studies and Toxicology, Space Studies Board, and the Committee on Global Change Research, but others as needed), international project offices, and bodies whose activities involve atmospheric sciences and whose actions may impact atmospheric science policy, societal impacts and educational issues. The relationship with the Committee on Global Change Research is particularly close with both the BASC chair and the chair of the Climate Research Committee serving as members.&lt;br/&gt;(v) creating a national forum for responsive dialogue on a number of atmospheric science phenomena of immediate and growing concern to society, including the conduct of specific studies and workshops in response to emerging science issues and Federal agency needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These activities are important because they provide advice to and review of the Federal atmospheric and climate sciences funding agencies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/02/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0135923</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elfring</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>celfring@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elbert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Friday</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jfriday@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/02/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/13/2002</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0319000</Code>
      <Name>Climate Related Activities</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5740</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>V007</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>W222</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1324</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY AND PREDICTABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
