<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Online Ethics Center for Engineering and Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>230845</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda Layne</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, the Online Ethics Center for Engineering and Science at Case Western -. Reserve University (OEC) further realizes the potential of World Wide Web to be a major ". &lt;br/&gt;resource for learning and practice of responsible practice in science and engineering. The OEC, which is staffed primarily by students, has become the foremost Web site for science and &lt;br/&gt;engineering ethics. It serves a wide audience ranging from pre-college students to distinguished senior practitioners and research investigators This project builds on and advances the ease of navigation, accessibility, responsiveness to users, and organization of content for which it is already known. Through a multi-site collaboration, the OEC advances learning and understanding of science and engineering ethics in the following areas: .Social and Ethical Implications of Information and Communication Technology, led by Joseph Herkert, North Carolina State University. Computer Ethics for Software Engineers and other Computing Professionals: led by Keith Miller, University of Illinois at Springfield. Academic Integrity: Cases and Commentaries for Scientists and Engineers, led by Elizabeth Kiss, the Kenan Institute for Ethics, Duke University and Daisy Waryold, The Center for Academic Integrity, Duke University. .Ethical Issues in Genomics and Biotechnology: Cases and Commentaries,1ed by Elizabeth Kiss, the Kenan Institute for Ethics and Center for Genome Ethics, Law, and Policy, Duke University. .Ethics Education in Conjunction with Senior Design Projects or Thesis, led by Elysa Koppelman, Oakland University &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through further indexing, organizing, and adding key words to materials on the site, the OEC will greatly aid those seeking to find information on the topics addressed on the OEC s pages. The organization of information extends to indexing of our introduction to materials maintained by others. &lt;br/&gt;This project sets the stage for still wider collaboration through the development of pilot collaborations between junior scholars in the U.S. and their colleagues in other countries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0135585</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Caroline</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whitbeck</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>caroline.whitbeck@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
