<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Adsorbate Mediated Electrodeposition: Experimental and Multiscale Numerical Investigations on Surface Roughness and Shape Evolution</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glenn L. Schrader</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Title: Adsorbate Mediated Electrodeposition: Experimental and Multiscale Numerical Investigations on Surface Roughness and Shape Evolution&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: CTS-0135621&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator:Richard Alkire&lt;br/&gt;Institution:University of Illinois&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this collaborative effort is to improve understanding of how surface roughness and shape evolution are influenced by trace quantities of solution additives during electrodeposition of metals and alloys. Multiscale simulations of the electrodeposition process including both continuum and non-continuum behavior will be performed. Hypotheses for how additives influence surface roughness evolution will be inferred from large datasets obtained through atomic force microscopy (AFM) measurements carried out in conjunction with high throughput electrochemical cells and well-characterized model additive systems. Hypotheses will be refined through quantitative comparison of these data with multiscale simulations of roughness evolution. Non-continuum phenomena will be modeled by a three-dimensional kinetic Monte Carlo method that simulates how roughness evolution is controlled by additives. Verification experiments that measure shape evolution on surfaces of convoluted geometry will be carried out to test predictions over multiple length scales. This work will lead to a better understanding of processes used in the manufacture of novel structures formed by electrodeposition of metals, alloys and semiconductors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0135621</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alkire</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>r-alkire@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Braatz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>braatz@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1401</Code>
      <Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1403</Code>
      <Text>PROCESS &amp; REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
