<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Risk communication and public participation during the investigation of cancer clusters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>259623</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Every day in the United States, on average, three communities reach a&lt;br/&gt;sufficient state of concern to contact their state health department for the&lt;br/&gt;investigation of a suspected cancer cluste, ran unusual and unexplained&lt;br/&gt;increase in the occurrence of cancer in space and time. State health&lt;br/&gt;departments investigate about a third of these cases in one way or another,&lt;br/&gt;but find that very few (about 1%) present suspect cancer rates. However,&lt;br/&gt;these cases of community concern and health department response present an&lt;br/&gt;effective circumstance in which to investigate risk perception, risk&lt;br/&gt;communication, and public participation in risk analysis. This project is&lt;br/&gt;the continuation and expansion of an established research effort designed to&lt;br/&gt;examine the social and psychological circumstances surrounding&lt;br/&gt;citizen-initiated cancer cluster investigations, with an emphasis on two&lt;br/&gt;aspects: the effects of state health department communications, and the&lt;br/&gt;experiences of citizens and officials in public meetings held during these&lt;br/&gt;cases. To meet the first goal, the project will integrate, and develop, two&lt;br/&gt;primary theoretical models, one central to risk perception (the Psychometric&lt;br/&gt;model) and one central to information processing and decision making (the&lt;br/&gt;Heuristic-Systematic model). Previous work in this effort has examined a&lt;br/&gt;series of five such cases. This expansion will use mail and phone survey&lt;br/&gt;methods to look at a larger and more diverse set of cluster investigations&lt;br/&gt;(about 50), enabling a comparison across cases. The analysis will continue&lt;br/&gt;the refinement of a model that describes the effects of information provided&lt;br/&gt;to communities in these cases, and will also evaluate the effects of the&lt;br/&gt;specific circumstances unique to theses cases (e.g., types of cancer,&lt;br/&gt;suspected causes). The analysis will also focus on the different&lt;br/&gt;communication techniques used by various state health departments to convey&lt;br/&gt;the results of their epidemiological investigations. To meet the second&lt;br/&gt;goal, a set of five cases will be more deeply studied with an emphasis on&lt;br/&gt;the public meetings that are almost always an important feature of these&lt;br/&gt;community experiences. That effort will make further use of mail and phone&lt;br/&gt;survey methods, and will also make use of extensive interviews and focus&lt;br/&gt;groups. Overall, the project is expected to provide a detailed examination&lt;br/&gt;of how information is conveyed in these cases, and how citizens make use of&lt;br/&gt;information to reach, or modify, their orientation toward concerns about&lt;br/&gt;cancer rates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Relative to scientific interests in risk perception, one of the most&lt;br/&gt;interesting aspects of this investigation resides in the fact that cluster&lt;br/&gt;cases almost always present a circumstance in which the scientific evidence&lt;br/&gt;indicates little or no risk, yet that evaluation is couched in the&lt;br/&gt;probabilistic language of cancer epidemiology. This investigation will&lt;br/&gt;advance scientific understanding of how individuals react to this form of&lt;br/&gt;information, a problem that has been a long-standing concern in the fields&lt;br/&gt;of psychology, social-psychology, and risk communication. In more practical&lt;br/&gt;terms, this project is also designed to evaluate the methods by which this&lt;br/&gt;form of information is provided to communities. The analysis will illuminate&lt;br/&gt;the more effective means of communicating the results of epidemiological&lt;br/&gt;studies and as such will provide important and useful feed-back for those&lt;br/&gt;who are charged with that work. The project's ultimate goal is that this&lt;br/&gt;kind of information will be communicated more effectively and the&lt;br/&gt;communities involved in such cases will be better served.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0136935</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Trumbo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ctrumbo@mac.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>McComas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kam19@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shanna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swans@health.missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1321</Code>
      <Text>DECISION RISK &amp; MANAGEMENT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
