<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ADVANCE Fellow / Preservation and Change: The Social Context of Spatial Patterns in a Southern City, 1900-2000</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>447044</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bonney Sheahan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This ADVANCE Fellows project studies social and spatial change in residential and family patterns that occurred in Charleston, S.C., during the 20th century, with a particular focus on segregation patterns from the city's historic preservation movement. The main research questions to be addressed by this project involve the relationship between racial and economic segregation and the individual-level patterns of residential mobility resulting from changes in the urban environment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will combine historical census records with City Directories to follow a sample of residents from 1900 to 1960. Patterns of spatial and social change will be mapped, overlaying ecological change and political change in the context of historic preservation. This will provide an overview of economic and residential segregation patterns. One of the main innovations of this study is that it will match individuals across multiple time periods. In addition, the study will combine traditional sociological perspectives with recent developments in spatial analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is supported through the NSF ADVANCE Program. The overall mission of the ADVANCE Program is to increase the participation of women in the scientific and engineering workforce through the increased representation and advancement of women in academic science and engineering careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137949</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Regina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bures</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rbures@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
      <CityName>Albany</CityName>
      <ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5184374550</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1681</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCE - FELLOWS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1397</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-DIRECTORATE ACTIV PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1681</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCE - FELLOWS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
