<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Phylogeny of Flea Beetles: Testing 3 Hypotheses of Relatedness Using 3 Different Data Sets: Larval and Adult Morphology and DNA Sequence Data</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>341894</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Porter Ridley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This study will produce a phylogeny (family tree) of the 38 flea beetle &lt;br/&gt;supra-generic groups and 5 galerucine tribes, which will test three &lt;br/&gt;proposed hypotheses of relationships, between the flea beetles and the &lt;br/&gt;galerucinae using a comprehensive taxon set and an exhaustive character set &lt;br/&gt;from adult and larval morphology and 3 gene fragments from the &lt;br/&gt;mitochondrial, nuclear and ribosomal genomes. This phylogeny will also be &lt;br/&gt;used to test hypotheses of evolution of jumping behavior, evolution of host- &lt;br/&gt;plant choice, Biogeography and geologic age of the flea beetles, and &lt;br/&gt;evolution of larval leaf feeding which are of general scientific interest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The flea beetles (Chrysomelidae: Alticinae) together with their sister &lt;br/&gt;group, the Galerucinae, are a huge group containing over 12,000 species; &lt;br/&gt;they are also extremely damaging to agriculture. The flea beetles are &lt;br/&gt;renowned for making "shot holes" in table crops such as potato, broccoli and &lt;br/&gt;grapes. The galerucines are infamous for the multi-billion dollar damage to &lt;br/&gt;corn and beans. Unfortunately, the taxonomic status of the flea beetles is &lt;br/&gt;so confusing that it impedes proper research and pest management. Over 500 &lt;br/&gt;described genera of flea beetles are divided into 38 supra-generic tribes, &lt;br/&gt;sub-tribes and sections and there is no taxonomic or phylogenetic hypothesis &lt;br/&gt;of how these tribes and series are related to one another. This lack of a &lt;br/&gt;trust -worthy phylogeny is especially important to pest management, where &lt;br/&gt;assumptions about pesticide applications or search for biological control &lt;br/&gt;agents are often made based on taxonomic position and where money is often &lt;br/&gt;wasted if these assumptions are incorrect.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137624</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Duckett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cduckett@monmouth.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kjer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kkjer@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Smithsonian Institution</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>222023709</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026337110</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1681</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCE - FELLOWS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1681</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCE - FELLOWS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
