<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ADVANCE Fellows Award</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180078</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dean M. Evasius</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS Award Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award #: 0137987 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Gwendolen Hines&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Nebraska, Lincoln &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: ADVANCE Fellows Award&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Gwendolen Hines will collaborate with Konstantin Mischaikow on a mathematical model for the evolution of dispersal rates in a population which experiences both spatial and temporal heterogeneity. Together, they will analyze models with dispersal mechanisms other than simple diffusion, specifically dispersal described by integral operators. They will search for the existence of stable solutions for different combinations of spatial and temporal homogeneity and heterogeneity. The global dynamics of the system will be studied. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Gwendolen Hines has been out of the full-time academic mathematics workforce for several years to care for her young daughter. She plans to reestablish her research career by spending a semester at Georgia Tech's Center for Dynamical Systems and Nonlinear Studies to work on a problem in evolutionary biology having to do with how natural selection is related to dispersal rates. Upon returning to the University of Nebraska at Lincoln, she will resume her full-time tenure-track position in mathematics. She will continue to work on this research problem, intensifying the collaboration with summer visits to Georgia Tech. At Nebraska, she will promote the interaction between Mathematics and Biology departments, as part of the university's initiative in Quantitative and Integrative Biology. Dr. Hines remains active in outreach activities for girls and women in mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137987</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gwendolen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hines</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ghines@math.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 Vine St, 151 Whittier</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
