<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ADVANCE Fellow: The Role of Electrostatics in Nucleic Acid Structure and Function</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>446005</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This ADVANCE Fellows award, through the Divisions of Chemistry and Physics, will support the research of Marcia O. Fenley in the Institute of Molecular Biophysics at Florida State University. The project will use theoretical and computational approaches to elucidate the role of electrostatics on the structure and function of nucleic acids. Specifically, the ion atmosphere and electrostatic potential of model structures of triple-stranded nucleic acids will be examined using numerical counterion condensation and Poisson-Boltzmann methods. These calculations may elucidate the role of various ions on nucleic acid structure, conformation changes and phase transitions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is supported through the NSF ADVANCE Program. The overall mission of the ADVANCE Program is to increase the participation of women in the scientific and engineering workforce through the increased representation and advancement of women in academic science and engineering careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137961</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marcia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fenley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mfenley@sb.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
