<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Quest Atlantis Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>87316</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth VanderPutten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will take advantage of advanced technologies and&lt;br/&gt;strategies proven successful in online role-playing games to create&lt;br/&gt;exciting opportunities for children in an after school context. There are&lt;br/&gt;almost no examples of learning environments that build on lessons and&lt;br/&gt;strategies from the commercial success of 3D online, role-playing games,&lt;br/&gt;environments that are populated by tens of thousands of users each day.&lt;br/&gt;Leveraging 3-D technologies and principles so successful for the gaming&lt;br/&gt;community to develop educationally meaningful environments is a topic of&lt;br/&gt;which we, as an educational community, know very little and which has much&lt;br/&gt;potential to engage typically underrepresented groups in SMT learning.&lt;br/&gt;This work is exploratory and has exciting potential both in terms of its&lt;br/&gt;direct service to the disadvantaged children at the local Boys and Girls&lt;br/&gt;Clubs and in terms of the broader implications of the research to inform&lt;br/&gt;the education community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Our 18 month relationship with the Boys and Girls Clubs is currently&lt;br/&gt;strong and recently Compaq and Microsoft donated $100,000 in equipment,&lt;br/&gt;software, and service to both local Boys and Girls Clubs to create&lt;br/&gt;Technology Centers. The Quest Atlantis program is viewed as an exciting&lt;br/&gt;opportunity to integrate the computers in Club programming, and staff, and&lt;br/&gt;space will be committed to the project. Continuing this relationship and&lt;br/&gt;leveraging this still-new technology and the current interest in&lt;br/&gt;innovating with this equipment and software creates a timely opportunity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137298</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sasha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barab</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbarab@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1666</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH ON LEARNING &amp; EDUCATI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
