<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: A Multi-Systems Violence Prevention Program for Girls</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4840</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul J. Wahlback</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Youth violence is a serious social health problem with physical, psychological, and legal implications. The most robust predictors of youth violence are frequent criminal acts and juvenile delinquency exhibited prior to or during adolescence. Types of delinquent behaviors most often seen during early adolescence include truancy, fighting, and minor, first-time offenses. The negative impact of early delinquency on the legal system can be seen in terms of high costs for court time, personnel, probation services, and residential facilities. However, delinquency also affects the educational and mental health fields as well. Since violent behavior is multi-determined, interventions that identify and prevent the multiple causes that lead to violence are necessary at this time. The present study is an empirical investigation of the efficacy of a school-based violence prevention program for 6th grade girls at-risk for violence due to signs of early delinquency and academic failure. Girls from low-income, inner-city schools in Baltimore City will participate in an intensive 10-week program that focuses upon preventing violence through reducing behavior problems, enhancing academic performance, and improving psychological functioning. Evaluation of the violence prevention program will be based upon indicators of delinquent behavior and academic status following completion of the program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/15/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/15/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137096</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jordan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ljordan@umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland Baltimore County</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4104553140</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Hilltop Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1372</Code>
      <Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
