<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Theory of Quasi-One-Dimensional Organic Conductors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daryl W. Hess</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research is devoted to the theory of quasi-one-dimensional (Q1D) organic conductors (TMTSF)2X and (TMTTF)2X, where TMTSF is tetramethyltetraselenafulvalene, TMTTF is tetramethyltetrathiafulvalene, and X represents a monovalent inorganic anion, such as PF6 and ClO4. These materials demonstrate an antonishingly rich variety of physical properties and states: metallic, insulating, superconductive, charge-and spin-density-wave states, antiferromagnetism, spin-Peierls states, and the state of Mott-Hubbard paramagnetic insulator. They exhibit a multitude of magnetic oscillations as a function of the magnitude and orientation of the magnetic field. A strong magnetic field induces the cascade of phase transitions between the magnetic-field-induced spin-density waves (FISDW), which exhibit the quantum Hall effect.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Theoretical research will be conducted on the following topics: fractional quantum Hall numbers of the subgap electron states; electron states in superconducting junctions; bound electron states at the superconducting and FISDW vortices and impurities; collective modes in the triplet superconducting state; and, coesistence of metallic Fermi surface and charge gap. There will be close collaboration with experiments and an emphasis on real materials.&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;Theoretical research will be conducted on a novel class of organic conducting materials which display a rich variety of properties. These materials are of great fundamental interest due these properties arising in organic materials and of great practical interest due to many potential applications.&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137726</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yakovenko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yakovenk@physics.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
