<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: MLT Dynamics, Structure, and Variability Using the Weber Sodium Lidar and Other Optical and Radar Instrumentation at ALOMAR</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>195000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020201</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert B. Kerr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The ALOMAR Weber sodium lidar is a newly completed, state-of-the-art instrument built and installed at the Arctic Lidar Observatory for Middle Atmosphere Research (ALOMAR) in northern Norway (69.3 degrees N) with Air Force funding under the Defense University Research Instrumentation Program (DURIP). Its capabilities for dual-beam temperature, wind, and momentum flux measurements have recently been demonstrated under continuing Air Force support. This is an NSF-funded collaborative project for a comprehensive study of the dynamics, structure, and variability of the mesosphere and lower thermosphere (MLT) using the Weber lidar and associated instrumentation at ALOMAR. Such funding of Weber lidar dynamics studies is expected to enhance dramatically measurement and research activities and the potential of U.S. PIs to participate in various collaborative programs, including ground-based support and correlative science with the thermosphere ionosphere mesosphere energetics and dynamics (TIMED) satellite and the MaCWAVE rocket dynamics studies, of considerable relevance to the NSF Aeronomy Program objectives. This award will also make ALOMAR facilities and correlative research opportunities available to other U.S. scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0137354</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fritts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dave@gats-inc.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NorthWest Research Associates, Incorporated</Name>
      <CityName>Redmond</CityName>
      <ZipCode>980525164</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4255569055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4118 148th Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0205000</Code>
      <Name>Space</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1521</Code>
      <Text>AERONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
