<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Compression of Geometry Datasets</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>112500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lloyd E. Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0138458&lt;br/&gt;Peter Schroder&lt;br/&gt;DMS-0221642&lt;br/&gt;Ronald A. Devore&lt;br/&gt;DMS-0221669&lt;br/&gt;Mathieu Desbrun&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a collaborative project funded by the CARGO program under&lt;br/&gt;DMS-0138458, DMS-0221642, and DMS-0221669. This is the Age of Information. Whether it be in scientific computation or reverse engineering, in remote sensing or medicine, data sets of &lt;br/&gt;incredible resolution and exquisite detail are created&lt;br/&gt;daily. These data sets often have geometric structure which &lt;br/&gt;contains important information about the data and its &lt;br/&gt;application. The usefulness of such geometric datasets &lt;br/&gt;rests on our ability to process them efficiently, whether &lt;br/&gt;it be for storage, transmission, visual display, correlation, &lt;br/&gt;or registration against data from other modalities. &lt;br/&gt;Compression is the common critical issue in all&lt;br/&gt;these applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Current data processing technology does not provide the &lt;br/&gt;efficient and geometrically faithful representations demanded &lt;br/&gt;by applications. In fact, a satisfactory data processing &lt;br/&gt;platform will not be created by incremental advances of current technology but rather through a fundamental investigation of &lt;br/&gt;how to represent large data sets with inherent geometry. To &lt;br/&gt;pursue the necessary advances a team of researchers and &lt;br/&gt;application developers representing expertise from&lt;br/&gt;several disciplines including mathematics, computer science, &lt;br/&gt;and engineering has been assembled. As drivers of the research, specially targeted applications (DTED, reverse engineering, &lt;br/&gt;physical simulation) have been selected to guide the formulation &lt;br/&gt;of the most critical and meaningful problems, as well as testing approaches to solving them. The team is carrying out &lt;br/&gt;fundamental investigations on the representation and compression &lt;br/&gt;of data sets with geometry by building new mathematical theory&lt;br/&gt;including deterministic models, appropriate application &lt;br/&gt;specific error metrics (e.g., Haussdorf distance rather&lt;br/&gt;than Lp norms), an information theory based on Kolmogorov &lt;br/&gt;entropy to determine the optimal compression, and the &lt;br/&gt;development of nonlinear methods for representing the data &lt;br/&gt;sets which are near optimal in the entropy sense.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138458</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schroder</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ps@cs.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
