<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-India Cooperative Research: Enzyme-Inorganic Materials: Peroxidase Behavior at Selected Interfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>16880</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Lueck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0138401&lt;br/&gt;Kumar&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Description: This award is for US-India collaborative research in biochemistry entitled Enzyme-Inorganic Materials: Peroxidase Behavior at Selected Interfaces. The investigators will test the hypothesis that solid surfaces perturb enzyme structure, and that the extent of perturbation depends on the strength of interaction between the solid and the enzyme. The key issues addressed in this research are important for the rational design of materials for enzyme binding. Advanced materials of this type have applications in biocatalysis, biosensors, implants, and artificial organs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Scope: This initiates a three-way collaboration between US PI Challa V. Kumar of the University of Connecticut and C.P. Rao, Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Mumbai and V. Jagannadham, Osamania University (OU). The proposed studies are logical extensions of the research interests of the US PI and overlap with the collaborators interests. The IIT group brings to the collaboration their expertise in design, synthesis, and chacterization of ligands/metal complexes, while the OU group brings its high level expertise in reaction kinetics and mechanistic studies. It will enhance research and teaching activities at all three institutions. The project is supported by the Indian Department of Science and Technology(DST) under the NSF/DST joint program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138401</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Challa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Challa.Kumar@UCONN.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
