<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Elementary, Secondary, and Informal Education: Assessing Technological Literacy in the United States</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>710578</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen F. Zuga</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The National Academy of Engineering and the National Research Council Center for Education propose a two-year project, the goal of which is to determine the most viable approach or approaches for assessing technological literacy. Technological literacy, as defined in the proposal, includes an understanding of the nature of technology, the design process and the history of technology; a capacity to ask questions and make informed decisions about technology; and some level of hands-on capability related to the use of technology. The project will focus on three distinct populations in the United States: K-16 students, K-16 teachers and out-of-school adults. It is to be overseen by a committee appointed by the National Research Council in consultation with the National Academy of Engineering which is to be comprised of experts in such fields as cognitive science, assessment, curriculum development, technology education and teacher education. The committee will collect and analyze relevant literature and get information through workshops and commissioned papers prior making a recommendation for assessing technological literacy. The primary product will be a report that describes the committee's work, findings and conclusions, and then presents its recommendations. The outcome will be a widely disseminated, visible, well-supported document that will: (a) increase the ability of educational researchers and policy makers to critically evaluate established and new methods for assessing technological literacy; (b) encourage the inclusion of technology-related items in established assessments (e.g., NAEP); and (c) help develop new approaches for determining what various subsets of the U.S. population know about technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138715</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pearson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gpearson@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Naomi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chudowsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Nchudows@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1666</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH ON LEARNING &amp; EDUCATI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7355</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUCTIONAL MATERIALS DEVELP</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
