<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Computational and Algorithmic Representations of Geometric Objects - CARGO: The Geometry of Optical Paths: Intrinsic Properties, Complexity of Approximation, and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0138440&lt;br/&gt;James R. Arvo&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The most familiar principle of geometrical optics asserts &lt;br/&gt;that a ray of light impinging on an ideal mirror will emerge &lt;br/&gt;in such a way that the angle of reflection equals the angle of incidence. The trajectory of a photon (or a billiard ball, &lt;br/&gt;using another common metaphor), is thus completely determined &lt;br/&gt;by its initial conditions and the geometry of the mirrors it subsequently encounters. The geometry of such trajectories &lt;br/&gt;has been of interest in numerous fields, including plane &lt;br/&gt;geometry, computational geometry, and computer graphics, &lt;br/&gt;yet they comprise a vanishingly small subset (a set of &lt;br/&gt;measure zero) within the class of all optical paths that &lt;br/&gt;fall within the purview of geometrical optics. In particular, &lt;br/&gt;optical paths resulting from non-specular reflections &lt;br/&gt;constitute a vastly larger class. Moreover, they are of far &lt;br/&gt;greater importance to image synthesis as they result from &lt;br/&gt;physically realizable models of reflection. Nonetheless, &lt;br/&gt;non-specular paths have thus far been largely overlooked as &lt;br/&gt;a source of interesting geometrical problems. The main &lt;br/&gt;objective of this research is therefore to launch an&lt;br/&gt;initial investigation into the basic geometrical properties &lt;br/&gt;of non-specular optical paths, both in the traditional &lt;br/&gt;combinatorial sense, such as finding a optimal paths &lt;br/&gt;connecting two points, and in the continuous sense, such &lt;br/&gt;s finding extremal paths, or computing the measure of all &lt;br/&gt;k-segment paths connecting two regions. A secondary &lt;br/&gt;objective is to explore connections with probabilistic &lt;br/&gt;methods, such as standard Monte Carlo visibility techniques &lt;br/&gt;and Metropolis light transport, which will likely be the &lt;br/&gt;first direct beneficiaries of this work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work is expected to contribute primarily to the&lt;br/&gt;mathematical foundations of image synthesis by identifying&lt;br/&gt;optical paths as interesting geometrical entities in &lt;br/&gt;themselves, and by exposing some of their fundamental &lt;br/&gt;properties in terms of density, measure, and computational &lt;br/&gt;complexity. Moreover, it is expected that this new &lt;br/&gt;perspective will ultimately be instrumental in studying &lt;br/&gt;the accuracy and computational complexity of realistic &lt;br/&gt;image synthesis in general, about which very little is &lt;br/&gt;known currently. While the problems investigated here &lt;br/&gt;will invariably have much in common with previous work on&lt;br/&gt;direct and indirect illumination problems in computational&lt;br/&gt;geometry, the approaches taken will have a distinctly more&lt;br/&gt;continuous flavor, drawing heavily from fields such as &lt;br/&gt;measure theory, differential geometry, and geometric &lt;br/&gt;probability. Finally, it is expected that this work will &lt;br/&gt;serve as a segue into a longer-term investigation of &lt;br/&gt;computational complexity in computer graphics by &lt;br/&gt;establishing basic tools and connections with other disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138440</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Arvo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>arvo@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>2865</Code>
      <Text>NUMERIC, SYMBOLIC &amp; GEO COMPUT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>X871</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
