<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Computational and Algorithmic Representations of Geonetric Objects - CARGO: Degeneracy Detection for Curved Solids</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0138446&lt;br/&gt;John Keyser&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Degeneracies are a major source of robustness problems &lt;br/&gt;in many geometric algorithms. Many degenerate situations &lt;br/&gt;can be expressed as a root of a multivariate system of &lt;br/&gt;polynomials. We propose to study the use of toric resultants &lt;br/&gt;to detect degenerate situations in solid modeling applications. &lt;br/&gt;By taking advantage of the underlying monomial structure &lt;br/&gt;of a system of polynomials, the toric resultant can provide &lt;br/&gt;a method for solving systems of polynomials that is &lt;br/&gt;dramatically more efficient than the classical "dense" &lt;br/&gt;resultants of Macaulay and Cayley. We will focus on &lt;br/&gt;application to boundary evaluation for curved solids.&lt;br/&gt;Our work will include enumeration of degenerate conditions &lt;br/&gt;and identifying detection algorithms for each category, &lt;br/&gt;using the toric resultant where appropriate. The work &lt;br/&gt;is intended to foster future collaborative research &lt;br/&gt;endeavors on topics including resolution of geometric &lt;br/&gt;degeneracies, general algebraic number computation, and&lt;br/&gt;computational Morse theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Geometric degeneracies occur when a minor perturbation &lt;br/&gt;of the geometry would cause a qualitatively different &lt;br/&gt;positioning between the objects. Degeneracies, such as &lt;br/&gt;two overlapping surfaces or a vertex of one object lying &lt;br/&gt;on the face of another, are common occurances in many&lt;br/&gt;real-world solid modeling examples. The problems of &lt;br/&gt;detecting and dealing with degenerate situations becomes &lt;br/&gt;particularly difficult when dealing with curved surfaces. &lt;br/&gt;Usually, detecting such cases involves finding roots of &lt;br/&gt;polynomials. Thus, accurate and efficient root-finding &lt;br/&gt;is crucial to an effective approach for handling&lt;br/&gt;degeneracies. The toric resultant is an approach for &lt;br/&gt;finding solutions to systems of polynomial equations. &lt;br/&gt;Because of its efficiency compared to other methods of &lt;br/&gt;solving such systems, it is a promising approach&lt;br/&gt;for detecting and treating degeneracies. We propose &lt;br/&gt;to address degeneracies in solid modeling applications &lt;br/&gt;through the use of the toric resultant.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138446</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Maurice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rojas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rojas@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Keyser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>keyser@cs.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>2865</Code>
      <Text>NUMERIC, SYMBOLIC &amp; GEO COMPUT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>X871</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
