<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MORB Petrogenesis and Crustal Development on the East Pacific Rise from 8 - 10 Degrees N</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>244034</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040205</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rodey Batiza</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal outlines a two-year course of study to fully analyze and synthesize petrologic and geochemical data together with geologic and geophysical constraints to come up with fully integrated models of melting, melt ascent, plumbing and eruptive systems at the fast-spreading EPR 8 degrees -10 degrees N. The PI will collaborate with geologists and geophysicists at IPGP in Paris and WHOI. Distinct goals include using existing and new analyses to understand the mantle sources, melting, and fractionation of the axial and off-axis basalts, using gabbroic xenoliths, U-series dating, and geologic information to paint a picture of layer 2a thickening and the role of off-axis eruptions, and to evaluate the correlations between U-series ages, magnetic paleointensity values, and volcanic and geomorphic features. This ABR will bring together a decade of sampling and analytical work to produce a fully integrated interpretive model of crustal growth and evolution at fast spreading rates.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138088</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Perfit</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mperfit@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
