<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Elementary, Secondary, and Informal Education: West Virginia Reach Out: Expanding the WV-Handle on Science Project to Grades 7 and 8</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>151656</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David B. Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The West Virginia Pilot Local Systemic Change project will build upon an NSF-funded teacher enhancement project targeting K-6 grade teachers. The proposed project will provide content enhancement and leadership development in science for sixteen seventh and eighth grade science teachers over a two-year period of time. Two participants from each of the five counties in the region served by the Northern Regional Consortium for science, mathematics and technology, and three rural counties outside of the Northern Panhandle will participate in the project. The six rural county teachers will be involved via distance learning technologies. Participants will experience a 10-day summer workshop, on-line chat sessions, informal science workshops during the academic year, and ATM (asynchronous transfer mode) technology. Four informal science education providers will help to expand upon the participants' content knowledge and to link real life experiences to the study of science. During the two hundred professional development hours over two years, teachers will field test and evaluate modules from the STC/MS, FOSS and SEPUP curricula. Appropriate teaching techniques and a redesign of the current curricula are required to allow all of the area's middle level students to learn concepts that will serve them well in their changing economy. As a result, science content, especially physical science, and materials will be the primary focus of this Pilot LSC project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138285</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goodwin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dgoodwin@1st.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>H</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cook</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>09/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>West Liberty State College</Name>
      <CityName>West Liberty</CityName>
      <ZipCode>260740000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3043365000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 295</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7300</Code>
      <Text>TEACHER ENHANCEMENT PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
