<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: High Throughput Activity and In-situ Infrared Spectroscopy and X-Ray Absorption Fine Structure Studies of the Effect of Sulfur on Noble Metal Supported Oxidation Catalysts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>238906</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John R Regalbuto</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Title: GOALI: High Throughput Activity and in-situ FTIR and EXAFS Studies of the Effect of Sulfur on Noble Metal Supported Oxidation Catalysts&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: CTS-0138070&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Eduardo Wolf&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Notre Dame University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this proposal is to investigate the effects of sulfur on the state of the surface of supported platinum, palladium, and rhodium catalysts and to develop structure-activity correlations for these catalysts during oxidation reaction. The approach is to conduct a comprehensive study on the effect of sulfur poisoning on model oxidation reactions by combining kinetic measurements, catalyst characterizations, and microkinetic and Monte Carlo simulations of the experimental results. High throughput catalyst evaluations will be used to ascertain the effect of sulfur on carbon monoxide, propane, and proplyene oxidation on Pt, Pd, and Rh on a variety of oxide supports. An array of catalysts will be used to identify the major trends in activity caused by sulfur poisoning of the catalysts' surface. Selected samples will be studied using a variety of surface analytical techniques such as EXAFS and FTIR. An industrial collaborator brings expertise in surface science and catalyst preparation techniques. The results of this study may be useful in developing more sulfur-tolerant catalysts in automobile exhaust applications and for fuel cells.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138070</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>millerjt@anl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eduardo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wolf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wolf.1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
      <CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
      <ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
