<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Partial Differential Equations and Statistical Mechanics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>165500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joe W. Jenkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Joseph G. Conlon, University of Michigan&lt;br/&gt;DMS-0138519&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; This project is concerned with elliptic and parabolic partial differential &lt;br/&gt;equations and their applications in statistical mechanics. The first part of the&lt;br/&gt;proposal is concerned with elliptic and parabolic equations in divergence form &lt;br/&gt;where the coefficients are random variables. The author intends to study the &lt;br/&gt;regularity properties of the expectation value of the Green's function, and the &lt;br/&gt;rate of convergence of the solution of the equation to the solution of the &lt;br/&gt;homogenized equation. The second part of the proposal is concerned with the &lt;br/&gt;application of ideas from the theory of divergence form parabolic equations with&lt;br/&gt;random coefficients to Euclidean field theory. The relationship between elliptic&lt;br/&gt;and parabolic equations with random coefficients and Euclidean field theory was&lt;br/&gt;discovered recently by Helffer and Sjostrand. It was then more fully developed &lt;br/&gt;by Naddaf-Spencer. The author intends to apply some ideas he and Naddaf have &lt;br/&gt;developed for random elliptic equations to the Euclidean field theory situation.&lt;br/&gt;In the third part of the proposal the author proposes to study nondivergence &lt;br/&gt;form elliptic equations with random coefficients, in particular an&lt;br/&gt;equation corresponding to Brownian motion with a random drift. It has been&lt;br/&gt;shown by Sinai that in one dimension diffusion with random drift is strongly&lt;br/&gt;subdiffusive for large time. It has been conjectured that in dimension larger &lt;br/&gt;than 2 the scaling limit of diffusion with random drift is Brownian motion. The &lt;br/&gt;author has found a connection between this conjecture and certain combinatorial&lt;br/&gt;problems concerning the existence of cycles in graphs. He plans to continue his&lt;br/&gt;program to solve these combinatorial problems. The final part of the proposal is&lt;br/&gt;concerned with uniformly elliptic equations with deterministic coefficients.&lt;br/&gt;The coefficients can oscillate arbitrarily rapidly however. The author plans to&lt;br/&gt;continue his work to obtain estimates on the underlying diffusion which are&lt;br/&gt;independent of the degree of oscillation of the coefficients. This part of the&lt;br/&gt;proposal is related to the previous parts since random equations have&lt;br/&gt;coefficients which are rapidly oscillating.&lt;br/&gt; The goal of the proposal is to understand properties of the solution to a&lt;br/&gt;partial differential equation when the only information one has is that the&lt;br/&gt;coefficients of the equation are bounded in some way. Within this goal there&lt;br/&gt;are two sub-themes: (a) understanding worst possible behavior, (b)&lt;br/&gt;understanding "on average" behavior -given our knowledge of the coefficients.&lt;br/&gt;The sub-theme (a) is the subject of the final part of the proposal. It is&lt;br/&gt;intimately related to problems of stochastic control theory. Examples of&lt;br/&gt;stochastic control theory abound in the world of engineering and finance. To &lt;br/&gt;take a financial example, consider the problem of valuing a stock option. The&lt;br/&gt;classic work of Black and Scholes shows that the value of the option depends&lt;br/&gt;only on the stock volatility. For a stock with constant volatility they have a&lt;br/&gt;formula for the value of the option in terms of the volatility. The formula is&lt;br/&gt;the solution to a partial differential equation in which the volatility is a&lt;br/&gt;coefficient. (a) is therefore related to the problem of estimating worst&lt;br/&gt;possible scenarios for option values when one can only assume some bounds on &lt;br/&gt;stock volatility. The sub-theme (b) has similar applications to (a). The most&lt;br/&gt;exciting of these to this author is that it offers a way of beginning to&lt;br/&gt;understand the problem of turbulence in fluids. Turbulence is roughly speaking&lt;br/&gt;the onset of random behavior in the velocity of a fluid. It is well known that &lt;br/&gt;a fluid will undergo turbulent behavior when subject to a sufficiently large&lt;br/&gt;disturbance. The mathematical problem of understanding turbulence is well&lt;br/&gt;defined. One simply needs to understand the solutions of a partial differential&lt;br/&gt;equation known as the Navier-Stokes equation. To date there is not even the&lt;br/&gt;beginnings of an understanding how to derive turbulence in a mathematically&lt;br/&gt;rigorous way out of the Navier-Stokes equation. The reason is that the fluid&lt;br/&gt;velocity is a coefficient of the equation. In the turbulent regime therefore&lt;br/&gt;the Navier-Stokes equation is like a partial differential equation with a&lt;br/&gt;random coefficient. The sub-theme (b) is then concerned with the "typical"&lt;br/&gt;behavior of the fluid velocity in this situation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0138519</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Conlon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>conlon@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
