<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Japan Joint Seminar: Advanced Polymer Chemistry for the 21ST Century</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>22400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myra McAuliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0139883&lt;br/&gt;Swager&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the participation of American scientists in a U.S.-Japan seminar on advanced polymer chemistry for the 21st century to be held in Nagoya, Japan from December 7-10, 2002. The co-organizers are Professor Timothy Swager of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and Professor Yoshio Okamoto of Nagoya University in, Japan. The emphasis of the seminar will be on polymers that in contrast to commodity materials are chemically complex and not necessarily inexpensive to produce. New generations of polymers that can justify such expenses are expected to play a role in many evolving technologies. The last decade has resulted in enormous progress in the development and understanding of synthetic chemistry, molecular recognition, molecular scaffolds, biological processes, and self-organization. Presently these advances are under-utilized in the design and synthesis of new advanced polymers. The term "advanced" is used to describe polymers with non-traditional properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This seminar seeks to bring together specific individuals from the United State and Japan that have synergistic programs to catalyze new advances in the design and synthesis of advanced polymers. The seminar advances international human resources through the participation of a number of younger researchers. Through the exchange of ideas and technology, this project will broaden our base of basic knowledge and promote international understanding and cooperation. Arrangements are being made with the "Journal of Polymer Science" to have proceedings published in a special issue.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0139883</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swager</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tswager@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
