<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Observing and Documenting the Inter-Organizational Response to the September 11, 2001 Terror Attacks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Miriam Heller</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Observing and Documenting the Inter-Organizational Response to the 9/11 Terror Attacks&lt;br/&gt;This research entails collecting, documenting analyzing time sensitive data from the sites of the devastating terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center (WTC) in New York City, NY and the Pentagon in Washington, DC on September 11, 2001. The objective of this research is to build on the knowledge base relating to the coordination of emergency responders. While communication and coordination of emergency management and medical efforts is an active area of research in earthquake and other natural disasters, this event is the first time where, at such a large scale, emergency efforts have been required to integrate with those of law enforcement and military resources as well. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Information flows between and within response organizations as well as information management problems that occur will be collected using personal observation, structured interviews, document collection. They will be analyzed and written up as a summary document for use by emergency planners and researchers. The results will support future research to enhance the emergency management and response in the US. More generalizable impacts are expected in terms of decision-making and inter-organizational coordination in complex, stressed environments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0139309</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barbera</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbarbera@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harrald</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jharrald@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200522000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2029946255</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2121 Eye Street NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
