<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Representations of Finite Groups and Algebraic Lie Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>356954</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tie Luo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigators will continue their study of the representation theory&lt;br/&gt;of finite groups, especially the symmetric group and its double covers, by &lt;br/&gt;exploiting various connections to Lie theory. These connections arise at&lt;br/&gt;many different levels, combinatorial, algebraic and geometric, and involve the &lt;br/&gt;representation theory of algebraic groups, supergroups, quantum groups and &lt;br/&gt;infinite dimensional Lie algebras. The investigators intend to study in &lt;br/&gt;particular the Shapovalov form on highest weight modules over affine&lt;br/&gt;Kac-Moody algebras via vertex operators, Broue's conjecture for the&lt;br/&gt;symmetric group, and to further exploit the relationship between branching&lt;br/&gt;rules and crystal graphs in representation theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is in the area of mathematics known as representation theory. &lt;br/&gt;The tools of mathematics provide a precise way to describe the symmetries&lt;br/&gt;of something. Representation theory is the study of the ways such&lt;br/&gt;symmetries can arise in the real world, and as such it has applications to many &lt;br/&gt;areas of mathematics, physics and chemistry. In the last few years, there has&lt;br/&gt;been some major progress in our understanding of representation theory, thanks&lt;br/&gt;in part to a new influx of ideas from mathematical physics. This project is&lt;br/&gt;concerned in part with the representation theory of the most important of all the&lt;br/&gt;finite groups, the symmetric group, which is closely related to the theory of &lt;br/&gt;symmetric functions. The work is expected to have applications to other areas of&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, as well as a wider impact in mathematical physics, statistical &lt;br/&gt;mechanics and coding theory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0139019</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kleshchev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>klesh@math.uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brundan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brundan@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
