<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GK-12 and GeoKids: Bringing Place-Based Science to Urban Philadelphia Children</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>971570</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sonia Ortega</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project builds on strong existing collaborations between Saint Joseph's University (SJU) science faculty and a Philadelphia museum, the Wagner Free Institute of Science (WFIS), and between WFIS staff and principals at three nearby urban Philadelphia public schools. GK-12 Fellows are M.S. candidates or advanced undergraduates studying Biology, Chemistry, or Environmental Science. Each year 4-8 Fellows will collaborate with WFIS education specialists, SJU faculty, and K-6 teachers to develop and present semester-long thematic units to students attending schools in one of Philadelphia's most underserved neighborhoods. "GeoKids" incorporates a place-based approach that uses the local environment as a resource to teach earth and life sciences, a unique and challenging learning strategy for an inner-city program. GeoKids emphasizes hands-on science, project-based learning, and development of fundamental skills such as reading, writing, and observing. The program includes annual summer workshops where Fellows, K-6 teachers, and participating SJU and WFIS educators review curriculum standards, study in appropriate content areas, and become more familiar with education issues specific to students from the target schools. Doctoral education students will collaborate with an education assessment expert in designing and administering assessment tools. Expected outcomes of the program include: development, testing, and documentation of environmentally-based lessons, K-6 teachers empowered to develop their own place-based lessons, SJU faculty and graduate students committed to enhancing science literacy, and incorporation of GK-12 program elements into existing Service Learning activities at SJU. The grant activities support efforts underway at SJU to enhance and expand the graduate programs in Chemistry and Biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0139303</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rmurray@sju.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mc Robert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smcrober@sju.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Snetselaar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksnetsel@sju.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Glassman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>04/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmccann@sju.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>St Joseph's University</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191311308</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158797300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5600 City Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
