<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site Proposal: The Calder Center Summer Undergraduate Research Program in Ecology and Field Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>105613</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080303</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Calder Summer Undergraduate Research (CSUR) program will provide eight undergraduate students each summer the opportunity for independent research in ecology and field biology at the Louis Calder Center, Fordham University's biological field station. Since 1967, the Calder Center has provided undergraduate and graduate students opportunities to study relatively undisturbed communities near an urban center, and has afforded many urban students their first opportunity to examine the natural world first hand. As part of this mission, the Calder Center and Fordham University have established the CSUR program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CSUR program is a 12-week, intensive curriculum in which students learn the fundamentals of experimental design, use of the scientific literature, data collection and analysis, preparation of manuscripts, and oral presentation. A core component of the program is an independent research project each student will conduct in conjunction with faculty mentors. Projects may be developed in a broad range of topics including aquatic ecology, forest ecology, physiological ecology of plants and animals, soil ecology, vector ecology, and wildlife conservation. Students will also participate in weekly scientific seminars, seminar courses on the philosophy of science and ethics in science, and a student exchange program with the American Museum of Natural History. In addition, CSUR participants will be able to interact with other undergraduate and graduate students at the Calder Center who are supported through university fellowships and extramural grants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CSUR-REU project targets highly motivated students interested in pursuing a career in ecology, especially those who are from institutions that offer limited opportunities for independent research, are from urban backgrounds, or are from groups under-represented in science. In addition to these considerations, students will be selected based on academic performance, research interests and potential, and previous research experience. Students interested in participating in the program may contact Dr. John Wehr at 914-273-3078 ext. 11 or at wehr@fordham.edu for information and application forms. Students may also obtain information and forms online at http://www.fordham.edu/calder_center/calder-center/CSUR-Program.html</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0139767</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wehr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wehr@fordham.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lewis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdlewis@fordham.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fordham University</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104585149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7188174651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>441 E.Fordham Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
