<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Experiences for Undergraduates Site in Biology: Ecology, Behavior and Physiology of Exotic Species</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>164786</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080303</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Eastern Illinois University (EIU) Biology Department's Research Experience for Undergraduates Program, funded by the National Science Foundation, will provide an intensive research experience for 10 undergraduate students during the summers of 2002 and 2003. The research experiences centered on the ecology, behavior and physiology of exotic species is designed to (1) stimulate the student's interest, intellectual independence and project ownership, (2) develop each student's technical skills and understanding of the research process, and (3) foster an appreciation of the cooperation and interdependence necessary for research teams to achieve success. To accomplish these objectives participants will be recruited nationally and selected based on their professional goals, motivation and maturity, and academic achievements. Students will be fully immersed in the research process as they choose their own research problem, write a proposal, conduct the work, and report their results and conclusions. Each participant will work closely with an individual mentor and as a member of a research team. Opportunities to interact and collaborate with other faculty and research teams will be provided through an orientation retreat, weekly group meetings, and a series of formal workshops and field trips. In addition, "visiting scientists", recognized leaders in the field of conservation biology, will spend 1-2 days apiece interacting with program participants by presenting seminars, participating in informal discussion groups, and critiquing research projects. The overall goal of the 10-week research experience is to foster in each participant an understanding of the research process, encouraging each student's growth from dependent learner to independent researcher to interdependent member of a scientific team.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0139028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bollinger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cfekb@eiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fischer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cfruf@eiu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Eastern Illinois University</Name>
      <CityName>Charleston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>619203099</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2175812125</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>600 Lincoln Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9184</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY - INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
