<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in the Behavioral &amp; Cognitive Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>68000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bonney Sheahan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award continues support for the Summer Undergraduate Research Program in the Cognitive and Behavioral Sciences at the University of Minnesota. This ten-week program will emphasize student participationh in the research activities of faculty affiliated with the Center for Cognitive Sciences. Eleven undergraduates will be selected from across the country. They will (1) work as a full member of a faculty mentor's research team; (2) give an oral presentation to peers and participating faculty and write a formal report on the research project engaged during the program; (3) take part in workshops devoted to research ethics, technical writing, and preparation for graduate studies; and (4) participate in a thrice-weekly multidisciplinary research training seminar. Seminar activities include presentations by faculty, laboratory tours, and field trips. The integrated program includes opportunities for the participants to learn specific research methods, to apply these methods in the context of their own research, and to examine broad conceptual and methodological issues relevant to the cognitive sciences and related areas. Participation in special social and cultural team building events as well as common housing in a university dormitory is designed to foster a strong community of students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award contributes to the Foundation's continuing efforts to attract talented students into careers in science through active undergraduate research experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0139449</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Herbert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>herbpick@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fletcher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fletc002@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
