<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Computability Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>120003</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lempp proposes research in both applied and pure computability&lt;br/&gt;theory. In the former area, Lempp proposes to investigate the&lt;br/&gt;computational complexity of models of uncountably categorical&lt;br/&gt;first-order theories, and of Boolean algebras. He also propose to&lt;br/&gt;study the proof-theoretic strength of combinatorial statements,&lt;br/&gt;esp. variants of Ramsey's Theorem, in order to find new&lt;br/&gt;proof-theoretic systems of weak second-order arithmetic. In the&lt;br/&gt;latter, i.e., in pure computability theory, Lempp plans to reach&lt;br/&gt;a better understanding of three important degree structures, the&lt;br/&gt;computably enumerable Turing degrees, the enumeration degrees of&lt;br/&gt;the Sigma^0_2-sets, and the Turing degrees of differences of&lt;br/&gt;computably enumerable sets, by investigating their finite&lt;br/&gt;substructures, in particular the embeddability of finite lattices&lt;br/&gt;and extensions of embeddings of partial orders into these degree&lt;br/&gt;structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computability theory is the study of the theoretical limitations&lt;br/&gt;of computation by machines, irrespective of limitations of bounds&lt;br/&gt;on memory space or run time. It is thus in some sense the&lt;br/&gt;theoretical cousin of complexity theory, an area of computer&lt;br/&gt;science studying computability within given time or memory space&lt;br/&gt;bounds. Typical results in computability theory show that certain&lt;br/&gt;mathematical problems cannot be solved by any computer, no matter&lt;br/&gt;how fast or how large. Up until the late 19th century,&lt;br/&gt;mathematics was essentially algorithmic: If you solved a problem,&lt;br/&gt;you could also give an effective procedure to find a&lt;br/&gt;solution. However, in the late 19th century, it turned out that&lt;br/&gt;many mathematical proofs could be done more abstractly and more&lt;br/&gt;elegantly, at the expense of effectiveness. Suspicions about this&lt;br/&gt;approach came to the front in the 1930's with the first&lt;br/&gt;undecidability results, showing that this abstraction often led&lt;br/&gt;to "non-algorithmic solutions". Lempp's research focuses on the&lt;br/&gt;analysis of unsolvable problems, mainly in algebra and&lt;br/&gt;combinatorics. Techniques and results in this area are often not&lt;br/&gt;only of great theoretical interest, but also have practical&lt;br/&gt;applications in computer science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0140120</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steffen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lempp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lempp@math.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
