<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Innovations in Net-Shape Composite Fabrication through Microscale Modeling of Melt Infiltration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>154325</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Lynn Realff</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Many important composite materials are made by melt infiltration, in which polymers or metals are infiltrated into fibrous preforms. To minimize post-processing and machining, it is desirable to create parts directly from the impregnation step, a procedure called net-shape fabrication. While numerical simulation is a crucial part of process design, standard models operate at the continuum scale (i.e., the underlying fiber matrix is viewed as a continuum phase). This approach is necessary for practical reasons, but it requires significant empiricism to generate spatially averaged constitutive equations and parameters. Furthermore, current empirical techniques do not effectively account for important microcscale phenomena such as fiber anisotropy, wetting effects, and void formation during impregnation. In this collaborative research project conducted by researchers at Louisiana State University and Tulane University, state-of-the-art microscale modeling techniques will be applied to the impregnation process, which will allow analyses to be performed using first principles. Experiments will be performed to aid in the model development and to validate its quantitative capabilities. In a second phase of the research, results from the microscale simulations will be scaled up and transferred to continuum-scale models for net-shape fabrication. The ultimate goal is for this multiple-scale approach to replace much of the empiricism associated with current methods, thereby improving fabrication techniques. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The collaborative nature of this project will provide unique learning opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, with graduate students from LSU participating in experimental aspects of the research at Tulane, and undergraduates from both institutions being included in research meetings at LSU. In addition, active participation in the Louisiana Alliance for Minority Participation is planed to provide summer research opportunities for students from under-represented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0140175</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karsten</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thompson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>karsten@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
