<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Mathematical Problems Inspired by String Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>114278</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigator studies IIA and IIB superconformal field theories on &lt;br/&gt;a Calabi-Yau variety in an attempt to give a rigorous mathematical &lt;br/&gt;definition of the vertex algebra of the theories. This algebra is &lt;br/&gt;expected to be a deformation of the cohomology of the chiral de Rham &lt;br/&gt;complex constructed by Malikov, Schechtman and Vaintrob. The second &lt;br/&gt;aim of the project is to extend the definition of IIA and IIB models &lt;br/&gt;to some singular varieties. The most pressing question is to connect &lt;br/&gt;two existing definitions of elliptic genus of singular varieties, &lt;br/&gt;which is a generalization of cohomological McKay correspondence. The&lt;br/&gt;third part of the project focuses on problems from number theory that&lt;br/&gt;arise in connection with the concept of elliptic genus and are related&lt;br/&gt;to products of Eisenstein series.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;String theory in its various flavors is a leading candidate for the&lt;br/&gt;``theory of everything'' in mathematical physics. Its development &lt;br/&gt;has led to rapid growth in several areas of mathematics, in particular&lt;br/&gt;algebraic geometry, which concerns itself with spaces of solutions of &lt;br/&gt;polynomial equations. Unfortunately, there is still a lack of rigorous &lt;br/&gt;understanding of some of the underlying rich mathematical structures,&lt;br/&gt;which the project aims to rectify. Such mathematical understanding is&lt;br/&gt;important, because it may be a necessity for future development of &lt;br/&gt;string theory which in turn may yield a more coherent picture of the&lt;br/&gt;basic processes and forces of our universe. A separate part of the &lt;br/&gt;project deals with certain number-theoretical questions inspired &lt;br/&gt;by string theory. These are related to long-standing mathematical&lt;br/&gt;problems in the theory of elliptic curves. The theory of elliptic&lt;br/&gt;curves is a crucial part of the proof of Fermat's Last Theorem and &lt;br/&gt;has practical applications to cryptography. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Algebra, Number Theory, and &lt;br/&gt;Combinatoric Program and the Topology and Geometric Analysis Program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0140172</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lev</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borisov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>borisov@math.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
