<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Groups and Algebraic Geometry at the Centre de Recherches Mathematiques</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>52000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia M. Wiegand</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will fund U.S. graduate students and post-doctoral &lt;br/&gt;fellows attending the Centre de Recherches Mathematiques in&lt;br/&gt;Montreal for periods of several weeks during a semester of&lt;br/&gt;activities centered on the theme of Groups and Algebraic Geometry&lt;br/&gt;during Spring, 2002. The activities planned include a strong&lt;br/&gt;component of training, including 1) a four day workshop on&lt;br/&gt;Hilbert Modular Varieties and Forms, 2) a one week Winter school&lt;br/&gt;on Computations in Coxeter Groups, 3) a one week workshop on&lt;br/&gt;Group Actions on Rational Varieties, 4) a two week workshop on&lt;br/&gt;Invariant Theory, 5) a one-month concentration period on the&lt;br/&gt;Langlands Program for Function Fields, 5) a two week workshop on&lt;br/&gt;Computational Lie Theory, and 6) a one week workshop on&lt;br/&gt;Algebraic Transformation Groups.&lt;br/&gt; The Centre de Recherches Mathematiques in Montreal is one of &lt;br/&gt;Canada's three research centers in the mathematical sciences, and &lt;br/&gt;has a broad mandate covering all of the various aspects of&lt;br/&gt;development of the discipline, with activities comprising theme&lt;br/&gt;years in various topics, a general conference program, an&lt;br/&gt;industrial program, a publications program in partnership with&lt;br/&gt;the American Mathematical Society, as well as activities devoted&lt;br/&gt;to education. The themes cover some of the most exciting areas&lt;br/&gt;of the mathematical sciences and typically alternate between pure&lt;br/&gt;and applied disciplines. This award will provide support for&lt;br/&gt;U.S. students and postdoctoral fellows so that they can attend&lt;br/&gt;the events during the Spring 2002 semester. This semester is&lt;br/&gt;thematically devoted to Groups and Algebraic Geometry, a&lt;br/&gt;difficult area of research in which few, if any, universities can&lt;br/&gt;offer coverage by advanced courses which allow for adequate&lt;br/&gt;graduate student preparation. This award will allow students to&lt;br/&gt;take advantage of an exceptional opportunity for education and&lt;br/&gt;training by the world's leading experts in areas that have seen&lt;br/&gt;significant numbers of recent breakthroughs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0140239</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dummit</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dummit@math.uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Vermont &amp; State Agricultural College</Name>
      <CityName>BURLINGTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>054050160</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8026563660</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>85 SO. PROSPECT ST.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Vermont</StateName>
      <StateCode>VT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
