<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Langlands Reciprocity and Automorphic Forms</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew D. Pollington</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project concerns reciprocity laws, which are correspondences between different sets of objects preserving certain quantities, each defined by separate means. Reciprocity laws are found in abundance in many disciplines, ranging from mathematics and physics to engineering, network theory, and social sciences. The two sets of objects may a priori have no way of seeing each other and that makes such laws truly fascinating. One of the deepest examples of reciprocity are those appearing in number theory, a rather general form of which is due to Artin and Langlands, for which the famous "Quadratic Reciprocity Law" is just a first example. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Such reciprocity laws suggest an indexing of certain presentations of "Galois groups" by complex matrices, objects of arithmetic nature, with infinite dimensional presentations of general linear groups over local fields, objects of analytic nature, preserving certain complex functions (root numbers and L-functions) attached to them by totally separate means. An important part of this project is to show that this reciprocity is robust by developing an approach to establishing this equality for all such factors. More precisely, this project suggests an approach to establishing the equality of certain Artin factors (Artin root numbers and L-functions) with those obtained from analytic methods, e.g., those coming from Langlands-Shahidi method. These will carry information from one side to the other including equality of conductors, root numbers and possibly R-groups. There will be consequences in representation theory and automorphic forms such as many cases of tempered L-packet and its converse, generic A-packet conjectures, as well as normalization of intertwining operators by means of Artin factors as demanded by Arthur and Langlands and the conjecture of Lapid and Mao as well as others. As another project, one hopes to obtain results on p-adic L-functions by means of Fourier coefficients of Eisenstein series where their complex versions show up. Certain intertwining relations for covering groups will also be established, as well as study of Weyl's law by means of twisted trace formula as part of a student doctorate thesis. The project suggests training of graduate students through teaching courses, mentoring, and advising.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1500759</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Freydoon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shahidi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shahidi@math.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
