<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2015-2020 Louis Stokes Louisiana Alliance for Minority Participation - Louisiana Senior Level Alliance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1950000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dr. A. James Hicks</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) program assists universities and colleges in diversifying the science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) workforce through their efforts at significantly increasing the numbers of students from historically underrepresented minority populations to successfully complete high quality degree programs in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Southern University and A&amp;M College, lead institution for the Louis Stokes-Louisiana Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (LS-LAMP), consists of a consortium of twelve two-and four-year institutions and one research organization in the state. The alliance, located in a NSF Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR) jurisdiction, will expand its research capability through this project by producing up to 900 new STEM baccalaureate degrees annually and retaining 25% of these students for STEM graduate studies by 2020. These goals will be accomplished by expanding partnerships with the pre-college community, community colleges, 4-year institutions, and other institutional, state, and national programs, public and private research organizations, and funding sources to expand student and faculty opportunities and to address continuing sustainability and institutionalization of successful practices in engagement and retention of STEM students. The continued implementation of the Ten Strand Systemic Mentoring Model and best practices in teaching and learning for STEM minority undergraduate students (including financial support and research participation locally, nationally, and internationally) will be employed over the next five years in addition to enhancing the instructional and research infrastructures of partner institutions to achieve project success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Evaluation will be conducted by an external evaluation review board. Project results will be disseminated via the alliance and partner institution websites and the LS-LAMP "Best Practices Manual" and Journal.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1503226</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ella</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kelley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>elkchem@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diola</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bagayoko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bagayoko@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kerry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davidson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kerry.davidson@regents.la.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stubblefield</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>luria_stubblefield@subr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana Board of Regents</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708025243</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2253424253</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1201 N. Third Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9133</Code>
      <Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
