<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Commercialization of Microgrid Controllers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Microgrid technology (an emerging technology to enhance power system reliability) is essential to manage the transition to tomorrow's energy supply model. The United States power grid is evolving into a network of new technologies with increased reliance on a diversity of energy resources - resources that are sustainable, renewable and abundant to power homes, businesses, military installations and industry. Yet, the resources are at the same time fluctuating and inconsistent. The proposed technology aims to reduce dependence on the utility grid, and the possibility of major blackouts reduces to infinitesimal for customers. The successful implementation of the proposed technology will pave way for more advanced research and development in this field and contribute to transforming the current energy infrastructure to becoming more resilient. The benefits of the proposed technology can and will be felt throughout the spectrum of generators and consumers: generators will deliver their energy in an optimal and efficient way; and consumers will receive uninterruptible power supply. With lesser wastage of power, higher power quality, good storage management at reasonable costs, the proposed technology resonates with the current demands of the energy market target customers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This technology is based on novel control strategies for various elements of the microgrid system (such as different energy resources, energy storage systems, and customer loads, etc.). This I-Corps team has developed a unique smart microgrid controller that will enable resource optimization as well as increase stability of renewable microgrid. With the advent of this technology, the microgrid will become more robust and efficient. In addition, the goal is to minimize the total operation cost so that microgrids can be widely adopted in the energy market. The controller has the ability to effectively synchronize among different energy resources such as diesel, solar, wind, hydro, etc. under different operating conditions. The possibility of major blackouts is thereby reduced to infinitesimal. Thus, the proposed controller equips the microgrid with higher stability, efficiency, better power quality, reliability and resiliency. Some distinct features of this smart microgrid controller include: user-friendliness; increased penetration of renewable energy sources; better co-ordination and optimal utilization of different energy sources such as wind, solar, diesel, hydro, etc.; enhanced stability and power quality; effective battery storage management. The controller works as an intelligent unit and supports the entire microgrid system thereby enabling customers to save energy and money.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1506772</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David Wenzhong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Wenzhong.Gao@du.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Denver</Name>
      <CityName>Denver</CityName>
      <ZipCode>802104711</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3038712000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2199 S. University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
