<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>UNS:Collaborative research: Resolving changes in microscopic properties as a result of hybrid polymer-ZIF membrane formation to enable rational design of such membranes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>230000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Angela Lueking</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1510442/1510411&lt;br/&gt;Lively/Vasenkov&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Approximately 15% of domestic energy in the United States is consumed in separation processes. Composite membrane separators comprised of particles of advanced molecular sieve material embedded into a polymer film are a promising class of membranes with the potential to make meaningful impact on the energy efficiency of separation processes. The proposed research will establish experimental framework that allows resolving microscopic transport, sorption and structural properties of such composite membranes and finding relationships between these properties and the corresponding macroscopic properties relevant for applications in separations. The fundamental understanding of the microscopic properties of the composite membranes will lay the foundation for rationally designed composite membranes optimized for gas separations and pervaporation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIFs), a class of metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) that have zeolite-like structures, can be embedded into a glassy polymer matrix to form a mixed matrix membrane (MMM). Such membranes capture both the molecular sieving properties of the ZIF and the ease of processing associated with polymers. The main goal of this work is to develop a fundamental understanding of the relationship between the transport, sorption and structural properties of the MMM constituents and those of the corresponding neat materials. The PIs propose to use a synergetic strategy based on the application of several state-of-the-art and even unique NMR and sorption characterization techniques to achieve such resolution. The potentially transformative outcome of the proposed work is to enable the design of ZIF-polymer MMMs based on the understanding of changes of the transport, sorption and structural properties of the MMM constituents in comparison to those of the neat materials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary focus of the educational and outreach project plan is to establish a new inter-campus research mentoring program for K-12 and undergraduate students from underrepresented groups. This program will offer students participation in well-defined engineering projects, development of engaging animations and educational demonstrations related to membrane separations, presentation of these animations and demonstrations to younger students and participation in a student exchange between the UF and Georgia Tech groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1510442</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Johannes</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leisen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johannes.leisen@chemistry.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lively</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ryan.lively@chbe.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1417</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL &amp; BIOLOGICAL SEPAR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>045E</Code>
      <Text>Adv Mats for Separation Process</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>136E</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Separation Processes</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
