<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>UNS: multiphase-UQ: Uncertainty Quantification Framework for Multiphase Flow Simulations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>276365</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1511325(Owkes)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposal is to develop a novel methodology to quantify the uncertainty of computational fluid dynamic (CFD) simulations of gas-liquid multiphase flows. While a lot of effort has been spent on developing more accurate numerical techniques for simulations, the important question of the accuracy of computational results in the face of unavoidable uncertainty about fluid properties, boundary and initial conditions, which is present when real life engineering problems are simulated, has not been addressed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is proposed to build upon recent developments for single-phase flows in order to couple uncertainty quantification and multiphase flow numerical techniques and to create a rigorous methodology for measuring output uncertainties from input uncertainties. Specifically, a framework for representing a stochastic interface with associated discontinuities will be developed. The PI will couple an interface capturing methods (level set and Volume of Fluid) with intrusive Uncertainty Quantification techniques to develop a stochastic level set method to represent discontinuous gas-liquid interfaces. This framework will be applicable for propagating uncertainty in other applications with discontinuities such as crack propagation in solid mechanics and fluid-structure interactions and will have the potential to change the way engineers study and predict these systems. Applications of multiphase flow occur quite commonly in the process and manufacturing industry. The simulations proposed can have applications to many areas, since a myriad of engineering and environmental flows including fuel injection, proton exchange membrane (PEM) fuel cells, nuclear power generation, concentrating-solar plants, biological flows, and wave energy harvesting devices are affected by multiphase flows. A dedicated website hosted at Montana State University will provide a central access point to the simulation parameters and data. Numerical codes and results developed during this project will be disseminated through the PI's website and through the library at Montana State University which provides open-access dissemination services.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1511325</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Owkes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mark.owkes@montana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Montana State University</Name>
      <CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1443</Code>
      <Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6892</Code>
      <Text>CI REUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>058E</Code>
      <Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
