<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAPSI: Pattern Formation on Liquid-Air Interfaces Due to Resonance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>When a stacked two fluid system is shaken in a direction perpendicular to the fluid interface, patterns on the fluid interface will develop as a result of resonance. This phenomenon is known as Faraday instability. Experimental research in collaboration with Dr. Satoshi Matsumoto at the Japanese Aerospace Exploration Agency (JAXA) will allow the PI to study and validate theoretical calculations for the development of patterns generated on a liquid-air interface through the use of electric fields. This collaboration offers access to both a unique experimental apparatus and a world-class research staff. The apparatus has been used previously to perform successful preliminary trials. The understanding of interfacial pattern generation will lead to advancements in a multitude of industrially relevant processes, including semiconductor crystal growth, microfluidic mixing enhancement, and oil recovery techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Electrostatic parametric forcing offers a unique approach to the generation of Faraday instability within multi-fluid systems. Through the application of nonlinear dynamics, researchers will delineate the underlying physics of this instability when generated via electrostatic oscillations. Experiments conducted in JAXA will allow for the validation of the stability thresholds for systems of multiple fluids and geometries obtained through a linear stability analysis that rigorously treats viscosity. The research will complement traditional studies on mechanically forced Faraday instability, offering additional insight into the physics of surface forcing. This knowledge will translate into the understanding of self-induced oscillations that occur in interfacial convection, interfacial evaporation, and phase transformations such as solidification and electrodeposition. The separation of the scales that govern surface forcing and bulk forcing will advance the understanding of other instability phenomena where both bulk and surface forces participate. Direct applications of the research include microfluidic mixing enhancement, a deeper understanding of liquid sloshing dynamics, and the potential for enhanced oil recovery when using hydraulic fracturing. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1514711</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ward</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>06/08/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ward Kevin L</Name>
      <CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326076047</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
