<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: On-Site, Real-Time, Continuous Measurement of Hazardous Pesticides in Water Matrices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>148000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project can be seen through the increased measurement requirements of pesticides in drinking in the U.S. and around the world. Several government agencies including the U.S. EPA Office of Water, U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), and State Environmental Departments, and local city and county agencies monitor drinking water for pesticides. And new studies are reporting additional and worsening health effects of ingesting various pesticides. Quick identification and measurement, in addition to low-cost and simplified testing methods the technology can assist by significantly increase the frequency of testing, identifying the contaminating source and then remediating thus helping to reduce the quantities of pesticides being consumed overall. While ANDalyze has already shown the technology potential with various heavy metal sensors, additional opportunity can be seen in the measurement capability for pesticides and other organic molecules which will be initially proven by first developing a fluorescent sensor for the herbicide atrazine using DNA aptamer technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will help to address the contamination of trace pesticides, such as Atrazine, in our water resources which pose a serious health concern. Their simple, quick and inexpensive measurement is essential for driving effective removal technologies. Currently pesticide measurements are conducted solely in the laboratory using sophisticated instrumentation which are expensive (~$900ea test) and require skilled operators. Using a patented DNA-based sensing technology, ANDalyze has created a method of detecting and quantifying chemical levels based on the recent discovery of the catalytic properties of DNA. By applying in-vitro selection to identify DNA aptamers that have high selectivity and sensitivity for atrazine, performing biochemical characterization and optimization of the DNA aptamers to assess their selectivity and sensitivity for the atrazine against similar molecules (triazine class) and other common pesticides, and finally developing a fluorescent sensor for detection using the ANDalyze fluorimeter, ANDalyze can offer simple, fast, inexpensive, reliable and on-site, real time detection of such contaminants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1520261</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Debapriya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mazumdar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmazumdar@andalyze.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Andalyze</Name>
      <CityName>Champaign</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207460</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173280045</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2109 S. Oak St.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1185</Code>
      <Text>SENSORY SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6840</Code>
      <Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8035</Code>
      <Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
