<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Reconstructed Boat Landing for California Polytechnic State University's Center for Coastal Marine Sciences Pier Facility</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>344272</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter H. McCartney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>California Polytechnic State University will replace a fixed-level vessel landing at the Cal Poly Pier, the primary field facility of the Center for Coast Marine Sciences (CCMS). The CCMS coordinates the marine research and teaching at the University, primarily using the Cal Poly Pier. The Pier extends 1 km into Port San Luis Bay, and has an extensive flow-through seawater system as well as facilities for diving operations and the deployment of small boats. However, the existing boat landing on the pier is an aging, fixed platform that is marginally safe and usable only during the calmest of sea conditions, conditions that are rarely present on the California central coast. This project will replace the current access platforms with a larger fixed platform and calls for the installation of a camel vessel mooring and fender system to provide a buffer between the pier and vessels moored against it. The project will also increase the capacity of the hoist, allowing for easier deployment of vessels. This will make deployment of vessels and access to the waterline and vessels much safer and easier, permitting access in a variety of sea conditions and tidal heights. The new platforms and hoist will allow the CCMS to further increase capacity and scope for year-round field research and field teaching, all while improving access and efficiency and greatly increasing safety. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CCMS, the Pier, and all resources are managed by the College of Science and Math. These resources are available to any researcher or faculty member in the College for no cost, aside from consumables (e.g. fuel), providing a significant in-kind contribution to and lowering the cost of marine science teaching and research. The CCMS currently operates five research vessels, from a 13 foot Boston Whaler to a 26 foot Radon, the R/V Tom Richards. In the Pier's current state, the only boat access to the water is via a fixed landing with upper and lower elements at approximately 3 and 1 m above mean lower low water (MLLW), respectively. As such, access to the water is challenging in all but the calmest sea conditions, which are rarely present along the California central coast. The main elements of this project include removal of the current lower landing, expansion of the upper landing to cover an area of 12 x 20 ft., installation of a camel vessel mooring and fender system to provide a buffer between the pier and vessels moored against it, and replacement of the current jib crane motor and hoist mechanism to a 1-ton capacity system. This expansion and improvement will provide greatly enhanced access to the waterline and to Cal Poly's fleet of small boats in a range of sea conditions, significantly improving safety and expanding the educational and scientific opportunities for marine science students and researchers at Cal Poly.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1522528</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Crow</FirstName>
      <LastName>White</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cwhite31@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wendt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dwendt@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruttenberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>benjamin.ruttenberg@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Polytechnic State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Luis Obispo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>934070830</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8057562982</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Grand Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1104</Code>
      <Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
