<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2015 Summer Program at Center for Theoretical Underground Physics and Related Areas (CETUP*)/PPC June 15-July 17, 2015 in Lead/Deadwood, SD.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James J. Whitmore</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will provide participant support for early career scientists and graduate students to participate in the fifth CETUP* (Center for Theoretical Underground Physics and Related Areas) summer program that is planned to take place on June 15 - July 17, 2015 in Lead/Deadwood, SD. The main goal of CETUP* is to bring together people with different expertise to address the most exciting questions in particle and nuclear physics, astrophysics, geosciences, and geo-microbiology. This year's program will focus on Dark Matter and Neutrino Physics, bringing together experts in dark matter, neutrino physics, particle physics, nuclear physics, astrophysics and cosmology. Scientists invited to participate in the program will not only provide theoretical support to the underground science, but they will also examine core questions of the 21st century including: What is dark matter? How well do we know the neutrino parameters? How have neutrinos shaped the evolution of the universe? How were the heavy elements made? What are the fundamental underlying symmetries of the Universe? Is there a Grand Unified Theory of the Universe? How do supernovae explode?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2015 CETUP* will consist of a 5-week long program. A two-week long session on Dark Matter physics will be followed by a two-week long program on Neutrino physics. The IXth International Conference on Interconnections between Particle Physics and Cosmology (PPC) will be hosted in the time between these two sessions covering the subjects of dark matter, neutrino physics, and collider physics from both theoretical end experimental aspects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: basic research affects many areas of modern science and technology. A better understanding of the potential connections between new fundamental particles will lead to determining their impact on the early universe. The program will offer a stimulating environment for research collaborations between diverse groups of scientists and training of young scientists, including undergraduate and graduate students and underrepresented groups. Numerous outreach efforts will aim to share the excitement of the research with K-12, undergraduate and graduate students, teachers and the general public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1523395</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kumar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jkumar@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Szczerbinska</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Barbara.Szczerbinska@dsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bhaskar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dutta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dutta@physics.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Teruki</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kamon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kamon@physics.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Akif Baha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Balantekin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baha@physics.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Dakota State University</Name>
      <CityName>Madison</CityName>
      <ZipCode>570421799</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6052565112</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>820 N. Washington Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1221</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1286</Code>
      <Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1643</Code>
      <Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7235</Code>
      <Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
