<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Fourth Symposium on Industrial Ecology for Young Professionals (SIEYP IV)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49775</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1523263 (Chertow)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is in partial support of the fourth Symposium on Industrial Ecology for Young Professionals (SIEYP IV), to be held in Surrey, UK on July 11, 2015. SIEYP IV is to be held in connection and immediately following the biannual International Society for Industrial Ecology (ISIE) conference, and is planned, organized, and attended by students and young professionals. It aims at promoting communication among graduate students and post-doctoral researchers in industrial ecology (IE) about their research, ideas, and experiences. This project is organized by the Student Chapter of the International Society for Industrial Ecology in an effort to encourage and financially support participation by U.S.-based students and post-doctoral researchers in the symposium and the ISIE 2015 Conference immediately preceding it. Members of groups underrepresented in IE are especially encouraged to apply. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium will enable young professionals from around the world to establish an international network of industrial ecology researchers for ongoing exchange and future collaborations in topics such as life cycle assessment, industrial symbiosis, eco-design, material flow and stock analysis, environmentally extended input output analysis, and sustainable consumption. The theme of SIEYP IV will be "Envisioning Future Agendas in Industrial Ecology". During the past decades, industrial ecology has developed and matured in terms of its knowledge structure and content, theoretical foundations, analytical methods and tools, and its applications in real-world practices. It is thus the right time to ask where the discipline has been and where it is going, in order to drive it towards an unfolding new era. SIEYP IV will provide this opportunity for international students and young professionals- the next generation of industrial ecologists- to share and learn from each other, collectively reflecting upon the evolution of the discipline and envisioning its future agendas. It echoes the theme and focus of the ISIE 2015 Conference, which is aimed at "Taking Stock of Industrial Ecology".</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1523263</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chertow</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marian.chertow@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7643</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8020</Code>
      <Text>Green Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
