<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBP 2015 Outreach Efforts to Increase Diversity and Participation of Minorities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19836</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 2015 Social Computing, Behavioral-Cultural Modeling, and Prediction (SBP) conference will be held in Washington DC from March 31- April 3, 2015. The primary objectives are to provide an international platform for collaborative and exploratory research for a synergistic advancement of the emerging field of social computing. Social computing and behavioral modeling lie at the intersection of various disciplines, from computing and linguistics to the social sciences, economics and medicine. SBP is a highly interdisciplinary conference offering a rare and exciting opportunity for behavioral and social science researchers to come together with computational and computer scientists and other related disciplines. Through reaching out to students from diverse backgrounds, the travel grants supported by this award will broaden the base of interdisciplinary research involving computer science; students from many of these disciplines are less likely to have other travel support options than computer scientists. Past travel awards to SBP have been effective in attracting applicants from groups underrepresented in Computer Science. Through paper and poster presentations, interdisciplinary tutorials, keynote presentations, technical challenge problems and cross-fertilization round table sessions involving researchers and program staff from federal agencies, the conference aims to offer training, professional development, and community building opportunities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1523458</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nitin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Agarwal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nxagarwal@ualr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adjeroh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>don@csee.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>West Virginia University Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>265066845</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3042933998</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 6845</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
