<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GLOBE@20 Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>ICER</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Jones</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This RAPID project supports the advancement of STEM education among elementary and secondary students and the general public through increasing opportunities to participate in authentic, inquiry-based science investigations of the environment using scientific protocols and infrastructure offered by the Global Learning and Observations to Benefit the Environment (GLOBE) program. The GLOBE program, launched on Earth Day 1995, is a highly successful, science education program that now operates in more than 110 countries. Over 66,000 teachers and millions of students have participated in the program. In conjunction with the upcoming 20th anniversary of the program, GLOBE is launching a new citizen science campaign that will expand GLOBE beyond its traditional focus on formal education settings. If successful, this pilot citizen science effort will allow GLOBE to greatly expand its reach and impact on science literacy worldwide. In addition, GLOBE will initiate a year-long GLOBE@20 campaign of observations and collaborative student research projects that will culminate in a new International Science Fair that will be held during the week of Earth Day 2016. With its focus on inquiry-based science, use of authentic data, and addressing real-world environmental problems, GLOBE supports development of the scientific and critical thinking skills necessary for tomorrow's STEM-literate workforce. The opportunities offered by GLOBE to engage and collaborate with an international community of participants also promote global awareness and cross-cultural understanding, collaboration, and environmental stewardship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GLOBE@20 celebration events are being co-developed by NASA (primary sponsor of GLOBE operations), the GLOBE Implementation Office (GIO) based at UCAR, and WestEd, recipient of this award. WestEd's role in the GLOBE@20 efforts include: 1) developing the strategies, tools, and resources for communicating with, engaging, and enabling participation of members of the public who seek to participate in the pilot GLOBE citizen science campaign; 2) developing the assessment rubrics, participation protocols and guides, and supporting materials that underpin implementation of the 2016 International Science Fair for GLOBE students; and, 3) developing the coherent communications strategy and resources to showcase the outcomes of GLOBE program activities and promote awareness of opportunities to participate in on-going GLOBE program education and research activities, either through school-based or citizen science-based activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1528209</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schneider</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sschnei@wested.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Svetlana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Darche</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sdarche@wested.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>WestEd</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941071242</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4156153136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>730 Harrison Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7699</Code>
      <Text>ICER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
