<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Testing Cognitive and Affective Interventions to Improve Public Understanding and Affective Reactions to Pandemic Risks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>336626</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>When thinking about infectious diseases and making decisions about how to protect themselves, people often overreact to infectious diseases with low risk of infection, such as Ebola, and at other times fail to respond to infectious diseases with higher risk of infection, such as the flu. Both types of responses can lead to negative outcomes such as stress and anxiety, less productivity at work, and inefficient use of healthcare resources (either using too much or too little depending on the disease). We think that one reason that people may exhibit these responses to infectious diseases is that there may be a conflict between their beliefs about their risk and their feelings about their risk. This research will examine areas of misinformation and emotional responses to three infectious diseases: Ebola, the flu, and MERS. After identifying key areas of misinformation and excessive or subdued emotional responses to these three diseases, the research team develops and tests a number of communication strategies that best correct misinformation and resolve conflicts between beliefs and feelings of risk to motivate more appropriate responses to infectious diseases. After determining which strategies are better at doing those things than others, the research team creates a website to display "best-practices" in communicating about infectious diseases.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research involves conducting a number of web studies to investigate when and for whom cognitive- and affective-based communication strategies work best at modifying cognitions, affect, and behavioral intentions towards pandemic risks. The research uses the theory of "risk-as-feelings". These studies will advance our understanding of risk-as-feelings in a number of ways. First, the research team examines the frequency of simultaneous contradictory responses (SCRs) - when beliefs and feelings of risk conflict - at least with these three infectious diseases. Second, the research team tests for the existence of simultaneous contradictory affective responses. Third, the team then assesses the relative influence of cognitive and affective sources of information on cognitions, affective reactions, and behavioral intentions, as well as in the possible resolution of SCRs. Fourth, the application of risk-as-feelings to determine optimal communication strategies about these infectious diseases should serve as a test-case for the utility of incorporating risk-as-feelings into public health theories of health behavior and communication. Fifth, due to its foundation in the theory of risk-as-feelings, insights gleaned from the current studies should help shape the way information is communicated about other public health issues beyond these disease. And finally, the research tests whether resolving SCRs is key to inducing appropriate responses to pandemic risks or whether improving knowledge, acknowledging fears, and/or improving feelings of efficacy, is sufficient to improve responses, as would be predicted by standard health behavior theories from public health.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1529788</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scherer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aaron-scherer@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scherer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aaron-scherer@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/05/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fagerlin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fagerlin@med.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zikmund-Fisher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bzikmund@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zikmund-Fisher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bzikmund@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/05/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1321</Code>
      <Text>DECISION RISK &amp; MANAGEMENT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1638</Code>
      <Text>INFRAST MGMT &amp; EXTREME EVENTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
