<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of A Multiphoton Confocal Laser Scanning Microscope for Life Science and Biomedical Research and Training at SUNY Binghamton</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>610868</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexander Leonessa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal seeks to acquire a Zeiss LSM 880 NOL 3-channel multiphoton confocal laser scanning microscope to upgrade SUNY Binghamton University's (BU) eight-year-old Leica SP 5 single photon confocal microscope that has helped BU faculty to successfully develop top-ranked research programs. The existing microscope was originally configured for thin tissue sample and microorganism imaging. With the expansion of BU research programs in neuroscience, stem cell and regenerative medicine, 3D tissue bioprinting, nanomedicine, etc., the University is in urgent need of a more advanced multiphoton confocal microscope for live cell imaging. LSM880 NOL is a two photon confocal microscope capable of subcellular imaging. Access to this state-of-the-art microscope will propel BU's recent Health Science Initiative, boost faculty research capabilities in Biomedical Engineering, Biological Science, Chemistry, and Psychology Departments and the newly-formed Pharmacy School. It will also help more individuals on campus obtain preliminary results to seek for NSF and NIH funding. The outcome of this project would have a broader impact on our fundamental understanding of how cell and protein behave dynamically in vivo. This project address unmet needs to study cell biology, gene regulation, neuron firing, and tissue regeneration/remodeling in live cells, tissues, and small animals at single cell and single molecule level. Furthermore, its acquisition will foster BU's collaboration with industries to accelerate the translation of life science and biomedical engineering discoveries into bioproducts. A comprehensive management plan will ensure that the instrument always runs at peak and near peak capacity. The strong financial and management commitment from BU and the researchers involved in this project will sustain the facility after the project period.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal seeks to acquire a Zeiss LSM 880 NOL 3-channel multiphoton confocal laser scanning microscope to upgrade SUNY Binghamton University's (BU) eight-year-old Leica SP 5 single photon confocal microscope that has helped BU faculty to successfully develop top-ranked research programs. LSM880 NOL is a two photon confocal microscope. Its pulsed, ultrafast infrared laser excites fluorescent dyes or proteins only at the focal point, where photon density is high enough to produce fluorescence. The red excitation light penetrates much deeper into tissue close to 1 mm. It can resolve 140 nm laterally and 400 nm axially at 488 nm, allowing for subcellular imaging. The breadth of research interests, coupled with the current funding of investigators involved in this project poses urgent need for the acquisition of the microscope at BU. The acquisition of this advanced multiphoton microscope will immediately affect more than 17 research labs across six Departments in three schools. More labs will be impacted once the system is set up on campus. The investigators involved in this project are well funded by NSF, NIH, etc. and have research projects that are directly related to the microscope. The acquisition of the instrument will not only permit them to develop more collaborative projects with researchers across the campus, state and nation, but it will also allow faculty to pursue new directions of research and contribute greatly to the growth of BU's research and academic programs. It will enable investigators to study interaction between cell-cell and cell-extracellular matrix; to track cell migration, differentiation, and proliferation; to investigate cell recruitment during wound healing, organ transplantation and tissue regeneration/remodeling; and to measure biochemical reactions such as diffusion, receptors/ligand interaction within live cells, tissues, 3D printed organoids or small animals. Knowledge gained from these studies will significantly advance both bioscience and bioengineering. The acquisition of the microscope will propel and accelerate these advances. It will remarkably enhance BU's research infrastructure in life science and biomedical engineering by providing a multiuser imaging facility that is open to all investigators and students across the campus, state, and nation. Furthermore, it will provide a powerful resource for teaching modern biology and bioengineering. A new lab course focusing on live cell and tissue multiphoton microscopy will be developed and offer to both undergraduate and graduate students. Workshops and open house will be held to train and attract new users to access to the microscope and to reach out to K-12 and local communities, especially those from underrepresented groups. It will offer additional research training opportunities for summer REU students. Finally, it will serve as an excellent recruiting tool for attracting top-notch faculty to the university.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1531944</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sjin@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eriks</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rozners</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>erozners@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kaiming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ye</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kye@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gloria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meredith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gmeredith@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
      <CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
