<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Engineering Education Maker Identity Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299778</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research effort at Texas State University, a large Hispanic Serving Institution in San Marcos, Texas, advances the field of engineering education by exploring the creative and novel learning environment of Makerspaces in a university setting while benefiting current Engineering/Engineering Technology students as well as Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) Education students (future teachers). The research team will study issues relating to the effects of these novel learning environments on engineering learning and how these spaces may best leverage the real world experiences of students as pathways to engineering, including prior work on the ranch, farm, construction, home or military. Reaching over 900 students, University partners and faculty will carry out design and engineering activities that value students and their prior making skills, life experiences, and cultural funds of knowledge. The project will examine how design courses may be restructured to foster a positive and inclusive environment and enhance the success of students from underrepresented populations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Makerspace experiences have the potential to be a valuable complement to structured classroom learning, but little is known about how and in what ways they are effective, and what characteristics of makerspaces optimize their effectiveness. The primary experimental work for this research aims to: 1) discover key concepts and principles that particularly enable a more diverse group of students to leverage creativity and innovation toward success in engineering careers; 2) discover specific learning models that involve both STEM university students and pre-service teachers in order to develop teamwork, self -efficacy, communication, and identity formation in the Maker environment; and 3) validate instruments to measure the impact of such programs on students self-efficacy, communication, and identity formation. Perspectives gained will facilitate the retention and persistence to graduation of participating students. The insights gained from this research will enable institutions across the nation to be able to restructure design-based education and engineering courses so as to enhance student success by incorporating makerspace-based design projects. The project employs a non-cost prohibitive and replicable approach as well as a model for scaling operation and research to a broad level.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1531375</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vedaraman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sriraman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vs04@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Talley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kgt5@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Araceli</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ortiz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amo56@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shaunna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sfs36@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas State University - San Marcos</Name>
      <CityName>San Marcos</CityName>
      <ZipCode>786664616</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5122452314</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>110E</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
