<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TIP: Infusing Laboratory-Bench STEM Into Exercise Physiology Via Integration of Chemistry, Biology, and Biophysics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399961</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrea Johnson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) through Targeted Infusion Projects supports the development, implementation, and study of evidence-based innovative models and approaches for improving the preparation and success of HBCU undergraduate students so that they may pursue STEM graduate programs and/or careers. The project at Winston-Salem State University (WSSU) seeks to infuse a novel, engaging bioengineering project into the existing Exercise Physiology curriculum. This project will enhance student abilities to use lab-bench techniques to provide an innovative educational opportunity to funnel the next generation of talent into the STEM pipeline. Novel aspects of this proposal include: offering this experience to undergraduates; offering this experience using Exercise Physiology as a platform; infusing the lab-bench modules using a bioengineering project as a vehicle; and offering this experience at a HBCU, so that underrepresented students are funneled into STEM graduate schools and careers. The Department of Exercise Physiology at WSSU will be one of the first, if not the first in the nation, HBCU or otherwise, to offer this experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to infuse lab-bench modules into the Exercise Physiology curriculum at WSSU. The objectives of this project are to: 1) improve student attitudes toward use of lab bench-based techniques; 2) improve student perceptions of scientific inquiry in Exercise Physiology; 3) increase student intentions to engage in undergraduate research; and 4) increase student intentions to persist in STEM-related fields. Thus, this project has the potential to advance knowledge related to cognitive and behavioral factors that may determine whether or not an underrepresented STEM undergraduate pursues graduate school.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1533476</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Henderson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hendersondx@wssu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Breonte</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>guybs@wssu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Markert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>markertcd@wssu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/29/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Winston-Salem State University</Name>
      <CityName>Winston Salem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>271100001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3367502413</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 Martin Luther King Jr., Driv</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
