<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IPAC'15 - Student and Teacher support - The International Particle Accelerator Conference (IPAC'15) will hold it's Sixth Annual Meeting in Richmond, Virginia, May 3-8, 2015.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vyacheslav S. Lukin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will provide support for graduate and undergraduate students to participate in one of the world's leading accelerator conferences, the 6th International Particle Accelerator Conference, to be held in Richmond VA May 3-8, 2015. This conference expects over 1300 participants from around the world, including many of the leaders in accelerator science research. There are many presentations in all major topics in accelerator science: linear and circular colliders, photon sources, electron accelerators, alternative sources, hadron accelerators, beam dynamics, instrumentation and controls, and others. In addition the conference will have sessions on technology transfer and accelerator applications applicable to a wide field of industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award will be used to support, entirely or in part, approximately 35 students. They will be making presentations which will be made available on the public web page. The students will also participate in broadening representation programs: Teacher's Day Program, Women in Science and the National Society of Hispanic Physicists. This program will be an excellent opportunity for young scientists to gain information and for them to interact with more experienced researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1534731</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rmoy@sura.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/20/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southeastern Universities Research Association</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200053928</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2024087872</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1201 New York Avenue NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7243</Code>
      <Text>Accelerator Science</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
