<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Understanding the Behavior of Policymakers: Accountability, Other-Regarding Behavior and Fiduciary Motivation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>290000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nancy A. Lutz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award funds research that will use formal modeling and empirical methods, including laboratory decision making experiments, to develop and test a number of hypothesis about the factors that determine the behavior of elected group leaders. The overall goal is to consider how the way a leader was selected affects his/her leadership decisions. For elected leaders, concern for one's supporters, the desire for re-election, and a fiduciary interest in the group's overall wellbeing may interact to determine how leaders make decisions. Appointed or promoted leaders would make different decisions. The project advances science by developing and testing richer theories of leadership. The work may give us new practical insights on the best way to choose leaders for groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Current theories in political economy view policymakers (whether they are elected or appointed) as economic agents with their own motivations and objectives. However, these leaders generally have a mix of objectives, ranging from ideology to re-election to concern for the public good. The project examines how this mix of objectives affects leadership decisions. The first part of the project considers structural estimation of a political agency model. The second part of the project includes theoretical and empirical investigation of other-regarding? behavior by office holders who are not driven by re-election. The last part of the project uses lab experiments to test the theory that other-regarding behavior by policymakers is in part the result of a fiduciary motive. That is, simply holding an elected office makes individuals more likely to value the common good.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1534132</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Drazen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drazen@econ.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1320</Code>
      <Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
