<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SI2-SSE: yt: Reusable Components for Simulating, Analyzing and Visualizing Astrophysical Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>427003</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajiv Ramnath</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Computational modeling of astrophysical phenomena has grown in sophistication and realism, leading to a diversity of complex simulation platforms, each utilizing its own mechanism and format for representing particles and fluids. Similarly, most of the data analysis is conducted with tools developed in isolation and targeted to a specific simulation platform or research domain; very little systematic and direct technology transfer between astrophysical researchers exists. The yt project is a parallel analysis and visualization toolkit designed to support a collaborative community of researchers as they focus on answering physical questions, rather than the technical mechanics of reading, processing and visualizing data formats. This project will enable the development of advanced, physics-based modules that apply universally across simulation codes, advancing scientific inquiry and enabling more efficient utilization of computational and human resources. In doing so, it will help advance a myriad of research goals from the study of black hole binaries to the growth of cosmic structure. In addition, the project will serve as a touchstone for collaboration and cross-code utilization between many groups studying diverse phenomena. Moreover, the project will be developed through a community-oriented process, engaging a wide range of participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The infrastructure development in this research will enable these capabilities by broadening the applicable simulation platforms within yt, enabling cross-code utilization of microphysical solvers and physics modules and in situ analysis, and developing collaborative platforms for the exploration of astrophysical datasets. In particular, it will develop the capabilities of yt in three primary mechanisms. The first is to enable support for additional, fundamentally different simulation platforms such as smoothed particle hydrodynamics, unstructured mesh, and non-Cartesian coordinate systems. The second is to provide simulation instrumentation components to ease the process of developing simulation codes, interfacing and exchanging technology between those simulation codes, and to enable deeper, on-the-fly integration of astrophysical simulation codes with yt and other analysis toolkits. The final focus is on developing interface components to enable collaborative and interactive exploration of data utilizing web-based platforms. An explicit goal of this SI2-SSE project is the development of collaborative relationships between scientists, furthering the development of the field as a whole. By conducting all business in the open with a focus on developing and encouraging collaborative, welcoming environments for contributors and researchers, this SSE will help to foster a level playing field that is more accessible to all parties, particularly women and underrepresented minorities. An explicit milestone of this project is to streamline the process of conducting direct outreach through scientific visualization, greatly expanding the domains and individuals engaged in STEM-based public outreach.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1535651</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Turk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjturk@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1217</Code>
      <Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8004</Code>
      <Text>Software Institutes</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1206</Code>
      <Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8005</Code>
      <Text>Scientific Software Elements</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8004</Code>
      <Text>Software Institutes</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
