<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Redox Cycling of Phosphorus in the Western North Atlantic Ocean</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>689502</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henrietta N. Edmonds</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Redox Cycling of Phosphorus in the Western North Atlantic Ocean&lt;br/&gt;Benjamin Van Mooy&lt;br/&gt;ID: 1536346&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding controls on the growth of plankton in the upper ocean, which plays an essential role in the sequestration of carbon dioxide, is an important endeavor for chemical oceanography. Phosphorus is an essential element for marine plankton, and has been a research focus of chemical oceanography for nearly a century. Yet, phosphorus redox cycling rates are almost completely unknown throughout the ocean, and the specific molecular identities of the phosphonates, a form of phosphate, in seawater have defied elucidation. This project will explore and refine entirely new pathways for the biological cycling of phosphorus. This project will support teaching and learning by funding the PhD research of a graduate student, and through the continuation of conducting K-12 classroom laboratory modules and hosting 6-8th grade science fair participants in the investigator's lab.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Phosphorus has never been viewed by oceanographers as an element that actively undergoes chemical redox reactions in the water column, and it was believed to occur only in the +5 valence state, in compounds such as phosphate. However, over the last 17 years, numerous lines of geochemical and genomic information have emerged to show that phosphorus in the +3 valence state (P(+3)), particularly dissolved phosphonate compounds, may play a very important role within open ocean planktonic communities. This is particularly true in oligotrophic gyres such as the Sargasso Sea, where growth of phytoplankton can be limited by the scarcity of phosphate. To better understand these new data, the investigators will design and execute a research program that spans at-sea chemical oceanographic experimentation, state-of-the-art chromatography and mass spectrometry, and novel organic synthesis of 33P-labeled P(+3) compounds. Specifically, they will answer questions about rates of production and consumption of low molecular weight P(+3) compounds, the impact of phosphate availability on the production and consumption of P(+3) compounds, and the groups of phytoplankton that utilize low molecular weight P(+3) compounds. Results of this project have the potential to contribute to the transformation of our understanding of the marine phosphorus cycle.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1536346</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Van Mooy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bvanmooy@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1670</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
