<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Planning Grant: Collaborative Research: I/UCRC for Surveillance Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14545</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dmitri Perkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This collaborative project will support the planning activities for adding two new sites to the existing NSF I/UCRC Center for Surveillance Research (CSR), which is currently composed of Wright State University and Ohio State University (both of which are in Phase 2 effective September 2015). A successful execution of this project will lead to addition of these two new sites to the Center for Surveillance Research, where students and faculty will be working on industrial relevant applied research problems that could generate US Jobs in this unique area, and help with the industrial job placement of students working on Center projects. The fundamental intellectual issues addressed by these new sites will have immediate application in application domains including medical imaging, transportation, and law enforcement. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The core objective of the CSR I/UCRC center has been the development of algorithms for sensor signal and image exploitation, and the development of means to predict the performance and reliability of these algorithms under a variety of operating conditions. Proposed new sites at the University of Kansas and the University of Oklahoma will extend the center's core technologies into weather radar, waveform optimization and spectrum usage, multi-function systems, space-based sensing, and maritime applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1540037</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goodman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>goodman@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/03/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
      <CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8039</Code>
      <Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
