<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GP-IMPACT - Pathways into Geosciences at the University of Arizona</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>288404</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>ICER</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Jones</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of Arizona (UA) is developing a new program to increase the recruitment, retention and professional opportunities of geoscience majors transferring from two-year colleges (2YC). Transfer students in this science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) field tend to have longer times-to-graduation, lower metrics of academic performance, and more limited job prospects than non-transfer students. Two-year colleges have a higher proportion of underrepresented minority (URM) students than most four-year institutions. The UA GeoPathways project builds on and contributes to the evidence base for effective student engagement, learning and retention in STEM, particularly among traditionally underrepresented minority students. The program consists of active recruiting by UA undergraduates at Pima Community College (PCC), focused mentoring, professional development, and paid internship with Arizona-based, geoscience companies, agencies or non-governmental organizations. This program supports STEM education, increasing diversity in this STEM field, engaging students with community businesses and organizations, and advancing the field by improving the academic and practical preparation of its workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The UA GeoPathways program is establishing a community-based program of support for geoscience majors transferring from PCC and other 2YCs in Arizona. The UA Department of Geosciences currently enrolls 208 B.S. majors; about 40 are transfers from PCC and other 2YCs. Each year, between 10 and 20 2YC students transfer in to major in Geosciences at UA. PCC has a greater proportion of under-represented minorities, veterans, and older students than UA. This project leverages existing instructional relationships between the two institutions, in that the first two years of courses for the geosciences major are well-articulated between Arizona 2YCs and UA. Additionally, two PCC faculty have taught geoscience courses at UA. Despite course alignment and shared faculty, transfer students are often under-prepared in coursework, unsure of UA degree requirements, uncertain about job prospects, and concerned about financial support. Transfer students are also less likely to have occupational mobility after receiving their undergraduate degree because of their family commitments. These challenges are being addressed by establishing a recruiting, mentoring and internship program for transfer students. UA students are reaching out to prospective transfer students by leading field trips and by participating in PCC classroom activities. New transfer students are participating in two new workshops on professional skills in their first year at UA: "Success Strategies in STEM" and "Research Readiness." These workshops and their coursework are preparing students for paid internships with local businesses in the mining industry, hydrologic and environmental consulting, federal, state and local agencies and with environmental NGOs. Participating GeoPathways hosts are matched with student interns after their first year at UA. The 320-hour internships are being implemented either as 8 weeks fulltime during the summer or for part-time over a longer period, depending on the needs of the host and the intern. Between 8 and 10 interns are being selected each year of the project. Members of the first-year's cohort serve as peer mentors during later years of the program, and make presentations at PCC or other 2YCs on their internship experiences. The new UA strategic plan, "Never Settle", calls for the engagement of every undergraduate student with professional or community service during their degree program. This UA-wide effort will help sustain the program beyond its initial NSF support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project effectiveness of the integrated approach involving mentoring, workshops and internships in support of 2-year to 4-year college transitions is being evaluated in order to document its potential as a model for similar partnerships among 2YCs, research universities, and potential employers in the local community. It is hypothesized that the UA GeoPathways experience will enhance the recruitment, retention, academic performance and graduation rates of students transferring from PCC and other Arizona 2YCs. The project will better serve prospective geoscientists from groups that are under-represented in four-year academic programs and the workforce: economically disadvantaged students, under-represented minorities, older students and military veterans. Providing hands-on experience for transfer students will assist them in selecting coursework for specialization and may prepare them for entering graduate school. UA GeoPathways will strengthen ties between UA Geosciences and local employers, creating more opportunities for all students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1540596</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Noah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>npfay@pima.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Flessa</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kflessa@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1998</Code>
      <Text>IUSE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1697</Code>
      <Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
