<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ESPRIT de Corps: Expanding STEM Professionals Roles in Teaching</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1444643</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sandra Richardson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In recognition of the national shortage of STEM teachers, especially in high needs schools, collaborators at the University of Houston-Downtown have designed a Noyce Teaching Fellows (TF) project to increase the number of highly qualified science and math teachers in at-risk schools in the greater Houston area. A complementary goal of this project will be to increase the supply of dual credit STEM teachers. The project will facilitate the transition of 20 STEM professionals into teaching careers through a program of coursework and professional development featuring (a) a Masters of Arts in Teaching (b) field experiences with teacher/leaders, (c) classroom observations, and (d) an online, professional community of practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project, led by STEM faculty and collaborators from the Urban Education Department, relies on current research on teacher preparation related to improving their ability to thrive in high-needs urban schools with diverse learners and to cope with standard issues that such schools face. It also takes advantage of current trends for creating online learning communities and training high school instructors to teach college-level courses. Formative evaluation will involve the assessment of the TF's progress throughout the project, regarding their perceived competence and self-efficacy, certification test scores, and results of observations by faculty, mentors and principals. Summative assessment will also include the impact of TF's teaching on student achievement scores and career interest. Results will be presented at conferences and meetings of professional societies such as the National Science teachers Association and the Association of Science-Technology Centers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1540769</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hoge</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hogeb@uhd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sack</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sackj@uhd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
      <LastName>Quander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>quanderr@uhd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston - Downtown</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770021001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7132218005</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Main Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7908</Code>
      <Text>Teaching &amp; Mstr Tchng Fellows</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
