<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2015 Applied and Environmental Microbiology Gordon Research Conference, July 11-17, 2015, Mount Holyoke College, South Hadley, MA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010209</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will support student and/or postdoctoral participation in the Gordon Research Conference in Applied and Environmental Microbiology (GRC-AEM). The main goal of the conference is to present and discuss new, fundamental research findings related to the activities of microorganisms. The GRC-AEM embraces the philosophy that early dissemination of pioneering research into microbial physiology and metabolism facilitates translation of fundamental knowledge into practical application with contributions to ecosystems monitoring and management, bioremediation, bioenergy production and other commercial uses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This year the GRC-AEM has scheduled a series of topics that directly serve national and global interests and align with the missions put forth by the National Science Foundation. The scientific program illustrates attention given to globally significant themes ranging from nitrogen and phosphorous cycling in the ocean to the connection between gut microbiota and human health. Presenters were invited based upon their scientific contributions and their ongoing commitment to education and community outreach. This year the GRC-AEM also introduces the Gordon Research Seminar for Applied and Environmental Microbiology. The Gordon Research Seminar is a one and a half day meeting that precedes the GRC and is designed to provide graduate students, postdoctoral fellows and early career scientists the opportunity to present and discuss recent research findings on topics related to environmental impact and industrial application of microorganisms at the single cell and ecosystem level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GRC-AEM has been a forum for the consideration of critical or even controversial issues that have led to the development of new technologies. The conference has always had a diverse theme of topics, covering the metabolic, physiologic and evolutionary diversity of microbial life, the complex roles that microorganisms play in life on Earth, and the multitude of applications of microbes in biotechnology, the food industry, agriculture, and medicine. The Conference has a long record of stimulating advanced research in industrial laboratories, colleges and universities, research foundations, and government laboratories.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This year's conference will cover a diverse range of research areas including the ecophysiology of microbes, molecular ecology, genomics, metagenomics and postgenomic technologies, evolutionary diversity of microbial life, the complex roles that microorganisms play in life on Earth, and the many important applications of microbes in medicine, agriculture, biotechnology and the food industry. In continuing to provide a forum for presentation and discussion of cutting edge science in applied and environmental microbiology, the conference will hold scientific sessions on a wide range of microbes and how they sustain and protect our planet. The environments harboring microbes and how microbes adapt to these environments and interact with each other will be considered; for example biogeochemical cycles of carbon, nitrogen, sulfur and other elements in the terrestrial and marine environment, interactions between microbes and animals and between microbes and plants, virus-host interactions, microbial communication and signaling will be covered. The importance of new methods in microbial ecology, single cell technologies and the use of genomics and post-genomics in environmental and industrial microbiology will be also be covered. These topics, together with sessions on the use of microbes as fuel and bioenergy sources, as sources of natural products and in bioremediation and biocatalysis processes, will all provide platforms for established and newer researchers in the field to discuss a wide variety of aspects of the fundamental and applied aspects of environmental microbiology and to provide the driving force for innovation and impetus in this vibrant research field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1541611</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gorby</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ygorby@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1181</Code>
      <Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1181</Code>
      <Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
