<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CC*DNI Campus Design: Networking Upgrades for Colorado State University Pueblo</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>306663</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project provides networking infrastructure upgrades to support research and education particularly in STEM disciplines, by implementing a research-level high-speed subnetwork DMZ for the local area network (LAN); adding a data transfer node; deploying the multidomain network measurement/monitoring toolkit known as perfSONAR to improve the ability to identity and isolate network problems and increase productivity; implementing the globus toolkit (software infrastructure for distributed computing, including large file storage and transfer); and installing fiber optic cable to the CSU-Pueblo observatory, providing increased bandwidth for telescope images and video. The research DMZ connects via a 10 Gbps wide area network (WAN) connection to the Front Range GigaPop (FRGP) network, which provides access to multiple research networks including Intra-FRGP, Western Regional Network, Internet2, and ESnet. Upgraded equipment is primarily at Colorado State University - Pueblo (CSU-P) in Pueblo, CO; some optical equipment is housed in Colorado Springs, Monument Hill, and Denver, CO.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The upgrade improves networking for CSU-P, allowing high-speed research to be centralized and supported with networking resources (relieving congestion on CSU-P's existing LAN and WAN). Nine particular research projects benefit from this project. Broader community impacts include computer science courses incorporating details about this next-generation network, along with transporting, storing, preserving, manipulating, processing and analyzing big data; and the entire community participating remotely in imaging of astronomical events through CSU-P's observatory telescope. Large datasets generated on campus are preserved regionally on the shared digital repository, and then made accessible and reusable for others.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1541373</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Burns</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pburns@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kreminski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rick.kreminski@csupueblo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Erich</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matola</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>erich.matola@colostate-pueblo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University-Pueblo</Name>
      <CityName>Pueblo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>810014901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7195492480</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 Bonforte Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
