<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CC*DNI Region: Campus Cyberinfrastructure/Operating Innovative Networks (CC*OIN)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149136</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project develops and hosts hands-on advanced technology workshops for campus network engineering staff in the US. Each CC-OIN workshop is being hosted in partnership with regional networks and tailored to their region's needs. Participants gain the practical understanding they need to support data-intensive science projects on their campuses, and learn how to improve science performance using state-of-the-art network technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CC-OIN builds on past work with similar workshops and is open to participants around the country and abroad. Over the previous three years, collaborators have shared detailed technical content on the Science DMZ paradigm, the perfSONAR network performance measurement system, and the use of open Software Defined Networking (SDN) technologies. The project also broadens and updates content related to emerging areas of need for supporting science on campuses. New topics include advanced cybersecurity, new SDN methods, orchestration of networks with scientific cloud applications, and an SDN-based Science DMZ for increased performance and security. Finally, the project explores ways to broaden the reach of the workshops through alternative delivery methods like videos and cloud-based, hands-on exercises.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CC-OIN project advances the expertise large and small campuses in every region of the country needs, supports technical staff to become regional resources supporting science, and brings each region's community together to collaborate on improving network capabilities for better science outcomes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1541421</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>McMullen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcmullendf@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/07/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jon-Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Herron</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpherron@iu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hunsinger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ana@internet2.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/07/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
