<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CC*DNI Networking Infrastructure: Enabling International Data Intensive Scientific Collaboration for Vanderbilt Researchers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project significantly improves the Vanderbilt University external network link, which is fostering and enabling national research programs in a wide variety of disciplines. For example, Vanderbilt hosts a computing site for the Compact Muon Solenoid experiment (CMS) running at the Large Hadron Collider at CERN in Geneva, Switzerland, and this resource is used by global collaborators. Biochemists in the medical center make extensive use of remote network access to robots and beamlines at the Advanced Photon Source at Argonne National Lab and the Advance Light Source at Lawrence Berkeley National Lab, and download the resulting crystallography data to disk at Vanderbilt. The Vanderbilt Television News Archive project routinely uploads digital copies of network news programs that it has archived to the Library of Congress in Washington DC and makes them available to a large research community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project Vanderbilt acquires the hardware necessary to upgrade the Vanderbilt external research and education network connection between the campus and Southern Crossroads point of presence in Atlanta to 100 gigabits per second. Vanderbilt is also replacing the perimeter research router, and upgrading the research router that sits between it and the Science DMZ and the rest of the campus research network.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1541443</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sheldon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Paul.Sheldon@Vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mathews</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.mathews@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maguire</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>charles.f.maguire@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
      <CityName>Nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
