<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of X-ray Atlas, a high-brilliance high-sensitivity high-load-capacity X-ray diffractometer for mineralogy and mineral physics research at the University of Hawaii</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>520701</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Herbert Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Experiments that allow probing the structure, behavior and properties of Earth forming minerals at extreme pressure and temperature conditions representative of the Earth deep interior are one of primary sources of information about the inner workings of our planet, indispensable in creating reliable geophysical models used e.g. to predict earthquakes. X-ray diffraction based experiments play a special role in mineral physics, being the only reliable source of information about changes in the crystal structure and bonding that take place at depths. Within this project we will develop X-ray Atlas, a new generation of instrument optimized for innovative, laboratory-based diffraction experiments with tiny mineral fragment samples at extreme pressures and temperatures. X-ray Atlas will also provide the much needed and currently non-existent experimental capabilities for the mineral physics lab at the University of Hawaii, and will be a valuable resource to a large number of geology-focused faculty and students on campus. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;X-ray Atlas will be capable of exploring pressure and temperature conditions relevant for the Earth upper mantle, transition zone and some of the lower mantle (up to 50 GPa and 1000o C, corresponding to depths greater than 1000 km). The new instrument will consist of commercial X-ray diffractometer, Bruker D8 Venture as a base platform. The Venture diffractometer will retain its original full functionality after the planned modification, but a range of new unique capabilities will be added by integrating a parallel kinematics hexapod robotic device as an alternative sample mounting platform for high pressure diamond anvil cells and thin sections. In addition to the hexapod, we will incorporate a fiber optics transport to the sample viewing system of the Venture diffractometer, which will enable collection of ruby fluorescence and Raman signal using an existing standalone Princeton Instruments spectroscopy system, while the sample is mounted on the diffractometer. Through development of the X-ray Altas we will create new and very exciting opportunities for lab-based mineralogy, petrology and mineral physics undergraduate and graduate education at the University of Hawaii, create a personnel training and new technology and software prototyping site for mineral physics and deliver novel, unique, robust and custom-designed technology that will be transferred to other university mineral physics research labs, and will be marketed by a commercial instrument vendor.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1541516</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Przemyslaw</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dera</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pdera@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
