<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT: Robust High Porosity Filter for Circulating Tumor Cell Enrichment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199898</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating robust, high open area microfilters to fill the need for rare cell separation in various research and diagnostic contexts. The microfilter is important because it makes possible rapid, high purity separation of rare cells from complex mixtures, such as cancer cells circulating in blood. This high purity separation could enable the early detection of cancers and other diseases. The project will result in a prototype and scalable process for the manufacture of microfilters with greater than 40% open area. The resulting microfilter will be unique due to the combination of a high open area while maintaining mechanical robustness required for integration with standard medical equipment. These features enable both a higher purity separation and a higher volume capacity when compared to track-etched filters, the leading filter material in this market space. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gap(s) as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application. First, the method of manufacture will be determined so that a prototype can be made with greater than 40% open area. This will be developed by applying variations of known three-dimensional microfabrication techniques. Second, through testing and iteration, design parameters will be determined to achieve sufficient burst strength. Third, tests will be performed with clinical samples to determine if the filtration capacity and purity meet minimum requirements for an initial application as a cancer diagnostic. In addition, personnel involved in this project, undergraduates and a postdoctoral researcher, will receive technology translation experience through participating in the customer development process as interviews are conducted. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project engages two partners to enable clinical testing and continuation of other business activities. Precision Membranes LLC is a startup co-founded by participating personnel to lead customer development and business model generation activities. Astrimmune LTD will incorporate prototype filters into a clinical trial and provide feedback about performance parameters of various designs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1543559</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>davis@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brigham Young University</Name>
      <CityName>Provo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>846021231</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8014226177</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>A-285 ASB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
