<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal: How Did the "World's Largest Single Volcano" Form at a Triple Junction? A Magnetic and Bathymetry Survey of Tamu Massif, Shatsky Rise</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>52919</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Candace O. Major</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Part 1&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will attempt to gain a better understanding of the formation of Tamu Massif, the main volcanic edifice of Shatsky Rise oceanic plateau. This will be accomplished by collecting and analyzing magnetic anomaly and bathymetric data over Tamu Massif during of a 32-day cruise on the Schmidt Ocean Institute research vessel Falkor in the fall of 2015. The project will support an early-career female investigator and promote international collaboration with Japan. Graduate students as well as undergraduates will be involved in the sea-going experience. The project will have an outreach component consisting of learning modules for students to learn about submarine volcanoes and marine geology and geophysics as well as partnering with museums to create exhibits with video feeds to the ship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will test two end-member hypotheses about the formation of Tamu Massif on the Shatsky Rise: 1) that Tamu Massif is the result of a large mass of thermally-buoyant material arising from the core-mantle boundary region as a new mantle plume is formed (?plume head? hypothesis); or 2) that Tamu Massif is the result of plateau eruptions occurring where plate boundaries or plate cracks release pressure above areas of the upper mantle with lower melting temperatures (?fertile? mantle hypothesis). The project results will allow for the revision of the existing map of magnetic anomalies and the revision of the tectonic and structural interpretation. The project will have an outreach component that will be organized by Leslie Peart, former outreach coordinator for Consortium for Ocean Leadership for IODP, who currently works for the Corpus Christi Aquarium. Potential outreach activities consist of learning modules for students to use to learn about submarine volcanoes and marine geology and geophysics as well as partnering with museums to create exhibits with video feeds to the ship.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1543903</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Masako</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tominaga</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>masako.tominaga@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M University Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
