<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CPS:Synergy: Safety-Aware Cyber-Molecular Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>823930</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gurdip Singh</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Cyber-molecular systems are networks of nanoscale physical devices in which computation controls the behavior and activities of the molecular devices. In some cyber-molecular systems the programmable controller itself is implemented by DNA gates and algorithms. Many of the planned future uses of cyber-molecular systems are safety-critical, such as biosensors to detect pollutants in water or disease markers in the body, and drug therapeutics to deliver a customized medicine only to the locations in the body where the disease has been detected. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The problem is how to design cyber-molecular systems to be safe for use in a dynamic and only partially understood physical environment. This project addresses this problem by introducing a new model of chemical reaction networks that can be implemented robustly. The class of computations accepted by the model can be implemented in such a way that they will provably perform correctly even when crucial physical parameters are perturbed by small amounts. The project will leverage this advance to establish an end-to-end safety-aware perspective for creating cyber-molecular systems. The approach entails tightly integrated computational and physical risk analyses; advances in reaction-network-based modeling and verification techniques; and model-driven experimentation and evaluation on prototyped cyber-molecular systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has the potential to make future cyber-molecular systems safer. Results also will provide capabilities in risk analysis and automated verification to meet the need for future certification of safety-critical cyber-molecular systems, such as biosensors and drug therapeutics. More broadly, the new model of biochemical reaction networks will advance understanding of how to analyze very large sets of nanoscale cyber-physical systems that operate in a probabilistic physical environment from a safety perspective. This project will also focus on interdisciplinary training of a diverse student population, and results will be integrated into undergraduate and graduate courses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1545028</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lathrop</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jil@cs.iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lutz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lutz@cs.iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lutz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rlutz@cs.iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Henderson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>telomere@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/16/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8235</Code>
      <Text>CPS-Synergy</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
