<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PIRE: International Program for the Advancement of Neurotechnology (IPAN)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cassandra M. Dudka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project entitled "International Program for the Advancement of Neurotechnology (IPAN)" is about understanding the complexity and mysteries of the brain. It is cited by many as the biggest scientific challenge of this century. In this International Program for the Advancement of Neurotechnology (IPAN), the researchers are creating a holistic system for studying brain activity by closely integrating hardware from leading neurotechnologists with novel software from leading neuroscientists. Enabling this large-scale collaboration should accelerate the rate of discovery in neuroscience. This in turn will pave the way to improved treatments for neurological disorders and to breakthroughs in artificial intelligence in the next decade. The PIRE team will also provide advanced educational opportunities for undergraduates with the express purpose of recruiting future U.S. STEM (science, technology, engineering and mathematics) researchers. Graduate students and postdocs will also be enrolled in a unique cross-training program between neuroscience and neurotechnology laboratories. The resulting experience will prepare a new generation of globally-connected multi-disciplinary engineers and scientists while driving critical advances in neurotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IPAN is an explicit partnership of leading neuroscientists and technologists to develop and deliver a hardware and software system that fundamentally simplifies the ability of a neuroscientist to (i) identify recorded neuron types, (ii) reconstruct local neural circuits, and (iii) deliver biomimetic or synthetic inputs in a cell-specific targeted manner. This project teams the University of Michigan, New York University, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, and the University of Puerto Rico with the University of Freiburg, the University of Hamburg-Eppendorf, the Korea Institute of Science and Technology, Singapore?s Institute for Microelectronics, and University College London. Complementary strengths, world-class infrastructures, and strong student exchange programs are an important part of this IPAN team, with major thrusts in Technology, Neuroscience, and Education. The enabling technology to meet these three system goals (i-iii) will be next-generation neural probes equipped with novel optoelectronics, high-density recording interfaces, and low-noise multiplexed digital outputs. The neuroscience thrust will help define the technology from the onset and are developing novel software tools to accelerate the analysis of large neurophysiological data sets. The team includes leading system neuroscientists with unique capabilities specializing in memory, sensory, fear, and development, and will work with technologists to validate both the technology and the software tools in distinctive neuroscience applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1545858</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Euisik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yoon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esyoon@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kensall</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wise</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wise@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stuenkel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esterm@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gyorgy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buzsaki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gyorgy.buzsaki@nyumc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Quirk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gregoryjquirk@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7742</Code>
      <Text>PIRE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5927</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA, OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5936</Code>
      <Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5942</Code>
      <Text>KOREA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5946</Code>
      <Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7742</Code>
      <Text>PIRE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
