<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Seasonal Sensitivity of the Midlatitude Circulation to Future Climate Warming</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599693</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric T. DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The climate change induced by increases in greenhouse gas concentrations is generally characterized as an increase in globally averaged temperature, but the climate impacts experienced locally will be determined in part by the changes in atmospheric circulation that are induced by global warming. In particular, climate model simulations suggest that the westerly jet streams found at upper levels in the middle latitudes will shift towards the poles, so that the mean Northern Hemisphere jet stream will migrate northward, with a corresponding southward shift for its the Southern Hemisphere counterpart. These shifts are small but consequential, as patterns of rainfall and storminess in the middle latitudes are determined in large part by the positions of the jet streams. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The poleward shift of jet streams as a consequence of greenhouse warming is a robust feature of global warming simulations and has been a research topic since at least 2005, but the seasonality and geography of the response has not yet been fully explored. Preliminary work for this project shows that in the Southern Hemisphere the largest shift is in the Fall (March to May), followed by Summer (December to February), Winter (June to August), and Spring (September to November). In the North Atlantic the order is, from largest to smallest, Fall (September to November), Summer (June to August), Spring (March to May), and Winter (December to February). The ordering is again different in the North Pacific, with Fall leading by a large margin followed by Winter, Spring, and Summer. By now several theories have been proposed to explain why the jets shift poleward in an year-round, longitudinally averaged sense, but none of these theories provides a clear intuition for the seasonality (i.e. why the shift is largest in Fall) or the regional variations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research under this award consists of analysis of observational data from reanalysis products and simulations of future climate from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project and the Large Ensemble archive of simulations using the Community Earth System Model. This analysis is followed by numerical experiments using models of varying levels of complexity, intended to isolate and study possibly physical mechanisms leading seasonally and geographically varying jet shifts. One issue to be considered is that the pattern of greenhouse warming generally includes a deep tropospheric warming maximum in the tropics together with surface trapped warming near the poles (referred to as polar amplification). The jet shifts can be regarded as a combined response to the tropical and polar influences, which are likely to have opposing effects and very different seasonalities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The work is of societal as well as scientific interest due to the strong impacts of jet shifts on local climate, for instance a northward shift of jet streams could cause drying in the region downwind of the present-day jet location accompanied by excessive rain and snow to the north. In addition, the project will support and train two students, thereby contributing to the future workforce in this research area. The PI and her students will also organize a special session at an annual geosciences meeting to publicize results of the study and encourage further investigation of the topic.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1545675</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barnes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eabarnes@atmos.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5740</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
