<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Group Travel to the 12th International Symposium on Antarctic Earth Sciences (ISAES), Goa, India</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36993</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Wilch</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Symposium on Antarctic Earth Sciences (ISAES) is held every four years and is a premier conference for the presentation of the latest scientific research in Antarctica. The 12th ISAES meeting will be held 13-17 July 2015 in Goa, India. In previous symposia, U.S. scientists made important contributions to the success of the meetings. These funds will be used to support the travel costs associated with the attendance of approximately 19 U.S. Earth scientists, enabling them to present their scientific findings and benefit from the scholarly exchange of ideas. The highest priority will be given to graduate students and early career investigators who do not have other resources to offset their travel costs. Requests for travel support will be evaluated by the two project PIs along with a group of geoscientists from the Byrd Polar and Climate Research Center and School of Earth Sciences at The Ohio State University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scientific program for ISAES 2015 emphasizes interdisciplinary research that places Antarctica in a global context, and is of interest to all Earth scientists. The meeting provides essential perspective for students and early-career researchers. The science themes include: Antarctica, the Southern Ocean, and the Evolution of Climate and the Global Cryosphere; Biodiversity and the Evolution of Life; Antarctic Surface Processes, Landscapes, and Links with Cryosphere and Climate; Antarctica and supercontinent evolution and Frontiers in Antarctic Earth Science, amongst many other topics. Symposium presentations and publications provide a key record of research activities in Antarctic Earth Sciences, and an invaluable resource for planning future, international, collaborative research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1545594</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cristina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Millan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>millan.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>twilson@mps.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5112</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC EARTH SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5116</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC GLACIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5292</Code>
      <Text>ANTARCTIC INTEGRATED SYS SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5407</Code>
      <Text>POLAR CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
