<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AGU Chapman Conference on Slow Slip Phenomena</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Luciana Astiz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The phenomena of slow slip, which includes slow slip events (SSE) and tectonic tremor (TT), have now been observed in nearly every subduction zone with dense geodetic and seismic networks and along some major crustal faults. Slow slip processes are now viewed by the seismological community as a crucial aspect of fault mechanics. Documents such as Seismological Grand Challenges in Understanding Earth?s Dynamic Systems and science plans for GeoPRISMS and EarthScope all point to the importance of studying slow slip. Previous conferences dedicated to slow slip have primarily focused on the Japan and Cascadia subduction zones. However new detailed studies in subduction zones in Alaska, Costa Rica, Mexico, New Zealand and fault zones such as the San Andreas and on faults beneath the Hawaiian volcano complex are providing additional observations. This Chapman Conference proposes to examine these phenomena globally and promote discussion and interaction by bringing together scientists working on Slow Slip in all places where they are observed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The slow slip community is now beginning to move beyond just observational studies, as many new datasets and modeling studies in the last few years have begun to shed light on the physical processes that produce slow slip. These recent efforts towards understanding process make this workshop even very timely. The conference will focus on the following topics:1) Observations of slow slip phenomena, 2) Fault structure and physical conditions where slow earthquakes are observed, 3) Slow earthquakes and their relationship to large earthquakes and seismic hazard, 4) Models and laboratory experiments, 5) Improving observational methods for the analysis of slow slip phenomena. The meeting will occur over 3 days. Its format will include oral presentations and posters. Participation in the conference will be open to anyone with an active interest in slow slip/slow earthquake processes. We will invite key speakers to provide the observations and structure from each subduction zone, as well as modeling, and laboratory experiments.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1547543</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pranoti</FirstName>
      <LastName>Asher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pasher@agu.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Geophysical Union</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200099123</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2024626900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2000 FLORIDA AVE NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1576</Code>
      <Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5922</Code>
      <Text>MEXICO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5977</Code>
      <Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
