<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CIF: Student Travel Support for the North American School on Information Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cozzens</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The IEEE North American School for Information Theory (NASIT) is an annual event of the IEEE Information Theory Society, and this will be its eighth edition. NASIT is hosted by different institutions each year, with the intent of increasing the geographic diversity of the participants. The 2015 School for Information Theory (NASIT ?15) will be held at University of California, San Diego (UC San Diego) in La Jolla, California, from August 10 to August 13, 2015. The School provides a supportive environment where foundations for learning and long-term future scientific collaborations are established. The School delivers interactive education for graduate students in the mathematical, engineering, and computer sciences. It presents students the opportunity to meet with and learn from senior researchers from academia and industry who present long format tutorials. Student and post-doc participants present their own research results in poster sessions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Student attendance at recent schools has varied from 110 to 180 student participants. This proposal requests support for the expenses of school participants from the United States such as graduate students and postdocs. These participants would be individuals who would benefit from attending the school ? learning from senior colleagues, presenting their own research in poster sessions, and expanding their network with their community ? but who lack funds and would not be able to attend without travel support.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1547772</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Massimo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Franceschetti</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>massimo@ece.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
