<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>"Strengthening the Collaboration and Partnership between US and African Engineering Programs by Working Closely with the African Engineering Deans Council (AEDC)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99257</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carmina Londono</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Countries around the globe, whether developed or developing, recognize that having a well trained workforce in science and engineering is critical for economic success. To successfully address global challenges there is a serious need for engineering education and appropriate pedagogy that includes hands-on experience and that is based on global perspectives, expertise and "success-stories". One innovation in engineering education that has the potential to completely transform the way hands-on engineering is taught in engineering programs in the developing world and in areas that are economically disadvantaged in the developed world is the "Mobile Studio Technology and Pedagogy". The Mobile Studio Project (originally funded by NSF) has developed pedagogy and supporting hardware and software that provides functionality similar to that of standard laboratory equipment (oscilloscope, function generator, power supplies, among others) typically associated with a highly instrumented laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs are convening a "Summit to Strengthen Collaboration and Partnership between the US and African Engineering Programs" to be held in Addis Ababa in Ethiopia on September 27-28, 2015. Applications that will employ the Mobile Studio Project pedagogy in new curricula will be presented and discussed at the Summit. The main objectives of the Summit are to: (a) ) establish collaborations between universities with engineering programs in Sub-Saharan Africa; and (2) lay the foundation for long term collaborations and partnerships with US universities with engineering programs. The effectiveness of the Summit will be evaluated by two teams. The internal (on-site) team will be responsible for local, immediate data collection, on-site interviews and assessment of Summit activities. The data will be forwarded to the external evaluation team for review, verification and analysis. The external evaluation team will be responsible for the design of the evaluation methodology, preparation of all instruments, data analysis, and report preparation including recommendations for change.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1548542</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kilpatrick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pkilpat1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>craig.scott@morgan.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yacob</FirstName>
      <LastName>Astatke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yacob.astatke@morgan.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Morgan State University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212510002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4438853200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 East Cold Spring Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1480</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING RESEARCH CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1480</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING RESEARCH CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>113E</Code>
      <Text>ENG CURRICULUMN DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
