<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>6th Annual International Conference in Computational Surgery and Dual Training; Boreaux, France; Spring/Early Summer, 2016</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>17600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Seta Bogosyan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Part 1:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;COSINE (COmputational Surgery International NEtwork, computationalsurgery.org) was founded in 2008 to engage young student scientists and clinical fellows collaboratively in healthcare innovation. Computational surgery is the application of principles from mathematics, engineering and computer science to solve specific challenges encountered in surgical settings. Dr. Marc Garbey, together with an organizing committee, arranges an annual conference to offer the opportunity to exchange ideas in this field. COSINE fosters strong collaborations across the Atlantic involving researchers, clinicians and trainees in the U.S. and abroad.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The committee members and participants are located across the US and Europe and therefore the conference location alternates between the US and Europe. The 6th Annual International Conference in Computational Surgery and Dual Training is to be held in Bordeaux, France in late spring or early summer of 2016. Invited speakers include David Eckmann, M.D., Ph.D. (US), Dimitris Metaxas, Ph.D. (US), Michael I. Miga, Ph.D. (US), and Oktar Asoglu, M.D. (Turkey). The travel grants for the graduate students and surgical residents will be awarded to deserving members of Dr. Garbey?s NSF I/UCRC center group. About 40% of this highly diverse research group consists of female researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference is vital to promote the concept of dual training between computational scientists and medical residents. In the short term the conference will deepen participants' understanding of computational surgery and spark new collaborations. In addition to networking opportunities with a diverse group, student scientists and medical fellows will develop a shared understanding of how surgery and computational science can synergize to solve challenges encountered in patient care. Trainees will also present and gather feedback on their recent work, participate in discussions and visit local laboratories and clinical facilities. The conference will also help continue to attract new bright students to the field of computational surgery. Furthermore, it will have a strong impact on the solidification of the center's new NSF I/UCRC international node in France and foster collaboration between the US and European partners for the ultimate aim of improved healthcare, which is a priority of the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;COSINE (COmputational Surgery International NEtwork, computationalsurgery.org) was founded in 2008 to nurture a new breed of engineers and scientists working across clinical and research silos to innovate and invigorate medical practice with computational tools. Dr. Marc Garbey, together with an organizing committee, arranges an annual conference to maintain momentum, enhance collaboration and offer the opportunity to interested clinicians and researcher to expand their knowledge in the field of computational surgery. The organizing committee consists of a diverse group in both gender and ethnicity from the US and Europe working to ensure diversity among participants of the conference. The COSINE fosters strong collaborations across the Atlantic involving researchers, clinicians and trainees in the US and abroad. Therefore, the committee alternates the location of the conference between the US and Europe. The 6th Annual International Conference in Computational Surgery and Dual Training is scheduled to be held in Bordeaux, France in late spring or early summer of 2016. Invited speakers include David Eckmann, M.D., Ph.D. (US), Dimitris Metaxas, Ph.D. (US), Michael I. Miga, Ph.D. (US), and Oktar Asoglu, M.D. (Turkey).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The travel grants for speakers will be awarded to two internationally acclaimed researchers based in the United States. The travel grants for graduated students and surgical residents will be awarded to deserving members of Dr. Garbey's NSF I/UCRC center group. This highly diverse research group is about 40% female and comprised of citizens from the US, France, Italy, Vietnam, and Germany with backgrounds in computer science, engineering, surgery and mathematical modeling, among others.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computational surgery is the application of principles from mathematics, engineering and computer science to solve specific clinical challenges. Computer science has revolutionized the operating room through digitization of many commonly used tools. The scientifically-recorded activity of surgery and its everyday use on patients produce enormous volumes of digital data, demanding enhanced methods for data representation and medical informatics processing with the goal of improving the surgical process. Computational surgery is therefore also involves techniques to improve the surgical process by systematic analysis of a large volume of digital data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference is vital to promote the concept of dual training between computational scientists and medical residents. In the short term the conference will deepen participants' understanding of computational surgery and spark new collaborations. In addition to networking opportunities with a diverse group, trainees will develop a shared understanding of how surgery and computational science can synergize to solve challenges encountered globally in patient care. In addition to talks by invited speakers, the conference will offer the opportunity to trainees to present and gather feedback on their recent work, participate in plenary discussions and visit local laboratories and clinical facilities. The conference is also vital to keep momentum in COSINE and continue to attract new bright students to the field of computational surgery. Furthermore, it is expected that this conference will have a strong impact on the solidification of the center's new I/UCRC international node in France and foster collaboration between the US and European partners in this priority area of the nation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1550995</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garbey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mgarbey2@houstonmethodist.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7796</Code>
      <Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5918</Code>
      <Text>FRANCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5980</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7931</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7945</Code>
      <Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
