<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF International Travel Grant for 2015 Future Directions in Spectrum Management Research Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The growth of high-speed mobile internet access has already revolutionized our lives and is expected to continue unabated. As new applications such as Machine-to-Machine (M2M), self-driving cars, and ubiquitous video appear on the horizon, rapid growth of traffic in wireless mobile and nomadic access will dwarf all other wireless applications. Therefore, design of future wireless networks that can sustain such traffic growth is an important research challenge. A critical piece of such design is spectrum management strategies that leverage maximum efficiency and maximum public benefit from the radio spectrum. This workshop will explore the key technical and policy challenges in spectrum management facing researchers in the coming decade. The proposed international travel grants will enable U.S.-based researchers to participate in these important global conversations. U.S.-based researchers will both be able to represent the U.S.'s unique perspective on spectrum management and be informed by the different approaches being adopted in Europe and elsewhere. Moreover, U.S.-based researchers will return home with a clearer sense of key research problems to guide their own future research, helping to enable the U.S. to remain at the forefront of wireless communications research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will enable travel grants to be made to up to 15 U.S.-based researchers to attend the 2015 Future Directions in Spectrum Management Research Workshop. The workshop is being held in Stockholm, Sweden on September 29, 2015, co-located with IEEE DySPAN 2015. Travel grants will be made to enable U.S.-based researchers that are not presenting at IEEE DySPAN to bring a diversity of views to the workshop. A few smaller travel grants will also be made to enable DySPAN presenters to be in Stockholm for an additional day to participate in the workshop. The PI will seek to identify and make some travel awards to researchers from underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1551912</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allen</FirstName>
      <LastName>MacKenzie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mackenab@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
