<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: High-Density Non-Fouling Bioactive Coatings for Processing of Biological Fluids</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>533019</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Angela Lueking</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CAREER 1553183 - Schilke&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bacterial sepsis is a common and life-threatening condition which kills hundreds of thousands of Americans and costs ~$20 billion every year in the U.S. alone. Sepsis is currently treated with antibiotics, but this does not remove the circulating dead bacteria and fragments of their cell membranes (endotoxin), which could cause a serious immune response. One promising method to mitigate this risk involves passing a patient's blood through a device to capture circulating endotoxin, helping to stabilize the immune system and potentially to improve their prognosis. However for this application, all materials in contact with blood must be biocompatible (i.e. resist fouling or clotting, and not induce an adverse biological response). For treatment of sepsis, surfaces must also present endotoxin-binding agents in controlled orientations and at high density. These bioactive and biocompatible coatings must be inexpensive and easy to apply to a wide range of materials, including plastics used in medical devices, needles, flexible tubing, and other associated equipment. Biocompatible and bioactive coatings could have transformative impact on the safety and efficacy of treatment of sepsis, in which even a modest improvement could result in many lives and much money saved. In other biomedical applications, the technology could also impart biological activity to a variety of other household, consumer and industrial products. The integrated educational activities of this project are expected to achieve the following benefits: (a) research concepts will be incorporated into bioengineering coursework at Oregon State (OSU) and hands-on learning modules will be adapted for OSU's STEM Academy for pre-college students and (b) the PI will work with the OSU business school to provide a summer "Entrepreneurship Boot Camp" for the group's graduate students and faculty mentors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project's research will result in the development of high-density, non-fouling bioactive coatings (HNB's) by living polymerization from surfactant-based immobilized initiators, producing branched, hydrophilic polymer brushes on the surface. This coating, essentially an ultrathin immobilized hydrogel, will provide excellent resistance against protein adsorption and cell interactions (biocompatibility). To impart bioactivity at the hydrogel surface, a nearly-ideal bioorthogonal ligation (BOL) will be used to immobilize enzymes, peptides, polysaccharides, or other biologically active molecules at the periphery of the brush. This chemistry enables quantitative conjugation from even dilute solutions of the active molecule, allowing precise control of surface functionalization. Unreacted groups are biologically compatible and chemically inert. Economical immobilization of peptides or proteins is provided by Genetic Code Expansion (GCE), in which engineered microbes express active proteins with BOL reactive groups incorporated at genetically-controlled positions. The resulting specific immobilization of only the desired proteins from a crude cell lysate eliminates costly purification or pre-concentration steps, and guarantees that the protein is in a precisely defined orientation for maximal biological activity. Although the main objective of this work is to demonstrate biocompatible and bioactive coatings for devices to capture pathogens from blood, myriad other potential uses include safer medical devices, food processing, pharmaceutical production, active packaging, and self-cleaning fabrics, as examples.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1553183</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schilke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>karl.schilke@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1417</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL &amp; BIOLOGICAL SEPAR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
