<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Extreme Toughening of HCP Metallic Alloys via Nanospaced Stacking Faults</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Magnesium, titanium and cobalt are included in a particular class of metals with hexagonal structure at the microscopic level. A barrier to their widespread application has been the inability, based on the hexagonal structure, to design materials that have both high strength and high formability; these more often than not are mutually exclusive. The basic research supported in this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) award will discover and unravel the underlying mechanisms responsible for the formation of novel toughening features within the hexagonal structure, and enable processing methods to realize strategic metallic materials with unprecedented strength and formability. By engineering metallic alloys that are stronger and tougher, the lightweighting strategies critical for developing vehicles and transportation systems that reduce our dependency on fossil fuels and decrease pollution can be realized. More so, the knowledge can be extended to make advancements in other industries, such as aerospace and healthcare, thus promoting further technological advancement and economic growth. This research will be inherently multidisciplinary in nature and provide research and education opportunities for the many students from underrepresented groups at University of California Riverside.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While planar boundaries such as nanotwins have shown the ability to concurrently strengthen and retain ductility in nanocrystalline metals with body center cubic and face center cubic crystal structures, they have not proven feasible in hexagonal close-packed materials based on the difficulty in twinning as the grain size decreases. Literature clues and preliminary observations by the PI have shown that nano-spaced stacking faults may afford synergistic strengthening and ductility for hexagonal close-packed materials, but there are no experimental studies that systematically investigate the intrinsic ability for these materials to form such features, nor the factors that lead to their formation, spacing and density. Thus, the objective of the research supported by this award is to explore and unravel the effects of grain size, texture, stacking fault energies and deformation conditions on the fault nucleation and growth kinetics that govern size, spacing and density. Next, the magnitude and mechanisms of mechanical property improvements achievable will be investigated. Lastly, new theoretical constructs will be developed to explain the formation, strengthening and ductility observed in these novel materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1554632</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suveen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mathaudhu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smathaudhu@engr.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8092</Code>
      <Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>080E</Code>
      <Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8037</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
