<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IRES: International Research Experience for Students on the Behavioral Ecology and Conservation of African Carnivores</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles H. Estabrook</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Title: IRES: International research experience for students on the behavioral ecology and conservation of African carnivores&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nontechnical abstract&lt;br/&gt;This international research training program allows advanced undergraduates and junior graduate students to spend extended periods conducting field research on free-living African carnivores in Kenya, building on a strong long-term program of carnivore research in the Masai Mara National Reserve. Several students each year will undertake projects designed to acquire new and useful information about the carnivores inhabiting the Mara-Serengeti ecosystem, and to develop strong, long-lasting professional relationships with Kenyan scientists. A strong team of American and Kenyan trainers will help students address a broad array of research questions about the behavior, conservation and physiology of African carnivores, ranging from the evolution of their cognitive abilities to the effects of human activity on their stress physiology. Pairs of undergraduate and graduate students will be linked by topical research focus, and work closely with local experts. While in Kenya, students will receive explicit training in science writing, and present their work at an annual conference on carnivore biology sponsored by the Kenya Wildlife Service. The research opportunities offered to students here are unparalleled, not only to investigate the biology of several carnivore species that remain very poorly understood, but also to make important contributions to behavioral ecology, stress physiology and conservation biology. The knowledge acquired in this research should facilitate conservation of African carnivores, and thus contribute to the economic well-being of Kenya, which is intimately linked with revenues from eco-tourism. This research program will also contribute significantly to the professional development of a new generation of global scientists who are united in their desire to understand and protect the natural world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical abstract&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual focus of this project is the behavioral ecology, physiology, and conservation of African carnivores. Mammalian carnivores are critical to the stability and integrity of ecosystems around the world, largely because they play key roles in regulating such important ecosystem processes as interspecific competition and predator-prey dynamics. Despite their importance, however, carnivores are in global decline due to a combination of habitat degradation and direct human persecution. In fact, today many carnivore populations are declining even within protected areas. It has become clear in recent years that our ability to conserve mammalian carnivores, including most of those in Africa, is limited by a dearth of knowledge about many aspects of their basic biology. This international research training program aims to fill these gaps in our knowledge in regard to African carnivores, and to apply that new knowledge to improving carnivore management; this program should thus ultimately facilitate carnivore conservation across the African continent. During the proposed funding period, students will use experimental and observational methods to test hypotheses suggesting 1) relationships among social complexity, foraging demands and general intelligence, 2) endocrine substrates of cooperative behavior, 3) how anthropogenic activities affect the behavior, physiology and demography of mammalian carnivores, and 4) best carnivore management practices. This is the only training program in the United States where both undergraduate and graduate students can obtain field research experience investigating the biology of free-living African carnivores. Most past participants in this program have reported their experiences in Kenya to be life-changing, setting them on trajectories of professional development they otherwise never would have dreamed possible.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1556407</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Holekamp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>holekamp@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7727</Code>
      <Text>IRES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5976</Code>
      <Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5991</Code>
      <Text>KENYA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
