<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Reshaping and Modeling the Criminal Justice System through Science, Technology, and Systems Analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>146057</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES-1557082&lt;br/&gt;Bruce Hoffman&lt;br/&gt;Ohio University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses archival materials from the Presidents Commission on Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice (1965-67) and interviews with commission staff to investigate the use of empirical science and technologies of systems analysis to rationalize and reshape traditional criminal justice practice. Regarded as a defining moment in the organization of criminal justice and criminological science due to its creation of federal institutions to fund criminal justice research, other contributions of the commission have been less appreciated, including its impact on criminal justice education by creating a disciplinary field of criminal justice distinct from sociology and its use of systems analysis to create models of the criminal justice process as an integrated system whose varied components were coordinated towards the common goal of crime control. This project will conduct the first sustained analysis of the Crime Commission, investigating how diverse visions of crime prevention and criminal justice were introduced, negotiated, packaged, and enacted over the course of the commission and by other groups in its immediate aftermath; how knowledge production was shaped through organizational dynamics between commissioners and the staff of the commissions nine task force panels; and the specific impact of the Science and Technology Task Force, which brought systems analysis to the field of "civil defense" and the "war on crime." &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project's focus on science and technology provides a nuanced challenge to interpretations of the commission as extending Great Society agendas in uncomplicated ways. It explores how initial commission concerns with poverty and social causation dropped out of the commission's mappings and models of the criminal justice process, anticipating and shaping subsequent approaches and policy, and helps illuminate the subsequent extension of criminal justice technologies into everyday life. The analysis of extensive transcripts of meetings spanning a sixteenth month period adds to our understanding of the construction of scientific advisory reports, showing how diverse understandings of scientific aims and political interests are negotiated and packaged for perceived audiences. The project also serves as the last opportunity to preserve the memories and contemporary evaluations of justice practices by commission staff whose careers that began with the possibilities of the Crime Commission and witnessed unprecedented transformations in criminal justice practices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is based in the empirical collection and analysis of three types of data. First, the study will use the tools of contemporary science studies to engage in a careful textual analysis of the public documents of the crime commission, interpreting these technical reports as public performances through which scientific credibility is communicated and maintained. Second, the analysis of official accounts will be complemented by the analysis of internal accounts collected at NARA sites and related collections. The archives are believed to contain a variety of relevant documents, including transcripts from commission meetings, notes from advisory panels, internal letters and memoranda, drafts of reports, and early maps and models of the criminal justice process. Both the public documents and internal documents will be coded using similar coding mechanisms enabling larger themes and developments to emerge. Third, the investigator will seek to contact and conduct audiotaped or videotaped interviews of all available staff connected with the commission. The goal of these interviews is to collect general perspectives of recollected operations, aspirations, and tensions within the crime commission across multiple organizational roles and standpoints, which can be cross-referenced with archival documents and other interviews. The investigator will also seek to record and gain participants' insights into previously unrecognized connections between the systems model being set forth and the subsequent development of criminal justice and criminology, as well as their interpretation and evaluation of later developments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will design an interactive website designed for classroom use. The site will use techniques of science and technology studies to translate the project's central themes concerning science and the origins of the criminal justice system. At a time of heightened interest and criticism of US policies of mass incarceration and institutionalized criminal justice responses to racial inequality and popular protest, the project and website serves as an important "history of the present" that contextualizes how contemporary configurations of criminological science and criminal justice practices emerged and illuminates alternative paths not taken. The study also trains a team of undergraduates in archival research, the organization and analysis of primary source documents, and the development and presentation of research at professional meetings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1557082</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hoffman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hoffmanb@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio University</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7405932857</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>108 CUTLER HL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1331</Code>
      <Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
