<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Interdisciplinary Research Experiences in Robotics for Assistive Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>230400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wendy Nilsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>REU Site: Interdisciplinary Research Experiences in Robotics for Assistive Technology&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site award funds a new REU site focused on Robotics in Assistive Technology at the University of Wisconsin-Stout. Robotics has potential appeal across a wide range of disciplines, especially as robots become increasingly integrated into society, performing useful tasks in the home and elsewhere. The REU site will provide 8-week interdisciplinary research experiences in robotics targeting first generation, underrepresented students, and students from institutions with limited research opportunities. Students and faculty will participate in professional development, interdisciplinary data sharing, and research activities designed to empower and prepare students for advanced degrees and careers in engineering. This project will make a meaningful impact in how we apply robots in enhancing our quality of life. It is imperative that we provide a larger pool of individuals trained in the field of robotics to address the increasing number of national needs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a new REU proposal in the area of assistive robotics. The proposed research projects for participants focus on several areas such as dynamic model design, control, human-machine communication, teleoperation, and wireless control. The proposed comprehensive three stage program touches all components of an REU site from introductory workshops for the basic concepts to the preparation of their final research report that could lead to a publication. The PI is an expert in the area of assistive technologies and the other faculty members are experts in the areas of rehabilitation, robotics, and bio-sensing. This REU site provides modern facilities and professional mentors to guide undergraduates in explorations of real-world problems related to robotics in assistive technology. Students will learn how to use current tools and techniques to solve those problems through exciting research projects across a wide range of research topics. The goal of the site is to increase participation of first generation, underrepresented minorities, women and persons with disabilities, and provide opportunities for students from schools with limited research opportunities. The students will participate in research and professional development activities all designed to achieve the goals of retaining and graduating undergraduate students in engineering and increasing recruitment of students into graduate programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1560219</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Anderson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>andersoncay@uwstout.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shiw@uwstout.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liuc@uwstout.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Devin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bergdev@uwstout.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Stout</Name>
      <CityName>Menomonie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>547510790</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7152321123</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 790</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
