<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Analyze This: Analytical Chemistry Applied to Interdisciplinary Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry (CHE) supports a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site at Purdue University entitled, "Analyze This: Analytical Chemistry Applied to Interdisciplinary Research" that exposes undergraduate students to how analytical chemistry continues to be one of the foundations of innovation across the science spectrum. The REU site highlights the need for analytical chemists in a broad range of fields and aims to satisfy the needs of science, technology, and chemical industries by training and mentoring students who are specializing in chemical analysis. The main activity is student emersion into research labs where the research spans a range of interdisciplinary fields from environmental chemistry to cancer research and drug discovery to forensic science. The Monday morning cafes called "The Business of Chemistry" include informal discussions between REU participants and Chemistry faculty members who have formed start-up companies based on their research discoveries. The topics focus on how to bring innovative research to market and the role of chemists in the private sector. Additional activities include chemical health and safety, ethics in the sciences, scientific writing and presentations, resume building, and graduate school preparation. The REU is open to all, but student recruitment efforts target underrepresented groups by partnering with six universities that historically serve underrepresented students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under the mentorship of a faculty member and graduate student, undergraduates complete an independent research project in analytical chemistry. By participating in the methods of discovery the students gain in-depth knowledge in their research areas. Students give oral presentations and participate in poster sessions along with other students in the Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF) Program at Purdue University. Co-authorship in a peer-reviewed research article is a key goal for the REU student. Through individual research, teamwork, and outreach they gain an understanding of what is required to succeed in a career in chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1560244</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yxia@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Michalski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gmichals@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/05/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
