<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI/Collaborative Research: Electrically-Enhanced Precision MicroRolling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/31/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>123425</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas F. Kuech</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Grant Opportunity for Academic Liaison with Industry (GOALI) award is to significantly enhance the formability of thin sheet metals and the dimensional accuracy of formed features at the micrometer scale by integrating high-density electrical current with mechanical deformation through an instrumented desktop rolling mill. Two fundamental questions will be addressed in achieving the objectives: (1) how electrical current affects the plasticity and residual stress of metals subjected to deformation; and (2) how to realize in-process measurement for effective microrolling process control. The planned research tasks are: (1) Experimental characterization and constitutive modeling of material behavior subjected to mechanical and electrical loading; (2) Multi-physics modeling of mechanical stress, thermal and electro-magnetic fields in the microrolling process and mill structure; (3) In process sensing and data mapping for process characterization; and (4) System integration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the new hybrid process will reduce process design complexity, reduce energy consumption, and reduce chemical wastes in achieving thin metal foils with desired surface finish. The new sensing methods and instrument design will push the current limits of the rolling process in terms of size, precision, cost, and energy efficiency. One of the many uses of the metal foil is micro-electrodes and contacts for the next generation of bio-implants, such as pacemakers for treating heart disorders, deep brain simulation electrodes for potentially treating Parkinson?s disease, depression, dystonia or chronic pain, and artificial pancreas for monitoring and developing new therapeutics that regulate Type 1 Diabetes. Device miniaturization enabled by microrolling will benefit patients by improving their quality of life. The collaboration between academic institutions and industry will inspire the innovations and talents needed for U.S. manufacturing companies to remain competitive. The project will provide training to graduate and undergraduate students and practitioners through research opportunities, class projects, short courses, and internships.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1560628</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Robert.Gao@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/09/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>080E</Code>
      <Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8025</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
