<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Undergraduate Knot Theory Conference III</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>39350</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal is to fund the Undergraduate Knot Theory Conference 2016 to bring together undergraduates and undergraduate faculty interested in knot theory, to be held at Denison University from July 31 to August 2, 2016 as a satellite conference to "2016 MathFest" which will take place in Columbus, OH. Knot theory is a field very amenable to research by undergraduates. There are a variety of REU programs with a knot theory component. Moreover, there are many faculty members who would like to involve their students in undergraduate research in knot theory. This conference will bring together experts in knot theory with undergraduates who are either currently participating in knot theory REUs, undergraduates who have participated in knot theory research, current graduate students who participated as undergraduates in knot theory research, and perhaps most importantly, faculty who either have involved undergraduates in knot theory research or who would like to involve undergraduates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a centerpiece, the organizers plan to have a collective problem session to give participants numerous ideas for future research directions. This conference will provide an opportunity for students to experience a mathematics research conference that is specifically designed and directed toward them. Moreover, the conference will establish a supportive network of students and faculty with an interest in knot theory research, thus furthering the involvement of students in the field of mathematics. The conference URL is www.denison.edu/unknot.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1561524</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Colin.Adams@williams.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lewis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ludwig</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ludwigl@denison.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/18/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Denison University</Name>
      <CityName>Granville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>430230607</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7405876679</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P O Box 713</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
