<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Cognitive Mechanisms of Early Math Learning - Improving Outcomes by Harnessing Multiple Memory Representations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>80958</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal was submitted in response to EHR Core Research (ECR) program announcement NSF 15-509. The ECR program of fundamental research in STEM education provides funding in critical research areas that are essential, broad and enduring. EHR seeks proposals that will help synthesize, build and/or expand research foundations in the following focal areas: STEM learning, STEM learning environments, STEM workforce development, and broadening participation in STEM. The ECR program is distinguished by its emphasis on the accumulation of robust evidence to inform efforts to (a) understand, (b) build theory to explain, and (c) suggest interventions (and innovations) to address persistent challenges in STEM interest, education, learning, and participation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study will investigate the processes that connect gestures and mathematics learning. Gestures are an important yet under-investigated aspect of mathematics teaching. They can influence students' memory and understanding of mathematical representations. The series of studies will examine students' learning of the concept of mathematical equivalence by testing instruction that incorporates commonly used verbal explanations and gestures. Mathematical equivalence includes understanding the meaning of the equal sign and determining if two expressions are equal. Second and third grade children will be participants. Of particular interest in the studies is the influence of gestures on preexisting knowledge of procedures, how gestures support learning beyond emphasizing information and direct learners' attention, and the creation of procedural knowledge. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The series of experimental studies will examine the mechanisms that connect gestures and procedural understanding of mathematical equivalence. The studies begin in the first phase with examining how gesture is connected to procedural knowledge of mathematical equivalence. Subsequent studies investigate how gesture functions as a mechanism for learning beyond emphasizing or directing attention to relevant information. Data collected will students' responses to equivalence problems and eye tracking data to follow whether students are looking from one side of the equal sign to the other. In the second phase of the work, the studies will examine how gesture has beneficial effects on learning more generally in mathematics. Working memory will be assessed in order to examine the role of gesture across different individuals. Fraction tasks will be used to examine the generalization of the previous results regarding gestures to other mathematics concepts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1561182</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cook</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>susan-cook@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Iowa</Name>
      <CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7980</Code>
      <Text>Core R&amp;D Programs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
