<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CyberCorps: New Scholarships for Service (SFS) Program at the University of Kansas - Jayhawk SFS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1197646</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal will inaugurate a CyberCorps®: Scholarship for Service (SFS) program at the University of Kansas under the name of Jayhawk SFS. The goals of the proposed Jayhawk SFS program are: establish an active, well-managed, student-centered SFS program; recruit outstanding students who are dedicated to cyber-security profession and government service; provide them with superior education and professional training, achieve 100% student retention and placement; and expand research and education capacities at the host institution. The Jayhawk SFS program will be evaluated internally and externally to ensure the quality and continuous development of the program. Promotion, recruitment, education, research, professional development, outreach, placement and evaluation plans are carefully crafted to identify well-qualified and highly-motivated students, provide them with outstanding education and training experience, and in-turn expand the education and research capacities at the host institution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will produce well-trained security professionals to serve the needs of government agencies. The program will closely work with the 1st Infantry Division at Fort Riley, Kansas National Guard, U.S. Army Cyber Command (ARCYBER), and the Graduate Military Program at KU to recruit transitioning soldiers and veterans. In addition, the Project Team will extensively collaborate with University TRIO programs, such as the McNair Scholars Program, to recruit underrepresented and underserved students (e.g., African-Americans, Hispanic-Americans, indigenous students, and first-generation college students). The proposed program will also increase the representation of minorities in cybersecurity education through a variety of enrichment activities. Through outreach and community-service activities, the Jayhawk SFS program will highlight cybersecurity issues to the community, introduce educational opportunities, and stimulate public awareness with the long-term goal of changing people?s security and privacy perceptions and improving their security behaviors in daily life.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1565570</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Frost</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>frost@ittc.ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Warren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alexander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>perry.alexander@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Luo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bluo@ittc.ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fengjun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fli@ittc.ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>FED CYBER SERV: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7434</Code>
      <Text>CNCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
