<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ion-paired cooperative catalysts for carbon-carbon bond formation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>277554</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Gilje</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Graham Dobereiner of Temple University is developing methods for using carbon monoxide (CO) in the preparation of important chemicals. Carbon monoxide is widely used as a feedstock in the chemical industry for the formation of commodity chemicals. Because its use is so ubiquitous, there is significant value in finding new approaches to using CO that are more efficient than those now used. In this project a new type of catalyst, where two separate parts work together in making chemical bonds, is being developed in order to reduce energy input and decrease resource consumption relative to traditional methods. The investigation includes a sustained outreach program with local schools, as well as readying students for the STEM workforce by organizing regional meetings for future scientists with interests in inorganic chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, a general approach to preparing ion paired complexes composed of two oppositely charged metal complexes is being developed. The purpose is to provide a library of tunable bimetallic catalysts and to establish the conditions required for preparing stable bimetallic ion pair catalysts. Using this library, catalysts are being designed for several catalytic reactions, including hydroesterification and the selective copolymerization of carbon monoxide and alkenes. Besides yielding efficient catalytic processes, potential benefits include an improved fundamental understanding of ion pairing as well as advancements in the inorganic synthesis.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1565721</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Graham</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dobereiner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dob@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Temple University</Name>
      <CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191405104</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2157077379</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3340 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8037</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8396</Code>
      <Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8398</Code>
      <Text>Hydrocarbon Conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
