<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Highly Active Neodymium Catalysts for Polymerization of Dienes and Vinyl Monomers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Mihaela C. Stefan of the University of Texas at Dallas is supported by the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Division of Chemistry to develop polymerization catalysts based on neodymium (Nd) metal complexes. The objective is to provide research laboratories and the chemical industry with an alternative for the well-known Ziegler-Natta (ZN) catalyst system, which is widely used in industry for the preparation of polymers (large multi-unit molecules) from smaller molecules. The proposed Nd-based catalytic systems have the advantage of producing polymers from unusual starting materials, in reactions that are beyond the capabilities of current ZN catalysts. The versatile nature of the Nd-based catalytic system enhances the likelihood of success for the synthesis of stereoregular (highly ordered) polymers from different classes of small organic compounds. If successful, the project is likely to have immediate impact on the commercial production of polymeric materials, such as elastomers, adhesives and man-made fibers. Students working on the project are trained in organic and polymer synthesis and product characterization techniques. Female high school students are given the opportunity to participate in summer research to gain skills in a chemistry laboratory environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to develop a novel catalytic system composed of NdCl3 and phosphate ligands for the polymerization of a variety of monomers, such as dienes, styrene and polar vinyl monomers. A mechanistic investigation of these polymerizations will be conducted to understand the function of each component and to optimize the reaction conditions for the production of polymers with high stereoregularity and well-defined molecular weights. The variation of the phosphate ligands around the Nd metal center is expected to influence the stereoregularity, molecular weights, and polydispersities of the synthesized polymers. The crystal structures of the synthesized neodymium catalysts is determined and correlated with their catalytic activity. The use of these catalysts for copolymerization of dienes with polar vinyl monomers demonstrates the versatility of the neodymium catalytic systems. The ability to polymerize polar vinyl monomers is especially attractive because the conventional Ziegler-Natta catalysts are not active for polymerization of polar vinyl monomers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1566059</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mihaela</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stefan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mci071000@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
      <CityName>Richardson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8037</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8396</Code>
      <Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8398</Code>
      <Text>Hydrocarbon Conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
