<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Cybersecurity Scholarship-for-Service at The University of Arizona</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4457334</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project intends to create a new CyberCorps(R): Scholarship for Service (SFS) program at the department of Management Information Systems (MIS) of the University of Arizona (UA) especially aimed at recruiting from across the state, with particular emphasis on minority recruitment and retention. The proposed program encompasses several important areas of activity such as student mentoring and development; independent research study integrated into the program; assessment of student progress; internship and post-graduation placement assistance; and program assessment and evaluation. Cybersecurity and Information Assurance are critical to ensuring the integrity and availability demands of a modern, globally-networked infrastructure. The biggest challenge facing employers is finding employees with the right security skills, including operations security, information security risk management, and security management practices thus proving the SFS program timely, relevant, and beneficial. The MIS department at UA is renowned for its consistent ranking in the top five MIS programs in the country (U.S. News and World Report) for over 20 years. The approach to managing the program is deliberately cross-disciplinary and intended to support the broadest definition of cybersecurity, including information assurance, network security, trustworthy computing, risk management for IT, etc. The program is intended to address the great need for security training in the U.S. The curriculum includes dedicated coursework and significant research with world-class faculty in security and risk management, operations security, information security risk management, and security management practices. The ultimate goal of this program is to help broaden representation in science and technology and increase interest in and technological competence for government service. The program addresses a burgeoning need for knowledgeable security specialists by providing a pool of carefully cultivated and highly trained personnel. The project contributes to meaningful curriculum development that can serve as a model to other programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1303362</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Salim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hariri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hariri@ece.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hsinchun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hchen@eller.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Patton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mpatton@eller.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paulo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pgoes@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/23/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7434</Code>
      <Text>CNCI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
