<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Summer School on Biocomplexity from Gene to System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michele Grimm</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Metin&lt;br/&gt;Proposal ID: 1303460&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The biological sciences have become a more quantitative and information-driven sciences since emerging computational and mathematical tools facilitate the collection and analysis of vast amounts of biological data. Complex analysis of biological systems provides biological knowledge for the organization, management and mining of biological data by using advanced computational tools. The biological data are inherently complex, non-uniform and collected at multiple temporal and spatial scales. The investigations of complex biological systems and processes require an extensive collaboration between biologists, mathematicians, computer scientists and engineers to improve our understanding of the various complex biological processes from gene to system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merits: The main objective of the summer school is to expose undergraduate and graduate biological science and bioengineering students to the relatively new approaches of Nano-Bio-Info-Cogno (NBIC) Technologies and translational research. This summer school will be helpful, also, to students in computer science and mathematics who are interested in pursuing research in biology, bio-molecular engineering and bioengineering, since the summer school provides exceptional insights into the fundamental challenges in biological sciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The summer school uses lectures, oriented toward biological science students, by expert faculty and will focus on the Nano-Bio-Info-Cogno (NBIC) Technologies and Translational Research: Opportunities and Challenges. In addition to these lectures, the summer school will employ 2 two-hour panel discussion, with active participation by the summer school participants, focused on Engineering Better Medicines and Advances in Biomedical Engineering Research and Education in the World. The summer school will stimulate further interdisciplinary research and collaborations among engineers, mathematicians, computer scientists, and medical researchers, and will help in identifying new, challenging directions in complex biological science and bioengineering research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1303460</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Metin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Akay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>makay58@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>004E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>017E</Code>
      <Text>Cellular and Tissue Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>137E</Code>
      <Text>Neural-engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>138E</Code>
      <Text>Stem cells/regenerative medicine</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7479</Code>
      <Text>NANO AND BIO MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
