<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Microwave Impedance Microscopy Study of Topological Structures of Quantum Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>560000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this program is to study local structures of quantum materials with electrical contrast. Because of its scientific as well as technological importance, the electronic properties of complex quantum materials have been an important area of research. As model material systems, their understanding often leads to revelations well beyond these materials themselves, as well as to important technology. A recent development of the field is the emerging importance of local organizations in these materials, such as edge channels, domain walls, glassy patterns and interface structures. As a result, it is highly desirable to probe the local electrical response to external excitations and gain insight on electronic organization in these materials. The experimental tool to carry out this study is a novel scanning near-field microwave impedance microscopy (sMIM). With optimized sensitivity, the minute local dielectric response to electromagnetic waves can be detected by RF electronics to form microwave images, with a spatial resolution determined by the tip diameter which can be one million times smaller than radiation wavelength. The combined strength of high resolution microwave imaging and temperature/field environment in the experimental system will allow the team to spatially visualize many interesting physical processes. This project will support the education of a PhD student and postdoc in these highly sophisticated experiments, which have historically been excellent training for many scientific careers from academia to the most advanced technology industries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this program is to study electrical properties of materials that are candidates to continue the Si revolution. This understanding often leads to revelations well beyond these materials themselves, as well as to important new technology. A recent development of the field is the emerging importance of local organizations in these materials. As a result, it is highly desirable to probe the local electrical response to external excitations and gain insight on electronic organization in these materials, thus optimizing the opportunity to tailor their properties for application. The experimental tool to carry out this study is a novel scanning near-field microwave impedance microscopy (sMIM). This project will support the education of a PhD student and postdoc in these highly sophisticated experiments, which have historically been excellent training for many scientific careers from academia to the most advanced technology industries. Because of the relative ease of operation of RF electronics, a first-order understanding of the technique and its contrast mechanism are easily understood with a simple lumped-element circuit models, which can be taught in high school physics classes. Further, the dual nature of both science and instrumentation development is an excellent platform to engage college students for research. This technology is also of industrial interest, for example in semiconductor metrology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1305731</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhi-Xun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zxshen@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/20/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1710</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6863</Code>
      <Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
