<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Thermodynamics of Strongly Coupled Non-Relativistic Matter.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>First-principles investigations of neutron and nuclear matter are at the forefront of research activities in nuclear physics and take ample advantage of the recent advances in high-performance computing. This project will lay the groundwork for finite-temperature studies of nuclear physics by pursuing the systematic study of strongly-coupled Fermi systems and by testing this approach with related few- and many-body problems in atomic physics. The numerical methods developed here focus on nonperturbative aspects of the nuclear many-body problem and the results are expected to impact other fields such as atomic and condensed matter physics, high-energy physics and astrophysics. The group will establish a database of Monte Carlo configurations that will serve the scientific community in the USA and abroad.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will promote an interdisciplinary study employing advanced first-principles calculations in several fields, ranging from nuclear physics to condensed matter and atomic physics. This will present unique opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students to develop a broad understanding of various physical systems and perform creative multidisciplinary research. The database developed here will provide hands-on tools useful for teaching nonperturbative numerical methods for students worldwide. Education at the undergraduate level will benefit the local Computational Astronomy and Physics Research Experience for Undergraduates (CAP-REU) program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1306520</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joaquin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Drut</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drut@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
      <CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
      <ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1285</Code>
      <Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
