<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal:RUI: Single-Walled Carbon Nanotube Nanopores for Motion Control of Biologically Important Molecules and Ions and Undergraduate Training in Nanopore Transport</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James Lisy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Mark Ellison from Ursinus College and Dr. Michael Strano from MIT are supported by an award from the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Division of Chemistry to investigate the motion of ions and biologically relevant molecules through single-walled carbon nanotubes. Using nanotube nanopore devices fabricated at MIT, they are conducting experiments to study fundamental properties of these systems and to assess their usefulness for the nanoscale detection and control of the flow of ions and molecules. This research extends the knowledge of motion through nanopores to several important areas, including amino acids and small neutral molecules. The research also enhances our understanding of the role of nanopore properties, such as the effects of functional groups at the pore mouth and nanopore surface charge on the motion of ions and molecules through nanopores. The results of this research provide foundational knowledge of nanotube nanopores and take an important step toward utilizing them in practical devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The undergraduate researchers at Ursinus College involved in these projects attain a variety of scientific skills. First, they obtain significant experience conducting experiments in nanoscience. They also develop their abilities to formulate, test, and revise scientific hypotheses. Additionally, the Ursinus students significantly benefit from the collaboration with MIT, which includes visits to MIT to conduct experiments with the high-grade research instrumentation there. Students involved in this research will emerge as well-trained young scientists with the tools to approach a wide range of scientific questions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1306529</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>strano@MIT.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/26/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6885</Code>
      <Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7234</Code>
      <Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
