<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Millimeter-wave Micro and Nano-Ferrite Circulators Integrated in CMOS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>457921</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this program is to develop the next generation broadband millimeter-wave circulators integrated in CMOS using nano- and micro-hexaferrite materials operating in the 10 GHz to 100 GHz range. The proposed research objectives will be revolutionary in the emerging area of a low-cost, miniaturized millimeter wave devices and technology. The approach is based on micro- and nano-sized hexagonal ferrite crystalline with strong internal anisotropic magnetic field which can provide strong ferromagnetic resonance in the millimeter wave length without strong external magnetic field. The post-processing compatible with the standard state-of-art commercial CMOS process will be developed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this program is the development of novel microstrip circulators and the innovative post-processing methods for complete system on-chip millimeter-wave integrated circuits in CMOS using micro- and nano-ferrite materials. A comprehensive characterization study will be performed to analyze the dielectric and magnetic properties of nano- and micro-ferrite. The study will expand the current body of knowledge on fundamental characteristic properties of micro- nano-size ferrites, and techniques to assemble unidirectional field ferrite layers on CMOS substrates. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this program include: (i) developing the high-frequency millimeter-wave circuits in low-cost silicon CMOS processes with ferrite materials which enable the realization of high-performance components for critical applications ranging from phased-array radar to wireless transceivers for military as well as for satellite communications; (ii) providing interdisciplinary training to students in ferrite material science, electromagnetic waves, millimeter wave circuits, semiconductor processing, as well as in application areas such as wireless network and radar, with a particular focus on inclusion of members of underrepresented groups in science and engineering; and (iii) enabling outreach by communicating to a wider audience, the exciting interdisciplinary nature of the proposed device development and the research it will enable, through public lectures, websites, magazine articles, and undergraduate course material.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1309894</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Valencia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koomson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vkoomson@ece.tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mohammed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Afsar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mafsar@ece.tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tufts University</Name>
      <CityName>Medford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021555807</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6176273417</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>20 Professors Row</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>m655</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
