<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Australia</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Lindsey Furman Dougherty of the University of California Berkeley to conduct a research project in Biological Sciences during the summer of 2013 at the Queensland Brain Institute and University of Queensland (UQ) in Brisbane, Australia. The project title is "Mechanisms, Ultrastructure and Behavioral Function of Flashing in Ctenoides Ales: Disco Clams.'" The host scientist is Dr. Justin Marshall. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ocean's euphotic zone is an environment in which light is extremely variable, yet a wide array of organisms use visual displays that require ambient light for reflection. The bivalve mollusk Ctenoides ales lives at depths up to 20m and often inside crevices, where ambient light is dim and wavelength-restricted. Despite its light-limited habitat, this species evolved a reflective mantle edge that emits vivid light, leading to its common name, disco clam. C. ales is the only known bivalve with a behaviorally controlled photic display, yet virtually nothing is known about its mechanism, function or life history. Preliminary research in transmission electron microscopy, high speed video, spectrometry, hyperspectral imaging and particle modeling have advanced intracellular and mechanistic understanding of how the photic display is produced, but its behavioral purpose remains unknown. During this field season, hypotheses about the function of the flashing are being tested, including that it acts to attract phototaxic prey, larval juveniles for settlement, or is an aposematic warning toward predators. The study of photic displays by organisms advances knowledge about visual systems, communication, physical optics, photonics, structural composition and biomimetic technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, undergraduate students at Berkeley and at UQ are helping with research and field studies, allowing insight into graduate-level work and collaboration. Research results are being disseminated through the Understanding Science website of the University of California Museum of Paleontology. Project updates, photographs and videos are being uploaded through a blog. As these bivalves are well known in aquariums and popular with the public, there is substantial interest in this project. This project is also being communicated through involvement with WIS (Women in Science) by examining the role of women in Australian scientific communities. Finally, the results are being communicated through community involvement in the Dinner With A Scientist program at the Oakland Zoo; Science Nights at multiple local elementary schools; and through volunteer efforts with the Expanding Your Horizons (EYH) Conference which targets girls in middle school, the Surfrider Foundation and SurfAid. This research and outreach are forging partnerships between the international community, UQ, and Berkeley.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1310703</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lindsey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dougherty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Dougherty Lindsey</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803090265</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5912</Code>
      <Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
