<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in China</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Maxwell Christopher Wilson of Arizona State University to conduct a research project in Biology during the summer of 2013 at Beijing Normal University in Beijing, China. The project title is "Gauging the Impacts of China's South-to-North Water Transfer Project." The host scientist is Dr. Li Xiaoyan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The North China Plain (NCP), home to more than 25% of China's population and served by three rivers (Hai, Huang, and Huai), faces per capita water scarcity as acute as any region of the world. Exacerbated by the NCP?s critical place in China's food supply, this scarcity has long lead the Chinese government to seek alternative measures for alleviating water stress. First conceived in the 1950s by Chairman Mao, the South-to-North Water Transfer Project (SNWTP) represents the grandest attempt to permanently solve the NCP's water woes. Started in 2002, after a 50 year feasibility study, currently one of three planned routes is completed, delivering 9 billion cubic meters per year of water to the NCP. However, while construction is ongoing, the impacts of the SNWTP on ecosystems are unknown. This project aims to close two main knowledge gaps, taking lessons from similar water transfer projects in Arizona and applying them to the SNWTP. Specifically this research quantifies both water lost to evaporation and the impact of habitat fragmentation along the canal route. To assure that the data are actionable, this project focuses on the middle route of the SNWTP which is currently under construction. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, this research will act as a seed project, enhancing collaboration between Beijing Normal University and Arizona State University. Lastly, upon the completion of this project the Fellow and host plan to share the results directly with policy makers in a formal report as well as to the broader scientific community though publication in internationally recognized journals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1311077</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maxwell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wilson Maxwell C</Name>
      <CityName>Phoenix</CityName>
      <ZipCode>850083464</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9200</Code>
      <Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
