<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Graphene-based Nanocomposite Filters for Antibacterial and Heavy Metal Removal</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Adsorbent-based nanotechnologies have been shown to remove various toxic contaminants from water rapidly and efficiently to acceptable levels. The major benefit of this nanotechnology is that it does not generate brines or other toxic disinfectant byproducts like other water treatment methods. Currently, point-of-use commercial membrane filters available in the marketplace are not capable of simultaneous inactivation of microorganisms and removal of heavy metals. This project presents an inexpensive and easy method to prepare membranes capable of removing heavy metals and inactivate microorganisms in water at an affordable price. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed technology has economical and societal benefits since this water purification system is portable, multi-functional, and presents a low fabrication cost. This technology has the potential to be applied in industrial, military, and domestic settings. Furthermore, this technology, successful, could help improve water quality availability worldwide and relieve water-related diseases that kill more than three million people in the world every year.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1311794</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Debora</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rodrigues</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dfrigirodrigues@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
