<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Developing sensitive tests for detecting water chemistry changes associated with shale bed methane production in the Appalachian Basin</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>95574</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030109</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Hydraulic fracturing of shale gas deposits has a potentially large impact on water supplies. In contrast to the current shale gas boom in Pennsylvania, New York State has been under a hydrofracking moratorium. This creates an opportunity to complete a large-scale, unbiased assessment of water chemistry pre-hydraulic fracturing, to facilitate detection of water chemistry changes following hydraulic fracturing. This project will develop a shale chemistry signature fingerprint based on a combination of halogen concentrations (Br, I, and Cl), isotopic ratios (129I/I, 87Sr/86Sr), and fluorescence of organic matter. The project will contribute to a scientifically-defendable protocol, applicable throughout the Marcellus play, whereby potential contamination from hydrofracking can be determined.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop geochemical fingerprinting tools to unambiguously identify changes in chemistry of surface water and groundwater due to activities related to energy production via hydraulic fracturing. These new geochemical fingerprinting tools will contribute to science-based decision making about the sources of contamination in regions where hydraulic fracturing is occurring and will lay the framework for developing best practices for evaluating evolving water quality in shale gas basins. The project will characterize geochemical parameters for present-day surface and shallow ground waters and establish a regional, pre-production baseline against which to compare future surface and shallow ground waters following the onset of hydraulic fracturing in New York State. This study will utilize; 1) unbiased sampling, 2) novel and unambiguous geochemical fingerprinting, and 3) rapid dissemination of results through a public database and web interface. All participating landowners will receive results of all water quality testing for their well water. The project will develop an open-access, detailed, geospatially-referenced database of surface and groundwater chemistry. The database will be made publically-available online and will have a web-GIS interface, such that it is navigable by a non-technical audience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/28/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1313522</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zunli</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zunlilu@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hoke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gdhoke@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lautz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lklautz@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Samson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sdsamson@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Siegel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>disiegel@mailbox.syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1579</Code>
      <Text>HYDROLOGIC SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7699</Code>
      <Text>ICER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
