<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Examining the Climatology of Extreme Storms in the Northeast US and Putting Hurricane Sandy in Context</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25168</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Candace O. Major</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Hurricane Sandy was an extreme storm with a historic impact on the northeastern U.S. The proposed work will lead to a better understanding of this event by placing it in the context of the regional paleohurricane record. To compare Hurricane Sandy with past storm events, the project will conduct numerical surge and wave modeling, as well as textural analyses of Sandy-related and paleo-overwash deposits. This work will leverage previous surge modeling and paleo-overwash studies by the PIs in order to develop a more comprehensive paleohurricane record for the New York/New Jersey/Connecticut area. In addition, the project will compare Hurricane Sandy with modeled synthetic storm scenarios to evaluate the likelihood of Sandy-like events under current and future climate conditions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will help to determine the frequency and probability of severe storms in a heavily populated coastal region of the U.S. Two undergraduate students and two post-doctoral researchers will be involved. The PIs will continue ongoing engagement with managers and policy makers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1313859</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Donnelly</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdonnelly@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
