<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Stakeholder Alignment for Public-Private Partnerships</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Across societal infrastructure systems, the inherited institutional mechanisms for stakeholder alignment are incomplete or inadequate for the twin challenges for creating value and mitigating harm. New proprietary technologies developed by the project team enable speedy representation of stakeholder interests at the system level. These technologies, combined with a service delivery model and a neutral stance, represents a powerful platform for advancing "the science of science" and increasing societal capabilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Preliminary applications of the technology have focused on community green energy, biomedicine, regional innovation, the geosciences, and other domains where a mix of public and private stakeholders are engaged in large-scale initiatives. The impacts of the proprietary technology are threefold: 1. The implementation of large-scale scientific and technological initiatives is accelerated; 2. Clear "go/ no-go" decisions, and strategic pivots, can be made more quickly; 3. New institutional arrangements, anchored in real-time data, are more effective, robust, and sustainable. Commercially, an entrepreneurial business with defined practice areas is contemplated, with a mix of public and private sector clients. The neutral "honest broker" stance is distinct from the work of single-client consulting firms. The entrepreneurial business will have a "double bottom-line" that emphasizes financial success and societal contributions. Of particular importance will be the multiplier effects through job creation, which will be documented on each project. For example, in a potential future project on the siting of a new power plant on a former Air Force base, there is the potential to generate over 500-800 jobs through the construction process and an additional 50-80 jobs associated in ongoing operations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1313562</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haberman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haberman@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Canavan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>patc59@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nolan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmnolan@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cutcher-Gershenfeld</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>joelcg@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8023</Code>
      <Text>I-Corps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
