<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multi-Wavelength X-ray, SZ, and Lensing Analysis of the CLASH Clusters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>278441</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard E. Barvainis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Clusters of galaxies are the largest gravitationally bound objects in the Universe and provide excellent sensitivity for determining cosmological parameters. In particular, cosmological simulations predict an approximately universal form for cluster dark matter mass profiles. This project proposes to do a modeling analysis of a sample of galaxy clusters. This analysis would provide three-dimensional shapes and alignments of the gas and dark matter in these clusters and thus allow for the physical properties of these clusters to be more accurately estimated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will use a three-dimensional triaxial X-ray, Sunyaev-Zel'dovich (SZ), and lensing analysis of the 25 clusters in the Cluster Lensing and Supernova survey with Hubble (CLASH) sample. The analysis will exploit the different line-of-sight dependences of the X-ray and SZ signals to constrain the three-dimensional morphologies of the clusters with the ultimate goal of testing predictions of Lambda Cold Dark Matter cosmological models in the context of large-scale structure formation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Educationally, the investigators will make regular classroom visits with primarily low-income, local high school students of diverse backgrounds to inform and inspire these students about science. In addition, the investigators will sponsor multi-week summer research programs with high school students and teachers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1313447</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sayers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jack@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1217</Code>
      <Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7480</Code>
      <Text>ARCHIVAL DATA ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
