<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PIF: Beyond Adiabatic State Preparation with Ultracold Trapped Ion Quantum Simulators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>175000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexander Cronin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In the early 1980's, Richard Feynman proposed a new way to perform computation that directly involves quantum mechanical effects and differs from conventional digital computers that are classical in nature (having one of two states in each bit). Recently, experimental groups have started to realize these Feynman ideas with trapped ion quantum simulators. These devices mimic the quantum behavior of particles by simulating them in a controlled quantum-mechanical arena. The work in this grant focuses on determining how to carry out the next generation of these experiments. They are controlled by shining lasers onto the ions that are in the trap which apply forces onto the ions that depend on the quantum state the ion is in. These forces induce vibrations into the collection of ions, and these vibrations can be detrimental to the functioning of the simulator. This work will determine the effects of these vibrations on the computation and will develop methods to both understand and to control those effects. Work will be carried out in close collaboration with two experimental groups who are building these simulators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One graduate student will be trained during the period of this grant. The training will help develop the technologically savvy workforce. In addition, a number of classroom visits to local schools in the Arlington, VA school district will be undertaken and presentations will be made that cover different phenomena in quantum mechanics (magnetism for elementary school and the two-slit experiment for middle school). The research work will focus on new paradigms for analog quantum simulation which, if successful, could have an impact on developments of novel computing technologies in the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1314295</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Freericks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>freericks@physics.georgetown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgetown University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200571789</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026250100</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>37th &amp; O St N W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7281</Code>
      <Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7203</Code>
      <Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
