<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Unitary Qubit Lattice Algorithms for Quantum Turbulence with Non-Abelian Vortices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>85000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will pursue the development of unitary qubit lattice algorithms (QULA) to solve problems in nonlinear physics by extending ideas used in lattice Boltzmann and lattice gas algorithms. QULA for scalar 2D and 3D Bose-Einstein condensates (BEC) have already provided new information on the unexpected behavior of continuum Hamiltonians. The major thrust of this project will be to examine energy spectral cascades in spinor-BEC quantum turbulence where the flow involves both Abelian and non-Abelian vortices. Such spinor quantum turbulence has yet to be simulated in any real detail, particularly in 3D, and the novel algorithms developed here can be viewed as a mesoscopic model for nonlinear physics. This research is also expected to have a profound impact on plasma and space physics applications, as QULA will allow for the study of magneto-hydrodynamics turbulence and magnetic reconnection. The QULA algorithms are manifestly unitary and can be readily encoded onto future quantum computers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broad impacts of this project include the training of the workforce of the future, with graduate and undergraduate students having the opportunity to learn and work in an important field of scientific inquiry. Students will acquire hands-on experience on the use of high-performance computational platforms, as QULA scale ideally on modern supercomputers and the scaling was tested up to several hundreds of thousands of cores.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1314245</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vahala</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lvahala@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7244</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8084</Code>
      <Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
