<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Project Near-Earth Object</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glenn H. Larsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I innovation addresses deficiencies in science content knowledge exhibited by many elementary school teachers. Project Near-Earth Object is a game-based professional development product that teachers can also use as a self-assessment tool to evaluate their content knowledge in science. It uses interactive science experiments in the form of fast-paced mini-games to increase pre-service and in-service elementary teachers' ability to teach science topics. Research indicates that teacher competence in the content area greatly affects elementary students? interest in and success in science. The innovation relies not only on gaming, but also on a narrative in which players are "recruited" by a league of scientists to help Earth prepare for a pending asteroid collision; they must stop a villain determined to destroy the Earth's anti-asteroid defense. In the interactive science experiments, teachers: use simulations to gather information related to the problem; test hypotheses to solve to science problems; and collaborate using social networking. The innovation uses computer-adapted differentiated instruction, meaning that each mini-game has six levels of difficulty and the computer adapts difficulty levels according to the learner's performance. Other features include scaffolding of instruction, instant feedback, video tutorials, mobile access, and a backend administrative dashboard for viewing performance data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader/commercialization impact of Project Near-Earth Object lies in its unique design and large but targeted market niche. There is no direct competition for this product. Project Near-Earth Object is the only intervention on the market that is a science learning game for teachers, available on both Web and mobile platforms, aligned with recognized national standards, featuring a community-based social component, and an easy-to-use dashboard for viewing and tracking performance. There are approximately 3 million teachers and 1200 teacher education programs in the U.S., and demand for elementary teachers is growing. Research indicates that elementary teacher interest and subject matter knowledge in science is low. Teachers recognize that content knowledge is essential for good teaching. 99% of elementary teachers say that performance evaluations should include knowledge of subject matter. This game can be easily integrated into existing teacher training curricula or offered as a stand-alone professional development product. Its scalable online design is conducive to distribution through multiple channels and to competitive pricing structures. Project Near-Earth Object can significantly impact teacher understanding of science content and more importantly how to "do science," which will contribute to better attitudes about science and ultimately to better teachers in the classroom.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1315394</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brewster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scott@triadinteractivemedia.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Triad Interactive Media</Name>
      <CityName>Jamestown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>272829383</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3369085884</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1601 Guilford College Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>079E</Code>
      <Text>VISUALIZATION &amp; VIRTUAL DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8031</Code>
      <Text>Education Products</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8039</Code>
      <Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8043</Code>
      <Text>System Design and Simulation</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
