<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Korea</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Rory Walsh of University of Oregon to conduct a research project in the Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences area during the summer of 2013 at Chungbuk National University in Cheongju, Chungcheongbuk-do, Republic of Korea. The project title is "Ancient State Formation in Korea: Ceramic Production, Consumption, and Exchange in the Baekje Kingdom." The host scientist is Dr. SEONG JeongYong.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using previously excavated materials from the archaeological archives at Chungbuk National University, this project investigates the role of pottery and food systems in the formation of the Baekje kingdom. Baekje was the first state-level society in the southwestern Korean peninsula, and served as a nexus of trade and cultural exchange among contemporary peoples in mainland and insular East Asia. This makes Baekje an excellent case study for economic and agricultural processes in the development of complex political systems, with ramifications for the worldwide study of state formation. Neutron Activation Analysis helps determine geochemical sources for clays, revealing continuity and change in systems of production, and chemical residue analysis identifies patterns in food use for ritual or symbolic purposes, as well as everyday subsistence. The archaeology of Korea presents a particularly vital and productive venue for international collaboration. Korean studies, including art, media, language, and history are currently enjoying a meteoric rise among international students and scholars. While this has led many to describe Korea as "emergent" on the world stage, the archaeology of Korea belies this label, demonstrating the pivotal role of Peninsular societies in shaping the collective culture of East Asia for at least the last three millennia. Archaeology provides an essential perspective to the study of Korean culture, by allowing us to track the uniqueness of Korean ways of life as well as to examine the curatorial role played by Korea in transmitting various technological, social, and artistic innovations across East Asia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, Korean archaeology is underrepresented in English language literature, although domestic research in South Korea is impressively meticulous and thorough. The Fellow's research also advances realignment of archaeological goals with the concerns of local communities. This project deploys state-of-the-art analytical techniques with a collaborative international sensibility, and will produce lasting, mutually beneficial cooperation between the institutions and researchers involved.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1316936</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walsh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Walsh Rory C</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974024740</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5942</Code>
      <Text>KOREA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
