<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NRI: Small: Reflex approximation of optimal control for an energy-efficient bipedal walking platform</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>999912</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The broad research goal of this project is to better understand the mechanics, balance, and energetics of bipedal walking. The first specific goal is to design, build and test a two-legged walking 'platform', a waist-down robot, and its computer controller. One can think of this platform as a legged Segway, for use by others putting on robotic upper bodies with arms and heads. The goal is to match the robustness of existent bipedal robots but with no need for electrical cords or hydraulic tubes and with approximately a 90 percent reduction in energy use. This will be achieved by the development and use of a reflex-based controller that minimizes the needed sensor bandwidth and on-board computation. The second goal is to advance the theories of walking balance and energetics including, especially, basic models for understanding the tradeoffs between robustness, versatility, energy efficiency, sensor accuracy and motor size. Deliverable outcomes include a demonstrable robot with a new 'reflex-based' controller, public access to complete design and control information, basic design formulas for the fundamental design trade-offs, student design and research experience, and inspiring demonstrations for public viewing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, robots based on this platform design could replace wheel and tread based systems used for, and proposed for use for, service robotics. The advantages of legs over wheels include a more anthropomorphic look, for human interaction, and, ultimately with further development, the ability to function on rough terrain. The basic theories of balance and energetics developed in this work will add insight concerning human walking, ultimately helping with the diagnosis and remediation of human disabilities, including aiding the design of assistive and prosthetic devices. The hands-on development work will educate and inspire engineering students working on the project. The demonstrations and demonstration videos will serve as an inspiration to those considering engineering careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1317981</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ruina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ruina@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8013</Code>
      <Text>National Robotics Initiative</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8086</Code>
      <Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
