<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Japan</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds Michelle Lee Galloway of University of California, Berkeley to conduct a research project in Engineering during the summer of 2013 at the School of Engineering, University of Tokyo in Tokyo, Japan. The project title is "Deployment of a Gamma-ray Imaging Instrument for Characterizing Radioactive Land Contamination." The host scientist is Professor Hiroyuki Takahashi.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project investigates the use of a novel gamma-ray imaging instrument for the purpose of informing the environmental remediation efforts within the Fukushima prefecture. The instrument uses semiconductor detectors (cadmium zinc telluride) that are configured to allow for Compton imaging of radioactive sources. The instrument is being integrated into the existing infrastructure of the Japanese aerial monitoring program. This project assesses the capabilities of this technology for use in environmental monitoring applications. Successful deployment of the instrument allows for isotopic identification, localization and morphology of radioactive sources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, this experience provides the Fellow with a unique opportunity to learn first-hand about the impact upon and needs of the local community as a result of radioactive contamination and also how the existing scientific infrastructure, policies, and technologies are able to address these issues. The project provides the opportunity for further collaboration between the two institutions as well as facilitating technological advancement within a field that is of local, national, and global interest.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1317094</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Galloway</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Galloway Michelle L</Name>
      <CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947091306</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5921</Code>
      <Text>JAPAN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5978</Code>
      <Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7316</Code>
      <Text>EAPSI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
