<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CIF: Small: Topological Interference Management</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>454877</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Summary: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main technical goal of this research is to solve the problem of index coding from an interference alignment perspective. The index coding problem lies at the intersection of several challenging problems in network information theory such as broadcast channels, source coding and network coding. This project explores the index coding problem and its generalizations as they relate to the problem of optimal interference management in wireless and wired communication networks, when only a coarse knowledge of network topology is available to the transmitters. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Significance:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the capacity limits of wireless and wired networks under practical assumptions is critical for industry, academia, government agencies and society in general, to have realistic expectations from communication networks of the future. Interference between concurrent information flows is a key bottleneck in both wired and wireless networks. The unified perspective of interference management taken in this research allows existing insights to be translated from wireless networks to wired networks and vice versa, as well as the discovery of new insights that cut across applications. The research brings together areas like wireless communications, network coding, classical information theory, graph-theory, as well as optimization and algorithms, providing cutting-edge training to the participating student researchers in these critical technical areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1317351</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Syed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jafar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>syed@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/29/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
