<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>University of Hawaii Oceanographic Instrumentation CY2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>163311</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James S. Holik</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A request is made by the University of Hawaii to fund additional and replacement instrumentation for the R/V Kilo Moana, (KM), a 185? general purpose research vessel operated as part of the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System (UNOLS) research fleet. The University of Hawaii (UH) supports two research vessels that provide platforms for research in the fields of oceanography, marine biology, geology and atmospheric science. They request funds to purchase oceanographic instrumentation and equipment in support of the multidisciplinary NSF/UNOLS projects to be undertaken on R/V Kilo Moana in 2012. In order of priority, they propose: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) Acquisition of spares for EM 710 Multibeam Sonar $113,329&lt;br/&gt;2) Multi-year plan to upgrade and maintain underway DAS on Kilo Moana $49,982&lt;br/&gt; $163,311&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under criterion two of the Proposal Guidelines. They provide infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF). The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1322167</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shor@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ferguson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jscottf@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/17/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
      <CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
      <ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
      <StateCode>HI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5413</Code>
      <Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
