<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ASME 2013 2nd Global Congress on Nanoengineering for Medicine &amp; Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Siegmund</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support for young researchers to attend the ASME 2013 International Congress on NanoEngineering for Medicine and Biology (NEMB 2013) in Boston, Feb. 4-6, 2013. The general goal for NEMB 2013 is to bring together&lt;br/&gt;leading experts in biology, medicine, nanomaterials, and engineering so as to review experimental methods, synthetic methods, results, models, computations, analyses and innovative methodologies for quantifying and treating medical disorders using engineering approaches. These are emerging areas that are of greatest importance not only for mechanics and materials but also for engineering and science in general, and for the development of new technologies in particular.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The combination of engineering and biology with a strong focus in medicine will be a hallmark of the planned event. We will actively involve a large community of participants, and provide an exciting forum to exemplify the intellectual merit of mechanics of materials&lt;br/&gt;in the solution of pressing problems in biology and medicine. Specific research areas to be covered include manufacturing and materials for nanomedicine, biology and nanoengineering, nanotechnology and public health, bioinspired materials and structures, and the application of mechanics principles to detect and treat cancer. Key intellectual questions include multiscale coupling of mechanical systems, linking chemical to continuum mechanical concepts, or the mechanics of adhesion and in the context of nanoparticles for cancer treatment, such as cell uptake. These are emerging areas of mechanics that will receive considerable attention through this event. This award will specifically enable support for student participants, student awards (oral and poster presentations), and networking opportunities for young researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1323457</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Markus</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buehler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbuehler@MIT.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Guy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Genin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>genin@me.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1630</Code>
      <Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>027E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
