<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research: InforMath: Mathematics to Enrich Learning Experiences in Science and Art Museums</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1517474</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alphonse T. DeSena</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project establishes a new research center, the InforMath Collaborative, that brings together university educational researchers and professionals at art and science museums in San Diego's Balboa Park. The InforMath Collaborative is investigating and building the capacity of informal learning institutions to support content and identity learning in mathematics. Through sustained collaborations that unite research, design, and professional development, members of the InforMath Collaborative are conducting design-based research on exhibits and programs that integrate art and science content from participating museums with the mathematics of topology and projective geometry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader goal of the InforMath Collaborative is to transform cultural perceptions of mathematics in ways that broaden learners' access to the discipline. The project aims to develop informal mathematical learning experiences that make mathematics feel accessible, body-based, creative, and deeply relevant to a wide array of other knowledge domains, including both art and science. The project will build and strengthen regional and national networks of educational professionals who work in informal mathematics learning and expand the capacity of informal institutions to support engaging, innovative, content-rich, and culturally transformative mathematical learning experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1323587</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Siboroski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>psiboroski@rhfleet.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ricardo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nemirovsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bnemirovsky@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Molly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kelton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mollylou.kelton@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7259</Code>
      <Text>AISL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
