<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Investigating effects of aqueous speciation in 13C-18O clumping and its implications for paleothermometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030205</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The recently established "clumped isotope" paleothermometer is based on the Carbon 13 - Oxygen 18 bond abundance in carbonate minerals. Although this technique is becoming more widely used, there are still many questions about the underlying processes that control geochemical signatures in bio-minerals and non-biologically formed minerals. This project will address several of these outstanding questions. Investigators will compare results from theoretical calculations and experiments to observations, including from slowly-grown naturally occurring samples such as the Devils Hole speleothem and deep-sea corals of variable mineralogy. This work should improve the ability to employ clumped isotopes in surface and subsurface systems, and identify the limitations of this technique. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will be highlighted in UCLA's annual Physical Sciences Outreach Day that brings 2000-3000 members of the public to the campus and a few hundred people to the exhibits. All of the participants in this project will also conduct a mineral precipitation activity with school children as part of a regular outreach program the PI runs. Support of this project will benefit an early career PI who is establishing a NSF-supported state-of-the-art isotope lab and is committed to recruiting, mentoring, and supporting outstanding early career scientists from diverse backgrounds, thus furthering NSF's goals to support underrepresented groups in the Earth Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1325054</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edwin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schauble</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schauble@ess.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aradhna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tripati</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ripple@zephyr.ess.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7295</Code>
      <Text>GEOBIOLOGY &amp; LOW TEMP GEOCHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
