<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Solid Oxide Fuel Cell Promise, Progress, and Priorities Workshop, Arlington, VA, July 11-12, 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49797</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Burka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1326996&lt;br/&gt;Nicholas&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Solid Oxide Fuel Cells (SOFCs) are uniquely capable of improving the efficiency of today's hydrocarbon-based economy while simultaneously enabling a transition to a carbon-neutral energy economy. Aspects which support this contention are 1) the highest possible combined heat and power efficiency (90%) of any energy conversion technology, 2) gravimetric energy densities comparable to internal combustion engines and ~5x higher than the best Li-ion batteries, 3) gravimetric power densities comparable to the best Li-ion batteries and ~3x higher than internal combustion engines, 4) the co-generation of high-quality waste heat that can be used for water-heating, space heating, or the production of additional electricity, and 5) an ability to use either hydrocarbons (gasoline, propane, natural gas, etc.) or hydrogen as a fuel. Unfortunately, SOFC research and development efforts have suffered from technical challenges, funding scarcity/inconsistency, and a lack of public awareness. The objective of this proposal is to organize a SOFC Promise, Progress, and Priorities workshop that will allow representatives from academia, industry, and government to exchange ideas on how to best advance SOFC technology, through a series of moderated discussions and completion of various technology assessment tasks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These objectives will be met by convening federal officials, corporate representatives, and academic SOFC researchers for a workshop at the Westin Arlington Gateway Hotel in Arlington, VA from July 11-12, 2013. Jason Nicholas of Michigan State University is the primary Organizer for the Workshop. The workshop will engage the 36 invited participants and 14 general participants in poster presentations, review panels, committee meetings, and open discussions. Workshop conclusions will be disseminated through the publication of an open-access, peer-reviewed workshop summary article and by the online posting of committee reports, constituency whitepapers, and the workshop summary.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will have a broad impact by advancing a technology capable of improving the nation's environmental quality, economic sustainability, and national security. The workshop will result in improved awareness of the unique benefits of SOFCs by the public and the scientific community. The workshop will also improve the participation and impact of women and underrepresented minorities in science, technology, engineering and mathematics fields by having these individuals serve on high-visibility panel reviews and as committee chairs/co-chairs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1326996</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nicholas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdn@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
