<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Support for Recomb 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>RECOMB2013: 17th International Conference on Research in Computational Molecular Biology&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The RECOMB Conference Series (http://www.recomb.org/) was founded in 1997 by Sorin Istrail, Pavel Pevzner, and Michael Waterman to provide a scientific forum for theoretical advances in computational biology and their applications in molecular biology and medicine. Previous RECOMB conferences have been held annually in North America, Europe, and Asia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;RECOMB 2013 is the seventeenth in a series of well-established scientific conferences bridging the areas of computational, mathematical, statistical and biological sciences. The conference features 6 keynote talks by preeminent scientists in life sciences, including Scott Fraser (USC and Caltech, Imaging), Takashi Gojobori (Japan, comparative genomics), Deborah Nickerson (U Washington, Exon sequencing), Nadia A Rosenthal (Monash University, Australia, Stem cell), Chung-I Wu (U Chicago, evolutionary genomics), and Xiaoliang Sunny Xie (Harvard, single molecule). The conference will also feature 32 state-of-art scientific presentations selected from 167 submissions. The topics cover essentially every aspect of computational biology and bioinformatics, plus emerging areas such as molecular imaging and single molecule sequencing. There will also be 5 highlight talks selected from 47 submissions that are published in year 2012 up to 02/10/2013, plus about 200 poster presentations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference attracts research contributions in all areas of computational molecular biology, including but not limited to: molecular sequence analysis; recognition of genes and regulatory elements; molecular evolution; protein structure; structural genomics; analysis of gene expression; biological networks; sequencing and genotyping technologies; drug design; probabilistic and combinatorial algorithms; systems biology; computational proteomics; structural and functional genomics; information systems for computational biology and imaging.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The many events at RECOMB provide an excellent way for students to be exposed to new and exciting research areas, and learn of cutting-edge advances in their own research areas and beyond. Furthermore, students will have ample opportunity to meet leading researchers in both informal and formal settings. Thus, the attendance of RECOMB2013 will benefit the students greatly for their career development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1328201</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mona</FirstName>
      <LastName>Singh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mona@cs.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
