<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I/UCRC FRP: Collaborative Research: The Physical Internet for a Sustainable Logistics Future -- Advancing CELDi's Leadership Position</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>60292</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Raffaella Montelli</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Program Director's Recommendation &lt;br/&gt;Center for Excellence in Logistics and Distribution (CELDi) &lt;br/&gt;Proposal #1332047, 1332007, 1331997, 1331989 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal seeks funding for the Center for Excellence in Logistics and Distribution (CELDi) located at Virginia Tech, Clemson University, the University of California-Berkeley, and the University of Arkansas. Funding Requests for Fundamental Research are authorized by an NSF approved solicitation, NSF 11-570. The solicitation invites I/UCRCs to submit proposals for support of industry-defined fundamental research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Physical Internet (PI) is envisioned as a transformative, open, global, intermodal logistics system that utilizes standard, modular, reusable containers, real-time identification, and routing through shared logistics facilities. In the proposed research, the PIs focus on two aspects of operations: (1) algorithms for container-level processes so as to build loads in the PI and handle these loads at intermodal interfaces; and (2) algorithms for system-level processes so as to route, schedule and coordinate loads that flow through the PI. CELDi is in a unique position to advance the PI for a sustainable logistics future. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposed research include the potential to dramatically increase the efficiency of freight transportation systems. Direct benefits to member organizations include access to the algorithms and operational insights developed as part of this research. Other direct benefits are likely to result as data from member organizations are used to test the algorithms through insights into their data and potential operational improvements. Member organizations will have early access to the results of the research. Indirect benefits include enhancing the reputation and attractiveness of CELDi as an organization, which is likely to lead to better retention and recruitment of CELDi members.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1331989</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rmeller@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/03/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chase</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rainwater</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cer@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
      <CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7609</Code>
      <Text>IUCRC FUNDAMENTAL RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7609</Code>
      <Text>IUCRC FUNDAMENTAL RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8043</Code>
      <Text>System Design and Simulation</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
