<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CyberSEES: Type 1: A Pilot Study on Cognitive Acoustic Underwater Networks (CAUNet) for Sustainable Ocean Monitoring and Exploration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Environmental awareness is a key to sustainable ocean monitoring and exploration. To meet the ever growing requirements of the ocean monitoring and exploration applications, and to preserve a sustainable blue ocean for next generations, a cognitive acoustic underwater network (CAUNet) that is aware of the coexistence of multiple underwater acoustic systems will be designed. The project goals include investigating acoustic spectrum usage via data collection and analysis, designing algorithms, software and hardware for acoustic spectrum sensing and spectrum management, and evaluating the feasibility and performance of the proposed work via simulations, and lab and field experiments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will make significant contributions to the underwater network research community by improving the efficiency of UANs while making them more environmentally friendly. The research activities in this project also provide a rich environment and platform that can facilitate educating and training students from high school to graduate level and inspire students in underrepresented groups to pursue research in science and engineering. Moreover, this project will motivate and enable a wide range of research and outreach activities within the underwater communications, networking, engineering, and marine science communities, and promote progress towards practical solutions in diverse aquatic applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1331851</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pengzheng@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7231</Code>
      <Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8060</Code>
      <Text>SEES Unsolicited</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
