<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Control of Reconfigurable Microgrids with Significant Renewable Power Sources</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research project is to develop a modeling and control framework to support a reconfigurable topology for electrical power microgrids that includes distributed sources or loads such as wind turbines, micro generators, and plug-in electric vehicles. The system ensures stable and efficient operation. The topology uses a decentralized optimal control framework to maximize efficiency with minimal communication among the microgrid components; a a way to assess stability of the microgrid as components such as wind turbines switch on and off; and a scalable, low-order modeling approach for the model-based control framework.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will support the adoption of reconfigurable microgrids as one way to increase plug-in vehicles and renewable resources in the energy portfolio of the future. Also, this research is developing fundamental knowledge on decentralized optimal control, stability in mode-switching systems, and modeling and identification have wide application beyond electrical grids, such as autonomous robotic swarms and large scale computer networks. The research results will be disseminated widely to the scientific community through publications; to graduate and undergraduate students through new courses and course modules; to over 40 industry partners through workshops, seminars, and short courses; to high school students and teachers through summer camps; and to K-12 students through two museum exhibits. The activities of this award will also provide underrepresented minorities with opportunities to participate in engineering research in both graduate and undergraduate level.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1334698</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dongmei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dmchen@me.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1632</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>030E</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>031E</Code>
      <Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>034E</Code>
      <Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
