<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Arctic Observing Summit 2013 US Coordination and Support for Participants</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34919</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Neil R. Swanberg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is for support for U.S. participation in the Arctic Observing Summit 2013 (AOS 2013). The AOS 2013 is the first in a planned series of high-level, biennial international Arctic observing summits. The AOS is led by the International Study for Arctic Change (ISAC) as part of the implementation of the observing change component of the ISAC Science Plan. It is a task of the Arctic Council's Sustaining Arctic Observing Networks (SAON) initiative and as such is also part of the broader SAON implementation process, which is led by the Arctic Council jointly with the International Arctic Science Committee (IASC), and the World Meteorological Organization (WMO). Support is sought for U.S. participant costs, and specifically for the participation of early career scientists and representatives of Alaska Native organizations and communities engaged in observing activities or requiring observational information. Exposure to the international community engaged in the diverse aspects of arctic observing and the process by which coordination and collaboration across multiple scientific and other boundaries will benefit early career scholars who will ultimately be responsible for creating the synergies and collaborations needed for the future. The participation of Alaska Native groups will ensure that the AOS outcomes reflect their observing needs and will serve to build the community of partners to advance arctic observing over the coming years.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337039</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schlosser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schlosser@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/22/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maribeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>msmurray@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/22/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5293</Code>
      <Text>AON IMPLEMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
