<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Nanotopography Capability at the University of Washington Microfabrication Facility</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1030000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eyad Abed</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The main objective of this proposal is to acquire an I-line stepper tool for high-throughput lithography with 350 nm feature resolution bridging the gap between electron-beam lithography and contact lithography. Nano-imprint and photolithography are usually done in separate machines and this proposal is to acquire an integrated machine that can do both simultaneously resulting in superior alignment. Numerous exciting projects will benefit from the acquisition of this equipment. Contact guidance studies using nanotopography, creating nanorachets for microfluidics, nanoelectrodes for energy, plasmonics are all high quality projects that will benefit from this acquisition. Overall, the projects are interesting and potentially transformative. The projects are cohesive and will rely on the stepper tool, it is well written and well organized proposal in all aspects. The PIs have the required expertise for use of this instrument in current and future research projects. The proposed tool will have a broad impact in research and education. The combination of projects including junior faculty with senior faculty is unique and well thought of. The acquisition of this tool will benefit the academic researchers and overall users for the UW NNIN node. The outreach efforts are broad and well described including involvement of students from community colleges, high schools and underrepresented minorities. The cleanroom facilities are already funded by NNIN, hence having this tool in the facility not only will serve a larger group of researchers, but also will be maintained well. More than100 academic users and about 40 industrial users are expected to use the tool.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337840</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bohringer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>karl@ee.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Posner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jposner@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaodong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xuxd@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kai-Mei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kaimeifu@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deok-Ho</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>deokho@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>105E</Code>
      <Text>RF/Microwave &amp; mm-wave tech</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
