<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Variable-Property Material Synthesizing Instrument</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>349200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) grant supports acquisition of a state-of-the-art variable-property material synthesizing instrument (OBJET Connex500) for leading-edge research on functionally-graded material systems at Texas A&amp;M University-Kingsville (TAMUK). The instrument directly combines two component materials in specific concentrations and structures to design novel variable-property material systems. With direct fabrication, complex systems can be fabricated in a single build process, eliminating design restrictions and saving energy. The instrumentation will advance fundamental research on the design of novel variable-property material systems, enabling the development of compliant mechanisms and smart structures, and formats for organic semiconductors, superconductors, and other organic electronic devices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The instrumentation will support research by a multidisciplinary team and by TAMUK undergraduate students. Underrepresented graduate and undergraduate Hispanic students will be given access to enhanced curriculum and the state-of-the-art instrumentation; this experience will give them unique skills and broader career options. The instrumentation will be featured in summer outreach programs and will be made available to regional educational institutions. The instrumentation will spur enhanced research competitiveness and innovation in South Texas-an economically challenged area. Local industry will gain access through the Javelina Innovation Center, which was established to aid local industry in simulating, designing, and manufacturing novel products in a low-cost manner.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337620</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xiaoliu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kfxc000@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hong.zhou@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Larry.Peel@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amit</FirstName>
      <LastName>Verma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amit.verma@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Reza</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nekovei</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rnekovei@tamuk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M University-Kingsville</Name>
      <CityName>Kingsville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>783638202</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3615933344</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Campus Box 201</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
