<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Field-Emission Scanning Electron Microscope to Catalyze Campus-Wide Research in Bio/Nano and Advanced Energy Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>529387</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) program award provides funding for acquisition of an advanced analytical field-emission scanning electron microscope (SEM) to enhance the research, education, and training capabilities at Utah State University (USU). The new equipment replaces an existing imaging device at the institution as the primary research device, and provides higher resolution for a variety of research applications as well as the ability for remote use by researchers and students at campuses across the state. At present, the only electron microscopy service at USU is a 22-year-old analog SEM with limited imaging capabilities and resolution. The new microscope provides advanced technical capabilities to USU's researchers that currently are not available at the institution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The acquisition of the microscope will provide a transformative improvement in the materials characterization infrastructure at USU, increase the quality and productivity of faculty research, and directly impact funded research in processing and manufacturing of biomaterials, nanomaterials, and energy materials for a number of researchers. Specifically, the enabled research includes characterizing nanoparticles for antimicrobial applications and biofuel production, bioplastics, and food microstructures; nanoscale-composition analysis for nanotubes, nanowires, nanoporous materials, nuclear materials, and charging effects in insulators; and microscale-composition analysis for geothermal and earthquake studies, soil, and leaf morphology correlated to climate. Overall, the equipment will be integrated into the USU Microscopy Core Facility that serves the research needs of faculty from at least six departments in three colleges of the university. The microscope also will be used extensively for educational outreach and training at USU and will be integrated into a new course on electron microscopy to help train students using the new microscope. Approximately 60 graduate and undergraduate students are expected to utilize this microscope in their research. Additionally, the microscope's remote operations will allow the microscope to be used for classes and research at USU branch campuses across the state of Utah. Additionally, K-12 students visiting the USU campus will take advantage of the unique capabilities of the instruments during visits to the university.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337932</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Britt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.britt@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shervais</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.shervais@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tsung-Cheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tc.shen@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ban</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>heng.ban@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tsung-Cheng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tc.shen@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/20/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Astrid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jacobson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>astrid.jacobson@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leijun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leijun.li@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/20/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Utah State University</Name>
      <CityName>Logan</CityName>
      <ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
