<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 2013 International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA-40)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Hong Jiang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA) is a premier forum for presenting, discussing&lt;br/&gt;and debating new and innovative architectural ideas and techniques for advanced computing and&lt;br/&gt;communication systems. This symposium brings together researchers in fields related to processor architecture,&lt;br/&gt;compilers, chips, and systems. This proposal aims to support this highly regarded conference by&lt;br/&gt;obtaining travel support for students in order to defray the costs of attending and participating in the ISCA&lt;br/&gt;conference in June, 2013 in Tel Aviv, Israel. Priority will be given to US&lt;br/&gt;citizens and permanent residents, students from under-represented groups, and students&lt;br/&gt;that will be presenting their research at ISCA or its joint workshops. &lt;br/&gt;The ISCA conference will be strengthened as a&lt;br/&gt;result of the greater attendance that this travel support will enable. Students receiving travel&lt;br/&gt;support will personally benefit from the opportunity to interact with peers and experts, as well as establish&lt;br/&gt;connections that will help their professional careers.&lt;br/&gt;More broadly, we expect additional indirect impacts. First, we plan to widely advertise the available&lt;br/&gt;support in order to attract women and under-represented minority groups (through postings on computer&lt;br/&gt;architecture web-sites and mailing lists). Second, by focusing on students, the grant will help foster the&lt;br/&gt;mentoring of subsequent generations of computer architects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337380</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rajeev</FirstName>
      <LastName>Balasubramonian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rajeev@cs.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
