<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Meeting Proposal: C. elegans and other nematodes, bridging the divide. Los Angeles June 26-30th, 2013.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14284</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Liliana Jaso-Friedmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nematodes (roundworms) are the most abundant multicellular animals on earth, colonizing virtually every terrestrial, marine and freshwater habitat. While the nematode laboratory model C. elegans is the focus of intense, technically sophisticated research, much less is known about other nematodes, despite their biological importance. Of particular significance are parasitic nematodes, which comprise more than half of the estimated 28,000 nematode species; these parasites have important effects on the biology of their plant and animal hosts, threatening agricultural crops, and causing debilitating human diseases that affect over a billion people worldwide. By promoting interactions and collaborations between C. elegans researchers and investigators of parasitic nematodes, this project will increase awareness among C. elegans scientists of the issues and problems that parasitic nematode researchers face, and will pave the way for application of the powerful molecular and cell techniques developed in C. elegans research to investigations of parasitic nematodes. The planned symposium at the International C. elegans Meeting (Los Angeles June 26-30th, 2013) will provide an exceptional opportunity to reach the majority of C. elegans researchers. Six internationally recognized experts on plant, animal and human parasitic nematodes will speak on the life history and unique biology of parasitic species and on the outstanding issues in their field. In addition to formal education of the C. elegans community, this session will provide time for researchers in the two communities to interact more informally as well. The symposium aims to stimulate C. elegans researchers to think about problems facing the study and control of parasitic nematodes and to apply their expertise toward solving these problems. This session will be particularly valuable for undergraduate and graduate students and post-docs by exposing them to new possible career paths. Funds will also be provided for under-represented minority graduate students to attend the session.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337108</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sullivan@biology.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Strome</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>strome@biology.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barton</FirstName>
      <LastName>Slatko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>slatko@neb.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chalfie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mc21@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
