<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a BioMark HD System for single-cell genomics research.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>370570</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher Sanford</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An award is made to The University of Texas at San Antonio (UTSA) to purchase the BioMark HD/C1 System (Fluidigm), a multi-mode instrument for high-throughput single-cell sample preparation, real-time PCR (qPCR), end-point PCR, and digital PCR that enables gene expression analyses (including on single cells), genotyping and absolute copy number determination. This instrument addresses a major limitation of contemporary biological research by permitting molecular experiments at the level of individual cells, which may differ within a population. By permitting single-cell analyses, this instrument enables novel experiments that would otherwise be essentially impossible to pursue. The BioMark HD/C1 system combines high-throughput nanofluidics with quantitative PCR to measure the expression of hundreds of genes or gene sequence variations in hundreds of individual cells or samples in just a few hours. Investigators Brian Hermann, Rena Bizios, J. Aaron Cassill, Garry Sunter and colleagues from multiple departments (Biology, Chemistry, Biomedical Engineering) within two colleges (Sciences, Engineering) at UTSA and around San Antonio will utilize this unique instrument to investigate basic biological questions in broad topic areas including germ cell biology, neurobiology, cellular biophysics, plant virus host defense, plant herbivore defense, and insect olfaction. This instrument will be established as a core resource for research and research training at UTSA and the San Antonio area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Acquisition of the BioMark HD/C1 System at UTSA through the Major Research Instrumentation program will provide scientists and students at all levels (high-school, undergraduate and graduate students) with access to a cutting-edge scientific instrument for research and training. This instrumentation will enhance the research environment at UTSA and provide opportunities for training students and postdoctoral fellows to become productive researchers. Since UTSA is a designated Hispanic-serving institution, this award will broaden participation of underrepresented groups at all levels. Indeed, the BioMark HD/C1 system will be utilized by students in several educational programs at UTSA that are specifically designed to attract and retain students from underrepresented groups to scientific research and promote their interest in pursuing research careers. This instrument will provide trainees with relevant experience using cutting edge technology, which will pique their interest in research and maximize their marketability for careers in academic and industrial science. Training in the use of the BioMark HD/C1 instrument will also be integrated with existing teaching and outreach programs to promote use of high-tech instrumentation in a manner that integrates training with real-world experimentation and discovery.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1337513</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Garry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sunter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>garry.sunter@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hermann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brian.hermann@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bizios</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rena.bizios@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Aaron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cassill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aaron.cassill@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
      <CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
