<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Big Data Benchmarking: THE BIGDATA TOP100 LIST</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>56200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Chadduck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>OCI 1338373&lt;br/&gt;Chaitanya Baru - U. of California at San Diego&lt;br/&gt;Workshop on Big Data Benchmarking: The BigData Top 100 List&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Workshop series on Big Data Benchmarking (WBDB) was created in 2012 by the Center for Large-scale Data Systems Research (CLDS) at the San Diego Supercomputer Center, UC San Diego to foster a community activity in the area of benchmarking of big data systems. The first workshop was held in May 2012 in San Jose, California and was sponsored by the National Science Foundation along with a few industry sponsors. Subsequent meetings followed, and a second workshop held in December 2012 in Pune, India. The meetings and the second workshop substantiated the initial ideas for a big data benchmark leading to the concept of the BigData Top100 List for ranking big data systems according to performance on a specified big data workload, while also recording and reporting system efficiency, for example, in terms of price/performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This current action is for the Third Workshop on Big Data Benchmarking workshop to be held on July 16-17, 2013 in Xi'an, China. The local hosts for this meeting will be the Xi'an University of Posts and Telecommunications and the Shanxi HPC Center. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: While a mature transaction processing and data management industry has been established over the last two decades based primarily on relational database (RDBMS) technologies, the emergence of the Big Data phenomenon characterized by the so-called "3Vs" - volume, velocity, and variety) of data along with the need for agile development of data-driven applications, has introduced a new set of challenges. A variety of new techniques and technologies have emerged to address these challenges. A big data benchmark could, indeed, be specified with the following components: (i) a definition for a synthetic benchmark dataset with a well-defined and well-specified data generation procedure; (ii) a representative workload for big data applications; and (iii) a set of metrics, run rules and full disclosure reports for fair comparisons among technologies and platforms. These results would then form the basis of the BigData Top100 List.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The first two WBDB meetings have had a total of about 100 (invited) attendees from about 60 different organizations from industry and academia. The BigData Top100 List initiative was officially introduced at a dedicated session at the Strata Conference in Santa Clara, on February 28th, 2013. This is a community effort and the benchmark will be released via the bigdatatop100.org website.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1338373</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Choonhan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Youn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cyoun@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chaitanya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baru</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baru@sdsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/18/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7726</Code>
      <Text>DATANET</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
