<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nebraska-Rouen Collaborations: Hyperbranched Polar Polymers as Solid Lubricants</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>53232</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Graham M. Harrison</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will address a very fundamental component in materials processing and manufacturing: grafting polar polymers to surfaces of a solid nanomaterial to create metal-organic frameworks (MOFs). This project will bring together three research groups with highly specialized expertise in an interdisciplinary approach to investigate surface corrosion, defect repair, and polymer binding on MOFs, as well as examine the kinetics of the grafting process. The goal is to develop solid lubricants which are essential in manufacturing processes and in applications of materials in highly demanding environments, such as long-term biomedical implants. This approach, which has never been attempted, would be a significant contribution to the field of materials research into solid lubricants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research into new processes to develop new properties of materials is critical to creating uses for materials in applications as varied as biomedical devices and automotive manufacturing. Solid lubricants would be invaluable applications in automotive manufacture where there are stringent standards for wear protection. The collaboration will also introduce US students and postdocs at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln to the facilities and expertise available at the Universite de Rouen and provide valuable training to enable the US to develop a globally competitive science workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1338988</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Li</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ltan4@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jiantao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Guo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jguo4@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5918</Code>
      <Text>FRANCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
