<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics for English Language Learners (STEMELL) Program at Lehman College</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1199603</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Teri Murphy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project is preparing science and mathematics teachers for high-need middle and high schools by offering extensive support at both undergraduate and graduate levels with a special focus on teaching English language learners (ELLs) in mainstream mathematics and science classrooms. Over the five-year project, the STEMELL Program is admitting three cohorts of 8 pre-service secondary mathematics and science teachers each, who progress through a three-year program: 2014-17, 2015-18 and 2016-19. Students are recruited from Lehman College's undergraduate population of mathematics or science majors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ELLs represent a growing population in U.S. schools. Nationally, estimates are that by the year 2030, 40% of the school-aged population will consist of ELLs. In New York City (NYC), 42.2% of students speak a language other than English at home with some classrooms consisting of 100% ELLs or former ELLs, who still have issues with the development of language and content. The percentage of students scoring below the basic level in mathematics and reading is higher among ELL students than among non-ELL students in grades 4 and 8. Presently, there are no expectations regarding teacher preparedness for providing instruction in classrooms for English language learners. Most teachers graduate with a teaching certification but do not have any substantive training or experience in working effectively with ELLs in mainstream classrooms. The preparation of mathematics and science teachers who can provide effective instruction in these content areas to meet the ELLs classroom needs is therefore crucial in addressing these issues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Preparing STEMELL pre-service Noyce teachers to meet the challenges of urban teaching in high-need schools, each cohort progresses through a 5 year BA/MA teacher preparation program. Beginning in the junior year as scholars, the sequence leads to a BA in mathematics or science, NYS Initial Certification to teach mathematics or science in grades 7-12 and a Master's degree in Science of Education. The program also offers additional advanced courses required for an extension in TESOL or bilingual education along with internships during the first two years, collaboration with middle and high school mathematics, science and TESOL teachers for the first two years, and full mentoring in the third year during the Noyce Scholars' first year of teaching in the NYC public schools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1339981</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Serigne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gningue</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sgningue@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gillian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bayne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gillian.bayne@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jitianu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>andrei.jitianu@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liesl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Liesl.Jones@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>05/19/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dellicarpini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>MARGO.DELLICARPINI@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/25/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Orlando</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alonso</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ORLANDO.ALONSO@LEHMAN.CUNY.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sunyata</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Sunyata.Smith@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Herbert H. Lehman College</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104681589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7189608107</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>250 Bedford Park Blvd West</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
