<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Mavric: Commercialization of Analog-Digital Configurable ICs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Researchers have developed large-scale Field Programmable Analog Arrays (FPAA) that enable products requiring ultra-low-power computation and computing within a programmable and configurable framework. This project plans to use the FPAA ICs to demonstrate core signal processing functionality for widespread use and begin the process of iterating and getting feedback regarding performance, power levels and features.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The potential impact from the FPAA ICs could empower a range of electronic devices and require a factor of 1000 times less power consumption than current digital approaches. This approach could enable a wide-spread change in low-power electronics. An additional impact from this technology will create an ecosystem for additional technological growth, in a range of applications spaces, empowered by programmable and configurable analog ICs eliminating the need for highly costly process of custom analog IC design, fabrication, and testing. This approach enables a range of new approaches to be realized, many applications not even envisioned.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1339041</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hasler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jennifer.hasler@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
