<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Pipeline to Teacher Preparation in Chemistry and Physics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1198577</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen B. Bergin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Pipeline to Teacher Preparation in Chemistry and Physics is a collaborative project between the Chemistry and Biochemistry Department, Biology and Physics Department, and Education Student Services at Kennesaw State University (KSU) to recruit 25 high school and early college STEM majors into secondary chemistry and physics programs with a teacher certification option. Support is provided through an induction program to provide a seamless transition into the students' new teaching career in a high-needs Georgia school district. Previous Noyce projects at Kennesaw State University (KSU) have developed targeted recruitment plans for Masters of Arts in Teaching Chemistry and Physics Education since 2008. These projects have highlighted the importance of developing strategic and deliberate recruitment efforts to attract highly competent chemistry and physics students who are close to, or have already graduated, into chemistry and physics certification programs. These projects also provide a general framework for the development of recruitment plans that target other populations. The Noyce project offers stipends to college-bound high school juniors and seniors and KSU freshman and sophomores who participate and lead a week-long science summer camp to engage in them in the science education community of practice and begin to build their teacher identity. Once accepted into the education program, eligible students receive up to a 2-year scholarship to complete their certification coursework and field experiences. This project is designed to engage students early on in educational experiences and keep them progressing at a rate that will allow them to graduate in four years. The specific objectives of this project are to: 1). develop customized recruitment strategies to attract academically strong and culturally diverse students to the B.S. Chemistry and Physics Education program at KSU from these two sources, 2). offer stipends to high school students and KSU freshmen and sophomores who participate in a week-long science summer camp intended to build their teacher identity, 3). provide 25 2-year scholarships to students to participate in the B.S. Chemistry or Physics Education program, and to assist with placement in high school chemistry, physics, and physical science teaching positions and 4). implement a teacher induction program to provide support to students graduating from these programs to enable them to successfully make the transition into the teaching workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is not only producing 25 highly qualified chemistry and physics teachers, but also serves to disseminate best practices for attracting early career deciders to these fields of education. The strategies and activities developed by this project serve as a framework for recruitment at other institutions. In turn, this knowledge is leading to a significant increase in the number of highly qualified chemistry and physics teachers nationwide.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1340019</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rushton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gregory.rushton@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rosengrant</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rosengrant@usfsp.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Meltem</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alemdar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>meltem.alemdar@ceismc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/04/2017</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charlease</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kelly-Jackson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ckellyja@kennesaw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dean</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdean28@kennesaw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maurice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mwilson1@kennesaw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/11/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kennesaw State University Research and Service Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Kennesaw</CityName>
      <ZipCode>301445591</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4705786381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Chastain Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
