<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CC-NIE Networking Infrastructure: High Speed Science DMZ @ Johns Hopkins for Data Intensive Computing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>494874</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This cyberinfrastucture project is focused on creating an advanced dedicated research network that will facilitate the transfer of large scientific datasets while eliminating the barriers of traditional packet based inspection technologies. The goal of this project is threefold: 1) to establish a robust research oriented Science DMZ that simplifies the network perimeter, 2) to expand high-speed connectivity to internal research groups throughout the institution, and 3) to connect to a newly constructed High Performance Research Computing Facility (HPRCF) opening in 2014.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ability to quickly transfer large scientific data sets from origination to destination is of paramount importance. The principal goal of this project will be the creation of a new network perimeter to significantly increase the transfer rates of large scale datasets. With network throughput speeds reaching 100G, traditional firewall technologies relying on packet based inspection introduce too much latency and need to be eliminated. The Science DMZ will embrace newer network protocols, such as Virtual Device Contexts and multi-packet layer switching to enable faster convergence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;JHU is at the center of several data-intensive activities that are transforming whole communities across the country. The archive of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey, the world's most used astronomy facility, is hosted at JHU, and our 100TB public turbulence database is largely responsible for a new access paradigm to numerical simulations. The new HPRCF will create new collaborations between JHU and University of Maryland scientists. This project will transform the JHU backbone and bring high-speed connectivity to a much broader community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1340754</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bagger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bagger@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zarriello</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>deanz@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sreel@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zeger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sz@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8080</Code>
      <Text>Campus Cyberinfrastrc (CC-NIE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
