<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AHSS: Development of Novel Finite Element Simulation Tools that Implement Crystal Plasticity Constitutive Theories Using an Efficient Spectral Framework</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/31/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>157014</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Siegmund</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Predictive tools used in simulating wrought alloy manufacturing processes and final product performance predominantly employ phenomenological constitutive theories. Such models are proving inadequate for various applications. On the other hand, physics based crystal plasticity models have enjoyed remarkable success in predicting anisotropic mechanical response and the concurrent evolution of the underlying crystallographic texture in finite plastic deformation of several polycrystalline metals. However, these tools are extremely computationally expensive. It is proposed to develop spectral crystal plasticity based finite element tools for simulating deformation processing operations and mechanical performance of Advanced High Strength Steels (AHSS) with computational times that are comparable to the tools currently used by the industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;AHSS represent a broad class of steels with dramatic improvements in properties over traditional steels. The proposed collaboration with two major industries will ensure that the tools developed will be rapidly adopted into the commercial environment. The proposed interdisciplinary research cuts across materials science, mechanical engineering and applied mathematics and will contribute significantly to the development of skilled human resources in critical science and technology fields. Furthermore, funding for this proposal will positively impact the initiatives already underway at Drexel University to ensure inclusion of traditionally under-represented minorities and women in engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1341888</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Surya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kalidindi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>surya.kalidindi@me.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/03/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
