<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US Bahrain Cooperative Research-CNIC: Intelligent Video Surveillance Systems for Hajjrites</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36649</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Lyons</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1341126&lt;br/&gt;Ahmed Abdelgawad&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support research by Dr. Ahmed Abdelgawad, Department of Engineering and Technology at Central Michigan University and Dr. Yasser Ismail, University of Bahrain. They plan to use surveillance system data taken during the pilgrimage in Mecca (the Hajj) as a unique occasion where some 2-3 million people gather for 4 days, and with the traffic that results as they move on foot or by car in prescribed paths. The research goal is to speed the encoding process of video signals that are transmitted from cameras to the monitoring room. The work will be in two phases: the simulation to study, investigate, and propose new algorithms for video encoding; and the hardware implementation phase which will focus on developing low power, high speed and efficient monitoring cameras that can be used for monitoring activities in Hajj traffic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The PIs plan to address some cutting edge problems in high-speed video encoding. This project can advance the science of signal processing by suggesting new motion estimation algorithms for real-time applications. Due to the logistical and time-consuming challenges of establishing a real time video streaming test bed, much of the current algorithms design work has relied on analytical or simulation models. This has significantly limited the development of the video surveillance systems. This project will focus on the design and test of a fully integrated infrastructure. It will enable novel and potentially transformative network research in signal processing. In addition the project is designed to support on-going research and experimentation in other areas such as environmental monitoring, autonomous vehicle, and robot applications. The PIs have some very promising results already in motion estimation. They will first formalize the improved motion estimation algorithms and then proceed to a hardware prototype implementation. The latter part will seek to validate the algorithms in realistic settings. The PI plans to test his design using large crowd-based video datasets, i.e., as obtained from video surveillance during the Hajj. This is a very realistic environment to evaluate the work and will have applicability to other surveillance settings as well. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: A major goal is to produce engineers that have the education and research expertise, this will help to infuse education with the excitement of discovery and enrich research through the diversity of learning perspectives. This will be accomplished, in part, through the design of an inter-disciplinary project based course (i.e., signal processing, embedded systems, and image processing). With international collaboration, the PI will orient emerging undergraduate and graduate students toward research in signal processing, open up new scientific directions, encourage new ideas, and facilitate knowledge transfer to society. The PI who is a new faculty is planning to use research work to develop new courses, and will partner with on-going and successful university student recruitment programs. The hands-on experience combined with theoretical principles will be a very attractive program to the innovative student and under-represented groups. The project will help to have demonstrations at local K-12 schools and youth groups. The PI will give presentations to Society of Women Engineers (SWE) to encourage women to participate in his research field. The outcome of this project will be available through a website. The project will identify new real time applications, which will benefit the society especially for security.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1341126</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ahmed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abdelgawad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abdel1a@cmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Central Michigan University</Name>
      <CityName>Mount Pleasant</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488590001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9897746777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research &amp; Graduate St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
