<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ACM BCB 2013: Conference on Bioinformatics and Computational Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal seeks funding for travel support for students to participate in the ACM BCB (Bioinformatics and Computational Biology) Conference in September 2013 in Washington D.C. The ACM-BCB is expected to be a premier forum in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology. The conference will host three keynote sessions, research sessions, session-specific invited speakers, workshops, tutorials, panel discussion, and poster sessions. Special activities such as a doctoral consortium and student poster session will be specifically targeted for the students. The ACM-BCB conference has been successful in building a bioinformatics and computational biology community through the newly established ACM Special Interest Group in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology (SIGBioinformatics). The proposed grant will broaden the participation graduate students and help develop the next generation of researchers and educators in the computer science, biological science, biomedical science and other related areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1341410</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sridhar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hannenhalli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sridhar@umiacs.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
