<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium on Cognitive Systems and Discovery Informatics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>13000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project provides support for Symposium on Discovery Informatics and Cognitive Systems. Discovery informatics aims to develop computational systems that support the scientific enterprise. Cognitive systems aims to develop computational artifacts that exhibit the broad range of intelligent behavior found in humans. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium brings together researchers who approach discovery informatics from a variety of perspectives but who share an interest in system-level approaches and the role of high level cognition in science. It focuses on a specific set of challenges at the intersection of cognitive systems and discovery informatics. The participants' interactions should lead to new insights and new collaborations in this emerging area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The new field of discovery informatics has the potential to not only accelerate but also advance the frontiers of the scientific enterprise by automating processes that researchers currently carry out manually. This symposim aims to clarify these processes and share insights with the broader community. The symposium fills a critical need in terms of building a vibrant community of interdisciplinary researchers in discovery informatics. It contributes to education and training of graduate students, and broadening participation of underrepresented groups in STEM areas that are critical to multiple NSF initiatives e.g., Big Data Science and Engineering, Computation and Data Enabled Science and Engineering, among others.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1342104</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pat</FirstName>
      <LastName>Langley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pat.langley@sv.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
