<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AIR Option 1: Technology Translation - Buckled Stiff Thin Films on Soft Substrates for High-Resolution Strain Sensing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>165986</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating the science of buckled stiff thin films on soft substrates as strain sensors to fill the technology gap in the strain measurement area to simultaneously realize both high spatial resolution and high sensitivity strain mapping. The translated science has the following unique features: well-defined nanoscale periodicity as a function of mechanical strain and material properties, easiness of fabrication, and tunability of 1D and 2D patterns that provides exemplary science to improve the performance of strain sensors and reduce the cost of fabrication when compared to the leading competing technologies, such as digital image correlation (DIC), micro-Moiré, and scanning electron microscope DIC techniques in this market space. The project accomplishes this goal by further optimizing the buckling patterns, achieving large scan area with a fast scan rate, and automated sample scanning and data acquisition resulting in a working prototype. The partnership engages Intel Corporation to provide guidance in the definition of industrial needs from the perspectives of microelectronic packaging, as well as through other forms, such as partial financial support and project mentoring as they pertain to the potential to translate the science along a path that may result in a competitive commercial reality. The potential economic impact is expected to be $85M in the next 10 years of commercialization, which will contribute to the U.S. competitiveness in the strain measurement area that have been heavily used in structural testing and electronic packaging applications. The societal impact, long term, will be the development of an innovative strain sensor as a new member in the family of strain measurement, which routinely impacts many different fields, ranging from structures, electronics, and health. The PIs will also integrate education, particularly professional development and entrepreneurship for students for the next-generation leaders in technical transfer.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1343474</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hongbin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hongbin.yu@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hanqing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jiang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hanqing.jiang@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
