<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>INSPIRE Track 1: Multifunctional Interfaces for Responsive Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1074044</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This INSPIRE award by the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials Research to the State University of New York Stony Brook is in developing novel materials transport systems, and a general method for creating (and tuning the properties of) aqueous nanocluster dispersions of interest for technologies that range from drug delivery to biofuel production, as well as a theoretical understanding of the mechanism for cluster formation and stability. This award is cofunded by the Biomaterials and the Polymer programs in the Division of Materials Research and International Science and Engineering program in the Office of International and Integrative Activities. In addition, the following programs in the Engineering Directorate - Biomedical Engineering, Particulate and Multiphase Processes and Interfacial Processes and Thermodynamics - all in the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems are also cofunding this award. The primary focus of this project is fundamental science approaches in developing a synthetic structure that has all the properties of its biological counterpart that can respond in a controlled manner to an external stimulus, by using synthetic polymer-peptide constructs on a patterned surface, manipulated by electric fields to achieve spatial control of cell migration and differentiation. These responsive surfaces would have a clear impact for the development of surfaces that can template biomineralization and scaffolds that direct the outcome of embryogenesis. This project would lead to a new interdisciplinary and potentially transformative research at the interface of colloid and interface science, multiscale modeling and statistical mechanics, biophysical characterization, materials sciences, drug delivery, interfacial processes, molecular engineering, multiphase processing and nanotechnology. Using an iterative process, theoretical models will be continuously probed and refined, and this would enable obtaining the optimal structures in designing the cell experiments using stem cells, human epithelial and endothelial cells. Significant advances could be expected as the result of this investment in inter- and multi-disciplinary research at the intersection of the engineering and material sciences, and synthetic biology that focus on advancing the fundamental experimental and theoretical answers to important fundamental questions about the possibility of forming aqueous dispersions of equilibrium nanoclusters with tunable size, shape and dissociation properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader technological impact of this project is in developing a model fundamental process of organ development, tissue organization, stem cell differentiation, and designing and synthesizing novel polymeric and dynamic surfaces with tailored properties that could have many industrial applications, if the project is successful. With respect to educational and outreach activities, the project is for the seamless integration of research and education, with a robust mentoring program, where contact with the students is often maintained throughout their educational and professional development. With the proposed model system, students learn by doing, observing, and participating fully in the research efforts from concepts through publications, and are evaluated by metrics for standard research proposals, i.e. innovation, impact, and publication. The planned high school program includes structured activities, which provide the students with the basic skill required for independent research, including statistics modules, data mining, proper reference notation, skills in keeping laboratory notebooks, awareness of intellectual property issues, filing for patents, ethics in education and sciences, and working within a group on environmental questions and awareness, and providing safety training courses in handling and disposal of hazardous chemicals and biological wastes. As part of the International activity, the project plans to initiate collaborations with University of Dortmund, Germany, where the education and outreach models practiced at the SUNY campus will be replicated. In addition, the project plans to expand these outreach activities in Europe and Asia by collaborating with Universities and High Schools in these areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1344267</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Miriam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rafailovich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>miriam.rafailovich@sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ober</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cko3@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dilip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gersappe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dilip.gersappe@sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>marcia</FirstName>
      <LastName>simon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marcia.simon@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria Victoria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fernandez Serra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maria.fernandez-serra@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1415</Code>
      <Text>PARTICULATE &amp;MULTIPHASE PROCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1414</Code>
      <Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8078</Code>
      <Text>INSPIRE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7623</Code>
      <Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7222</Code>
      <Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8653</Code>
      <Text>INSPIRE Track-1 (Creativ)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5936</Code>
      <Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7298</Code>
      <Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>055E</Code>
      <Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>056E</Code>
      <Text>Multiphase flow</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>004E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>017E</Code>
      <Text>Cellular and Tissue Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>138E</Code>
      <Text>Stem cells/regenerative medicine</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>051E</Code>
      <Text>Interfacial trans &amp; thermodynamic</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8614</Code>
      <Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1515</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7623</Code>
      <Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
