<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>INSPIRE Track 1: Imaging Neuronal Network Activity using Voltage-Gated Optical Transitions in Graphene</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Z. Charles Ying</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This INSPIRE award is partially funded by the Electronic and Photonic Materials Program and the Biomaterials Program in the Division of Materials Research in the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences; the Neural Systems Program in the Division of Integrative Organismal Systems in the Directorate for Biological Sciences; the Instrument Development for Biological Research Program in the Division of Biological Infrastructure in the Directorate for Biological Sciences; and the Nano-Biosensing Program in the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems in the Directorate for Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: This research project aims to develop a novel technique to detect electric activities of a neuronal network using voltage-gated optical transitions in graphene. A neuron receives, analyzes and conveys information in the form of electrical signals such as action potentials. The decoding of neural data requires accurate recording of those electrical signals. This project exploits unique electrical and optical properties of graphene to detect electric activities of a neuronal network in a highly parallel and non-invasive manner. It advances scientific understanding in several important fronts, including (1) fundamental understanding of graphene as a unique electronic and optical material for high-sensitivity bio-imaging, (2) interfacing graphene with neuron cells, (3) non-invasive optical detection of action potential, and (4) highly parallel imaging of neuron activity in a neuronal network. This project builds on the complimentary expertise of Professor Wang and Professor Cui on graphene optical spectroscopy and neural electrophysiology, respectively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Description: This project captures the tremendous opportunities provided by graphene for optical imaging of neural network activities, which has a potential to become an important tool in neuroscience. The research requires extensive collaboration and exchange of students between Cui and Wang labs, which provides a unique opportunity for graduate and undergraduate students to be exposed to sciences in different disciplines including biology, engineering, materials science, optics, and physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1344302</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bianxiao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cui</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bcui@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Feng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fengwang76@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1108</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1775</Code>
      <Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7275</Code>
      <Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7623</Code>
      <Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7714</Code>
      <Text>MODULATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8078</Code>
      <Text>INSPIRE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>142E</Code>
      <Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7573</Code>
      <Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8653</Code>
      <Text>INSPIRE Track-1 (Creativ)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
