<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 21st IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15750</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this travel grant is to broaden the audience attending the premier network protocol conference, the IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), and as a result, raise the level of interaction and the potential for new collaborations, new investigations, and higher quality research. Support from the National Science Foundation is requested on behalf of graduate students attending institutions in the United States. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: By supporting graduate students to attend ICNP 2013, this grant will increase the dissemination of the conference research results to a larger and a more diverse audience, which otherwise would not have been able to attend. In so doing, this proposal will contribute to the strength and inclusiveness of the research community, and will lead to the long-term health and vitalization of ICNP. In addition, preference in grant awards to women and under-represented students will hopefully increase the participation among these groups. By advertising to a wide range of colleges and universities, participants from a more diverse set of institutions should be able to attend and benefit from the conference. A broad, as well as diverse population is key to the health of the research community and the discipline. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Conference attendance is a crucial part of the life of a researcher. By creating new opportunities for students, especially those from under-represented groups to attend a high-quality conference, this project will benefit the research community in several ways. The students themselves benefit from the opportunity to meet and interact with many other researchers in a favorable setting, and from seeing research presented that may be related to what they are working on, or may inspire them to try a new direction. The research community benefits from the improvement of the students in the pipeline, and the introduction of new researcher perspectives. Additionally, everybody benefits from increased diversity of participants attending the conference.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1348891</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lijun@cs.uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
