<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AIR Option 1: Technology Translation - Advancing Microbial Fuel Cell Technology for Energy-efficient Wastewater Treatment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>166500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating microbial fuel cell (MFC) technology to address the need for energy-efficient, wastewater treatment technologies. The translated MFC technology has the following unique features: low energy consumption, low sludge production, and energy recovery from waste organic materials in low-strength wastewater. These features provide the advantage of reduced energy requirement and operating expense, when compared to the leading competing activated sludge technology in this market space. The project accomplishes this goal by establishing a transitional-stage MFC system and improving the industry's perception of this technology. The output of this project is a functioning prototype MFC system and identification of the key operating parameters for designing a pilot scale system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The partnership engages potential industrial partners such as Veolia Water and other business partners to provide market guidance about low-strength wastewater treatment system's competitiveness and potential commercialization pathways to introduce new bioelectrochemical treatment systems to translate the transitional-stage MFC technology successfully into a competitive commercial reality. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The potential economic impact is expected to be $700 million in next twenty years, which will contribute to the U.S. competitiveness in sustainable wastewater treatment. The societal impact, long term, will be improved environmental protection, reduced carbon footprint, creation of new business opportunities and jobs, and delivery of qualified talent for both the water/wastewater industry and research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1348424</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhen</FirstName>
      <LastName>He</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhenhe@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8019</Code>
      <Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9231</Code>
      <Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
