<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSBR: Natural History Collections: Critical infrastructure needs in the University of Alaska Museum's bird collection</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>405225</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Alaska represents about 20% of the land area of the United States. It hosts diverse assemblages of New World and Old World birds and an endemic regional avifauna. The Bird Collection at the University of Alaska Museum (UAM) is one of growing national and international importance, representing many preparation types that enhance its utility. Additionally, UAM now houses the 8th-largest vouchered avian tissue collection in the world. This collection is rather heavily used, probably because it contains the best (and only modern) bird specimens from this vast region, and supports research in biodiversity, evolutionary history, management, and conservation. It is also used by artists, birdwatchers, social scientists, ecologists, ecosystem biologists, and toxicologists. Thus, the collection informs studies including assessments of contaminants and stable isotopes, climate change, human artifacts and art, and the historic diets of Alaska Natives. These collections contribute to our ability to address large-scale societal challenges such as health, food, and the environment. The collection's impact is exemplified by its citation in at least 115 publications and 28 student theses in recent years, and its Google Scholar profile (UAM Birds) further shows its high impact. The collection also serves as a focus for training and education at undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral levels, and as a showpiece for public engagement in science. However, the collection is severely overcrowded and is becoming inaccessible as portions are forced into unsorted and substandard housing. Skin, skeleton, and open-wing specimens are inadequately stored, inaccessible to users, and decisions about collection growth now focus on the size of the specimen being considered. These problems severely impact the use of this research resource by its diverse community of users. This project addresses these problems by installing new specimen cabinets on a compactor system and supporting student trainees to work closely with museum staff in rehousing the entire collection and in developing and implementing public outreach activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports infrastructure that is critical to many types of studies requiring avian samples. It will enable the purchase and installation of 92 new specimen cabinets on a new mobile storage system, maximizing the use of space following the museum's expansion and renovation. This cabinet installation will adequately house and make accessible overcrowded specimens and provide room for growth for the next decade. Importantly, this project will train students in collections-based science, thus helping prepare the 21st century STEM workforce. It also engages the public locally and globally in the excitement of biological collections, fostering a better understanding of science and its role in serving society. More information about the UAM Bird Collection can be accessed through our web site at www.uaf.edu/museum/collections/bird/, or here: www.universityofalaskamuseumbirds.org/.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1349419</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Withrow</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jjwithrow@uaf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Winker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kevin.winker@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1197</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
