<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Measuring Search Engines' Ability to Help Users Complete Tasks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>318951</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The purpose of this project is to improve search systems' ability to help users complete tasks. The usefulness of any search engine ultimately depends on how good it is at aiding its users. The systems and the tasks they are used for can be very complicated; small changes in a system's implementation or a task's execution can have major effects on the usefulness of the system, especially over a long lifespan of use by a large base of people. The traditional approach to understanding utility involves the use of test collections, which consist of a collection of documents to be searched, unchanging information needs, and human judgments of the relevance of documents to needs; these components are put into a simple batch process that measures search effectiveness and tests simple statistical hypotheses. While this approach is useful, it often fails to capture variability present in users and tasks: different users often interact with the same system in very different ways, meaning a system that is useful for one user or one task may not be useful for another user or task. Therefore, this project focuses on developing new methods for understanding, estimating, and improving the usefulness of information retrieval (IR) systems that take variability into consideration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The methods investigated in this project are designed to model user interactions with a system to complete a task, including how users determine relevance in context, how they modify their interaction with a system over time, and how different approaches by different users affect the overall system usefulness. The project will produce new types of test collections, evaluation measures, and statistical methods for batch-style systems-based information retrieval evaluation for use by researchers and practitioners in academia and industry. The work will demonstrate how to use these both to improve system utility to a population of users as well as to pose deeper hypotheses about causality in IR system development, thus leading to improvements in IR technology in all domains. Research will be integrated with educational activities for students as well as researchers and practitioners to learn advanced experimental design and analysis. Educational efforts will include tutorials and teaching courses on empirical methods in IR and computer science, methods in use in the wider scientific community, and how the newly developed methods relate to those. Results produced from this project can be found on the project web site (http://ir.cis.udel.edu/IIS-1350799).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1350799</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carterette</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>carteret@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
