<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Modeling and Estimation Methods for Complex Traffic</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cynthia Chen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) program award is to investigate the dynamics of complex traffic. Complex traffic is characterized by heterogeneous vehicle types (e.g. bikes and cars) that vary in size and performance characteristics but share the same infrastructure, and is often controlled by humans. These features are increasingly common in the US during extreme congestion generated by special events, and are pervasive in emerging economies worldwide. This research postulates that advances in mathematical models, informed by and validated with large volumes of traffic data, are key elements to unlock the full understanding of complex traffic. This research focuses on (i) the development of mathematical models of heterogeneous traffic, (ii) modeling and analysis of human-directed traffic and (iii) the development of fast and accurate estimation algorithms to integrate data into city-scale models. Data to validate the models and estimation algorithms are obtained through a newly developed traffic sensing technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this work will support the development of next generation traffic monitoring and management systems. Ultimately, this will help reduce the multibillion-dollar annual cost of congestion during special events in the US. Educational and outreach activities are executed to prepare students with the computing competencies needed to engineer the next generation of computer enhanced infrastructure. This is achieved through new educational initiatives for undergraduate and graduate students that emphasize programming and computational skills applied to problems in civil engineering. Reproducible computational research initiatives within the transportation community will help maximize the potential impact of the research and increase likelihood of adoption by practitioners. Engagement of the broader community on applications of computing in transportation is achieved through outreach and open courseware activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1351717</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Work</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbwork@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/17/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1631</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>029E</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS MGT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>039E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
