<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: A Single Shot Camera Capturing Ultrafast Dynamic Phenomena</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vyacheslav S. Lukin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research is focused on developing new methodologies for ultrafast imaging. In particular, it will contribute to a new development of ultrafast optical and X-ray cameras capable of providing molecular movies with unprecedented spatial and temporal resolution. This will greatly advance ultrafast optical science in single-molecule imaging, light-matter interaction, and inertial confinement fusion. The project also includes educational activities such as developing a summer/winter short course in optical science for undergraduate and graduate students, as well as training one graduate and two undergraduate and/or local high school students per year in the PI's laboratory. The research also includes extensive educational activities for students in individual and collaborative research settings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conventional pump-probe methods can routinely provide ultrafast time-resolved imaging, but they mostly work for highly repeatable events. However, if event-to-event reproducibility is irregular or involves material damage, irreversible chemical reactions, and/or structural phase transition, single-shot detection is a necessity. The project here is to develop a single-shot camera capable of capturing ultrafast dynamic images, simultaneously recording spatial (2-dimensional) and temporal evolutions in a single-shot. Such a camera can capture images at a frame rate of ~50 trillion frames per second, recording 3 ~ 60 frames in a single-shot. Here, the enabling technologies include ultra-broadband spectrum generation, ultrafast optical pulse shaping, and single-shot hyperspectral imaging. This kind of camera can be potentially used in material characterization, biomedical imaging, bio-sensors, and optical and plasma diagnostics. In particular, its application in X-ray free electron lasers will lead to ultrashort electron beam imaging and characterization.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1351455</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ki-Yong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kykim@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1241</Code>
      <Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1242</Code>
      <Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1291</Code>
      <Text>ATOMIC &amp; MOLECULAR DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1062</Code>
      <Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
