<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Catalyzing Polymerization in the Laboratory and Discussion in the Classroom with Artificial Metalloenzymes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>650000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Jared C. Lewis at the University of Chicago is developing artificial metalloenzymes (ArMs) comprised of olefin polymerization catalysts covalently linked to protein scaffolds to control polyolefin structure and function. This research involves the synthesis of cofactors based on known olefin polymerization catalysts, the design and expression of different protein scaffolds, and the bioconjugation of different scaffolds using synthetic cofactors to generate the proposed ArMs. Detailed characterization of ArM structure is being pursued using spectroscopic methods and X-ray crystallography at Argonne National Labs. The ability of these ArMs to catalyze olefin polymerization is being explored, and a combination of rational design and directed evolution is being used to optimize the observed activity and selectivity. Given the importance of polyolefins in every day life, this ArM polymerization catalyst development program is being leveraged to develop teaching modules on chemistry, catalysis, and materials with local middle school (Grade 8) students at the Irene C. Hernandez Middle School for the Advancement of the Sciences (HMS). This will provide HMS students with additional curriculum-relevant discussion of materials chemistry and University of Chicago students with real world opportunities for explaining science and receiving feedback on their teaching. The broader impacts of this work include the potential for discovering new mechanisms to control polymer structure and function, new functional polymers, and unique training opportunities for students and postdocs at the interface of chemistry and protein engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on the development of artificial metalloenzymes comprised of olefin polymerization catalysts covalently linked to protein scaffolds to control polyolefin structure and function. The ability of artificial metalloenzymes to catalyze olefin polymerization is being explored, and a combination of rational design and directed evolution is being used to optimize the observed activity and selectivity. Given the importance of polyolefins in everyday life, this catalyst development program will be leveraged to develop teaching modules on chemistry, catalysis, and materials with local middle school students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1351991</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jared</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lewis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jaredlewis@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6884</Code>
      <Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
