<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: The Role of Mineral Dust in Atmospheric Ice Formation, and its Impacts on Past, Present and Future Climate</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>663463</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric T. DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a CAREER award in which the research component examines the climatic impacts of dust particles due to their role as ice nuclei (IN) in mixed phase clouds (clouds containing both liquid water droplets and ice particles). Mineral dust particles (particles composed of soil minerals, as opposed to soot and biological materials) are the most important IN in the atmosphere, and they can change the radiative properties of clouds by increasing the concentration of cloud ice particles at the expense of supercooled liquid water droplets. Measurement from ice cores suggest that atmospheric dust concentration varies by a factor of three to four between ice ages and interglacials, thus the modulation of clouds by dust could have important climatic consequences. In addition, the anthropogenic contribution to atmospheric dust, through changes in land cover including desertification, is estimated to be as high as 25% of the total burden, so that the role of dust in ice nucleation could lead to anthropogenic influences on climate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first task of the project is to improve the representation of the effect of mineral dust on cloud ice nucleation in atmospheric general circulation models (AGCMs, including the atmospheric component models of coupled climate models). Preliminary work for the project shows that AGCM-simulated clouds are deficient in supercooled liquid water droplets in comparison to satellite observations. Work in this project is based on the hypothesis that this deficiency is due to an exaggeration of the Wegener-Bergeron Findeison (WBF) process, in which cloud ice particles grow at the expense of neighboring supercooled droplets due to the difference in saturation vapor pressure over liquid water and ice. In nature the process is limited by its dependence on small-scale updraft and downdraft motions, which create local atmospheric temperatures which can be unfavorable to the process. Work under this project will develop a parameterization the effect of these small-scale vertical motions, which occur on spatial scales too small to resolve in current AGCMs. Once the parameterization is developed, it will be used to address several questions regarding the effects of dust on clouds and the climatic consequences of these effects, including: What is the net radiative effect of mineral dust perturbations in Earth's atmosphere when dust-ice-cloud effects are taken into account? Have the dust perturbations in past climates significantly impacted those climates via dust effects on ice-containing clouds? Have variations in atmospheric dust loadings over the twentieth century acted as an important climate forcing via effects on ice-containing clouds? Under the current atmospheric mineral dust loading, how sensitive are ice-containing clouds to IN perturbations?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational component of this CAREER proposal is organized in collaboration with the Yale Science Collaborative Hands-On Learning and Research (SCHOLAR) program, which offers a two-week on-campus residential summer learning program in STEM fields. Students in the SCHOLAR program come from the New Haven public high school system, and more than half of the students are from underrepresented groups, in many cases from families in which they would be the first to complete college. Work under this award will develop a module for the SCHOLAR program to introduce students to the fields of atmospheric and climate science, and more specifically to the roles played by aerosols and clouds in shaping weather and climate. The module includes both classroom and laboratory activities, and each summer a group of four students is selected to participate in a field experience at the Storm Peak Laboratory (SPL) in Steamboat Springs Colorado, during the following Spring. The students spend four days at SPL making measurements of aerosols and clouds under the PI's supervision, and make presentations of their research at their schools and at the next SCHOLAR session. In addition, the PI maintains a blog to which students contribute before, during, and after their visit to SPL.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1352417</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Trude</FirstName>
      <LastName>Storelvmo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>trude.storelvmo@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5740</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
