<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: In Situ Optical Probe for Real-time Monitoring of Protein Expression Bioreactors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>909999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruth M. Shuman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project proposes to develop an on-line, probe-based monitor for the real-time, continuous measurement of key analytes in protein expression bioreactors. This directly addresses the need for improved biopharmaceutical production monitoring. The current manual sampling and off-line analysis methods have significant limitations including contamination risks and inherent time delays that severely limit process control. The primary objectives of this effort include the optimization of a high brightness super luminescent diode (SLD) light source and the accompanying optical probe. The SLD provides the light throughput that is required for quantitative in situ measurements, and is perfectly suited for light coupling to an optical-fiber probe. This approach has the added advantage of multiplexing, thereby enabling a single monitor system to simultaneously track analyte concentrations in multiple bioreactors. Both the probe and SLD will be rigorously tested through a series of benchtop and live fermentation evaluations. The ultimate outcome of this effort will be a market-ready, probe-based bioreactor monitor compatible with the major expression platforms in the biopharmaceutical industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this proposed project, if successful, will be to enable the fast-growing biopharmaceutical industry to make game-changing advances in the development and production of critically important drugs. By replacing current manual chemical measurement methods performed during the production of biopharmaceuticals with automated and continuous monitoring, this real-time probe-based monitor will enable needed improvements in process efficiency, lead to reduced development costs, and accelerate the time to market for state-of-the-art drugs. Because of the high value of these medications, and the driving market need, the commercial potential for this real-time monitor is significant with a specific market niche estimated at $510 million in the U.S. alone, residing in the larger global biologics market estimated at $239 billion by 2015. Ultimately, these advantages will translate to lower costs and greater access for consumers to life-changing medicines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1353021</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gibson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>egibson@asl-analytical.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>ASL Analytical, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Coralville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>522414710</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3196652214</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2500 Crosspark Rd., Ste E224</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>169E</Code>
      <Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8038</Code>
      <Text>Biotechnology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8240</Code>
      <Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
