<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The role of selected traits in generating patterns of species diversification in a continent-wide radiation of birds (Thraupidae)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>424918</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Through studying the beak size of Galapagos finches Charles Darwin developed his fundamental idea of natural selection. These finches, and their relatives in the tanager family, continue to inform science today in a project to study why they have been successful in generating so many species. Beak size, feather color, songs, and ecological niche play important roles in the extraordinary diversification of this large American lineage that represents over 4% of bird species. This project will develop a phylogeny and a trait data matrix to compare evolutionary patterns and correlations of these traits with diversification rates. The results will determine whether the factors that drive natural selection in the Galapagos finches are the same factors driving speciation in other tanagers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates the broad question of how biodiversity is generated, which is essential information to the long term success of efforts to conserve biodiversity. This project will support the education and research training of least eight graduate and undergraduate students who will produce theses and publications. In addition, a large number of undergraduates will be involved in the production of online publications on tanagers, which will be published in six languages through Cornell University's Lab of Ornithology. This outreach will benefit researchers, wildlife biologists and conservationists. In addition, project researchers will present public lectures on this work to amateur birders, wildlife biologists, and conservationists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1354006</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Burns</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kburns@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
