<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SG: Evolutionary lag and the effects of clonal structure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149022</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Irwin Forseth</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In rapidly changing environments, organisms must constantly evolve to maintain the ability to survive and reproduce. Rapid environmental change may happen in many ways, such as the emergence of new pathogens and diseases, invasion by competing species, and shifts in temperature or other climatic conditions. Evolution, however, happens much more slowly because genetic mutations are rare and it takes many generations for favorable mutations to become common. This time delay results in a phenomenon called evolutionary lag, which is the difference between a population's ability to survive and reproduce currently and its ability to do so once favorable mutations have become common. This research will examine whether evolutionary lag is influenced by an organism's life history, i.e., how the organism lives and reproduces. The mathematical and computer simulation models developed by this research will generate testable hypotheses about how life history affects evolutionary lag. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Models like those created in this project are crucial for understanding and predicting patterns of evolution and extinction under changing conditions. This understanding can then be used to guide and prioritize conservation efforts. The project is also important because increased mathematical literacy and a better understanding of the linkages between the biological sciences, mathematics, and statistics have been identified as key concerns for both graduate and undergraduate education. Students participating in this work will benefit from a research experience that closely integrates evolutionary biology and mathematics. Recruitment will focus on the involvement of traditionally underrepresented groups and will utilize existing university infrastructure for increasing diversity in scientific training. As part of the outreach efforts of this research, a short video presentation on the interface of biology and mathematics will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1354754</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Orive</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>morive@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/14/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7377</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7377</Code>
      <Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
