<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>mTERF Function and Control of Plant Respiration and Stress Tolerance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Irwin Forseth</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Plant survival and fecundity/productivity under stress conditions determine species distribution in nature as well as agricultural output. The long term goal of this research project is to define critical features of plant energy metabolism that determine stress survival. The specific focus of the research project is the control of respiration in plant mitochondria, which are critical energy generating organelles in all organisms. A better understanding of the regulation of mitochondrial components is needed to explain plant energy balance and biomass accumulation. Because respiratory activity is part of the equation determining plant productivity, understanding the control of plant respiration may enable targeted manipulation of respiration to enhance productivity, particularly under stress conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Experiments will be performed to define the function of a class of proteins predicted to regulate plant mitochondrial gene expression known as mTERFs, for mitochondrial Transcription Termination Factors, using a combination of state-of-the-art biochemistry and genetics in the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana. The PI has demonstrated that mutation of an mTERF protein (SHOT1) targeted to plant mitochondria can enhance tolerance to high temperature stress apparently by limiting oxidative damage. Experiments will define the molecular mechanism of SHOT1 function, and go on to test how other mTERFs may also contribute to control of respiration and plant stress tolerance. The project will provide training in experimentation and communication for one postdoctoral scientist, one graduate student and two undergraduates for each year of the award. The PI will also engage in outreach activities to encourage teenage girls to consider science as a career option and to inform the public about the scientific basis of genetically modified plants. These talks will provide information in lay terms on the underlying biochemistry and molecular biology of GMOs so that individuals can make informed decisions about the technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1354960</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vierling</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vierling@biochem.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
