<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Tech Scholars</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>616417</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Tech Scholars program at the Pennsylvania College of Technology (Penn College) is providing scholarship support to twenty School of Industrial, Computing, and Engineering Technologies (ICET) students in majors of Information Technology, Electrical Technology, Automated Manufacturing and Machining, Engineering Design Technology, Electronics/Computer Engineering Technology, Plastics and Polymer Engineering Technology, and Welding and Fabrication Engineering Technology. Recruitment strategies for the Tech Scholars program target students who may not be aware of the array of technology-based majors in ICET at Penn College and the employment opportunities in these fields. Many of these students are the first in their family to attend college. This strategy, coupled with student support services and career education, is increasing student retention, leading to a greater number of graduates from ICET programs. In turn the project is helping to address a high demand for technology graduates and contributes to the diversity and improved capability of the technological workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to financial support through the S-STEM scholarships, technical features of the project include academic and professional support that promotes student retention and advances career education through establishing a learning community, offering peer and faculty mentoring, tutorial services, internships, field trips and guest speakers from industry. Furthermore, comprehensive approaches are employed to encourage students to select a four-year ICET major, to support them academically and financially until graduation and to increase their workforce preparation and skills. Penn College is building a cohort experience for the Tech Scholars through common seminar sections, designated study and networking spaces and a living/learning community. These strategies are implemented under the direction of an industry-focused Advisory Committee. Aided by this committee, Penn College is strengthening existing relationships with industry by involving industry partners in multiple program components, such as workshops, internships and participation in Advisory Committee activities. Further, through the Tech Scholars program, Penn College is establishing new relationships with community colleges through its outreach activities to transfer students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1355839</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Richards</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drichard@pct.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cotner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dcotner@pct.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stacey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hampton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shampton@pct.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania College of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Williamsport</CityName>
      <ZipCode>177015799</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5703263761</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One College Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
