<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Cortical Specializations for Behavioral Discrimination of Temporal Shape and Rhythm of Sound</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>510000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sridhar Raghavachari</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Human speech and other mammalian vocalizations exhibit extensive variability in their amplitude shape and rhythm. These sound features allow for discriminating and, ultimately, understanding the rich repertoire of vocal communications that characterize the vocal behavior of a large variety of animals including man. This proposal focuses on the roles of various stages of the mammalian forebrain ascending auditory pathway in categorizing and discriminating time variations in natural sounds, an important and open question in auditory physiology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Neural response timing properties suggest that secondary ventral auditory cortices allow for an extended range of sensory temporal processing not accounted for in primary auditory cortex. The neural response properties of primary and secondary auditory cortices will be examined to determine their functional organization and contribution to sensory discrimination behavior. The approach involves the creation of sophisticated acoustic stimuli that are analytically tractable on the one hand, while mimicking the important aspects of natural sounds on the other. Neural responses will be characterized using electrophysiological, intrinsic-signal imaging, behavioral and computational techniques. Pharmacological manipulations will allow reversible loss-of-function studies to determine how primary and secondary auditory areas interact to promote behavioral discrimination of temporal cues in sound. Further, this project will determine how temporal cues on multiple time scales in sound are discriminated and encoded on a neural and whole organism level for Rattus norvegicus, as this species has an expanded surface area for primary auditory cortex and secondary auditory cortex compared to other mammals commonly used in auditory studies. Another goal of the study is to determine the extent to which sound percepts are built up through parallel and hierarchal processing within auditory forebrain structures. Finally, computer models will be developed to determine what aspects of neural activity patterns are critical for discriminating between the shape and rhythm of communication sounds. This multifaceted approach should allow for an unprecedented understanding of vocal perception that could be broadly applicable. Results from the study will be disseminated through presentations at scientific meetings and through peer-reviewed journal articles.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1355065</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Monty</FirstName>
      <LastName>Escabi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>escabi@engr.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
      <LastName>Read</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>heather.read@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7713</Code>
      <Text>ACTIVATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
