<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: ITEST Longitudinal Study</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>168498</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Julia Clark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this study at Harvard University is to examine the impact of ITEAMS (Innovative Technology-Enabled Astronomy for Middle Schools) intervention strategies on student persistence in high school STEM course-taking and career expectations, and the value that students place on STEM careers. The central research questions are: 1) does ITEAMS participation boost students' STEM course-taking and their interest in, and valuation of, STEM careers throughout their high school years; 2) to what extent did students' ITEAMS experiences, in terms of knowledge and disposition, have an effect; and 3) which ITEAMS strategies or attributes have been most effective in bringing about positive outcomes? Special focus is on the predictors of persistence for girls and minority students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project utilizes a mix of interviews and surveys with current high school students who in previous years participated in ITEAMS (DRL-0833378) as middle-school students, and who are now juniors and seniors. The project surveys a randomly selected cohort of 75 former ITEAMS participants who were enrolled in ITEAMS for two or three years. The project-specific survey instrument includes pertinent demographic questions. The random selection of up to 15 surveyed ITEAMS students for in-depth interviews is also included.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1355323</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sadler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>psadler@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Harvard University</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7227</Code>
      <Text>ITEST</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7645</Code>
      <Text>DISCOVERY RESEARCH K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
