<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: World War II Anthropology: Austrians and Germans in Poland, Japanese in Asia, and the Search for Survivors (AAAS, Pacific Division Mtg., U Cal-Riverside, June 2014)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20066</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Roger Christianson of Southern Oregon University will oversee an international symposium on the role of German, Austrian, and Japanese anthropologists in annexed territories (in Eastern Europe and Asia) during the first half of the twentieth century through the Second World War. The research will aid in our understanding of the role that anthropological science played in colonial and wartime Europe and Asia. They will discuss the roles these anthropologists played in consigning Polish people from immediate death to mindless labor, the records they created, how the records were used to find Polish survivors after the war, and what transpired once survivors were found. Also to be discussed will be research relating to the investigations of Japanese anthropologists in Asia, beginning with the colonization of Taiwan in 1895 through military expansion during World War II. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This anthropological research documents little known information about the role of anthropologists during wartime, how their services were used to support German and Japanese ambitions, and how anthropologists today search for survivors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This symposium will be conducted before scientists, graduate students, and high school students at a meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, Pacific Division, annual conference at the University of California, Riverside. Abstracts of the presentations will be published.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1356157</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bain</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baina@si.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
      <LastName>Christianson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rchristi@sou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Oregon University</Name>
      <CityName>Ashland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>975205001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5415528662</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1250 Siskiyou Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
