<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Biology Opportunities and Scholarships for Success (BOSS) Project</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>609360</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Connie K. Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of West Alabama (UWA) Biology Opportunities and Scholarships for Success (BOSS) is supporting 16 undergraduates majoring in either Biology or Environmental Sciences who demonstrate academic potential, motivation for STEM, and financial need. Nearly half of the University's students (46%) are from six western Alabama counties, four of which are among the 20 poorest counties in the nation. The majority of UWA students are affiliated with underrepresented groups including women, ethnic minorities, and first-generation students. With a large population of under-served students in its targeted service area, UWA is distinctively set to address the needs of first-generation and low-income students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The guiding objective of the BOSS program is to increase student retention through degree achievement by providing comprehensive educational opportunities so that the S-STEM scholars can reach their full academic potential. The program helps to increase the number of successful biological and environmental sciences graduates joining the workforce or graduate schools by providing career exploration and professional development opportunities. UWA also offers scholars a wide range of supportive services, including counseling services, focused student advising, and tutoring. The evaluation of student scholars involves an Individualized Success Plan (ISP) to assess every participant through ongoing evaluations pertinent to the student's success. Outcome data include academic progress reports, internship participation, professional presentations, and other professional networking activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1356248</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mustafa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morsy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmorsy@uwa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCall</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmccall@uwa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stanton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lstanton@uwa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of West Alabama</Name>
      <CityName>Livingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354702097</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2056523424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Station 47</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
