<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Inflation Dynamics During the Financial Crisis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>72839</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>From a macroeconomic perspective, one of the most puzzling aspects of the 2007-09 financial&lt;br/&gt;crisis and the ensuing slow recovery is the relative stability of inflation. Despite a large and sharp&lt;br/&gt;contraction in output in the second half of 2008 and the persistently high level of resource slack&lt;br/&gt;over the past several years, the U.S. experienced only a modest degree of disinflationary&lt;br/&gt;pressures-both at the wholesale and retail levels-behavior that is difficult to explain with&lt;br/&gt;canonical models of aggregate inflation determination. This project studies the extent to which&lt;br/&gt;the massive tightening of financial conditions at the height of the crisis in the latter part of 2008&lt;br/&gt;may help explain why inflation did not fall as much as expected during the financial crisis and the&lt;br/&gt;subsequent recovery. The underlying hypothesis posits that some firms may strategically set low&lt;br/&gt;prices to attract customers, behavior implied by the "customer-markets theory," which&lt;br/&gt;emphasizes the idea that price setting is a form of investment that builds the future customer base.&lt;br/&gt;According to this theory, firms will in normal times maintain low prices relative to their&lt;br/&gt;competitors in order to attract new customers. In turn, this implies low current mark-ups and&lt;br/&gt;hence lower cash flows.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;However, in times of widespread financial distress-when external finance becomes prohibitively&lt;br/&gt;costly or even unavailable-financially vulnerable firms will sacrifice their customer base by&lt;br/&gt;raising prices to stabilize current revenues and bolster their liquidity positions. Thus in periods of&lt;br/&gt;acute financial distress, inflation may actually rise despite a drop in economic activity and the&lt;br/&gt;emergence of a significant degree of resource underutilization. The possibility that inflation and&lt;br/&gt;output move in opposite directions in response to an adverse demand shock also challenges&lt;br/&gt;conventional thinking regarding the appropriate course of action for monetary policy during&lt;br/&gt;financial crises.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To examine this hypothesis empirically, the project merges firm-level financial data with the&lt;br/&gt;corresponding firm-level inflation rates computed from the confidential price data collected by&lt;br/&gt;the Bureau of Labor Statistics (BLS). Preliminary results indicate that financial factors had a&lt;br/&gt;significant effect on inflation dynamics during the 2007-09 crisis. Consistent with the hypothesis,&lt;br/&gt;financially "weak" firms raised prices in the latter part of 2008, whereas their financially "strong"&lt;br/&gt;counterparts lowered prices in response to a drop in aggregate demand. To date, the implications&lt;br/&gt;of this mechanism for aggregate inflation dynamics have remained largely unexplored, and this&lt;br/&gt;study provides some of the first systematic evidence on how financial conditions influence the&lt;br/&gt;price-setting behavior of firms through the incentives to set prices in a manner that preserves their&lt;br/&gt;liquidity and balance sheet capacity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To the extent that this channel is quantitatively important, the analysis in this project has a direct&lt;br/&gt;bearing on gauging the likelihood of destructive large-scale disinflations during financial crises. It&lt;br/&gt;also has important implications for the conduct of monetary policy by arguing that policy makers&lt;br/&gt;should take into account the interaction between changes in the quality of the firms' balance&lt;br/&gt;sheets and their price-setting behavior when deciding on the future course of nominal interest&lt;br/&gt;rates. In addition to developing the matching algorithm that links BLS' researcher databases with&lt;br/&gt;outside firm-level data sets, the project also provides a new measure of local bank credit-supply&lt;br/&gt;conditions based on the GPS coordinates that may be used in conjunction with future BLS&lt;br/&gt;studies, opening up a whole new set of research possibilities on the spatial interaction between&lt;br/&gt;financial conditions and firm behavior.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1357715</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raphael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schoenle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schoenle@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/03/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brandeis University</Name>
      <CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7817362121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>415 SOUTH ST MAILSTOP 116</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1320</Code>
      <Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
