<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Cradle to the Grave - CO2 Opportunities and Challenges</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>343143</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;The topic of this REU site is "Cradle to the grave - CO2 opportunities and challenges". The scientific objective is to leverage the expertise of an interdisciplinary team in nanoscience, materials science, heterogeneous catalysis, spectroscopy, electrochemistry, mathematical modeling, and geological CO2 storage to advance the understanding of the role that novel materials and processes will play in reducing the environmental impact of CO2. The REU students will participate in cutting-edge research, ranging from advanced combustion technologies, CO2 separation and sequestration, and chemical conversion of CO2 and biomass to hydrocarbon fuels. The combustion research will focus on oxy-fuel combustion and integrated gasification combined cycle. Gas phase chemistry of sulfur oxides and trace metals will be elucidated by experiments and kinetic modeling. Increasing energy production efficiency by raising the temperature of combustion environments will expose gas turbine blades to highly aggressive environments. Modern blades consist of high strength super-alloys blades, ceramic thermal barrier coatings and metallic/oxide bond coats. REU students will participate in the experimental aspects of this project including using state-of-the-art high-throughput deposition and characterization techniques or in the modeling and data mining aspects of this work. Once CO2 has been generated, it must be captured from the flue gas. Research here will emphasize the generation of novel unit operations for the efficient removal of CO2 and new high-capacity sorbent materials. Carbon forms the backbone for high energy density fuels. C=O bonds in CO2 therefore need to be converted back to high energy C-H and C-C bonds. Projects in this thrust range from the fundamental study and improvement of proven technologies, such as electrochemical reduction of CO2 to more ambitious projects, which rely on solar energy to promote conversion. However, the sheer scale of CO2 production is such that it is infeasible to completely convert the CO2 into chemicals or hydrocarbon fuels. Therefore, storage of CO2 is required to reduce the environmental impact of energy generation on a scale beyond anything that has ever been attempted. Research here focuses on sequestration of CO2 and in particular on the long-term stability of storage in geological formations in South Carolina&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;Our nation's ability to meet our future energy needs in a sustainable manner will be critical to our ability to continue to prosper. Advancing the scientific knowledge and developing the intellectual workforce for a variety of sustainable energy technologies will be at the center of this endeavor. This REU site will train and expose our future scientific leaders to cutting-edge research in sustainable energy in general, and in nanoscience, catalysis and CO2 capture and storage in particular. Professional development efforts will provide the students with the non-technical knowledge and experience required to take discoveries out of the lab and place them into society. Participants will include rising juniors and seniors majoring in chemical engineering. Special emphasis will be placed on minorities as well as students who would otherwise not have an opportunity to do cutting-edge research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We acknowledge the support from the Division of Engineering Education and Centers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358931</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jochen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lauterbach</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lauteraj@cec.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>WILLIA84@engr.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Carolina at Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Awards Management</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
