<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Support for Young US Scientists Attending the 2013 International Accelerator School for Linear Colliders, Antalya, Turkey, December 4 -8, 2013</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7928</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James T. Shank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lepton particle beam colliders (the International Linear Collider (ILC), Compact Linear Collider (CLIC) and the Muon Collider) are among the priority projects being considered by the International High Energy Physics Community to advance the scientific knowledge of the field. This award provides partial support for US students and post docs to attend the Eighth International Accelerator School for Linear Colliders to be held in Antalya, Turkey, 4-8 December 2013. The program of the school will cover a wide range of topics related to lepton colliders, from beam dynamics to damping rings, from superconducting radio frequency technologies to precise instrumentation, from room temperature radio frequency technology to beam delivery systems. The broader impact of the school is the opportunity for US students and post docs to interact with their counterparts from other regions of the world and to form collaborations and partnerships. The program is supported by NSF Division of Physics, through its programs in Experimental Elementary Particle Physics and Accelerator Research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358981</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Weiren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chou@fnal.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/10/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Fermi Research Alliance, LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Batavia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>605105011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6308404302</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Fermilab MS 105</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1221</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
