<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EPRI: Direct Contact Heat Exchange and Absorption Refrigeration Based on Green Non-volatile Ionic Liquids for Enhanced Dry Cooling of Thermoelectric Power Plants</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>605216</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1358034&lt;br/&gt;Ju &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is an urgent need to minimize or possibly eliminate industrial usage of freshwater. It has been estimated that thermoelectric power production withdraws close to 40% of freshwater in the US. Currently available dry cooling methods with zero water consumption have found very limited usage (&lt; 2%) due to the high capital cost, large footprints/weight, and low thermal efficiency. Therefore, research toward developing innovative alternative dry cooling methods that are economical are need to facilitate their broad adoption. This will eliminate the water withdrawal for cooling in power generation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research at UCLA will develop a new class of technology called DIrect-contact Liquid-on-String Heat Exchangers (DILSHE) for dry cooling of a steam power plant. A key feature of the DILSHE is the use of inexpensive and light-weight materials, making it highly economical and easily transportable. High heat transfer effectiveness is achieved using thin films of non-volatile liquids flowing over a dense array of parallel strings while reducing associated gas flow pressure drop. Another feature of DILSHE is its modular design; this allows multiple units to be stacked together to form large cooling units, with each module being field readily serviceable and/or replaceable.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research proposes to conduct systematic experimental and theoretical investigation to establish scientific and engineering foundation for rigorous design and optimization of the DILSHE. It will improve and apply advanced fluid mechanical and thermal metrology tools and techniques for studying the instability of gravity-driven thin liquid film flows and associated enhancement in mass, momentum, and energy transport. Comprehensive survey and preliminary screening of non-volatile heat transfer liquids will also be conducted to facilitate exploration of their novel use not only in the proposed DILSHE but also other heat transfer applications. The research will also build and test a lab scale prototype (25 kW capacity) to validate the proposed design and to facilitate further commercial development of the technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will also include dedicated efforts to involve undergraduate and graduate students from under-represented groups. K-12 STEM education will be promoted by developing innovative programs for high-school students based on a cradle-to-career philosophy that leverages the research components of the project in coordination with UCLA's outreach offices. The project will also include efforts to promote engineering business opportunities, which, when instilled early on, will help promote an entrepreneurial spirit that resonates with the youth in the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358034</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yongho</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ju</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>just@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vijay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dhir</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vdhir@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>064E</Code>
      <Text>Convection heat and mass transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
