<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthetic Tools for Understanding Biological Phenomena</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials Research is in support of the 2013 Materials Research Society Fall Meeting symposium titled "Synthetic Tools for Understanding Biological Phenomena." The goals of the symposium are to: a) showcase recent advances in the design, synthesis, characterization, and application of synthetic tools for understanding and directing biological phenomena; b) facilitate a dialogue between polymer scientists, chemists, bioengineers, and biologists to further the design and application of biomaterials with controlled properties through networking and the open exchange of ideas; and c) provide opportunities for young investigators, including junior faculty, post-doctoral fellows, and graduate students, especially from underrepresented groups, to present their latest research results. The planned oral and poster sessions would provide a cutting-edge scientific program and discussion forum that focus on specific fundamental, applied sciences and engineering challenges that would facilitate the translation of novel and facile chemistries for biomaterial synthesis and applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are high in terms of their impact on students, post-docs, as well as in stimulating new ideas within the biomaterials research community. The organizers of this MRS Symposium are junior faculty scientists in their areas of specialization and have put together an excellent program, and group of speakers and discussion leaders. Three of the four symposium organizers are women, and five of the twelve invited speakers are female scientists. Presentations by graduate students and post-doctoral researchers including members of underrepresented groups will be strongly pursued to encourage and facilitate scientific discourse, collaboration, and education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1358090</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>April</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kloxin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>akloxin@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chien-Chi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lincc@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Danielle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Benoit</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>danielleswbenoit@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. Ardie Butch</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dillen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dillen@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
      <CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
