<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: An Interdisciplinary Exploration of the Convergence of Science and Engineering: Micro to Nanoscale Materials, Processing, and Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>359866</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical Summary: Stereotypical science faculty drive toward the discovery of new physical phenomena, while stereotypical engineering faculty drive toward stabilization and control of new phenomena in order to create value for society. But as the materials and structures under investigation have shrunk from the microscale to the nanoscale (and beyond), neither of these stand-alone approaches are sufficient to create the full understanding and implementation of new phenomena. At the micro to nanoscale new and innovative potential uses of materials and structures evolve, driven by cross-fertilization of ideas between traditional engineering disciplines. Successful engineering research in this size regime requires close coordination with leading edge underlying sciences if the discoveries are to exit the laboratory to become products benefiting society. This REU site will provide students with an opportunity to work for ten weeks on cutting edge micro to nanoscale engineering and leave having created knowledge that could only have been imagined a decade ago. This REU site will be structured in an industry-like natural work-group environment that will give skills and practice in effective and efficient execution of this research-based educational experience. Full participation in an ethics class with ìEP grad students will lead participants to question their prior assumptions and adopt the mantle of "citizen technologists", while also demonstrating that rapid positive changes are best enabled through mutual support and cooperation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Sumamry: This three year REU site will provide students with research opportunities in labs that bridge the gap between science and engineering. Students will spend ten weeks working in a research lab with professors, postdoctoral researchers, graduate students, and/or other undergraduate students. This research experience will provide participants the opportunity to personally experience the thrill of advanced discovery. In addition to a vigorous and rewarding research experience, student discussions in weekly ethics classes and research meetings will examine issues of gender, religion, nationality, physical ability, age, race, and economic class. They will be taught to learn from different points of view, a skill needed to be a creative, competent, and effective engineer. The outcome will be the future leaders of our technical community who have converted new fundamental science into engineering reality, worked in research teams, developed communication skills, learned to appreciate people for their abilities, and gained enthusiasm toward graduate studies at the micro to nanoscale.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1359306</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ken</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vickers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vickers@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/26/2015</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shannon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Servoss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sservoss@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/22/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shannon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Servoss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sservoss@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/26/2015</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wise</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rickwise@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/22/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
      <CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
