<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Fundamental Research Topics Related to Unmanned Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>297792</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Alabama in Huntsville (UAH) Research Experience for Undergraduates program focuses on the missing links of fundamental research in five related fields of science and engineering: Dynamics &amp; Controls, Video Processing and Data Mining and Compression, Human-Machine Interface, Physics of Sensors, Material Science. As an example, one of the broader societal/economic impacts of these related fields is that they help the proliferation of Unmanned Systems civilian applications that affect humans quality of life. First, interaction-based learning controllers are formulated, which are able to learn how to control a system only by interacting with it, similar to the way humans learn how to control machines with minimum instructions. Second, vision-based object 3D reconstruction and classification will be researched. The goal is to formulate a method that only uses 2D videos to generate a 3D model of an arbitrary object, and classify objects using 2D video. In addition, the students will learn about data mining techniques for classi&amp;#64257;cation of phases of protein crystal growth classi&amp;#64257;cation of images based on presence of crystals. Third, new ways of integration of data from heterogeneous sensors will be researched. The goal is to be able to fuse data gathered from different sensor types to reconstruct a 3D environment. Fourth, research will be focused on finding optimum ways of real-time compression of video data. The goal is formulating a method that optimizes the need for computational power, use of energy, weight, and data bandwidth. Fifth, new ideas for human-machine interface will be generated. The objective is to fill the gap in the inability of human-agent interfaces to intuitively interpret the users intent. Sixth, fundamentals of physics will be employed to invent new sensors for accurate real-time measurement of high-frequency strain. Seventh, the specific catalytic activity of the IPPase under different temperatures, pH and ionic concentration will be determined.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The undergraduate students will be exposed to the state-of-the-art knowledge and background related to the research project of their choice. They will be trained in the required research techniques, methods of literature survey, generating hypotheses, formulating tests to validate hypotheses, collecting data, and communicating with colleagues via written materials and oral presentations at professional and scientific meetings. Students will solve research problems with the help of mentors, and will transform themselves into relatively independent young researchers. The research experience and independence generates enthusiasm and confidence for the students, and highly increases the their likelihood of pursuing graduate studies and careers in STEM-related fields. The program encourages diversity among US future scientific talent. Three two-year colleges and seven undergraduate institutions in Alabama and Central Southern Tennessee (EPSCoR states) are identified. The total student population of these ten institutions consists of 51% women and 82% minorities. By focusing most of the recruitment efforts on these institutions, the program aims for recruiting at least 50% of the students from two-year colleges and at least 70% participation by women and minorities. Students will prepare papers for presentation at relevant conferences and for publication in related conference proceedings and science/engineering journals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"This award is co-funded by the Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EHR/EPSCoR)."</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1359311</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ramazan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aygun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aygunr@uah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Farbod</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fahimi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>farbod.fahimi@uah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/13/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama in Huntsville</Name>
      <CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>358051911</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2568246120</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>301 Sparkman Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
