<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Chemistry at the University of Connecticut</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry (CHE) supports a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site at the University of Connecticut (UConn). Professors Mark Pezuh and Jose A. Gascon who will recruit motivated undergraduates from primarily non-Ph.D. granting institutions to participate in a graduate-level research project over a 10-week period. Students with limited opportunities for independent research, women, and students from under-represented groups are especially encouraged to apply. As a unique thrust, the program targets participation from nearby Central Connecticut State University (CCSU), a non-Ph.D.-granting institution. The program pays special attention to develop communication skills and ethical behavior in the research setting. Participants also obtain a foundation for making informed choices about future careers in chemistry and establish networks with peers from a range of disciplines and experiences. Overall, the UConn Chemistry REU program aims to enhance students' enthusiasm for chemistry and prepare them for post-graduate success in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The core aim of this program is to introduce participants to the full breadth of research-related activities, a number of ancillary technical workshops, and professional development seminars. In addition to the research conducted in the host laboratories, students participate in two hands-on workshops: one on computational chemistry and the other on single crystal X-ray crystallography held at CCSU. These activities introduce an intellectually challenging technical component to the program that involves the entire cohort and provides a deeper understanding about techniques that are instrumental to all fields of chemistry. The program incorporates a graduate assistant as a near-peer leader to cultivate a group identity for each year's cohort. Activities culminate in oral presentations and a poster symposium for which the University community, parents and faculty from the students' home institutions are invited.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1359081</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peczuh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mark.peczuh@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gascon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jose.gascon@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
