<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Salish Sea Research Center: Transforming STEM Education in Native Environmental Sciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Northwest Indian College (NWIC) students will investigate the productivity potential of traditional indigenous aquaculture using a growth increment laboratory to compare the growth rate of modern harvested clams such as Saxidomous gigantea, to clam shells from the archeological records. In addition, students will conduct research on in-situ intertidal ecosystems using underwater video systems, or will explore the impact of ocean acidification on culturally and economically significant organisms such as clams and crabs, using SeaFET pH sensors to better understand changes occurring in nearby oceanic ecosystems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These projects describe some of the ways that traditional knowledge and cultural experience will be combined with place-based research to enrich the Native Environmental Science degree and increase the relevance of STEM programs and careers to tribal students. It has been widely shown that undergraduate research experiences increase the success of students through STEM academic programs and related careers. In addition to increasing the STEM course offerings at NWIC, this project will promote the development of indigenous scholars through the creation of a space and organizational structure for student researchers, as well as capacity-building in the form of equipment to promote student and staff research. This project will increase the American Indian involvement in STEM measured through an increased achievement of Bachelor of Science, and graduate persistence into STEM careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1361825</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andres</FirstName>
      <LastName>Quesada</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aquesada@nwic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/30/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marco</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hatch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marco.hatch@wwu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/30/2016</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwest Indian College</Name>
      <CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>982269278</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3606762772</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2522 Kwina Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
