<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I/UCRC: Proposal to add North Carolina State University as a center site for the existing I/UCRC "Center for Lasers and Plasmas in Advanced Manufacturing"</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed new site of the Laser and Plasma for Advanced Manufacturing (LPAM) I/UCRC at North Carolina State University (NCSU) intends to deepen the understanding of plasma systems and how they interact with their environment, address critical areas such as new source design, validation of predictive models for virtual design, dynamic chemistry control for non-equilibrium processes, and enable advanced diagnostics. These challenges will be addressed by focusing on the basic science behind three critical areas: 1) interaction between plasmas and applied fields, 2) interaction between plasmas and surfaces, and 3) the underlying science that enable advanced diagnostics. This integrated effort will complement the current activities of the Lasers and Plasmas for Advanced Manufacturing I/UCRC and broaden the scope of the center to include a class of plasma systems poised to make substantial contributions to future manufacturing efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Low temperature plasma (LTP) science provides a base technology on which many modern industries exist. The NCSU site of LPAM?s research efforts target expansion of needed application inspired fundamental research in this area to support industry competitiveness. Industries that utilize LTPs for manufacturing are experiencing a shortfall in manpower for the design, development, and operation of these devices. As plasma process expands into new growth industries this demand will increase. By providing an environment that focuses on fundamental understanding of these systems, combined with industry engagement through collaborative research, industry residencies, and co-operative opportunities, we will fill a manpower void and accelerate the growth of low cost, repeatable manufacturing solutions for the domestic high-tech industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1362103</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shannon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scshannon@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/01/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
      <CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8041</Code>
      <Text>Fabrications and Processing Technology</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
