<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Identification and Functional Characterization of Novel Expressed Transcripts in the Rosaceae</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1012045</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Kevin M. Folta (University of Florida)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CoPI: Thomas M. Davis (University of New Hampshire, subawardee)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The species within the family Rosaceae represent economically valuable fruit, nut and ornamental crops. Over the last five years there has been a rapid expansion in the DNA sequence information in this family. This resource offers immense opportunity to address major unanswered questions about the genes that underlie traits of importance in this family. However, study of the databases reveals a significant number of genes that are exclusive to the Rosaceae, and it is now possible to elucidate their roles on a functional, genome-wide scale. By focusing on a plant family known and valued for its diversity of plant and plant-product forms (strawberry, raspberry, peach, almond, cherry, apple, pear, rose, and others), this project complements and significantly extends model system studies aimed at illuminating the functions of all plant genes. The research leverages available knowledge of expressed DNA sequences, innovative methods of new sequence capture, the agility of the recombination-based cloning systems, and the efficient genetic transformation capacities of strawberry and the model species Arabidopsis. Specifically, strawberry (Fragaria) and other Rosaceae expressed sequences cloned in Gateway vectors will be subjected to homology searches against GenBank databases to identify sequences that either have no apparent homologous counterparts outside of the Rosaceae family, or that have model system homologues that remain functionally uncharacterized. Employing a transgenic approach, manipulation of each target gene's expression in the diploid strawberry and in Arabidopsis will be used to investigate the functional significance of these poorly understood sequences. The resulting knowledge will translate into new avenues of progress in the field of molecular plant breeding - i.e., the use of DNA sequence information and molecular marker technologies to enhance the powers of plant breeders to develop superior plant varieties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the work will expand the resolution of expressed genes in Rosaceae and strawberry public resources, and promote a fertile set of resources to facilitate undergraduate and graduate student and postdoctoral training. Characterization of novel strawberry and Arabidopsis lines will be an excellent activity for undergraduate researchers. Long-term impacts may be found in cultivar improvement, application to sustainable agriculture and ultimately benefit the consumer with increased choices and accessibility to nutritious fresh fruit. Definition of novel gene function will expand current physiological and developmental models, and allow researchers to develop trait-associated molecular markers (and possibly transgenics) to assist breeders and growers and benefit consumers. Up to 1000 transgenic lines expressing genes of previously unknown function will be made available as a genomics-community resource, priming new and unpredicted avenues of research and application. Data and biological materials, such as clones, plant lines, and sequences, can be accessed through the project website (http://www.strawberrygenes.com) and through established no/low-cost repositories that include the Genome Database for Rosaceae (GDR; http://www.bioinfo.wsu.edu/gdr/), GenBank, and the USDA National Clonal Germplasm Repositories. In collaboration with minority institutions, the project will provide summer internships to support broader participation in plant science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0701488</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Folta</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kfolta@ifas.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tom.davis@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
