<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I/O Virtualization - From Self-Virtualizing Devices to Metadata-Rich Information Appliances</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Almadena Y. Chtchelkanova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Demands for online access to large data sets distributed across multiple machines are prevalent both in large-scale enterprises and in scientific settings. An example is remote data visualization for large-scale applications running on peta-scale machines, where researchers are seeking ways to accelerate the scientific processes they are carrying out via real-time inspection and validation of the outputs from their running codes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses a basic problem basic problem for the large-scale data movements implied by such tasks, which is the substantial semantic gap between application-level data exchanges and the I/O services provided by underlying hardware and system platforms. For instance, at the device level, data being moved may be described as a linear sequence of blocks, whereas the application level views it as highly structured data on which it is performing a complex checkpoint operation. To help close help close this gap, for future virtualized execution platforms, this project realizes the &lt;br/&gt;notion of Abstract IO (A-IO) devices, where each such device can be designed to provide useful new functionality to end user applications. Toward this end, it exploits new system- and device -level virtualization technologies to present to operating systems what appear to be physical devices, but are actually virtual representations of such devices. For such `logical devices', it then addresses the question regarding where to place their higher level I/O device functions on future many-core platforms: on the general computational cores of host machines or on specialized cores &lt;br/&gt;associated with devices. The utility of the approach is evaluated in the context of two realizations of A-IO based devices (NIC and block device), and with actual scientific and enterprise applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0702249</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eisenhauer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eisen@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ada</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gavrilovska</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ada@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karsten</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schwan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schwan@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7352</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTING PROCESSES &amp; ARTIFACT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
