<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Using Contracts to Support Development, Verification, and Maintenance of Multi-threaded Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>430000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sol J. Greenspan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Stirewalt Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A principal difficulty in the development of high-assurance software is to safely accommodate concurrency and synchronization. The propensity for concurrency to engender state-explosion confounds verification, and the tendency for synchronization logic to be interleaved with "functional" code complicates understanding and maintenance. Thus, development and long-term maintenance of high-assurance software requires design artifacts over which verification is feasible and processes that use these artifacts to maintain separation of concerns in the implementation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to achieve these goals. Specifically, it explores a design-for-verification (D4V) approach based on synchronization contracts, which provides the high level of abstraction needed to support verification while maintaining a good separation of synchronization and functional concerns. We are developing programming systems that leverage contract awareness for analysis; to automate the generation of models from design artifacts, (e.g., UML diagrams); and to separate synchronization and functional concerns. We are conducting these explorations in the context of an existing software baseline.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project also involves development of undergraduate courses in concurrent systems design, model-based software engineering, and D4V. One benchmark is the extent to which undergraduates are able to design and verify contract-aware programs using the tools and methods developed under this grant.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0702667</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dillon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ldillon@cse.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/07/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dillon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ldillon@cse.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/27/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kurt</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stirewalt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stire@cse.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/27/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
