<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Advanced Technology Environment and Energy Center: A Resource Center</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1762371</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David B. Campbell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Advanced Technology Environmental Education Center (ATEEC) was established in 1994 as an NSF ATE Center of Excellence whose mission is to advance environmental technology education through curricula development, professional development, and program improvement in the nation's community colleges and secondary schools. This current project provides a comprehensive, market-driven Resource Center to promote professional development, teaching, training, and support to environmental and sustainable energy educational programs at the secondary and postsecondary levels. The Center has recently been renamed Advanced Technology Environment and Energy Center. The three major goals of this project are to expand ATEEC dissemination and availability of exemplary educational materials, curricula, and pedagogical practices in the areas of environmental and sustainable energy technology; to expand the web-based, digital electronic Environmental Resources Library (eERL) to include sustainable energy technology and expand the user base; and to provide professional development opportunities in the area of environmental and energy technology to high school and community college teachers. ATEEC works with business and industry, educators and government agencies to disseminate exemplary educational materials, curricula and resources in the areas of environmental and energy technology to high school and community college educators and students as well as technicians across the country. This project utilizes the national and regional Partnership for Environmental Technology Education networks, mailings, newsletters (print and electronic), the web-based eERL library, print information, exhibits, regional and national presentations, CD-ROMs, the ATEEC website, and journal articles to disseminate project activities, products, and environmental and energy technology education information.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0702439</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maureen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clayton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maureen.clayton@uni.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kabat Lensch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ekabatlensch@eicc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kirk</FirstName>
      <LastName>Laflin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>KLaflin@maine.rr.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Eastern Iowa Community College</Name>
      <CityName>davenport</CityName>
      <ZipCode>528011221</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5633363300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>306 West River Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7731</Code>
      <Text>OTHER GLOBAL LEARNING &amp; TRNING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5914</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5979</Code>
      <Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
