<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Concurrent Error Detection in Analog Circuits</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>126000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal ID: 0702522 &lt;br/&gt;Title: Concurrent Error Detection in Analog Circuits&lt;br/&gt;PI: Yiorgos Makris &lt;br/&gt;Inst: Yale University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract &lt;br/&gt;Incorporation of extensive analog and radio-frequency (RF) functionality on modern mixed-signal integrated circuits has armed them with powerful new capabilities, especially in interfacing and communicating with their environment through sensors and on-chip radios. As such, mixed-signal integrated circuits are now part of a broad spectrum of systems, many of which are deployed in mission-critical applications (e.g. avionics, medical equipment) or operate in hazardous environments (e.g. space, industrial operations). Consequently, the reliability of such systems becomes paramount, calling for advanced solutions to monitor their functional health during their operation in the field and to report potential malfunctions. While reliability has been extensively studied and a plethora of Concurrent Error Detection (CED) methods have been developed for digital circuits in the past, there is an alarming lack of pertinent solutions for their analog and RF counterparts. The objective of this project is to fill this void. To this end, its key novelty and uniqueness lies in the amalgamation of state-of-the-art practices in VLSI design and test, with concepts from control theory and pattern recognition, in order to develop CED solutions for analog and RF circuits. In short, this project will facilitate the realization of reliable electronic circuits and systems, thus extending their deployment in a broad range of applications, enabling reliable computing, and fostering technology trustworthiness. The proposed research is complemented by educational and outreach activities, which offer graduate and undergraduate students the opportunity to participate in inter-disciplinary research projects and demonstrate the PI's commitment to an integrated role as a researcher, educator, and active community member.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0702522</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yiorgos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Makris</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yiorgos.makris@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
