<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Northern Cheyenne Connected Learning Network</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2500000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Through efforts and strategies employed during Phase One of the TCUP grant Chief Dull Knife&lt;br/&gt;College has seen remarkable results in the area of student interest in, enrollment in and&lt;br/&gt;completion of math and science courses. During Phase Two the college will develop a&lt;br/&gt;?connected learning network? with local partner schools and the universities to address several&lt;br/&gt;ongoing endeavors begun in Phase One of the TCUP project. The use of research to expose&lt;br/&gt;students to STEM careers and the improvement of students' capabilities in gatekeeper courses&lt;br/&gt;can have a combined effect of positioning the student for continued success in STEM&lt;br/&gt;undertakings. The college seeks to broaden and enhance the accomplishments of Phase One by&lt;br/&gt;continuing to offer research opportunities to our students on the university campus, but also to&lt;br/&gt;expand these research experiences to the home campus and Chief Dull Knife College. Research&lt;br/&gt;concepts, processes, and outcomes will be incorporated into science and math course work at&lt;br/&gt;the tribal college. Research findings will be presented by students at national meetings. The&lt;br/&gt;research carried out will be shared with surrounding high schools and the university partners&lt;br/&gt;through an Interactive Video system linking the laboratories and classrooms at the remote sites.&lt;br/&gt;The college will broaden the scope of computer-delivered mastery based math courses delivered&lt;br/&gt;on campus, as well as, assist local high schools in implementing a similar methodology for&lt;br/&gt;mathematics delivery. Transferring what we have learned in Phase One about math preparation&lt;br/&gt;and retention to the high schools and helping them adopt changes can have a huge effect on&lt;br/&gt;completion rates and level of ?math preparedness? for incoming college students. Increased&lt;br/&gt;preparation results in more choices in all areas of science, technology, and mathematics for the&lt;br/&gt;student. The curriculum in math and science at the college will be reviewed and revamped to&lt;br/&gt;reflect increased math-science integration. The faculty will also work closely with the Project&lt;br/&gt;Director to incorporate research into current curricula in science and mathematics. The college&lt;br/&gt;will also continue to offer summer workshops designed to interest students in STEM related&lt;br/&gt;course work and careers. Students will interact with instructors from NASA and local faculty on&lt;br/&gt;projects ranging from 3D animation and design to Lego Robotics. Throughout the various projects&lt;br/&gt;the students and interns will be asked to take on increasingly complex leadership roles with&lt;br/&gt;students in other levels of the program. High school students will model for the younger grades,&lt;br/&gt;tribal college students will model for high school students and university students will model for&lt;br/&gt;tribal college students. Connecting the campuses together through Interactive TV will afford a first&lt;br/&gt;foray into this type of mentor/leadership interaction for Northern Cheyenne students. Students&lt;br/&gt;involved in research at the tribal college and their high school associates will be able to link with&lt;br/&gt;siblings and relatives at the university research labs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0703747</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Madsen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bmadsen@cdkc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Littlebear</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rlbear@cdkc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hooker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hooker@cdkc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Chief Dull Knife Memorial College</Name>
      <CityName>Lame Deer</CityName>
      <ZipCode>590430098</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4064776215</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O.Box 98</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1744</Code>
      <Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
