<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GEOMETRIC DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS AND APPLICATIONS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/30/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>332132</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;GEOMETRIC DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS AND APPLICATIONS&lt;br/&gt;P.I.: Gang Tian (M.I.T.)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal concerns existence and regularity problems of the Einstein &lt;br/&gt;equation, the Yang-Mills equation on Riemannian manifolds and &lt;br/&gt;pseudo-holomorphic curves, as well as applications of these equations to &lt;br/&gt;geometry and topology. For the Einstein equation, we will focus mainly on &lt;br/&gt;(1) the existence of its solutions, particularly, K\"ahler-Einstein metrics &lt;br/&gt;in complex geometry and (2) behavior of its singular solutions. I will also &lt;br/&gt;study the associated K\"ahler-Ricci flow and its soliton-type solutions. &lt;br/&gt;The Yang-Mills equation is a nonlinear equation and may have singular &lt;br/&gt;solutions. We will study the basic problem how singular solutions behave &lt;br/&gt;along their singularity, e.q., the size of singularity. It has been found &lt;br/&gt;in my previous works that there is a connection between singularity &lt;br/&gt;formation of Yang-Mills fields and classical minimal submanifolds. I intend &lt;br/&gt;to explore this more and its related compactness problem for Yang-Mills &lt;br/&gt;fields, particularly, the interaction between self-dual solutions the &lt;br/&gt;Yang-Mills equation and calibrated geometry. I also intend to continue his &lt;br/&gt;study in symplectic geometry. The problems include symplectic isotopy &lt;br/&gt;problem in a rational surface and its applications toward classifying &lt;br/&gt;symplectic four dimensional spaces, computing well-defined symplectic &lt;br/&gt;invariants, such as the Gromov-Witten invariants, constructing new &lt;br/&gt;deformation invariants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Problems in this proposal arose naturally from our attempts to &lt;br/&gt;understanding nonlinear differential equations from geometry and physics. &lt;br/&gt;These equations include static Einstein equation, Yang-Mills fields as well &lt;br/&gt;as holomorphic maps. They played a fundamental role in our understanding of &lt;br/&gt;nature through mathematical means. They also have found many deep &lt;br/&gt;applications in geometry and topology, such as Seiberg-Witten theory, &lt;br/&gt;Mirror symmetry of Calabi-Yau spaces. The resolution of these problems will &lt;br/&gt;provide mathematical foundations for some physical theories and have &lt;br/&gt;profound applications to long-standing mathematical problems. Most natural &lt;br/&gt;phenomena are nonlinear and possess singular behaviors. These are reflected &lt;br/&gt;in possible singular solutions to the differential equations which describe &lt;br/&gt;those phenomena. It is still challenging to have a complete mathematical &lt;br/&gt;understanding of these singular solutions. This proposal will address some &lt;br/&gt;of these basic problems. I will also try to find more solutions of these &lt;br/&gt;nonlinear equations -and apply them to studying basic problems in geometry &lt;br/&gt;and topology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0703985</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tian@math.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/08/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
