<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Track 1 GeoPrep: Building a Geoscience Pathway for High Need Long Island High Schools</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99313</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jill L. Karsten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The GeoPrep Program at Stony Brook University represents a collaboration between a number of University partners and the Office of Educational Programs at Brookhaven National Laboratory. University partners include: the Department of Geosciences in the College of Arts and Sciences, the Department of Technology and Society in the College of Engineering and Applied Sciences, the Center for Environmental and Molecular Science, the Institute for Terrestrial and Planetary Atmospheres, the Marine Science Research Center, the Long Island Group Advancing Science Education, the Science and Technology Entry Programs, the Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation, and the Alliance for Graduate Education and the Professoriate. The goal of the project is to increase the participation in the geosciences by underrepresented minority (URM) students by introducing Earth science teachers and students from high need high school districts on Long Island to the broad array of disciplines contained within the geosciences. The aim of the project is to foster a further interest in pursuing geoscience as an undergraduate major in college and thereby increase participation in the geosciences by underrepresented minority students. Students will be exposed to an array of inquiry-based geoscience activities through high level academic year research experiences, summer research experiences, and enhanced teacher training programs that utilize facilities and resources available to the project partners. Project activities will tie in to existing state-wide networks of minority student programs that are supported by both NSF and the New York State Department of Education. Over the two years of GeoPrep, over 800 high school students and 45 teachers will be served.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0703632</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>R. David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bynum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbynum@notes.cc.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gilbert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hanson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Gilbert.Hanson@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kamazima</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lwiza</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>klwiza@notes.cc.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Colle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brian.colle@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ferguson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>David.Ferguson@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1697</Code>
      <Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1697</Code>
      <Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
