<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium on Polymer Surfaces and Interfaces, Chicago, Illinois, March 25-29, 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>3000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070012</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;Polymer surfaces and interfaces control the properties that define function in the emerging areas&lt;br/&gt;of biotechnology and nanotechnology. Although the general topic of polymer surfaces and&lt;br/&gt;interfaces has a long and rich history, the evolution of new polymer chemistries, fabrication&lt;br/&gt;approaches, characterization methods, and targeted applications provides unquestionable&lt;br/&gt;motivation for an inter-disciplinary symposium to foster discussions and cross-breeding of ideas&lt;br/&gt;and understanding to push this critical field forward. Accordingly, I and three co-organizers&lt;br/&gt;[Professor Jeff Youngblood (Purdue University), Professor Rigoberto Advincula (University of&lt;br/&gt;Houston), and Dr. Ying Chang (Academia Sinica Taiwan)] are leading the organization of a&lt;br/&gt;focused symposium entitled: Polymer Surfaces and Interfaces at the upcoming national meeting&lt;br/&gt;of the American Chemical Society in Chicago during March 2007.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;This symposium will consist of six focused topic sessions that will not only demonstrate the&lt;br/&gt;common foundation of polymer surfaces and interfaces across a wide range of applications and&lt;br/&gt;approaches, but most importantly the program will encourage the development of collaborations&lt;br/&gt;and cross-breeding of ideas. The focused topic sessions include: 1.) Polymer Brushes, 2.)&lt;br/&gt;Macromolecular Assemblies, 3.) Responsive Surfaces, Interfaces, and Films, 4.) Biopolymer /&lt;br/&gt;Bioactive Surfaces, 5.) Chemistry at Surfaces and Interfaces, 6.) Adhesion and Interfacial&lt;br/&gt;Physics. These six topics represent the current state-of-the-art research in the field of polymer&lt;br/&gt;surfaces and interfaces. The range of chemistries, processes, characterization methods, and&lt;br/&gt;applications within each of these focused sessions will provide a unique program to encourage&lt;br/&gt;collaboration and education among established and young researchers. The foundation for this&lt;br/&gt;program has been set with an extensive and diverse list of invited speakers that represent the&lt;br/&gt;leaders in research in the topics covered by the six focused topic sessions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this symposium will emerge from the diversity of the co-organizing&lt;br/&gt;committee, the diversity of the invited speakers, and the diversity of the general participants at&lt;br/&gt;the national meeting of the American Chemical Society. This symposium will encourage the&lt;br/&gt;exposure of young researchers in the field of polymer surfaces and interfaces by inviting several&lt;br/&gt;speakers that are either young professors or post-doctoral researchers, while also providing a&lt;br/&gt;poster session for the general participation of graduate student researchers. Furthermore, the&lt;br/&gt;participation of women and under-represented minorities will be encouraged through direct&lt;br/&gt;invitations and widely-distributed advertisements. This organization will not only provide&lt;br/&gt;opportunities for research scientists from all backgrounds to discuss current challenges and&lt;br/&gt;approaches in polymer surface and interface research, but it will provide an opportunity for&lt;br/&gt;young researchers to be educated and prepared for their future careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0704222</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alfred</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crosby</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crosby@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/04/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>Hadley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1773</Code>
      <Text>POLYMERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
