<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>FRG: Electronic Properties of Polymer-Derived Amorphous Ceramics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070009</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION:&lt;br/&gt;Polymer-derived ceramics are a new class of high temperature ceramics synthesized by direct thermal decomposition of a polymeric precursor. Compared to conventional ceramics, polymer-derived ceramics possess a set of excellent thermo-mechanical and electronic properties, as well as having flexible processing conditions. These materials are suitable for many energy, space and military applications. Examples include micro-sensors for detecting elevated temperatures, pressures at high temperature, and radiation environments. Understanding the structure-electronic property relationships of polymer-derived ceramics could serve as a guide for further design of better sensors and for the development of new multifunctional materials. Training of students will help to prepare America's next generation of scientists and engineers for materials and related industries, and to maintain and enhance U.S. leadership in this cutting-edge area. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS:&lt;br/&gt;Polymer-derived ceramics with systematically varied structures/compositions will be synthesized by tailoring the chemistry of the polymeric precursors. Nuclear magnetic resonance, Fourier transform inferred spectroscopy, Raman spectroscopy, small angle x-ray scattering, high resolution transmission electron microscopy, and scanning tunneling microscopy will be utilized to study the structures of polymer-derived ceramics synthesized from carefully tailored precursors. Electron paramagnetic resonance and optical spectroscopy will be used to investigate the electronic and defect structures of the materials. The structural information will be related to the electronic behavior of polymer-derived ceramics, which will be characterized by measuring their conductivity, Hall effect and piezoresistivity. The proposed research will enable better tuning of the material properties to different technical needs, and present opportunities for creating new materials. The proposed research will also provide a guideline for using this new class of materials in emerging technical applications, such as, high-temperature micro-sensors. Graduate students will be trained in the use of all of the aforementioned state-of-the-art techniques. They will also have the opportunity during summers to carry out research in national laboratories or industry. This project will also train undergraduate students by involving them into specially-designed research programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0706526</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linan</FirstName>
      <LastName>An</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lan@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lzhai@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ligong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lig_zhang@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1774</Code>
      <Text>CERAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1589</Code>
      <Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
