<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Fahmida N. Chowdhury</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal # 6632920&lt;br/&gt;PI: Murphy, Mary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding Interracial Interactions: How Social Identity Threat Influences Affect, Cognition, and Behavior during Intergroup Contact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract: Why are interracial interactions so difficult for many people to navigate? What are people's concerns during interracial interactions that keep them from going smoothly? This research takes a social identity threat approach to examine how two factors regulatory focus and situational cuesinfluence people's affective, cognitive and behavioral experiences during interracial interactions. Five experimental studies are proposed under the sponsorship of Dr. Jennifer Richeson at Northwestern University. These studies test causal hypotheses about how identity threat influences affective, cognitive and behavioral outcomes during interracial interactions. The proposed studies will investigate two potential influences on the experiences of social identity threat among Whites and ethnic/racial minorities during interracial interaction: 1) individuals' self-regulatory focus, and 2) situational cues within the interaction context. Ethnic minority and Whites' anxiety before the interactions, behavior during the interactions, and cognitive depletion and satisfaction resulting from the interracial interactions will be measured. Furthermore, we will test whether shifts in regulatory focus and/or particular situational cues in the interaction context can reduce identity threat, opening the door for more positive interracial contact in the future. Taking a relational view of interracial interactions, this work examines the processes by which regulatory focus and situational cues affect experiences of identity threat and its affective, cognitive, and behavioral outcomes from the perspectives of both majority and minority group members. This research will make novel theoretical contributions to the existing literatures on interracial interactions and social identity threat, as well as provide practical guidance about how interracial interactions might be structured to reduce identity threat and facilitate smooth exchange and more enjoyment for both minority and majority group members. In addition, this research will allow the PI to broaden her research focus and learn new methodology and skills under the mentorship of the premier investigator of interracial interactions. Learning interaction methodology and theory from this expert will be a key objective of her training. This research will expand and contribute to identity threat theory and provide a better understanding of the processes by which cues affect the psychology and behaviors present during interracial interactions. Finally, the fellowship will support an underrepresented minority scientist in behavioral science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0706749</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murphy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>04/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Murphy Mary C</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943062356</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber/>
      <StreetAddress/>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
