<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Influence of interfacial stress on the stability of epitaxial films</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>46832</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Fried&lt;br/&gt;0706460&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Epitaxially-grown thin alloy films are essential components&lt;br/&gt;in many nano- and microscale devices used in the electronics and&lt;br/&gt;other industries. Unfortunately, the growth of planar strained&lt;br/&gt;films is susceptible to instabilities. These instabilities are&lt;br/&gt;often manifested by the formation of surface ripples, surface&lt;br/&gt;cusps, and island-like mounds such as quantum dots and quantum&lt;br/&gt;wires. The demand for films with precisely tailored micro- and&lt;br/&gt;nanostructures has led to an extensive literature concerned with&lt;br/&gt;morphological instabilities during the epitaxy of thin alloy&lt;br/&gt;films. To date, attention has focused primarily on instabilities&lt;br/&gt;that arise from a mismatch in lattice parameters between the film&lt;br/&gt;and the substrate and surface diffusion. However, interfacial&lt;br/&gt;stress, which may strongly influence the formation of surface&lt;br/&gt;patterns, has received almost no attention. Moreover, because of&lt;br/&gt;the geometric complications associated with the description of&lt;br/&gt;evolving surfaces in three space dimensions, studies of&lt;br/&gt;growth-stress interactions have thus far confined attention to&lt;br/&gt;two-dimensional theories, wherein the interface is a curve. &lt;br/&gt;Additionally, no theory yet accounts for the influence of surface&lt;br/&gt;stress on phase segregation and related pattern formation,&lt;br/&gt;processes that occur during epitaxy. In this project, the&lt;br/&gt;investigator and colleagues:&lt;br/&gt; 1. Perform stability analyses and numerical simulations&lt;br/&gt; designed to explore the role of surface stress in the stability&lt;br/&gt; of epitaxially growing films. &lt;br/&gt; 2. Extend the existing two-dimensional theory to three space&lt;br/&gt; dimensions. &lt;br/&gt; 3. Develop a theory that describes the interaction of growth&lt;br/&gt; and phase segregation during the epitaxy of alloys. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator and his colleagues develop and analyze&lt;br/&gt;mathematical models, and carry out numerical simulations, of the&lt;br/&gt;behavior and characteristics of epitaxially grown thin films. An&lt;br/&gt;increased understanding of the morphological stability of these&lt;br/&gt;films allows for progress and innovation in a variety of&lt;br/&gt;strategically important applications. For instance, in the&lt;br/&gt;electronics industry, epitaxially grown multi-layers have been&lt;br/&gt;used to increase the storage capacity of hard drives and are now&lt;br/&gt;being studied for possible improvements. Progress rests directly&lt;br/&gt;on the ability to control small-scale features that form during&lt;br/&gt;growth. Another compelling example of the importance of&lt;br/&gt;epitaxial films is provided by recently proposed hybrid&lt;br/&gt;organic/inorganic devices capable of detecting airborne&lt;br/&gt;contaminants. These devices combine a monolayer of sensing&lt;br/&gt;molecules on a semiconductor transducer grown via molecular beam&lt;br/&gt;epitaxy. A precisely tailored surface structure is necessary to&lt;br/&gt;ensure that the sensing molecules adhere correctly to the&lt;br/&gt;transducer and perform reliably. Epitaxial films also have&lt;br/&gt;potential in the development of optical semiconductors for&lt;br/&gt;applications such as variable wavelength lasers. The devices&lt;br/&gt;have a wide range of potential applications, including the&lt;br/&gt;detection of toxic gases from vehicle exhaust, factories,&lt;br/&gt;accidents, fires, natural disasters, etc. With a variable&lt;br/&gt;wavelength laser, it is possible to shorten measurement times&lt;br/&gt;from 1-2 minutes to 1 second, allowing for more rapid containment&lt;br/&gt;and evacuation during emergencies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0706460</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eliot</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fried</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>budd@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7446</Code>
      <Text>MATH PRIORITY SOLICITATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7454</Code>
      <Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7303</Code>
      <Text>MATH SCI PRIORITY AREA: INTERDISCIPLINAR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
