<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Extensive Photometric and Spectroscopic Survey of M33</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>104181</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharina Lodders</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Sarajedini (University of Florida) will reduce and analyze archival imaging data from the Canada-France-Hawaii and Subaru telescopes in order to derive positions, magnitudes and colors for field stars, cluster stars, and the clusters themselves in M33. The resultant catalog will contain the deepest and widest-field ground-based photometry for M33 to-date. The field color-magnitude diagrams (CMDs) will be analyzed with synthetic CMD techniques to derive the star formation and chemical enrichment history of the field, while the cluster CMDs will be analyzed by comparison to theoretical isochrones and empirical cluster fiducials in order to estimate their ages and metallcities. These results will be used in conjunction with the integrated colors of the clusters to further constrain their ages and metallicities. The positions will be used to help characterize the structure of M33 and to search for substructure in its outer parts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to disseminating all of the results of the catalog of M33 photometrry and astrometry via a searchable web interface, Dr. Sarajedini and his group will also write a cook book for the analysis performed on the data. Undergraduate and graduate students will also be trained by working on certain aspects of this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0707277</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ata</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sarajedini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ata@astro.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
