<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometric Analysis, Wave Optics, and Geometric Gravity Models</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>353000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0707003&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Arlie O. Petters&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research project is to develop a mathematical&lt;br/&gt;theory of the shadow patterns cast in the cosmos by the action of&lt;br/&gt;gravity on light. The project aims to characterize the pointwise&lt;br/&gt;total magnification and magnification cross section functions of&lt;br/&gt;these shadow patterns, both in the geometric and wave optics&lt;br/&gt;limits for certain key gravity models. This study requires a&lt;br/&gt;geometric analysis of caustic singularities, diffraction&lt;br/&gt;integrals, and asymptotics in a curved spacetime setting. The&lt;br/&gt;proposed research would lay a platform for generalization a study&lt;br/&gt;of shadow patterns to arbitrary Lorentzian manifolds, which in&lt;br/&gt;turn would lead to a new exploration in Lorentzian geometry. The&lt;br/&gt;findings will also yield a detailed gravitational lensing&lt;br/&gt;comparison of current key geometric gravity models like general&lt;br/&gt;relativity, PPN models, and braneworld gravity, allowing for&lt;br/&gt;predictions that may test these gravity models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Shadow patterns are all around us. We drive through them on the&lt;br/&gt;way to work and swim among them in pools. Similar patterns are&lt;br/&gt;also cast throughout the universe by the gravitational fields of&lt;br/&gt;stars, galaxies, black holes, dark matter, and dark energy.&lt;br/&gt;Perhaps even more mysterious is that these shadow patterns are&lt;br/&gt;connected with one of the profound questions about the nature of&lt;br/&gt;our physical world -- namely, whether physical space has more&lt;br/&gt;than the familiar three spatial dimensions of length, width, and&lt;br/&gt;height. This research will employ gravity's cosmic shadow&lt;br/&gt;patterns to explore the nature of black holes and dark matter,&lt;br/&gt;and the dimensionality of physical space. The work will also&lt;br/&gt;formulate predictions that test Einstein's general theory of&lt;br/&gt;relativity and other gravity models. The project is&lt;br/&gt;interdisciplinary and creates a synergistic interaction between&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, physics, and astronomy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0707003</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arlie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Petters</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>petters@math.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
