<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Iterative Methods for Nonlinear Equations and Optimization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>263084</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Kelley&lt;br/&gt;0707220&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The principal investigator studies numerical methods for the&lt;br/&gt;solution of nonlinear equations and optimization problems with a&lt;br/&gt;focus on continuation methods, nonsmooth problems, and multilevel&lt;br/&gt;methods for integral equations. The main topics of the research&lt;br/&gt;are (1) the development and analysis of multilevel continuation&lt;br/&gt;algorithms for optimization problems with integral equation&lt;br/&gt;constraints and the application of those methods in simulating&lt;br/&gt;atomic and molecular fluids, (2) the design and analysis of&lt;br/&gt;continuation/quasi-Newton methods for nonsmooth nonlinear least&lt;br/&gt;squares, with applications to calibration of models of blood&lt;br/&gt;flow, (3) continued study of the conditioning of the linear&lt;br/&gt;systems and eigenproblems that arise when pseudo-arclength&lt;br/&gt;continuation is used in bifurcation analysis, and (4) multi-model&lt;br/&gt;methods in which one physical model, based on differential or&lt;br/&gt;integral equations, for example, is used as a preconditioner for&lt;br/&gt;a solver which is based on a more accurate, more expensive to&lt;br/&gt;evaluate model, such as a molecular dynamics or stochastic&lt;br/&gt;simulation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Nonlinear equations and optimization problems are commonly&lt;br/&gt;encountered in science and engineering. Motivated by&lt;br/&gt;applications in chemistry and medicine, the principal&lt;br/&gt;investigator studies equations with multiple solutions, the&lt;br/&gt;challenge being to determine which of those solutions represents&lt;br/&gt;the real world and which cannot be seen in actual physical&lt;br/&gt;systems, and optimization problems for which standard methods and&lt;br/&gt;computer codes fail. This work should lead to new approaches&lt;br/&gt;useful in many branches of science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0707220</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kelley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tim_kelley@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
      <CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
