<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF Workshop on Structures and Fire: Research Needs and State-of-the Art</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>43961</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mahendra P. Singh</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fire represents one of the most severe environmental hazards for the built infrastructure, and high temperature-resistant (fire safety) design is one of the key considerations in the design and fabrication of civil, mechanical, aerospace and nuclear structures. Based on a number of high level reports and white papers (such as the World Trade Center building performance investigation report that was presented to Congressional Committees) there is, at present, a serious lack of test data, numerical models, design tools and trained personnel for undertaking performance based fire safety design. A 2-day workshop will be held to identify research needs and state-of-the-art for structural design and behavior in fires. &lt;br/&gt;The format selected for the workshop allows for the attendees (which include university full-time faculty, principally those in the Structural Engineering, and/or Architectural Engineering disciplines) to better familiarize themselves with the background, current practices, and emerging issues in structural fire engineering, with emphasis on their relationships to the traditional structural and architectural engineering fields. Some of these topics were prompted or accelerated by the post-9/11 emergency response and public safety concerns, while others have long been acknowledged as matters for future study or professional debate relative to advancements in fire engineering and Performance-Based Design (PBD). Other industrialized countries, in particular those in Europe and the Pacific Rim, have already achieved significant progress in fire PBD, and all this knowledge needs to be imported, absorbed, qualified, further refined, disseminated, and adapted to US practices. For this reason, two notable experts and researchers from overseas have agreed to present their insights on the overall state-of-the-art advancements and its voids.&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will have impact on society by increasing the knowledge in an area where this country lacks expertise. The workshop announcement will be broadly disseminated and a select a group of attendees that represent a diverse community of faculty will be invited. Particular effort will be given to attracting underrepresented groups and early career faculty. This workshop is a seed that will grow an educated nation in structural fire performance. This workshop will develop a state-of-the-art report on "research and training needs in the structural fire safety field". University faculty and leading international experts from academia and industry will attend the workshop. Based on the workshop presentations, focus group meetings, and other deliberations, a "Fire Safety Research and Training Needs" report will be prepared for NSF. This report will help NSF program managers develop strategies for funding fire research proposals in the coming years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Douglas A. Foutch, Program Director, Structural Systems and Hazard Mitigation of Structures</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/26/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0707360</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Venkatesh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kodur</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kodur@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/26/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
