<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NER: Asymmetric End-functionalization of Nonaligned Carbon Nanotubes For DNA-directed Self-assembling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>105455</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal was received in response to Nanoscale Science and Engineering initiative NSF 06-595, category NER. The objective is to develop a general chemical modification method to asymmetrically end-functionalize nonaligned carbon nanotubes with different chemical reagents. The approach takes advantage of the reversible paring and denaturing of DNA double helices to form DNA brushes that support nonaligned carbon nanotubes for sequential end-functionalization. The research will focus on the chemistry for end-attachment of DNA chains of different base sequences; biomimetic self-assembling of the end-functionalized carbon nanotubes through the DNA pairing interactions; and control of the self-assembled structures for their effective incorporation into functional systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The accomplishment of this project will lead to not only a strong fundamental understanding of DNA chemistries for tailoring nanotube self-assembled structures, but also developing new carbon nanotube-based functional systems useful for optoelectronic and many other applications to potentially accelerate the commercialization of nanotube electronic and optical devices. The asymmetrically end-functionalized carbon nanotubes can also be used as nanoscale building blocks for developing new materials that synergistically combine the unique properties of carbon nanotubes and DNA chains. This project will enhance student training and learning by incorporating the research results into undergraduate and graduate courses. The results of this project will be further disseminated through journal publications and conference presentations to benefit the general scientific community in the multidisciplinary field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0708055</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liming</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liming.dai@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Dayton</Name>
      <CityName>DAYTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>454690104</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9372292919</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 COLLEGE PARK AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1676</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>081E</Code>
      <Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1676</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
