<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Manifolds and calculus of functors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>286027</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0708601&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Thomas G. Goodwillie&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All of the proposed research is connected with the calculus of&lt;br/&gt;functors in its various forms. First, the main results of&lt;br/&gt;homotopy calculus will be extended to a natural and high degree&lt;br/&gt;of generality. Geometric language will be used to develop the&lt;br/&gt;analogy with ordinary differential calculus, so that a suitable&lt;br/&gt;homotopical category gets something like tangent and cotangent&lt;br/&gt;spaces, spaces of tensor fields, connections, differential&lt;br/&gt;operators, and so on. The language should be useful both for&lt;br/&gt;clarifying the ideas and for suggesting new directions. Second,&lt;br/&gt;the derivative of algebraic K-theory will be investigated in a&lt;br/&gt;general setting. Third, the part of manifold theory which in some&lt;br/&gt;sense comes next after stable pseudoisotopy (it could be called&lt;br/&gt;metastable pseudoisotopy) will be explored from the calculus&lt;br/&gt;viewpoint. Its derivatives will be studied by methods analogous&lt;br/&gt;to the Hochschild and cyclic homology methods that were relevant&lt;br/&gt;to the stable theory; where loops in a manifold were involved,&lt;br/&gt;now there should be maps of rank two graphs into the manifold. In&lt;br/&gt;addition to working out the metastable analogue of cyclic&lt;br/&gt;homology, there is the more fundamental question of seeking to&lt;br/&gt;understand the metastable phenomena in non-manifold terms as&lt;br/&gt;Waldhausen K-theory does for the stable theory, and calculus may&lt;br/&gt;hold clues to this. There is a sequence: (0) homotopy theory,&lt;br/&gt;where calculus leads to trees, (1) algebraic K-theory, where&lt;br/&gt;calculus leads to circles, and (2) metastable theory, where&lt;br/&gt;calculus leads to rank two graphs. One thing to be worked out is&lt;br/&gt;the relevant kinds of interactions between all these kinds of&lt;br/&gt;graphs in a manifold.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Functor calculus involves extremes of abstraction, but it has&lt;br/&gt;down-to-earth roots. It is an organizing principle named for&lt;br/&gt;resemblance to the ordinary calculus of Newton and&lt;br/&gt;Leibniz. Sometimes a fact about numbers is best proved by placing&lt;br/&gt;it in a context where the number is part of a huge family of&lt;br/&gt;numbers -- a numerical function. Properties of the function can&lt;br/&gt;lead, by general theorems of calculus that at first seem like&lt;br/&gt;magic, to a computation of the number. The story here is similar:&lt;br/&gt;sometimes a fact about some mathematical entity -- not a number&lt;br/&gt;now, but perhaps a geometric object of some kind -- is best&lt;br/&gt;proved by placing it in a context where the object is part of a&lt;br/&gt;huge family of such objects -- a functor -- and using some magic&lt;br/&gt;of more recent vintage. One area of application of functor&lt;br/&gt;calculus is manifold topology. Another is homotopy theory. A&lt;br/&gt;manifold is a kind of mathematical system involving many&lt;br/&gt;variables. These are ubiquitous in science and&lt;br/&gt;mathematics. Manifold topology studies such systems for their own&lt;br/&gt;sake, treating them as geometric objects; an N-variable system is&lt;br/&gt;viewed as an N-dimensional object. Homotopy theory studies&lt;br/&gt;manifolds and other objects from a point of view in which a great&lt;br/&gt;deal of information is ignored, leaving only the coarsest&lt;br/&gt;features to consider. This change in viewpoint is a powerful&lt;br/&gt;idea, because this process of distillation leads to conceptual&lt;br/&gt;clarity and new methods. Besides being a key tool in the study&lt;br/&gt;of manifolds, homotopy theory is a branch of topology in its own&lt;br/&gt;right. Thus geometry grows, surprisingly and naturally, as the&lt;br/&gt;years go by. In functor calculus it becomes possible in a sense&lt;br/&gt;to view all of homotopy theory as a geometric object.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0708601</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goodwillie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tomg@math.brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brown University</Name>
      <CityName>Providence</CityName>
      <ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
