<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NER: Nanophotonic Superpolariton Junctions: tunable photon-polariton transistors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>123726</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric G Johnson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: The intellectual merit of this study consists of developing active Nanophotonic Superpolariton Junctions (NSJ) by inserting light-guiding optical fibers into tapered glass-membrane nanopores to form nano-scale transistors of light. Actively adjusting the insertion distance and the permittivity of a 'soft' dieletric material between the fiber and nanopore is expected to enhance field intensity and detection sensitivity at the NSJ tip 35-fold. Active adjustments improve transfer of energy from incoming light to oscillating, surface electrons (called 'polaritons') at the tip while the unique NSJ geometry reduces 'polariton' losses. Supporting this study develops an active alternative to existing passive light-to-polariton transistors that are difficult to prepare and produce &lt;10-fold increases in field intensity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This study will educate three graduate students, including two underrepresented females, in active nanostructures, photonics and sensing within a highly collaborative environment of 70 faculty who fabricate and analyze nano-scale devices like microarrays and lab-on-chips. The social impact of this study includes having undergraduates demonstrate NSJs in hands-on instructional modules prepared for class demonstrations, summer workshops and lab experiences for community college and high school students across the state. These demonstrations are part of a 5-year NSF (STEP)-sponsored collaboration co-initiated by the PI that plans to increase participation, improve retention, and ultimately double enrollment of underrepresented minorities in STEM courses. The economic impact of this study arises from NSJ applications that include photonic circuits, high-density magneto-optic data storage, highly-sensitive spectroscopic nano/bio/chemical sensors and high-resolution near-field optical microscopy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0709456</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
      <LastName>White</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>white@chem.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roper</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dkroper@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1676</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>099E</Code>
      <Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1676</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
