<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Gordon-Kenan Graduate Research Seminar on Catecholamines, Oxford, England, August 3-5, 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>J. Steven de Belle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Gordon-Kenan Graduate Research Seminar on Catecholamines (GRS-CA) is a unique opportunity for junior researchers to educate colleagues about their work, to learn about others'' work, and to forge professional relationships across countries and disciplines. In the last three and ½ decades, basic discoveries in the molecular biology of catecholamine receptors and neural signaling systems have been the driving force in our understanding of central and peripheral nervous system function at many levels. Successful catecholamine research requires students to understand brain-behavior issues encompassing neurobiology, neurotanatomy, neurology, pharmacology, molecular biology, genetics, and behavioral neuroscience. The Gordon Research Conference on Catecholamines (GRC-CA) has traditionally embraced young scientists. In an attempt to further enhance the GRC-CA experience for graduate students and postdoctoral fellows, a two-day GRS-CA will commence on Friday evening (August 3, 2007) and continue through Sunday. Graduate students and Post-Doctoral scholars will make all of the scientific presentations, faculty mentors will be present to facilitate research discussions, and also to highlight the important issues (methodology, topics, etc) of modern catecholamine research. The GRS-CA planning committee is committed to diversity in gender, research level (pre/post-doctoral), ethnicity, geography, and research discipline. A diverse pool of attendees further broadens the range of education and perspective for GRS speakers and audience members. Overall, the GRS-CA is an opportunity to incorporate the next generation of scientists into the infrastructure of catecholamine research</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0709607</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
      <LastName>Becker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbbecker@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
