<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Laboratory Studies Required to Quantify Airglow in CO2 Planets</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>285888</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas S. Statler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>AST0709173&lt;br/&gt;Kalogerakis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award Dr. Konstantinos Kalogerakis will conduct experiments to (1) measure the rate coefficients for O + O and O + O2 recombination in the presence of CO2; (2) determine their temperature dependence in the range 160 400 K, relevant to the CO2 on planets such as Mars and Venus; and (3) investigate the yields of the O2 ground and excited states produced following O-atom recombination. These laboratory measurements are necessary for a quantitative understanding and reliable modeling of the atmospheres of the CO2 planets and their airglow. Understanding processes involving atomic oxygen is crucial for the study and modeling of composition, energy transfer, airglow, and transport dynamics in planetary atmospheres. Significant gaps and uncertainties exist in our understanding of the above processes, and often the relevant input from laboratory measurements is missing or outdated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These laboratory investigations address specific problems in planetary science and supply basic physical measurements currently needed to interpret and model important O-atom processes in the upper atmospheres of Mars and Venus. The measurements are needed to quantify airglow in these two planets and probe their atmospheric dynamics by remote sensing. Dr. Kalogerakis' laboratory has in-depth experience and a strong performance record in conducting these types of experiments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of the work will benefit modelers of planetary atmospheres, theoreticians, and optical aeronomers. They will enhance the scientific returns on past and future missions to Venus and Mars. Application of basic chemistry and physics to the study of collisional processes on a fundamental level is also critical for understanding the operation of lasers, especially high-power chemical lasers. Finally, the project will contribute to the training and research experience of one or more postdoctoral fellows and summer undergraduate students.&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0709173</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Konstantinos</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kalogerakis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ksk@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dusan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pejakovic</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dusan.pejakovic@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SRI International</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508592651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
