<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CRI: CRD -- QuRiNet: A Wide-Area Outdoor Wireless Mesh Test-Bed</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>280000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal #: CNS 07-09264 &lt;br/&gt;PI(s): Mohapatra, Prasant&lt;br/&gt; Boucher, Virginia; Liu, Xin &lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of California - Davis&lt;br/&gt; Davis, Ca 95618-0000&lt;br/&gt;Title: CRD: QuRiNet: A Wide-Area Outdoor Wireless Mesh Test-Bed&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Proposed:&lt;br/&gt;This project, building an outdoor mesh Network so that the testbed is an interference free environment, facilitates access, provides measurement data and evaluation results. The testbed complements other testbeds deployed in environments susceptible to external interference. Wireless mesh networks (WMNs) have seen increased deployments in the areas of broadband home networking and enterprise networking. In addition, they are also being deployed at the community and municipal level, for extended service provider coverage to end users, and in areas lacking wired infrastructure. This project supports expanding the size, scope, performance, and robustness of current network, and facilitating the access and usability as a community resource. Quail Ridge, used for environmental research by the ecologists at UC Davis, is part of the University of California Natural Reserve System (NRS). The project continues ongoing efforts in the deployment of the Quail Ridge Wireless Mesh Network (QuRiNet) at the Quail Ridge Natural Reserve. It is located about twenty two miles west of Davis. This work in the reserve is expected to provide wireless coverage for over 2,000 acres of hilly terrain in the face of various topological and technological challenges. The mesh network enables a testbed for carrying out further research on the design and development of WMNs. Moreover, it will also be utilized for ecological research to study the flora and fauna in the region. Proposed is the addition of 20 more nodes to the existing 10 in the reserve expanding it to a 30-node mesh network. The status and current progress on QuRiNet are being updated at a web site.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The infrastructure contributes to education and training of students. Part of the research will be used as projects in graduate courses in computer and mobile wireless networks. Moreover, the testbed will be used for evaluation of research ideas. QuRiNet facilitates remote access for monitoring activities, recording data, and collecting measurements from various sensing devices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0709264</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liu@cs.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boucher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vlboucher@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Prasant</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mohapatra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmohapatra@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7359</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
