<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>III-CXT: Collaborative Research: A High-Throughput Approach to the Assignment of Orthologous Genes Based on Genome Rearrangement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>190000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Vasant G. Honavar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract &lt;br/&gt;Orthologous genes, or orthologs, are genes in different species &lt;br/&gt;that have evolved directly from a common ancestral gene. &lt;br/&gt;Genome-scale assignment of orthologs is a fundamental and &lt;br/&gt;challenging problem in computational biology, and has a wide range &lt;br/&gt;of applications in comparative genomics and functional genomics. &lt;br/&gt;This project continues the development of the parsimony approach &lt;br/&gt;for assigning orthologs between closely related genomes &lt;br/&gt;which essentially attempts to transform &lt;br/&gt;one genome into another by the smallest number of genome rearrangement &lt;br/&gt;events including reversal, translocation, fusion, and fission, as well as &lt;br/&gt;gene duplication events. The project addresses three key algorithmic &lt;br/&gt;problems including (i) signed reversal distance with &lt;br/&gt;duplicates, (ii) signed transposition distance with duplicates, &lt;br/&gt;and (iii) minimum common string partition. Efficient solutions to each of &lt;br/&gt;these problems are combined and incorporated into a software system for &lt;br/&gt;ortholog assignment, called MSOAR. The project encompasses &lt;br/&gt;genome-wide analysis of orthologous (and paralogous) relationships on &lt;br/&gt;the human and mouse genomes to valdiate the approach, and more importantly, &lt;br/&gt;to address several important evolutionary biological questions including &lt;br/&gt;the characterization of gains and losses of duplicated genes in the &lt;br/&gt;two genomes, the elucidation of gene movements in one genome with respect &lt;br/&gt;to the other genome, and the quantification of different mechanisms of &lt;br/&gt;gene duplication. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The parsimony approach presents a novel method for performing genome-wide &lt;br/&gt;ortholog assignment that takes into account both gene sequences and locations. &lt;br/&gt;The above algorithmic problems are new in the literature and their solutions &lt;br/&gt;likely require the introduction of novel algorithm design and analysis &lt;br/&gt;techniques. The questions regarding gene duplication and quantification of &lt;br/&gt;the duplication mechanisms in model species are of fundamental importance &lt;br/&gt;in evolutionary biology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As ortholog assignment is a fundamental problem in comparative genomics and &lt;br/&gt;has become a routine practice in almost all areas of genomics, MSOAR &lt;br/&gt;will find itself a wide range of applications in biology and genomics. &lt;br/&gt;Moreover, the research will provide the training opportunity for two computer &lt;br/&gt;science graduate students in the interdisciplinary field of computational biology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Information concerning this NSF project will be provided at the website: &lt;br/&gt;http://msoar.cs.ucr.edu/</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0710945</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liqing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lqzhang@cs.vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
