<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS - SGER - Chicago Spectrum Observatory Proposal</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99970</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alhussein A. Abouzeid</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research: (1) creates and deploys a spectrum observatory platform to collect spectral occupancy data (30 MHz to 3 GHz) for Chicago for one year; (2) analyzes the data on a weekly basis to identify anomalies (occupancy and vacancy); (3) projects future spectrum occupancy, including seasonal trends; and (4) results in a wide distribution of the findings to the wireless R&amp;D and regulatory communities via the Web, workshops, conference and journal papers. This research provides a quantum enhancement in the raw quantity and quality of the spectrum occupancy information available to wireless researchers and regulators.&lt;br/&gt;This grant supports collaborative research across and between academia, industry, and government entities enabling the rapid development of new wireless devices and networking concepts. In turn, the availability of this information and the techniques used provide a useful education platform, initially supporting graduate education at IIT. Minority students and women are engaged in the research, thereby deriving the ongoing benefit from this new knowledge. The US government communications policy-makers derive the greatest early benefit from this research. Currently information on spectrum occupancy is spotty at best, leading policy-makers to use worst-case analysis techniques that yield conservative policies and sub-optimal utilization of this scarce resource. Novel technologies including software definable and cognitive radios require an improved understanding of spectrum utilization to determine the most beneficial spectrum policy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0711094</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>LoCicero</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>03/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hood@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roberson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dennis.roberson@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
