<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Germany-U.S. Summer Research Program in Chemistry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>103272</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Division of Chemistry and the Office of International Science and Engineering supports a Research Experience for Undergraduate (REU) site to foster undergraduate exchange between the United States and Germany. Tamara Nameroff and her colleagues in the Office of International Affairs of the American Chemical Society will direct this pilot program. Collaboration with current Chemistry REU site directors will help ensure the success of this trial. The program will expand participation of US chemistry undergraduates in RISE (a summer undergraduate research program of the Deutscher Akademischer Austausch Dienst (DAAD)) and place an equal number of DAAD-funded, German undergraduate researchers in Chemistry REU sites in the US. Participants also will be provided the opportunity to present their research results at the Fall, 2007 meeting of the American Chemical Society. Students will improve their research skills and gain experience working with multicultural teams and communicating across international borders. The program will build on the existing NSF-REU and DAAD-RISE structures and promote the value of international partnerships to other countries and to other scientific and engineering disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0711786</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tamara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nameroff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>t_nameroff@acs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Armando</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rodriguez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c_rodriguez@acs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Chemical Society (ACS)</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200364800</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2028724600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1155 16th St NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
