<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: International Travel Grant for U.S. Team to Attend 4th UJNR Workshop on Soil Structure Interaction (March 2007, Tsukuba, Japan)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mahendra P. Singh</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is an application for an International Travel Grant, which will be used to provide partial funding for 10 U.S. or more researchers to attend the 4th UJNR Workshop on Soil-Structure Interaction, to be held in Tsukuba, Japan in March 2007. This workshop is part of a series of U.S.-Japan workshops on this topic organized under the auspices of the United States&amp;#8722;Japan Cooperative Program in Natural Resources (UJNR), a government to government program established in 1964 to promote conservation of marine and terrestrial resources through cooperation in applied science and technology. Intellectual Merit: The purpose of these workshops has been to provide a platform for experts from both countries to present their work, exchange ideas, identify future research needs, and foster collaboration. The topics covered are: (1) current methods of soil-structure interaction and practices in U.S. and Japan ? geotechnical and structural points of view, (2) code provisions and limitations, (3) observed data, (4) observational arrays and testing facilities, (5) recent research results on how to implement those into practice, (6) additional research needs, and (7) additional observational arrays and testing facilities needed. The fourth workshop will enable to continue the tradition of these workshops, and provide a venue for the U.S. researchers to present new developments in resources for and results on research on soil-structure interaction in the U.S. (e.g. NEES and ANSS), learn about such developments in Japan (e.g. E-Defense), and identify potential collaborators. Broader Impacts: Soil-structure interaction is an important problem in earthquake engineering. Related advances in research and technology will contribute towards reduction of loss of life and injuries, and of monetary losses caused by earthquakes. The workshop proceedings will be broadly disseminated. Integration of Research and Education: The papers presented at the Workshop will be published in a CD Rom proceeding, which will be widely distributed free of charge, and as such readily available to be used as educational material for graduate courses in earthquake engineering. Integrating Diversity in NSF Supported Programs: This grant will enable to include in the U.S. team researchers from groups that are underrepresented in earthquake engineering (women and minorities), and early career researchers. The PI herself is a female research faculty.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0712053</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Todorovska</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mtodorov@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
