<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>LHC and MC4BSM Workshops</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal is to provide partial support for two successive workshops which are of direct relevance for the LHC. The workshops will be held from March 21-March 24 2007. The first workshop (MC4BSM) is to develop Monte Carlo codes for Beyond the Standard Model analysis. The codes would be developed by theorists during the workshop and then tested by both theorists and experimentalists so that there ease of use could be determined. The codes would then be made available on a website. The second workshop is the next phase of the LHC Olympics where competing teams of graduate students will be asked to determine what type of model best explains events generated by&lt;br/&gt;a PGS-4 detector simulation program designed by John Conway. The purpose is to lower the potential barrier for theorists to learn about LHC physics via black box data analysis. The focus will be on developing new tools for solving the LHC inverse problem. The broader Impact is thatthe LHC Olympics is an extremely useful teaching tool to challenge various groups of students to compete in analyzing data. Students and other participants will learn the tools necessary to analyze the type of data that the LHC is expected to generate. &lt;br/&gt;The MC4BSM will provide broad web-based access to Monte Carlo tools that will enable Theorists around the world to determine how their favorite model compares with actual date that will be generated during the running of the LHC.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0714734</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Herman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Verlinde</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>verlinde@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liantao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lianwang@Princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
