<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: A Unified Framework for Multilevel Parallelization on Deep Computing Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/10/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>228600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eun K. Park</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nikolopoulos, Dimitrios&lt;br/&gt;College of William and Mary&lt;br/&gt;CCF-0346867&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research activity involves the design, development and deployment&lt;br/&gt;of a programming framework for explicit multilevel parallelization using a &lt;br/&gt;global address space model. The framework targets the upcoming generation of &lt;br/&gt;Petaflop-class supercomputers, which are based on architectural substrates &lt;br/&gt;with multiple levels of on-chip and off-chip parallelism and deep memory &lt;br/&gt;hierarchies. The research addresses the need for increased productivity and &lt;br/&gt;utilization of the National supercomputing power, by attempting to close the &lt;br/&gt;gap between computer architecture innovation and parallel programming &lt;br/&gt;practices. The main goal of this activity is to reduce the &lt;br/&gt;programming effort required for mapping algorithmic parallelism to &lt;br/&gt;hierarchical hardware components with heterogeneous means for parallel &lt;br/&gt;execution and assist programmers in deriving balanced designs of layered parallel applications. The programming framework &lt;br/&gt;investigated in this research unifies parallel programming models and &lt;br/&gt;methodologies and enables faster adaptation of parallel code to new hardware &lt;br/&gt;platforms. Concurrently, it forms a basis for education and training of &lt;br/&gt;interdisciplinary student audiences in high performance programming. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The parallel programming component of this research is designed around &lt;br/&gt;standard C++ templates with notation for nested threads and iterators. &lt;br/&gt;The notations for parallelism are coupled with a templated representation of &lt;br/&gt;data, which allows for arbitrary partitioning, sharing, and coherence control &lt;br/&gt;at multiple levels of parallel execution constructs. While the programmer &lt;br/&gt;highlights nested parallelism, the orchestration and management of multigrain &lt;br/&gt;threads and data are delegated to the compiler and the runtime system. The &lt;br/&gt;research investigates novel methods for controlling the &lt;br/&gt;granularity of multilevel parallelism via vertical analysis of the program. &lt;br/&gt;Periodicity analysis and selective runtime tracing are used as means to &lt;br/&gt;derive effective data distribution and layout schemes without user&lt;br/&gt;intervention. Alongside runtime analysis, new resource-driven scheduling &lt;br/&gt;strategies and novel microprocessor features, including on-chip &lt;br/&gt;multithreading, on-chip SIMD parallelism and speculative execution, are &lt;br/&gt;incorporated into the parallelization and program optimization processes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0715051</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dimitrios</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nikolopoulos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dsn@cs.vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>4080</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED COMP RESEARCH PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
