<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Faculty Development Award</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Faculty Development Award supports the effective integration of research, teaching and service. Research goals are the design of solvent separation systems, principally nanoporous ceramic membranes for non-aqueous separations. The project includes the characterization of nanoscale liquid transport as a function of solvent type and material morphology, creation of novel surface-modified membranes with specific transport behavior, and the development of new techniques for elucidating solvent-surface interactions. The education goals include incorporation of green chemistry and green engineering themes. Service goals include professional development training and mentoring for students, particularly those from underrepresented groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Discovery Corps Fellowship Program is a pilot program seeking new postdoctoral and professional development models that combine research expertise with professional service. Discovery Corps Postdoctoral Fellows are eligible to apply for this Faculty Development Award.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0715003</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Geoffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bothun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gbothun@uri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/25/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Rhode Island</Name>
      <CityName>KINGSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028811967</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4018742635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>RESEARCH OFFICE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
