<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Experimental and Numerical Characterization of Thin Films in Three-Dimensional Porous Media</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24770</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030109</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Existing analyses on thin film characteristics in porous domains are often built on two- or&lt;br/&gt;quasi-three dimensional geometrically simple pore structures without explicitly&lt;br/&gt;accommodating pore connectivity in the third dimension. More in-depth numerical and&lt;br/&gt;experimental studies are needed to bridge the gap between two- and three dimensional&lt;br/&gt;experimental analyses as well as the gap between three-dimensional numerical and&lt;br/&gt;experimental analyses of pore-scale thin-film characteristics in granular porous media.&lt;br/&gt;Hence, the proposed research, which builds on our ongoing pore-scale interfacial&lt;br/&gt;research, aims at integrating experimental and numerical analyses for better&lt;br/&gt;understanding of thin film characteristics and thermodynamics in three-dimensional&lt;br/&gt;porous media consisting of interconnected arbitrary rough-walled pore geometries.&lt;br/&gt;In this 1-year extension proposal, we aim to develop a thermodynamically sound&lt;br/&gt;free-energy-based multiphase lattice-Boltzmann model (that can handle fluids with highdensity&lt;br/&gt;contrasts and implements thermodynamically-sound solid-fluid interactions). To&lt;br/&gt;obtain data for model verification, we will measure thin film characteristics related to&lt;br/&gt;film formation and distribution in a crushed volcanic tuff. This includes imaging water&lt;br/&gt;distributions as they progress from adsorbed films to capillary held water with increasing&lt;br/&gt;vapor pressure. Based on the images it is possible to estimate the critical separation&lt;br/&gt;distance at which capillary condensation takes place. The film characteristics will first be&lt;br/&gt;measured in geometrically simple two-dimensional flow channels using time-lapse digital&lt;br/&gt;microscopy, and subsequently using computerized microtomography (CMT) for more&lt;br/&gt;complex three-dimensional systems in crushed tuff samples. From the CMT images we&lt;br/&gt;will determine the location and the extent of the capillary condensed regions to be used to&lt;br/&gt;validate new model developments.&lt;br/&gt;Once the model is validated using the two-dimensional experimental data, the&lt;br/&gt;model will be used to simulate thin film formation and distributions in a threedimensional&lt;br/&gt;natural porous medium with hydraulically connected arbitrary pore&lt;br/&gt;geometries. Numerically simulated results on the geometry and extent of capillary&lt;br/&gt;condensed zones will be compared to the microtomography data. The numerical model&lt;br/&gt;will then be used to map the spatial distribution of variables that cannot be measured&lt;br/&gt;experimentally such as fluid density, vapor pressure in thin films, interfacial width, and&lt;br/&gt;three-dimensional curvatures, to subsequently calculate interfacial energies, surface&lt;br/&gt;tension, chemical potentials, and disjoining pressures.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of the proposed research:&lt;br/&gt;We expect that the findings from the proposed research could have important&lt;br/&gt;wider impacts in diverse fields where processes relevant to the low saturation regime are&lt;br/&gt;of significance, including arid zone irrigation and water management, fate and transport&lt;br/&gt;of contaminants and colloidal particles in the vadose zone, nuclear waste disposal in very&lt;br/&gt;dry climates, enhanced oil recovery, and in planetary sciences. In addition, the project&lt;br/&gt;will provide training for undergraduate and graduate students, as well as a post-doc.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0715152</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marcel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schaap</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mschaap@cals.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/20/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1579</Code>
      <Text>HYDROLOGIC SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9189</Code>
      <Text>WATER RESOURCES/COASTAL &amp; MARINE ENVIRON</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
