<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Integrated Behavioral Phenotype: Links Among Functionally Different Behavioral Traits</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>436649</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michelle M. Elekonich</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Ann Hedrick, IOS-0716332&lt;br/&gt;The integrated behavioral phenotype: links among functionally different behavioral traits&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Correlations among multiple kinds of behavioral traits, such as mating behavior, territorial behavior and anti-predator behavior, can limit the potential variation in an animal''s behavior on which natural selection can act. These correlations therefore may influence the course of behavioral evolution. However, they have rarely been studied in natural populations of animals. This research will examine correlations among three behavioral traits: mating displays, anti-predator behavior and fighting behavior, as well as the consequences of these correlations in a natural population of field crickets, Gryllus integer. Previous evidence shows that male crickets with more conspicuous mating displays (songs) are more cautious about the risk of predation than males with less conspicuous displays. This evidence also suggests that more aggressive males are less cautious about predation risk than less aggressive males. The project has three parts, and builds on this prior evidence. The first part will compare the mating displays and anti-predator behavior of males that win fights with the mating displays and anti-predator behavior of males that lose fights. This will yield new information on the links between mating displays, anti-predator behavior and fighting ability in a natural population of animals. The second part will test the prediction that more aggressive males will have lower survival in the presence of predators than less aggressive males because they are less cautious about the risk of predation. The last part will determine whether female mating preferences can predict which males will win fights, and will illuminate the relationship between male aggression and female choice of mates. This project will contribute to the training and development of at least nine undergraduates and several graduate students, many of whom will be minorities and women. The project also will involve international collaboration and continued participation in an outreach program for disadvantaged schoolchildren.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0716332</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hedrick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>avhedrick@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7659</Code>
      <Text>ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1096</Code>
      <Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9282</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY GRADUATE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
