<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>One and two-dimensional superheated water chromatographies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>376000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor John Dorsey and his group at Florida State University are studying superheated water as a chromatographic mobile phase and reaction medium. Thorough thermodynamic and salvatochromic investigation of retention in superheated water chromatography, they aim to elucidate the retention mechanism and improve predictability and understanding of the technique. Because chromatography is such a widely used separation technique, and because the chromatography experiment is often used as a model for a variety of partitioning processes, such an understanding is highly desirable. Use of superheated water chromatography is currently limited to the academic laboratory; better fundamental understanding is necessary before the technique can be accepted in the analytical laboratory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are a variety of advantages that are associated with using superheated water as a mobile phase, such as a reduction in cost, increase in analysis speed, and improvements in analyte detection. These advantages could be especially important for furthering the goals of "green" chemistry, and for the recent drive for Process Analytical Technology (PAT) by the pharmaceutical industry. Information learned here will also impact the use of this solvent as a reaction medium. Students associated with this program gain valuable insight into important multidisciplinary areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0717701</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dorsey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dorsey@chem.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1974</Code>
      <Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1974</Code>
      <Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9156</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
