<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Systematics of the Dothideomycetes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>332879</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles Lydeard</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dothideomycetes is one of the largest and most diverse classes within the largest fungal phylum, Ascomycota. It contains a diverse group of fungi that subsist as general saprobes, plant and human pathogens, fungal parasites, mycorrhizae, lichens, and aquatic and marine fungi. Few other eukaryotic groups share this enormous ecological diversity. The best-known members of the group are plant pathogens that cause serious crop losses, but the majority of Dothideomycetes phylogenetic relationships are poorly known. A well-resolved evolutionary history is especially important because it provides the framework for understanding how fungi change in adapting to new environments and nutritional modes. A dynamic evolutionary history is reflected in the ecology of the Dothideomycetes. The ecological diversity of the class may hint at an unrevealed similarity in all fungi or it may reveal the unique ways that each of these groups adapt to the environment. As such, the Dothideomycetes provide an excellent system to gain insight into environmental adaptation. By using a broad approach to sampling in the group, this study aims to address ancient relationships while simultaneously expanding the knowledge of species diversity in the class. The project will rely on international collaboration and will link data generated about genetics, plant pathology, systematics, and taxonomy. Results will be communicated by workshops, publications, and the internet.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0717476</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thorsten</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lumbsch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tlumbsch@fieldmuseum.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spatafora</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spatafoj@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spatafora</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spatafoj@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/22/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Conrad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schoch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schochc@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/22/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
