<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop for Education and Outreach Managers of NSF Funded Large Projects, Centers, and Facilities; Arlington, Virginia; March 13-14, 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>39774</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A workshop will be convened to provide a forum for Education and Outreach (E&amp;O) managers from NSF-funded facilities, centers, and large projects to discuss present programs, potential future collaborations, issues of common interest, and the importance/relevance of E&amp;O programs in these NSF funded initiatives. A white-paper summarizing the discussion will provide various NSF GEO programs with input for future priorities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The leads for Education and Outreach programs will meet at NSF headquarters in Arlington, VA, on March 13-14, 2007. UNAVCO will provide logistics and leadership for the meeting organization. A Steering Committee will help define points of discussion and finalize the agenda for the meeting. Funding from NSF will provide expenses for approximately 24 participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Topics will include but not be limited to&lt;br/&gt;. Overview of present programs (provided in written form by participants)&lt;br/&gt;. Potential collaborations&lt;br/&gt;. Importance of the synergy, stability, and expertise provided by long term programs&lt;br/&gt;. Evaluation of large projects, expectations from NSF; do we have model programs for this?&lt;br/&gt;. Diversity&lt;br/&gt;. Future meetings&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific outcomes will include:&lt;br/&gt;. a well articulated statement regarding the current roles that these organizations play in achieving the mission of NSF;&lt;br/&gt;. a list of needs from these projects and organizations relevant to how they can better serve their constituencies;&lt;br/&gt;. how these organizations can provide scaffolding for the support of broader impact of scientific research; and&lt;br/&gt;. input to NSF program officers in preparation for a cohesive strategic plan for GEO and its divisions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0718531</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eriksson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>susan.eriksson@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/26/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>UNAVCO, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803015394</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3033817636</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6350 Nautilus Dr.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1575</Code>
      <Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1733</Code>
      <Text>GEOSCIENCE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>4444</Code>
      <Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
