<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Cultural vs. Natural Taphonomic Agents in the Reconstruction of Ritualized Postmortem Events on the North Coast of Peru</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14039</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Recent excavations of Pre-Inca sacrificial sites along Northern Coastal Peru has revealed a complex form of postmortem treatment for human remains. These discoveries have lent support to the argument that scenes of manipulation and display of remains in Moche art depict actual events, but accurate interpretation of the evidence requires the ability to reliably discriminate between human and natural agents among remains influenced by both environmental and ritual activity. Human activity can leave recognizable signatures in the burial record, but these are easily masked by non-human disturbances such as environmental and faunal activity. The scientific study of these postmortem processes is referred to as taphonomy. Under the supervision of Dr. John Verano, Heather Backo will use the remains of sacrificial victims at three Moche (AD 100-800), Chimu (AD 1100-1550), and Lambayeque (AD 800-1350) period sites from Peru, to reconstruct the sequence of events leading from death of individual to deposition and recovery, with a specific focus on differentiating between postmortem cultural and natural events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Taphonomy is an increasingly important field of study with a wide range of applications. Traditionally, taphonomic studies focus upon the slow incorporation of remains into the fossil record. More recently, however, the application of these techniques has expanded to more recent events, making a substantial contribution toward advancing the understanding of past and present human behavior. The definition of taphonomy can therefore be expanded to include research issues in paleopathology, the study of ancient disease and trauma, and forensic anthropology. The proposed research builds upon and expands this base by studying the patterns of distribution, preservation, and placement of skeletal elements to develop methods for distinguishing between intentional dismemberment, and ritualistic positioning of remains, as opposed to natural disarticulation and dispersal by carnivore activity, wind or water. In addition, patterns of missing elements will be examined for what they may reveal about postmortem treatment and intentional curation or use. The results will have value for multiple subfields of both archaeology and anthropology, and collections both ancient and modern. In addition, the excellent preservation of remains and associated artifacts of coastal Peru make this region an invaluable resource by providing a unique opportunity to greatly expand our knowledge of prehistoric cultural practices, as well as provide multiple case study environments with which to test and expand our knowledge of taphonomic and forensic processes that affect the subsequent interpretation of recovered remains.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All results will be submitted for publication through peer-reviewed journals, as well as academic conferences. Relevant journals include subjects in both paleopathology, forensic anthropology, archaeology and Latin American studies. However, this research has broader impacts as well. A local student with interest in anthropology is included in the budget for assistance with collecting and re-curating the skeletal remains. This is to encourage participation and research into Peruvian prehistory, with the end result of promoting preservation and opportunity for people local to the area. In addition, the doctoral research grant will lead to training and experience in the methods of taphonomic analysis for the author.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0718026</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Verano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>verano@mailhost.tcs.tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tulane University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
