<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High Resolution Spectroscopy of 3d Transition Metal Species: Chemical Insights into Organometallic Bonding</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>382874</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lucy Ziurys of the University of Arizona is supported by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program to investigate model systems of relevant 3d of transition metal compounds using high resolution gas-phase spectroscopy in the range of 4-680 GHz. This technique is particularly useful in the investigation of such species because basic molecular properties can be directly extracted from the spectra. The molecules of interest are almost entirely free radicals and molecular ions, and fall into four classes: (1) metal monomethyl neutral and cationic species including the metals nickel, manganese, and iron, (2) early 3d metal cyanides/isocyanides where the metal is titanium, vanadium, or scandium, (3) metal monocarbonyl radicals and associated ions, and (4) metal oxide clusters, such as the cations of FeO and MnO. These molecules are of fundamental interest for catalysis, C-H/C-C bond activation reactions, and biochemical systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Transition metals play a wide and varied role in modern chemistry, including organic and inorganic synthesis, industrial catalysis, materials science, and in biomedical sciences. Despite their ubiquitous presence in both industrial and academic sectors, the chemistry of transition metals is far from understood. This research project will lead to new knowledge about transition metals and molecules that could impact numerous applications such as catalyst design. Students who work on this project are being educated in experimental techniques in physical chemistry, and being prepared for challenging technical careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0718699</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lucy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ziurys</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lziurys@as.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aldo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Apponi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aapponi@as.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1962</Code>
      <Text>SPECTROSCOPY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
