<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NOAA Sea Grant Knauss Fellowship</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>135000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Interagency Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funds are provided to support three 2007 NOAA Sea Grant Fellow, two in the Division 0f Ocean Sciences and one in the Office of Polar Programs. Each Sea Grant Fellow will have a wide range of opportunities and experiences involving ocean science research, education and outreach, environmental protection in Antarctica, including marine areas, on basic science needed to better understand and manage marine living resources, and research on acoustics/marine mammals to using new information to formulate NSF environmental policy, The National Sea Grant Federal Fellowship Program is administrated through NOAA's Office of Oceanic Research Programs. Work will involve a variety of activities including active participation in the review process, reviewing and preparing summaries of environmental impact assessment, and involvement in meetings and conference preparation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the years, the National Sea Grant Fellowship program has provided NSF with highly qualified and motivated individuals who have provided much needed assistance to NSF in a variety of program offices. The Fellows have benefited from their experience at NSF and have gone on to further their careers in their field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/22/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0719417</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cammen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leon.cammen@noaa.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/22/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NOAA</Name>
      <CityName>Silver Spring</CityName>
      <ZipCode>209103282</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3017133388</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1315 East West Highway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
