<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium on Translational Seed Biology: From Model Systems to Crop Improvement, University California, Davis, on September 17-20, 2007</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>24560</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhongchi Liu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract for proposal 0719431&lt;br/&gt;Symposium on Translational Seed Biology: From Model Systems to Crop Improvement&lt;br/&gt;PIs: Kent Bradford and John Harada&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Knowledge of seed biology is advancing rapidly, particularly in model systems that allow the integration of genetic, genomic, metabolic, molecular, and biophysical approaches. At the same time, the demands upon seeds in agriculture are increasing. "Translational" seed biology is the effort to capitalize on this expanding fundamental knowledge to develop applications for the improvement of seeds as genetic delivery systems for crop production, as end products for food and diverse uses, and as storage materials for germplasm preservation. Bringing together fundamental (i.e., model-systems oriented) and applied (i.e., crop-systems oriented) plant scientists to share their results, challenges and insights will facilitate the transfer of knowledge from proofs of concept into agricultural and commercial applications. Model systems can also inform ecological applications of seed biology, such as using knowledge of seed dormancy mechanisms in management of weedy or invasive species. Similarly, studies of the biophysics of dry systems and desiccation tolerance mechanisms in model systems can translate into better ways to preserve and store germplasm as seeds. &lt;br/&gt; The ability to modify specific developmental and compositional aspects of seeds provides enormous potential to meet the growing global demand for food, but only if those discoveries can be adapted to the marketplace. This will be accomplished in an international symposium on Translational Seed Biology: From Model Systems to Crop Improvement. It will bring together leading public- and private-sector scientists across all aspects of seed biology to discuss the connections between fundamental discoveries and their applications in agriculture. Seed science will be advanced by focusing on seeds as a multifaceted system in which to integrate discoveries in genomics, proteomics, metabolomics, and regulatory networks with the outcomes of these processes with respect to seed yield and variation in composition for diverse uses and applications. In addition, the symposium will identify high priority challenges or opportunities that can be targeted by complementary research in model systems, crops and ecological settings.&lt;br/&gt; Communication and publication of the content and discussions at the symposium will have broader impacts upon education and public service as well. Participation at the symposium by undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral researchers will be encouraged and subsidized. Poster sessions will provide opportunities for young scientists to discuss their work with some of the world's premier researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0719431</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Harada</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jjharada@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bradford</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kjbradford@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1118</Code>
      <Text>PLANT FUNGAL &amp; MICROB DEV MECH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1329</Code>
      <Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
