<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>LEEM and STM Studies of Metal on Semiconductor Growth and Phase Transitions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450055</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With the support of the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program, Professor Chiang and her coworkers in the Department of Physics at the University of California-Davis are examining thin film growth and two dimensional phase transition behavior in thin film systems. Using scanning tunneling microscopy coupled with low energy electron microscopy, both local and ensemble studies of the growth and phase transitions of gold and silver thin films on Ge(111) surfaces are carried out. Information fundamental to the understanding of metal-semiconductor junctions is obtained from these studies. Experimental information is coupled with density functional theory and dynamical low energy electron diffraction calculations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Phase transitions and the nucleation and growth of thin metal films on semiconductor surfaces are the focus of the research supported here by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program. Professor Chiang and her coworkers combine experimental tools such as scanning probe microscopy with low energy electron microscopy to examine these systems, providing fundamental information about the nature of two dimensional phase transitions and the properties of metal-semiconductor junctions. This information is important for the design of microelectronic devices and the processes to manufacture them.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0719504</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shirley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chiang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chiang@physics.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1972</Code>
      <Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1972</Code>
      <Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
