<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: WN: Proper Location Identification in Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Min Song</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Wireless networks bring mobility to users by allowing them to change location without disrupting connectivity. On one hand, this opens space for a wide variety of location-aware services. On the other hand, it also poses a concern to users as to what extent their location can, or should, be identified in different scenarios.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main focus of the research is to address the proper identification of mobile device locations in wireless networks. There are two sides of the problem: the accurate determination of a mobile device's location in applications such as E911 services, and the effective protection of location information against adversaries which intend to intrude mobile device users' privacy. This project takes a systematic view of both sides of the problem, explores a solution space that spans both ends of wireless communication, and delivers solutions for various application scenarios. The sticking point is to determine the minimum location information necessary for the intended network service by understanding, analyzing, structuring, and controlling the complex interactions among different entities in the system including end-devices, base stations, and (potential) adversaries across application, network, and physical layers. Both control plane and data plane are considered.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is to form a scientific foundation for proper location identification.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0721569</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weizhao@umac.mo</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
