<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: NOSS: Autonomous Mobile Underwater SEnsor networks (AMUSE): Design and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>222178</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph Lyles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project investigates the design and applications of Autonomous Mobile Underwater SEnsor networks (AMUSE) consisting of a variable number of sonars (sensors) and vehicles that are deployed to perform collaborative tasks over a given area. Underwater acoustic sensor networks (UWA-SNs) are envisioned to enable applications for environmental monitoring of physical and chemical/biological indicators, tactical surveillance, disaster prevention, undersea exploration, and assisted navigation, etc. The major tasks under exploration include UWA-SN self-organization and deployment, self-reconfiguring (MAC, physical layer, and cross-layer design), and mission-aware waveform design/diversity with applications to target recognition, target tracking, and event detection. The AMUSE project is motivated by and targets to solve the following challenges: 1) the sensors in UWA-SN are expensive and mobile, therefore sound self-organization and self-deployment algorithms are needed; 2) waveform design and diversity for UWA-SNs with active sonars are still in its infancy; 3) the transmit and receive data rates are highly asymmetric, which requires new MAC layer design; 4) the underwater channel is impaired by fading, multipath, and doppler shift; 5) the GPS receivers do not work properly in underwater, thus new localization/navigation algorithms are required.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The success of the AMUSE project is able to benefit the two areas of urgent national interests: (1) Instrumentation for monitoring/prediction of natural ocean disasters including storm surges, hurricanes, tsunami, etc. (2) Harbor environments and security. In addition, this project can serve as a vehicle to promote cross-disciplinary graduate and undergraduate research and education, and to encourage the participation of under-represented and female students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0721515</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qilian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liang@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
      <CityName>Arlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
