<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Thin Film Deposition System - Supporting Nanoscience and Nanotechnology Research and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>294564</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajinder P. Khosla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this project is to acquire a thin film deposition (TFD) system to support funded research and to advance nanomaterials and nanofabrication development at Portland State University (PSU), as well as at surrounding institutions. The approach is that a KJLC AXXIS TFD system, capable of magnetron sputtering, electron beam deposition, thermal evaporation, ion beam-assisted deposition and substrate cleaning, will be installed at PSU's Center for Electron Microscopy and Nanofabrication (CEMN), a signature multi-user facility of Oregon Nanoscience and Microtechnologies Institute (ONAMI).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is that the unique capabilities provided by the AXXIS TFD system, not currently available at any Oregon university, will enable researchers from ONAMI to conduct funded research and to initiate many nanoscience and nanotechnology related projects. In addition, it will stimulate collaboration among researchers across different university campuses in Oregon, creating new partnerships with local high-tech industry and improving the educational curriculum in thin film physics and surface coating technology for both graduate and undergraduate students. The new instrument will enhance the research infrastructure at PSU and ONAMI. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact reflects the fact that more than two-dozen currently funded multi-disciplinary NSF, DOD, and DOE projects, representing more than 70 researchers, graduate and undergraduate students in 3 large universities in Oregon, will benefit directly from the new TFD system. The competitiveness and feasibility of many funded and new proposals by ONAMI members, covering areas from nanoelectronics, nanometrology, and nanofabrication to bioengineering, will be greatly enhanced.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0722660</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sanchez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esanchez@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jiao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jiaoj@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chunfei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cli@clarion.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Portland State University</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>101E</Code>
      <Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
