<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Tabletop Scanning Electron Microscope for Undergraduate Research and Training in Materials Chemistry and Geological Science and STEM Activities in Grades 7-12</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>70844</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>General abstract&lt;br/&gt;Many natural and man-made phenomena which we take for granted are dependent upon the size and shape of objects that are too small to be seen by the human eye. Natural processes can produce extremely tiny, highly organized structures that are less than 1000 times the thickness of a human hair, yet lead to remarkable properties. Humans are doing their best to learn how to mimic nature. The ability to accurately and consistently create objects on this scale is predicted to revolutionize medicine, electronics, manufacturing, building materials, and even fashion. We are proposing the acquisition of a scanning electron microscope that will magnify objects by up to 10,000 times, allowing us to see some of these important structural details. This microscope fits on a standard tabletop, can be operated with minimal training, and has few maintenance requirements. It is ideal for use in undergraduate research at community colleges, which are attended nationally by nearly 44% of science and engineering graduates. It will be used in many divisions of science and technology, including the development of efficient methods for creating biosensors applicable to human health issues such as diabetes management. A second project will explore new methods for producing tiny metal particles that will increase the efficiency of important chemical conversions. A third project will examine the structures that influence the properties of gem-quality pearls. Outreach projects in biology and electrical and computer engineering technology will also be developed for local students and teachers in grades 7-12. The electron microscope is integral to all of this work because it can reveal the structural origin of the useful properties of synthetic and natural materials. Further, the hands-on experiences made possible with this instrument are expected to inspire more students to enter and remain in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical abstract&lt;br/&gt;We are proposing the acquisition of a benchtop scanning electron microscope (SEM) and sputter coater. These instruments will be used by several investigators for research and teaching in chemistry, geology, biology, and electrical and computer engineering technology (ECET). The first project explores the influence of molecular structure and reaction conditions on the nanoscale morphology of the conducting polymer polyaniline and its ring-substituted derivatives. Using these materials, we will develop a one-pot method to fabricate an enzyme-based biosensor composed of a conductive polymer matrix with embedded metal nanoparticles. Glucose/glucose oxidase is our preliminary target, but we will extend this work to other enzyme-substrate systems. The second project is the novel synthesis of biodegradable polysilyl esters catalyzed by the formation of metal nanoparticles. Dispersible, polymer-stabilized palladium nanoparticles are also being investigated as catalysts in the chemo-selective reduction of conjugate double bonds. The third project will characterize the gemological nature of pearls sold in the New York gem trade, including features such as color, luster, surface perfection, sphericity, etc. These are related to the pearls' microstructure, which is easily investigated by microscopy and whose origin depends on variations in the amounts of mineral matter (aragonite and calcite), organic material (the protein conchiolin), and water. Ready access to SEM will allow us to optimize reaction conditions to produce nanostructures with useful properties and will uncover the physiochemical origin of macroscopic properties in naturally occurring materials. This particular electron microscope requires minimal training to operate and has few maintenance and facilities needs, making it ideal for undergraduate research in nanoscience/technology at a community college, as well as for outreach projects in biology and ECET for local students and teachers in grades 7-12. The hands-on experiences made possible with this instrument are expected to inspire more students to enter and remain in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0722607</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Moni</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chauhan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mchauhan@qcc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roland</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rscal@qcc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sarno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>DSarno@qcc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Queensborough Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Oakland Gardens</CityName>
      <ZipCode>113641497</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7186316222</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>222-05 56th Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
