<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS-WN: Gigabits/Sec/User</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>295000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Min Song</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project examines the problem of providing high data-rate wireless connectivity to users in indoor environments. The goal is to be able to reach gbps/user rates even when there are multiple users present. The technology that we are researching is to use is the 60 GHz ISM spectrum whose special propagation properties make it ideally suited to this task. The approach taken is to use multiple, spatially-distributed smart antennas in a room to provide coverage where needed and when needed. All the antennas are connected to a single access point which allows us to dynamically change spectrum and link allocation among the users (as they move or as their needs change). Indeed, the design of the access point is also novel since it needs to support a gross throughput of several gbps.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The innovations in this work include the exploitation of the special properties of 60 GHz, design of algorithms for efficient spectrum reuse, support for multiple MAC protocols within a room to better adapt to user needs, a novel access point architecture, and a tight correlation between design of the system and user access patterns. The methodology being followed is primarily theoretical and simulation-based.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Providing high data-rate wireless access to users is an important problem given the drive to push more and more services through the wireless pipeline. This project differs from previous ones in that this project has the ambitious goal of delivering gbps/user. The research is a mix of physical layer, MAC layer, and algorithmic design. The expected results will make significant contributions in the areas of spectrum allocation as well as novel access point designs. The work will also potentially impact future development standards for these environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One product of this project is a detailed Opnet/Matlab simulation environment for 60GHz indoor communications. This is useful to the larger wireless research community and will also be incorporated into the curriculum for lab practicum. In terms of outreach, the PI collaborates with the Saturday Academy (SA) of PSU, which serves K-12 students. The PI's contribution to SA is to lecture on rudimentary concepts of high-speed wireless networking (and the future of this exciting area). The PI, with the help of SAs, will actively recruit high-school students, particularly minority and under-represented, to intern under the Apprenticeships in Science &amp; Engineering program, in which interns explore and experience while contributing to this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0722008</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suresh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Singh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>singh@cs.pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Portland State University</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
