<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-RUI: Acquisition of a SQUID Magnetometer for Materials Science Research and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>353252</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Technical: For the past many years, research laboratories across the world have been routinely using Superconducting Quantum Interference Device (SQUID) magnetometers for measuring magnetic flux densities as small as 10-15 Tesla. With an array of research programs in electronic and magnetic materials, absence of a magnetometer believed to be so crucial for materials research has severely impacted researchers at Missouri State University in completing the basic fundamental aspects of their research. Acquisition of a state-of-the-art SQUID magnetometer will tremendously enhance capabilities and add a new dimension to materials science at Missouri State. The faculty members will use this instrument to study AC/DC magnetization, magnetoresistance, and Hall effect for the following projects: (1) Ferromagnetism in oxide-based dilute magnetic semiconductors; (2) Polarization-doped dilute magnetic heterostructures; (3) Magnetic exchange coupling induced at the interface of core-shell nanocomposites; (4) Magnetic and transport properties of conducting polymers; (5) Investigation of spin-crossover phenomenon in highly-colored anionic tris[Fe(II) cyanoximates]; and (6) Investigation of gadolinium and lutetium(III) porphyrin-doped polymeric films. The new SQUID facility will significantly elevate the quality of existing programs in spintronics, magnetochemistry, and novel magnetic nanocomposites. The undergraduate and graduate students who will use the SQUID magnetometer and acquire training and skills through research projects will be more suitable for employment in high-tech industries and research laboratories. A few selective courses will be modified to introduce SQUID magnetometry including at least one hands-on laboratory project. The SQUID magnetometer will complement the existing facilities available for Materials Science research and will be available for faculty and students in the disciplines of physics, chemistry, biology, biomedical sciences, and geology at Missouri State University. &lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical: For the past many years, research laboratories across the world have been routinely using Superconducting Quantum Interference Device (SQUID) magnetometers for measuring magnetic fields, which are a trillion times smaller than a refrigerator magnet. With an array of research programs in electronic and magnetic materials, absence of a magnetometer believed to be so crucial for materials research has severely impacted researchers at Missouri State University in completing the basic fundamental aspects of their research. Acquisition of a state-of-the-art SQUID magnetometer will tremendously enhance capabilities and add a new dimension to materials science at Missouri State. This state-of-the-art facility will provide new exciting research opportunities on diverse materials: (1) Some metal oxides and nitrides which could be used for non-erasable memory applications; (2) Tiny magnetic particles embedded in a non-magnetic material for applications in biological separation and targeted drug/gene delivery; (3) Plastics which conduct electricity and have applications as display units, solar batteries, etc; (4) Molecules with embedded magnetic atoms as chemical and biological sensors; and (5) Plastics doped with magnetic molecules for food and clinical fields. The new SQUID facility will significantly elevate the existing programs in nanoscience, nanotechnology, electronics, novel magnetic materials, and chemical and biological sensors. The undergraduate and graduate students who will use the SQUID magnetometer and acquire training and skills through research projects will be more suitable for employment in high-tech industries and research laboratories. A few selective courses will be modified to introduce SQUID magnetometry including at least one hands-on laboratory project. The SQUID magnetometer will complement the existing facilities available for Materials Science research and will be available for faculty and students in the disciplines of physics, chemistry, biology, biomedical sciences, and geology at Missouri State University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0723105</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pawan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kahol</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pkahol@pittstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lifeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>LDong03@hamline.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shyang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Huang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ssh383f@smsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kartik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghosh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>KartikGhosh@missouristate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nikolay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gerasimchuk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>NNGerasimchuk@missouristate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Missouri State University</Name>
      <CityName>Springfield</CityName>
      <ZipCode>658970027</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4178365972</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>901 South National</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
