<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Spectroscopy of Reduced Bis(imino)pyridine Iron Catalysts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award in the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry program supports research by Prof. Paul Chirik at Cornell University to develop new iron catalysts for selective organic transformations. The approach seeks to elucidate the electronic structure of bis(imino)pyridine iron derivatives and apply this knowledge to the synthesis of new, more environmentally responsible compounds that are active catalysts for the formation of C-H, C-C and C-Si bonds. The research will explore the electronic structure and catalytic activity of new structural types such as iron imides, nitrides, diazoalkane complexes and alkylidenes in order to develop catalytic systems that would replace toxic and expensive precious metals with cheaper, more environmentally benign iron compounds. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will be carried out in collaboration with Prof. Karl Wieghardt at the Max Plank Institute for Bioinorganic Chemistry in Mulheim, Germany. Students and postdocs involved in the project will spend time in laboratories at both Cornell and the Max Plank Institute and be exposed to complementary activities in synthesis, spectroscopy and computational methods. An important focus is the development and utilization of a cyber infrastructure designed to facilitate data exchange and management. These activities will serve as the foundation for community outreach including programs for economically disadvantaged students and new scientific opportunities for underrepresented minorities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0723581</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chirik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pchirik@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
