<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Magnetic Resonance Imaging System for UCSB Brain Imaging Center</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>995000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funds to the University of California at Santa Barbara to acquire a 3T magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scanner for basic-science brain imaging research. This instrument will be housed in a dedicated MRI research facility in the new Psychology East building where it will support a primary group of 37 basic-science faculty at UCSB. Ongoing research success by this group depends critically on access to a high performance 3T MRI scanner. These multidisciplinary researchers originate from eleven different departments that include Psychology, Computer Science, Education, Speech and Hearing, Molecular, Cellular &amp; Developmental Biology, Geography, Communications, Physics and Anthropology. Thus, this 3T facility will provide campus-wide support to neuroscience researchers in the Schools of the Arts and Sciences, Education, Engineering. It will also be a critical resource for researchers from other institutions in the central coast region of California. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Functional brain imaging (fMRI) is an essential research tool used to define how the brain is organized to enable thinking and behavior and how these functions may be affected by abnormal development or disease. The 3T MRI will be used in many fMRI experiments including studies of memory, language, vision, navigation, communication, reasoning and learning. MRI will also be used to investigate brain anatomy, focusing on how white matter (the connections that link brain areas together) changes with development, disease and aging. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The vision of the Imaging Center is that it will serve as a catalytic research center for a broad, campus-wide initiative in Mind Science, for the study of the psychological, biological, and computational processes that govern mental function. What sets the initiative apart from other programs in cognitive science is that it will embrace a diverse set of approaches to studying the mind. These include, but are not limited to emotion, stress, conflict resolution, decision-making, genetics of behavior, optimal control, understanding intentionality, impact of media and criminality. Such interdisciplinary efforts offer far-reaching explanations of a wide variety of human phenomena, including strategies for complex decision-making, social interactions, conflict resolution, classification and induction, and statistical reasoning. The initiative in Mind Science is complemented by research on Basic fMRI Methodology and Technology. This work includes methods to model the fMRI BOLD signal, to characterize individual subject differences of brain structure and function, to integrate fMRI and EEG based technologies and to create immersive virtual reality environments for fMRI. A third thrust is in Engineering and Computer Science. The effort includes development of content-based retrieval and analysis of brain imaging data, new methods of image analysis, improving brain-computer and methods for the secure and reliable delivery of large data sets. These efforts reflect a strong commitment by faculty and students at University of California at Santa Barbara to interdisciplinary science and education. The 3T facility will operate in this tradition, providing new opportunities for research, graduate and post-graduate training, educational outreach, recruitment of new faculty in neuroscience, and increasing involvement by female students and researchers, and those from underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0723170</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grafton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Grafton@psych.ucsb.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
