<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S. Participation in the 2007 Canadian-American-Mexican Graduate Student Conference (CAM2007)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>39200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support to the American Physical Society (APS) for organization and student travel to participate in the joint Canadian, US, and Mexican physical societies' graduate student conference (CAM 2007), to be held in August 2007 at McGill University, Montreal, Canada. The scientific program will include plenary talks by well-known invited professors in physics sub-disciplines such as Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics; Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics; Biophysics; Condensed Matter Physics; and Nuclear/Particle Physics, and followed by contributed talks from students to complement the plenary session topics. CAM2007 will also include a round table discussion on the future of physics from prominent younger researchers. A student poster session will round out the scientific portion of the program. All student participants will present, either through an oral or a poster contribution, the research they have performed in graduate school. By bringing together working scientists and students in an informal setting, the conference will also enable students to explore and discuss career options available to young physicists. Through special topical and technical sessions, students will have the opportunity to gain a broader view of physics beyond their own classrooms and research laboratories. The meeting will generate scientific exchange among them student participants, promote international collaborations among young scientists within the North American continent, expose graduate students to sub-disciplines in physics beyond their individual research areas, and promote interdisciplinary research within the sub-disciplines. The meeting's organization is carried out by the students. Overall, it will provide excellent training for next generation researchers in the U.S.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0723598</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Flatten</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>flatten@aps.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kyler</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kuehn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kuehn@cosmic.ps.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Physical Society</Name>
      <CityName>College Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207403841</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3012093220</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Physics Ellipse</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1219</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROGRAMS IN ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1712</Code>
      <Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7299</Code>
      <Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1711</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5977</Code>
      <Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7561</Code>
      <Text>CANADA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS EDUC &amp; INTERDISCIP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
