<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Immunological Tools for Trimetasphere Fullerenes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>529831</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory T. Baxter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II research develops antibodies and immunoassays for studying therapeutics based on carbon-based nanomaterials. This research will expand the immunological tools developed in Phase I to focus on detailed characterization of anti-fullerene antibodies and validate and down-select immunoassays and reagents for validated commercial formats. Commercial formats will include enzyme-linked, immunosorbant assays (ELISAs) for medical and environmental applications, neutralization schemes for mitigating potential toxicity of fullerene/nanotubes and biosensors platform for long-term monitoring systems. Biosensor platforms based on fullerene antibodies as affinity ligands will include the quartz crystal microbalance and surface acoustic waveguide. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts will be to provide a full spectrum of immunological tools for studying the medically-related nanomaterials and monitoring nanowaste by-products during manufacturing processes. These will be new to the marketplace and enable monitoring of the use of products based on these nanomaterials to asssure their safe application.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0724380</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
      <LastName>VanTassell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vantassellr@lunainnovations.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Luna Innovations, Incorporated</Name>
      <CityName>Roanoke</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240111921</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5407698400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>301 1st Street SW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
