<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Joint U.S./German Investigation of Extraordinarily Stable Glasses by Nanocalorimetry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>182232</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this award, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Prof. Mark Ediger from the University of Wisconsin and his research student colleagues will investigate the behavior of extraordinarily stable glasses using the techniques of nanocalorimetry . This research coordinates with a collaborative award funded by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) to Dr. Christoph Schick from the University of Rostock. This award will allow Prof. Ediger to build nanocalorimetry equipment in his own laboratory and draw on the expertise of Prof. Schick in the use of nanocalorimetry to study the interesting and unusual glassy materials that are the focus of Prof. Ediger's research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Amorphous materials take center stage in a number of modern technologies, including, but not limited to polymers, glasses and amorphous semiconductors. The type of molecular glasses that are the focus of the research supported in this award show promise as materials for improved pharmaceuticals. In addition, the students working on these projects will be exposed to research in an international setting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0724062</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ediger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ediger@chem.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1960</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURE AND REACTIVITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
