<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Partial Support of the Committee on Radio Frequencies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>558465</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew Clegg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The National Academy of Sciences' Committee on Radio Frequencies is comprised of prominent scientists and engineers who provide studies and advice to the Academy on issues involving scientific uses of the radio spectrum. Such uses often involve techniques and applications that are outside the realm of traditional radio spectrum applications, therefore the Committee is useful to help guide the FCC and other regulatory bodies toward the adoption of spectrum rules and policies that will not create unnecessary interference to radio astronomy, meteorology, remote sensing, oceanography, and other scientific uses of the spectrum. Because of the multi-disciplinary aspect of the Committee's goals, it is supported by both the National Science Foundation and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration. The full Committee, comprised of 15 members, meets approximately twice per year, and between meetings it works on crafting comments and other written documents in response to various regulatory proceedings. The Committee also sends representatives to appropriate meetings of scientific (e.g., the International Union of Radio Scientists) and policy-setting bodies (e.g., the International Telecommunication Union) to help publicize their positions. The Committee has been in existence for many years, and the current award will continue National Science Foundation support through fiscal year 2010.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0724073</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jlancaster@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>4650</Code>
      <Text>RADIO SPECTRUM MANAGEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
