<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Closely Coupled Antenna Systems for Wireless Communications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andreas Weisshaar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ECCS-0725929&lt;br/&gt;Yuanxun Wang, UCLA&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merits &lt;br/&gt;A communication system with multiple antennas promises enhanced robustness and increased data capacity in comparison with single antenna systems. However, this benefit degrades when antennas are placed close to each other. The objective of the proposal is to first explore the behavior of closely coupled antennas using tools from the fundamental physics of electromagnetics, information theory and network theory, and secondly, to develop a new class of multi-antenna systems that are appropriate for compact wireless communication platforms. The proposed research is to fully exploit the multiple information channels that exist even in closely coupled antennas. It is proposed that the parallel information channels in the form of multiple modes can be utilized independently through a passive mode decomposition network. Consequentially, enhanced antenna gain beyond conventional limits and wireless link capacity can be obtained. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts&lt;br/&gt;A new class of multiple-antenna radio systems on compact wireless platforms will be developed. It fosters the interactions among different engineering research areas in antennas, circuit design and wireless communications. The state of science and engineering can be advanced through the development of new multi-disciplinary curriculums on those areas in both college and post graduate educations and through the technology innovations driven by the demands of such applications. The key concepts and technological breakthroughs in the proposed activities will enable the next generation of communication or sensor products that will be of high performance, compact and affordable. These components and devices will change human lifestyle and facilitate the industry manufacturing process to benefit the social economy. The proposed activity will also promote simpler, more compact and effective designs of radars, military radios and sensor systems. It can thus provide enormous benefits to establishing strong national security and defense networks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0725929</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuanxun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ywang@ee.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>109E</Code>
      <Text>Sys theory in biology &amp; medicine</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
