<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Advanced atomic force microscopy using the FIRAT probe</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>299766</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>OBJECTIVE AND APPROACH&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to develop novel probes and imaging methods for atomic force microscopy to enable high speed tapping mode imaging and quantitative material characterization at the nanoscale. The approach is to take advantage of recent developments in microfabrication and microscale optical sensing technologies to implement high performance probe structures. These probes use integrated electrostatic actuation and optical interferometric detection for improved speed and detection sensitivity, eliminating several bottlenecks in high speed imaging at nanoscale. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL MERIT&lt;br/&gt;To achieve probes large actuation range (2-5um) that is adequate for a variety of target applications while maintaining the interferometric detection sensitivity, novel diffraction based optical structures will be investigated. Practical probe designs suitable for batch fabrication and with proper dynamics and noise -- imaging bandwidths in the 50-100kHz, and thermal noise levels in the nN range ? will be developed. Finally, control systems and methods using the unique capabilities of these probes will be designed and implemented.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACT&lt;br/&gt;This research can move the atomic force microscope from research labs to industrial platforms such as inline semiconductor device metrology to build faster computers, as well as broadening its use in basic science applications. Through dissemination of devices and know-how, a rapid impact in nanotechnology and nanoscience is targeted. In addition to involvement of teachers from K-12 institutions, and undergraduate students in the research project, the long term objective is to provide each high school with an easily operated, fast atomic force microscope, opening a real window for students to explore the nanoscale phenomena.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0725618</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Levent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Degertekin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>levent@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
