<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Behavioral and neuroendocrine consequences of phytoestrogen exposure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>262907</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Phytoestrogens are endocrine disruptors produced by plants that are analogous to estrogens produced by animals. Given this close analogy, phytoestrogens can mimic estrogen action in the bodies and brains of humans or non-human animals. This project will systematically characterize the effects of three representative phytoestrogens on normal behavior patterns of adult male fighting fish Betta splendens, an ideal animal model because their behavior and physiology are relatively well understood and because their neuroendocrinology is similar to that of other vertebrates, including mammals. The project will determine whether observed behavioral changes occur because phytoestrogens bind directly to estrogens receptors localized in the testes and determine whether such phytoestrogen exposure reduces the production of testosterone and 11-ketotestosterone, decreases sperm production, and causes testicular atrophy. Subsequently, the project will determine whether the observed behavioral effects are the direct result of phytoestrogen binding to estrogen receptors in the brain, which could alter brain neurochemistry and affect the production and metabolism of neurotransmitters such as serotonin, dopamine and norepinephrine. This research will contribute to a better understanding of how phytoestrogens affect animal behavior and physiology and indicate how reproduction persists in the face of environmental estrogen exposure. Funding from the NSF will also provide numerous research and training opportunities for undergraduate students at Amherst College.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0725186</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clotfelter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>edclotfelter@amherst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Amherst College</Name>
      <CityName>Amherst</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010025000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135422804</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Controller's Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
