<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Long-Lived Data Repositories</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>540832</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Long-Lived Data Collections: Models and Case Studies&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Modern science, social science and engineering generate and rely upon massive amounts of electronic data and complex digital objects. Sky data collected through telescopic arrays, computer structural models of the earth's crust, demographic information from national and international public opinion surveys, and the ever growing body of genetic information add terabytes daily to the nation's knowledge base. To preserve such information over time digital repositories have been created by government agencies, scientific consortia, universities, and even for-profit corporations. Some of these data repositories have flourished and persisted; others have not. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Long-Lived Data Collections: Models and Case Studies is a two-year project to determine why and how certain data repositories have achieved long lives, and how the scientific community can apply the lessons of longevity in forming and maintaining new data repositories. The project is analyzing eight well established, long-lived collections of data and digital resources from a wide range of disciplines to identify the practices, strategies and mechanisms that have enabled them to sustain massive data collections over substantial periods of time. Aside from simple longevity, the basis for measuring the relative effectiveness of the repositories is the requirements for digital preservation repositories enumerated in the CRL/OCLC Trustworthy Repositories Audit and Certification: Criteria and Checklist: http://www.crl.edu/PDF/trac.pdf. The project is focused particularly on funding, organizational, and governance models adopted by the repositories, and it is assessing the role that feedback and accountability mechanisms play in their sustainability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Long-Lived Data Collections project is producing risk assessment tools and cost data to inform future planning of and investment in Cyberinfrastructure by federal agencies, universities, scientific consortia and other stakeholders across the entire spectrum of science, engineering, and social science communities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/09/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0726250</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bernard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reilly</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reilly@crl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/09/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Center For Research Libraries</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606372804</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7739554545</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6050 South Kenwood Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
