<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>S-STEM Scholarships in Mathematics and Physics at Austin Peay State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>582740</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joyce B. Evans</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is increasing the number of individuals earning bachelors degrees in mathematics and physics, and ensuring that they are well prepared for graduate study in a wide variety of STEM disciplines. The project is awarding scholarships to approximately 75 students during years 2-5 of the program, after an initial year to accommodate setup. Recruiting efforts are focusing on high schools within the service region of the institution having a high proportion of financially needy, minority and first generation students. Scholarship eligibility is based on academic performance and financial need. Scholarship amounts are determined by categorizing students based on Pell eligibility and unmet financial need. Scholarships for students in the neediest category average $4,000 per student per academic year. Scholarships average $2,500 per student per year for other students with demonstrated financial need.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the project lies in the various support mechanisms designed to help students complete a degree in physics or mathematics within four years. To accomplish this, students must be prepared to successfully complete calculus and university physics in their first semester, a challenging task even for academically talented students. To help meet this challenge, students receiving S-STEM scholarships are participating in a Mathematics and Physics Summer (MaPS) Institute. Through the MaPS Institute S-STEM students are placed in a cohort where math and study skills are emphasized, and a learning community formed. These S-STEM MaPS students enroll in summer college-credit algebra and/or pre-calculus courses to prepare them for entry into a traditional math or physics curriculum. The learning community formed in the MaPS Institute is maintained as the students progress through the first-year curriculum. During their first year, students also receive mentoring from upper division math and physics majors. S-STEM scholars receive career counseling during the MaPS Institute and throughout their program of study. Participation in extended research activities serves to help students determine a career path and develop the comprehensive problem solving skills necessary for graduate study in a STEM discipline. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is broadening participation in STEM fields by helping to prepare disadvantaged and underrepresented students from poor areas with elevated high school drop out rates to pursue undergraduate degrees in physics and/or mathematics. Financial support is allowing students to reduce their workload outside the university, giving them time to participate in their learning community and in extended research experiences. In addition the MaPS Institute is providing a model for other programs interested in increasing STEM retention in the early undergraduate years.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0728476</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jaime</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taylor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>taylorjr@apsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>B. Alex</FirstName>
      <LastName>King III</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kinga@apsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Loretta</FirstName>
      <LastName>Griffy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>griffyl@apsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schultz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schultzk@apsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jonesmatt@apsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Austin Peay State University</Name>
      <CityName>Clarksville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>370440001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9312217881</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 College Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
