<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GOALI: Dynamic Coupling of Synthetic Jet Actuators and Flow Fields</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>547001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eduardo A. Misawa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of the proposed GOALI investigation is to understand the dynamic coupling between "synthetic jet actuators" and the flow fields they can influence. Synthetic jet actuators are devices that in this case will be embedded just below the surface of a wing and produce small jets of air that interact with air flowing over the wing to produce a desired change in the performance of the wing, such as a reduction in drag. The outcome from achieving this goal will be insights and guidelines needed for design, development and optimization of synthetic jet actuators for active flow control applications such as drag reduction and lifting-surface performance enhancement in fixed and rotary-wing aircraft. Initial model validation experiments will be conducted on flows over flat plates, first with a single jet and then with an array of synthetic jets. Then, in conjunction with students spending time over summers conducting components of their research at Boeing, we will develop synthetic jet actuators tailored for use in arrays and optimized for control of two distinct flow fields of importance to our industry partner: flow over an airfoil and flow over helicopter airframe components. The Broader Impacts of the proposal include a dynamic partnership of academia and industry that will inspire students and will facilitate technology transfer. Students will work closely with industry co-PI Clingman, who will visit campus several times a year and participate in weekly conference calls and web meetings. Students will also have multiple opportunities to work in Boeing labs. Lastly, the societal and economic impact of enabling next generation aircraft by realizing the proposed active flow control capabilities is enormous</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0729454</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alison</FirstName>
      <LastName>Flatau</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aflatau@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hubbard</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhubbard@nianet.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clingman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dan.j.clingman@boeing.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
