<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Non-Equilibrium Atmospheric Plasmas for Dental Restoration Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Semahat S. Demir</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0730505&lt;br/&gt;Yu&lt;br/&gt;The main objective of this project is to examine the surface preparation and surface/interface engineering using novel non-equilibrium atmospheric gas plasmas in dental treatment and restorations for significantly improved performance and durability. The research will include plasma treatment of dental surfaces without acid etching or demineralization in order to successfully replace the currently used drilling and acid etching procedures. The studies will also include micro- and nanoindentation in order to determine the mechanical properties of the interface regions as well as further study of the plasma-induced elimination of bacteria that will sustain the interface for a longer time after restoration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks solutions to existing dental problems by applying novel plasma surface/interface engineering principles. This project will have high impact for the dental treatment field. The knowledge gained will be valuable in solving many other biomedical problems. The interdisciplinary collaboration in the project provides a larger audience for research dissemination. Outreach and education activities will be: (1) to introduce students to the basic scope and frontiers of engineering and biomedical research, (2) to involve underrepresented groups in engineering and science; and (3) to promote public awareness and recognition of the importance of applying engineering principles to solve biomedical problems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0730505</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qingsong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yuq@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wangyo@umkc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hao</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liha@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
