<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Analysis of Peripheral MR Velocity Images for Direct Quantification of Pulsatile Pressures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>269999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Athanassios Sambanis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0730467&lt;br/&gt;Amini&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this proposal is to develop a Phase-Contrast (PC) based magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) technique to quantify blood flow velocity and thus to calculate intra-vascular pressure with quantified blood flow velocity by using the Pressure-Poisson Equation. The calculated pressure can be used for the noninvasive diagnosis of peripheral arterial disease. This project will develop new computational and imaging methods to be integrated with MR-based angiography to accomplish noninvasive measurement of geometric and functional data from stenotic and/or occluded arteries. The research methods used will automate the extraction of geometry of vessels, improve the acquisition of blood velocity, and optimize the calculation of pressure chances using MR techniques. The methods developed will be validated with phantoms of several geometries and under both steady and pulsatile flow conditions. Geometry extraction results will be compared against manual expert analysis. Quantification of velocity and pressure profiles would make available a unique noninvasive methodology for assessing and selecting the patients that can benefit the most from revascularization procedures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project can have an important impact in the fields of bioengineering, medical imaging, and vascular surgery. Furthermore, the project provides an excellent vehicle for interdisciplinary research and education opportunities of both undergraduate and graduate students. An outreach program for minorities and a web site for dissemination of the results are also planned.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0730467</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>M Keith</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>keith.sharp@louisville.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Amini</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amir.amini@louisville.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Louisville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>402021959</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5028523788</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>The Nucleus</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
