<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of an Elemental Analyzer for Geological and Biological Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>37499</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funds from this grant will support acquisition of a Costech Elemental Analyzer (EA) for the analysis of carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen and sulfur in lake sediments, sedimentary rocks and biological materials, as well as ancillary equipment. The EA will support a range of faculty and students research in paleolimnology, paleoceanography, terrestrial vegetation ecology, and marine and freshwater fish ecology. Undergraduate and Master-level students as well as other faculty from Cal-State Fullerton (CSUF) and institutions collaborative with the PIs will have access to the instrument with appropriate training. Data obtained from the EA will be used towards the completion of undergraduate research theses, Master's theses, and the 4 PIs own, and collaborative, research. The intellectual merit of this study is that each sub-project will advance the knowledge and understanding of major life-based elements in their respective Earth systems. The broader impacts of this work include research experience and thesis preparation for BSc and MSc students. As a Hispanic Serving Institute, this research will also provide research opportunities for underrepresented individuals in the sciences at CSUF. Acquisition of this system will also provide an opportunity for students to use technically advanced, yet accessible, equipment in the laboratory environment. Lastly, each of the PIs pursue environmental-based research. This research will expose students to important, socially relevant issues, particularly in Southern California where the impact of humans on the environment is especially salient.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0731843</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Horn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mhorn@fullerton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Darren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sandquist</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dsandquist@fullerton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Woods</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>awoods@fullerton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kirby</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mkirby@fullerton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State University-Fullerton Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Fullerton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>928313014</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6572782106</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1121 North State College Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1580</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
