<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Taxonomic, Phylogenetic, and Evolutionary Studies of Horse flies (Diptera:Tabanidae): An Integrated Approach to Systematics Training</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>742541</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The fly family Tabanidae (horse flies) includes an estimated 4000 extant species distributed throughout the world. Nearly all are blood-feeders as adults, but many are also important pollinators of flowers. The biology and taxonomy of horse flies has an important historical legacy, but modern revisionary work has lagged behind other dipteran groups due to a generational reduction in the number of horse fly taxonomists and to a perceived ""difficult"" morphology, which is often similar for many standard fly characters. Current classifications are heavily biased by previous work on better known fly groups, while many smaller groups need to be addressed to provide context and new characters from which more comprehensive phylogenetic revision can proceed. This study will integrate modern tools and practices in taxonomy and systematics to address the need for increased attention to horse fly biodiversity and classification. The research team extends a successful collaborative framework with expertise in monographic, phylogenetic, and bioinformatic data generation, and builds on active efforts initiated by previous Partnership for Enhancing Expertise in Taxonomy (PEET) projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will foster collaboration in laboratory and field studies between faculty and students from Australia and the US. The results of the work will be made available to scientists and the general public via a database and web site directly associated with the project, as well as the integration of taxonomic tools and a project database. Projects are designed to encourage both mentorship and collaboration amongst the student trainees. In addition to their taxonomic work, each trainee will be asked to specialize in one of three general areas: bioinformatics techniques, computational/analytical techniques, or outreach methods. As they develop in these areas, they will be expected to mentor each other in their chosen expertise and to produce products that are disseminated through the projects web portals. The project involves a strong component of academic training for postdoctoral associates, graduate, and undergraduate students. In addition, there is a comprehensive program of outreach, including educational material that will be presented via the project web site and several other online resources for undergraduate and K-12 levels produced by the collaborating universities and through the Education and Outreach resources of the National Evolutionary Synthesis Center.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0731528</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kampmeier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gkamp@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yeates</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>d.yeates@mailbox.uq.edu.au</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shelah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morita</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>simorita@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wiegmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bwiegman@unity.ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
      <CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7376</Code>
      <Text>PARTNER TO ENHANCE EXP IN TAX</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
