<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative research..Molecular Biology for Environmental Engineers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/06/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>37995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Don L. Millard</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this project is to adapt and implement a prior successful CCLI pilot project developed at the University of Cincinnati (DUE 0127279) where hands-on laboratory modules and multi-media course materials have been used to introduce teams of undergraduate engineering students to molecular biology as a screening tool to track microorganisms in the environment. The pilot project will be reproduced at four peer institutions with assessment performed both locally and a "meta-assessment" performed as an overall component of the project. An advisory board with representatives from two- and four-year undergraduate institutions, an HBCU, and the National Academy of Engineering will provide independent feedback to the team. Expected outcomes of the project include: four additional institutions offering an inquiry-based course where interdisciplinary teams of undergraduate students collaborate on open-ended group projects following the "full-cycle 16S rRNA approach"; a text book to be published by a nationally-recognized publishing house; and broad dissemination through presentations at conferences and publications in the peer-review engineering education literature. The project will include successfully bridging the gap between environmental engineering research and undergraduate instruction to integrate molecular biology tools into the day-to-day practice of environmental engineering. A two- and four-year institutions and an HBCU will participate in this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0731479</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Baikun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baikun@engr.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
      <CityName>Storrs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7428</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
