<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Teaching Excellence in Math and Science (TEMS): Noyce Math and Science Scholars Consortium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>917067</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan T Prival</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Phase I Noyce project is a collaboration between California State University, Chico and CSU Sacramento, in partnership with three area school districts - Chico Unified School District, Oroville Union High School District, and Sacramento City Unified School District, and the Northeastern California Curriculum Committee which represents all the rural schools of Northeastern California.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These two California State University campuses have long been leaders in providing highly qualified mathematics and science teachers for a service region larger than the size of Ohio that includes both rural remote regions as well as large urban areas with large populations of low income, culturally and linguistically diverse students. In conjunction with other existing programs, the Noyce Scholars program is assisting Chico and Sacramento in doubling the number of mathematics and science teachers they produce in the next five years, a statewide goal of the CSU system. Specifically, TEMS is producing 25-30 new math and science teachers at each campus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TEMS is adding to the scholarly work at both campuses. TEMS is providing support to create and enhance programs for all math and science pre-service teachers, not just Noyce scholars. Programs and activities that are being expanded through Noyce include: Hands-On Lab science teaching experiences, Project M.A.T.H. (Mathematics And Teaching on the Horizon), new courses for STEM professionals allowing them to gain teaching credentials, expanded teacher recruitment activities, expanded early field experiences for pre-service teachers, collaborative efforts with existing programs such as the Alliance for Minority Participation, the Mathematics and Science Teaching Initiative, California Postsecondary Education Commission grant programs for retaining new math and science teachers on both campuses, and the Beginning Teacher Support and Assessment induction programs. Mentoring and advising also is being expanded to insure the success of Noyce scholars from underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, TEMS is bringing the scholars and faculty from two different environments together to learn from each other, thus increasing their capacity to effectively teach populations of students throughout California. Finally, the project's evaluation plan is being designed to be a prototype evaluation model for the California State University System and is adding to the body of knowledge about widening the pipeline to the teaching profession in mathematics and science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0733758</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laurel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heffernan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>heffernanl@csus.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/27/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fisher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wfisher@csuchico.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/28/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deidre</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sessoms</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sessoms@csus.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Summers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dsummers@csuchico.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brandi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aranguren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baranguren@csuchico.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State University, Chico Research Fdtn</Name>
      <CityName>Chico</CityName>
      <ZipCode>959290001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5308985700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
