<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Incubator for Nanotechnology Ventures, Emerging Sciences, and Technologies (INVEST)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>142753</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan H. Hixson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Chemistry (12)&lt;br/&gt;Russell Sage College (RSC), an undergraduate college for women, is (1) enhancing the ability of undergraduates to visualize and understand nanoscale science concepts and giving them hands-on experiences related to nanotechnology, (2) preparing undergraduates to be fully prepared to undertake careers in the workforce or to enter graduate studies in nanoscale science, (3) educating future teachers about nanoscale science and the societal issues arising from this emerging technology while developing their teaching skills, and (4) enabling students to have significant interdisciplinary peer interactions, nurturing an appreciation in students for the multi-disciplinary nature of nanotechnology. This project focuses on educating women in the physical sciences, while at the same time emphasizing career opportunities available though the science and application of nanotechnology and related emerging sciences coupled with entrepreneurship and leadership. RSC is the only college for women with an incubator for start-up companies using emerging technologies located on campus. The INVEST incubator facility (opened in September 2006) and the Department of Chemistry and Physics are located in adjacent buildings, and this situation is leading to unique opportunities for RSC students and faculty, as well as senior scientific staff of Evident Technologies, the incubator's first tenant. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Making use of the INVEST facility, the project is adapting existing nanotechnology learning experiences from around the country while specifically addressing the need for recruiting women into the physical sciences, and nanotechnology in particular. Nanoscience modules previously developed at larger universities such as Binghamton University, the University of Northern Colorado, and the University of Wisconsin, and guided inquiry experiences are being implemented and adapted into first- and second year courses, impacting students majoring in chemistry, biochemistry, forensic science, biology, mathematics, and pre-engineering. Students in these courses are using a scanning tunneling microscope and a multi-purpose atomic force microscope in the laboratories. About 30 students per year will be involved in research opportunities in the incubator. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Nanotechnology learning experiences are being adapted for use in the Women in the World courses required of all students at the beginning and end of each student's college career. Thus the project is impacting students from STEM, non-STEM and pre-service education. The project also is working to increase involvement of students from groups underrepresented in STEM disciplines and nanoscale science, through active recruitment, financial support, RSC outreach efforts, and internships. A series of seminars and workshops is further disseminating information about nanotechnology to the wider academic community, as well as to middle and high school teachers in the greater Capital District and in rural school districts of the Hudson Valley.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0736881</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Donnelly</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>donnek@sage.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Keane</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>keanet@sage.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The Sage Colleges</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121804115</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182444551</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>65 1st Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
