<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Consortium Support for International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas H. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal 0737954&lt;br/&gt;""Doctoral Consortium Support for International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling""&lt;br/&gt;PI: Mark Boddy&lt;br/&gt;AAAI&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the participation of doctoral students from U.S. universities in the Doctoral Consortium of the 17th International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling (ICAPS-07) to be held September 22-26 in Providence, Rhode Island. ICAPS is the premier conference for research in artificial intelligence planning and scheduling. Topics include all aspects of scheduling theory and practice, including a wide spectrum of applications (e.g., software, manufacturing, robotics). At this year's conference, there will be a specific focus on incorporating work in two related areas of research: machine learning and model-based reasoning. This Doctoral Consortium will provide participants with the opportunity to interact with established researchers as well as fellow doctoral students. The overall goals of the ICAPS Doctoral Consortium include providing participants with valuable feedback and exposure to additional perspectives on their work at a critical time in their doctoral research projects as well as providing helpful career advice at a critical time in their professional development. Participants will receive feedback and advice from assigned mentors and fellow participants through activities and discussions at the Consortium as well as through a Poster Session of the main ICAPS conference. Participants in the Doctoral Consortium will be invited to publish their research abstracts on the conference web site and in the proceedings that will be distributed to all conference attendees</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0737954</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boddy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mark.boddy@adventiumenterprises.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence</Name>
      <CityName>East Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943033224</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6503283123</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2275 E BAYSHORE RD STE 160</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
