<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Combinatorics and Statistical Mechanics: Travel by U.S.-Based Researchers to the Newton Institute Special Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29946</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Recent years have seen the emergence of an exciting new interdisciplinary field situated in the area between mathematics, computer science and statistical physics, concerned broadly with the study of "probability theory on graphs"&lt;br/&gt;or "statistical mechanics on graphs" (or on other combinatorial structures). This new field is attracting a great deal of international interest, as exemplified by the flourishing of interdisciplinary journals such as _Combinatorics, Probability and Computing_ and _Random Structures and Algorithms_.&lt;br/&gt;Very frequently, identical problems arise independently in combinatorics and statistical mechanics, albeit in different guises, and much recent progress has come from exploiting the cross-fertilization of methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Isaac Newton Institute for Mathematical Sciences (Cambridge University, UK) will be holding a 6-month program on Combinatorics and Statistical Mechanics from January-June 2008.&lt;br/&gt;The PI is one of the co-organizers of this interdisciplinary program.&lt;br/&gt;The aims of this program are to bring together expertise in the areas of graph theory and combinatorics, statistical mechanics, probability and computer science to attack unsolved problems that seem ripe for solution.&lt;br/&gt;A further aim is attract research students and postdoctoral fellows by providing brief tutorial lectures in each field and by offering them close contact with leading researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a group travel grant aimed at supporting the participation of U.S.-based researchers, with special emphasis on those who may not have access to alternative funding sources for their travel and&lt;br/&gt;subsistence: particularly young researchers, women, minorities, and researchers based at small colleges.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0737730</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sokal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sokal@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
