<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>7th International Workshop on Future Information Processing Technologies. To be held September 4-7, 2007 in Dresden, Germany.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajinder P. Khosla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective:&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this proposal is to request partial support from NSF for the participation of some of the attendees from the universities in North America. This will enable some of the junior faculty to attend the 7th International Workshop on Future Information Processing Technologies (IWFIPT)&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The IWFIPT is designed to project long-term trends in information technologies across a wide spectrum of areas. This forum typically examines underlying trends as well as emerging and evolving areas of application for the technologies: solid state technology; nanotechnology; devices; circuits; and system architectures. The participants will identify research opportunities at the frontiers of information processing that will catalyze progress into the 21st Century and beyond the ITRS roadmap. One of the focus areas of the workshop is the anticipated end of scaling for charge-transport devices based on CMOS in the next 10 to 15 years and how to bridge into the next generation of nanoelectronics. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: &lt;br/&gt;The conference will establish a global communication link and network between researchers from different disciplines and backgrounds in an international environment. It will nurture a fruitful exchange of experiences and ideas. The findings of the workshop will be made available as summaries through a final report to attendees and sponsors of the workshop</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0738615</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Herr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>herr@src.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ralph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cavin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cavin@src.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Semiconductor Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277038447</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9199419400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1101 Slater Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>4710</Code>
      <Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
