<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EMSW21-RTG: New Techniques in Low-Dimensional Topology and Geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1999440</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS 0739392&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: John W. Morgan, Mikhail G. Khovanov,&lt;br/&gt;Walter D. Neumann, Peter S. Ozsvath&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Low-dimensional topology is undergoing a revolution thanks to an&lt;br/&gt;infusion of new techniques from other areas, including&lt;br/&gt;mathematical physics, representation theory, holomorphic curve&lt;br/&gt;theory, analysis, and algebraic geometry. This fusion of&lt;br/&gt;techniques has led to an explosion of results and also new&lt;br/&gt;avenues of research. Examples of this include Perelman's recent&lt;br/&gt;proof of the Poincare conjecture using methods from geometric&lt;br/&gt;analysis; Donaldson's gauge theory approach to construct&lt;br/&gt;invariants for smooth four-manifolds, and the subsequent&lt;br/&gt;discovery of the Seiberg-Witten equations; invariants of three&lt;br/&gt;and four-manifolds defined via holomorphic curves; the quantum&lt;br/&gt;polynomial invariants for knots and, more recently, their&lt;br/&gt;categorifications. This project aims to train the next&lt;br/&gt;generation of researchers in these exciting and vibrant subjects,&lt;br/&gt;including graduate students and postdocs; and also to widely&lt;br/&gt;disseminate the latest discoveries in these fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of this proposal is to stimulate the research training&lt;br/&gt;environment at Columbia University in the new developments in&lt;br/&gt;low-dimensional topology and geometry. Many of these developments&lt;br/&gt;have been pioneered by faculty at Columbia. The objectives of&lt;br/&gt;this program are: (i) to increase the number of undergraduates&lt;br/&gt;who will pursue graduate studies in this exciting and active area&lt;br/&gt;of mathematics, and to ensure that their training equips them&lt;br/&gt;well for graduate studies; (ii) to broaden and strengthen the&lt;br/&gt;research background of the graduate students at Columbia, so that&lt;br/&gt;they are better equipped to fulfill their research potential, and&lt;br/&gt;contribute meaningfully to this rapidly-changing subject; (iii)&lt;br/&gt;to prepare the postdoctoral associates for more independent&lt;br/&gt;research in this area; (iv) to foster communication among all&lt;br/&gt;strata in the research group at Columbia, and in fact to train&lt;br/&gt;the associated students and postdocs in expository skills,&lt;br/&gt;teaching, and research; and (v) to foster the dissemination of&lt;br/&gt;knowledge in this field from Columbia University to the wider&lt;br/&gt;mathematical community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0739392</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ozsvath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>petero@math.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/26/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morgan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmorgan@scgp.stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/26/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Walter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neumann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>neumann@math.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mikhail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khovanov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>khovanov@math.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mikhail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Khovanov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>khovanov@math.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/26/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
