<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR PHASE I: Simple Desulfurizing Component Enables Fuel Processing of Sulfur-laden Logistic Fuels for Fuel Cells</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149990</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cynthia A. Znati</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will investigate the technical and commercial feasibility of coating metal foils with a solid sorbent so that they act as a desulfurizing component for pre-treatment of sulfur-laden liquid fuels. The coated foils will be inserted into a small heat exchanger that acts as a platform unit for conversion of liquid fuels to hydrogen for fuel cell applications; the heat exchanger platform has already been demonstrated as a reforming device. This sorbent unit, when coupled with the reformer, will allow fuel cells to be operated on high-sulfur liquid fuels, allowing their use in power systems for military and aviation applications with no change in the fuel infrastructure. Novel nanoporous sorbents will be developed and tested for their sulfur sorption capability. A select group of these sorbent materials will be coated onto metal foils for further testing, including stability of the sorbent on foil and capacity for regeneration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial significance from this technology will be fuel cell technologies that will offer unique opportunities for significant reductions in energy use, emissions, noise, and thermal signature from auxiliary power systems in certain applications (such as transportation).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/17/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0740466</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sudipta</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chattopadhyay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sudipta@catacel.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CATACEL CORP</Name>
      <CityName>GARRETTSVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>442319749</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3304684984</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>7998 GOTHAM RD.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
