<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: Spectrally Diverse Ultrafast Lasers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I research project addresses the need for high-power ultrafast lasers from the visible to the mid-wave infrared spectral regions. This research will develop a highly innovative ultrafast laser system emitting sub-picosecond pulses that is based on unexplored coupling between stimulated Raman scattering, stimulated Brillouin scattering, and four-wave mixing. Because none of these processes requires resonance with a single-photon transition, the technique will lead to ultrashort pulse generation at virtually any wavelength. Furthermore, the wavelength flexibility enables pumping with mature, extremely high power diode and fiber laser sources. Unique features of the gain medium will enable scaling of this system to the kilowatt average power level. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is commercial potential for a high-power ultrafast laser system with such spectral accessibility. For instance, this source can be used to avoid or target atmospheric and/or material absorptions in the mid-wave infrared. It could therefore lead for example to greatly improved free-space ground-to-satellite communications systems, efficient laser machining /welding, active hyperspectral imaging, and ultrafast materials research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0740705</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>roos@bridgerphotonics.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/06/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Bridger Photonics, INC</Name>
      <CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597155652</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4065852774</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2310 University Way, Bldg 4-4</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
