<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Compact THz-ABCD Spectrometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I research project proposes to develop a Compact TeraHertz (THz) Air-Breakdown-Coherent Detection (ABCD) Spectrometer. Specifically, this research will construct and integrate this THz spectrometer based on recent experimental and theoretical research on broadband THz waves produced from laser-induced plasma in ambient air. A focused optical pulse in a gas creates atmospheric plasma (ionized gas molecules) which produces very intense, highly-directional, and ultra-broadband THz waves in the far field. Through the reciprocal process, this plasma could also serve as a sensor of pulsed THz waves through air-breakdown coherent detection. With the introduction of secondary synchronized laser pulses, amplification of the THz field (amplitude, phase, and radiation direction) can also be achieved.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent significant advances in THz science and technology will help scientists and engineers to use pulsed plasma to emit, control, enhance, and measure broadband THz waves. Applications include non-destructive testing, tomographic imaging, label-free genetic analysis, cellular level imaging, explosives detection, and chemical/biological sensing. In addition to advancing numerous sensing and imaging concepts in the THz frequency range, with an immediate impact on non-destructive analysis, a short-term application for homeland security and a longer-term interest in the biomedical sector.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/09/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0740625</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tongue</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ttongue@zomega-terahertz.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuguang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yuguang.zhao@zomega-terahertz.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/09/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/27/2008</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Zomega Terahertz Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>East Greenbush</CityName>
      <ZipCode>120614137</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5188330577</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>15 Tech Valley Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
