<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RET-PLUS (Partners Linking Urban Schools)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a 3 year standard award to support a Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) in Engineering Site program at Northeastern University entitled, "RET-PLUS (Partners Linking Urban Schools," under the direction of Dr. Michael Silevitch and Ms. Claire Duggan. This is a renewal of a previously supported three year RET Site. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Northeastern University's Center for STEM Education in collaboration with the Bernard M. Gordon Center for Subsurface Sensing and Imaging Systems (Gordon-CenSSIS) an NSF Engineering Research Center (ERC), and the College of Engineering, will continue its current RET program to build and support STEM change agents throughout partner schools. Ten participants per year for three years from local K-12 school districts and community colleges will participate in a six week comprehensive program during the summer. Participants and mentor faculty will engage in collaborative inquiry through shared research experiences. This will strengthen the content knowledge of teachers, build understanding and professional respect, and provide opportunities for leadership and professional development for all members of the RET team.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funding for this award is being provided by the Engineering Research Centers (ERC) Program in the Division of Engineering Education and Centers (EEC).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742924</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Silevitch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>m.silevitch@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Claire</FirstName>
      <LastName>Duggan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>c.duggan@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
