<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REVSYS: Phylogeny and Systematics of the Megachilid Bees</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>370000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maureen M. Kearney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The bee family Megachilidae includes over 3000 species (~20% of the bees in the world) including many important wild and managed pollinators. The classification and evolutionary history of this family are poorly understood and species-level identification is difficult for many groups. This project will analyze the systematics, taxonomy, biology and evolutionary history of the entire family with special emphasis on the tribe Anthidiini. The research involves two inter-related projects: (1) analysis of the evolutionary history of the group using morphological and molecular data and (2) analysis of the species-level taxonomy of select, speciose genera. These projects are tightly interwoven because evolutionary history provides the basis for a stable, species-level classification. Results (including illustrated interactive keys, online databases, species-level catalogs) will be made available as web-accessible digital resource that will be of considerable use to pollination and conservation biologists. Efforts to diversify crop pollinators and to monitor pollinator services in natural, as well as agricultural ecosystems, will be strengthened through knowledge of megachilid behavior, floral preferences, nesting habits, and distributions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bees are among the most important pollinators in both natural and agricultural settings. Bees provide pollination services for an enormous range of crops including cantaloupe, cocoa, coffee, kiwi, passion fruits, squashes, pumpkins, watermelons, apples, peaches and many others. The bee family Megachilidae includes some of the most important wild and managed pollinators, such as leaf-cutter bees, mason bees, and orchard bees. This study will greatly improve our ability to identify (and therefore manage) native pollinators as well as monitor native pollinator populations. The grant will provide training of a new generation of bee researchers with expertise in bee taxonomy. The project will involve substantial collaboration with entomologists in developing African countries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742998</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Danforth</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bnd1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Griswold</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Terry.Griswold@ARS.USDA.GOV</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
