<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Kansas Partnership for Graduate Fellows in K-12 Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2901286</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Tankersley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Graduate Teaching Fellows in K-12 Education (GK-12)&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal: # 0742523&lt;br/&gt;PI: Dennis Lane&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Kansas Center for Research, Inc.&lt;br/&gt;Title: The Kansas Partnership for Graduate Fellows in K-12 Classrooms&lt;br/&gt;The Kansas Partnership for Graduate Fellows in K-12 Education &lt;br/&gt;NSF supported STEM disciplines: Mathematics, Computational Biology, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will engage graduate fellows with middle school science teachers from the Middle School Science Academy (MSSA) to enhance the professional development of the fellows and associated teachers through activities involving Scientific Inquiry, multi-disciplinary physical science, and life sciences focusing on evolution. &lt;br/&gt;The Kansas Partnership for Graduate Fellows will provide middle school instructional experiences in urban Kansas school districts for science, mathematics and engineering graduate students. The goal of the Kansas Partnership project is to assist graduate students to be better communicators of their science with K-12 teachers and students in particular and with the broader community of non-scientists in general. The specific anticipated outcomes of this project are to: provide highly qualified Ph.D. candidates in engineering and science with a unique opportunity for professional growth through the development of their teaching and learning skills; foster the incorporation of additional hands-on science experiences and cooperative learning strategies into middle school classrooms; establish a sustainable outreach partnership among the partner school districts that will provide a vehicle for interpreting the significance of science and engineering, and; contribute to improving the science achievement of at-risk middle school students in two of the largest urban school districts in Kansas. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit of the project addresses removal of barriers to student engagement in science and engineering through innovative content delivery using active learning strategies and science research activities based on National and State curriculum standards for grades 6-9. The institutionalization of the professional development courses, the interaction with the Uplink program and the continued commitment of the Centers to maintain their partnership with the districts will ensure the sustainability and broader impact of the program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742523</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lane</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lane@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bozenna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pasik-Duncan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bozenna@math.ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heppert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jheppert@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Case</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stcase@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7179</Code>
      <Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7179</Code>
      <Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
