<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Revised Program Evaluation Standards, 3rd Edition: Field Trials of the Applicability and Quality for STEM Program and Project Evaluations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>26140</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul W. Jennings</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Hopson Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PROPOSAL SUMMARY: BACKGROUND AND PURPOSE &lt;br/&gt;The Joint Committee on Standards for Educational Evaluation (JCSEE) is an independent, non-profit, American National Standards Institute (ANSI) member organization whose mission is the development and dissemination of standards related to personnel, student and program evaluation (JCSEE, 1994; 2003; in press). The standards development process as approved by the JCSEE and endorsed by ANSI relies heavily on user and stakeholder input and feedback in the development of standard content and format. &lt;br/&gt;A most important group of stakeholders to provide information on the quality of the Program Evaluation Standards is comprised of practicing STEM educators and curriculum and program developers. The PgES Development Task Force is proposing three national meetings of STEM educators with a stake in STEM program evaluation to meet with the PgES Task Force members. Stakeholder-participants at these meetings will review selected 3rd Edition draft standards and apply them to evaluation tasks, such as STEM curriculum, program or project improvement or accountability studies. Using well-developed field trial and review materials, the Task Force members will facilitate trials of the developed standards that result in identifying ways to improve the standards for the typical applications and uses by STEM educators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742033</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yarbrough</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>d-yarbrough@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rodney</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hopson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hopson@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duquesne University</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152820001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4123961537</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Room 310 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7261</Code>
      <Text>PROGRAM EVALUATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
