<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Application of Cascade Processes for the Synthesis of Polycyclic Ring Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>455000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project will make use of novel cascade sequences for the assemblage of complex target molecules. One of the immediate goals is to develop a new approach toward piperidine synthesis that employs a tandem reaction sequence using various oximes with 2,3-bis(phenylsulfonyl)-1,3-diene. Formation of an aza-oxabicyclic ring cycloadduct involves conjugate addition of the oxime onto the diene to give a transient nitrone which then undergoes a subsequent intramolecular dipolar cycloaddition reaction. The research goals also call for a formal synthesis of the novel marine alkaloid halichlorine using a related series of reactions. The intramolecular Diels-Alder cycloaddition/rearrangement cascade of 2-amido substituted furans represents a very effective strategy for the preparation of a variety of naturally occurring alkaloids. As part of the project, the preparation of the Strychnos pentacyclic framework will be studied using this cascade approach. Another goal will be to explore the synthetic power of the tandem cyclization/cycloaddition sequence of rhodium carbenoids toward the synthesis of several Vinca alkaloids. Examination of the cyclization reaction using several alpha-diazo substituted beta-carbolines as well as its application toward the Vinca alkaloid family, including the synthesis of tacamine and vincarodine, will be undertaken. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor Albert Padwa of the Department of Chemistry at Emory University. Professor Padwa's research efforts revolve around the use of novel cascade sequences for the assemblage of complex target molecules often used in the production of new drugs and agricultural compounds. The research outlined in the proposal also represents ideal training for undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral students, which is in keeping with NSF's goals of research and education. Students trained during the performance of this research will use this knowledge to make important future contributions in pharmaceutical research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0742663</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Albert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Padwa</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chemap@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Emory University</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
