<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The role of sprinter in Wg signaling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven L. Klein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Principal Investigator: Erica Marie Selva&lt;br/&gt;Proposal number IOS-0744371&lt;br/&gt;Title: The role of sprinter in Wg signaling&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is well established that development of multicellular animals requires that cells can communicate their position and identity over large distances. One way this information is transmitted is that a sending cell releases proteins into spaces between cells and these proteins diffuse until a neighboring cell detects their presence and changes its behavior in response to this signal. The wnt genes encode a large family of secreted glycoproteins that act as such extracellular signaling molecules. The founding member in Drosophila is Wingless (Wg) and related proteins have been identified in all metazoans. Binding of Wnt/Wg to its cognate membrane receptor in the target signal receiving cells initiates intracellular changes that drive innumerable phases of both Drosophila and vertebrate development. Recently, the Selva laboratory has identified a novel protein in Drosophila named Sprinter (Srt, as known as Wntless and Evi) that is required for the secretion of active Wg/Wnt from the cells that express it. However, its actual function in the complex Wnt maturation process is not yet understood. Notably organisms from Drosophila to human have genes highly similar to srt and Srt might represent a dedicated factor for the secretion of all 7 Drosophila and 19 human Wnts. The goal of the proposed studies is to combine the sophisticated genetics of Drosophila with a cell culture model to dissect the function of Srt in Wg/Wnt maturation and deployment. These studies will have broader impacts on our understanding of the importance of Srt dependent Wg/Wnt signaling events during organismal development and promote the scientific enrichment and development of future basic researchers, as undergraduate students including underrepresented minorities will perform much of the work in this proposal.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0744371</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Erica</FirstName>
      <LastName>Selva</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>selva@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
