<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Mobility Control for Robotic Sensor Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>81761</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Yu Oh</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project focuses on the development of mobility strategies for&lt;br/&gt;Robotic Sensor Networks (RSNs) which are networks of robots equipped&lt;br/&gt;with communication, computation and sensing capabilities. For RSN&lt;br/&gt;technology to be utilized in critical applications such as emergency&lt;br/&gt;response and environmental monitoring, mobility algorithms for&lt;br/&gt;operation in dynamic and complex environments are needed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, three novel mobility problems which arise in many RSN&lt;br/&gt;applications are introduced. These problems are general enough to&lt;br/&gt;capture the interplay between communication, sensing and&lt;br/&gt;mobility. Yet, they can be succinctly formulated as geometric&lt;br/&gt;optimization problems. This work will focus on solving these mobility&lt;br/&gt;problems which will yield provably correct solutions for numerous RSN&lt;br/&gt;applications. In addition, bounds on the performance of a given RSN in&lt;br/&gt;fundamental problems such as tracking, collaborative sensing and&lt;br/&gt;estimation will be established.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The output of this research will be a significant step toward enabling&lt;br/&gt;the use of fully autonomous RSNs for crucial applications in emergency&lt;br/&gt;response, energy and environmental monitoring, and health care&lt;br/&gt;automation. Sensing and actuation play important roles in the&lt;br/&gt;evolution of information technology. The project will contribute to&lt;br/&gt;this evolution through the development of novel distributed sensing&lt;br/&gt;and control algorithms.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0745537</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ibrahim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Isler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>isler@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/31/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
