<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Storing, Querying and Re-Using Provenance of Computational Tasks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>434507</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Xiaoyang Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Workflow-based systems have emerged as an alternative to ad-hoc&lt;br/&gt;approaches to data exploration that are widely used in the scientific&lt;br/&gt;community. Workflows can capture computational tasks at various levels&lt;br/&gt;of detail and systematically record the provenance (history) information&lt;br/&gt;necessary for reproducibility, result publication and&lt;br/&gt;sharing. Although the benefits of using scientific workflow systems&lt;br/&gt;are well known, the fact that workflows are hard to create and&lt;br/&gt;maintain has been a major barrier to wider adoption of the technology&lt;br/&gt;in the scientific domain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to produce new algorithms and techniques&lt;br/&gt;for exploring and re-using useful knowledge embedded in workflow&lt;br/&gt;specifications and in the provenance of the data they manipulate.&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses key limitations in existing workflow&lt;br/&gt;systems. First, it develops a set of usable tools that enable casual&lt;br/&gt;users (who do not necessarily have programming expertise) to perform&lt;br/&gt;exploratory tasks and solve problems through workflows. These include&lt;br/&gt;intuitive user interfaces to manipulate collections of workflow and to&lt;br/&gt;query workflows by example. Second, it builds a scalable provenance&lt;br/&gt;management infrastructure to support the efficient execution of these&lt;br/&gt;operations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research results of this project advance the state of the art and&lt;br/&gt;build fundamental knowledge in storing, querying, and re-using&lt;br/&gt;provenance of computational tasks. This project has the potential to&lt;br/&gt;impact a variety of applications where the creation and maintenance of&lt;br/&gt;workflows is currently a major bottleneck. This includes large&lt;br/&gt;computational science projects and portals. Furthermore, it makes&lt;br/&gt;workflows and workflow technology more accessible to casual users.&lt;br/&gt;Through our interdisciplinary collaborations, this project will have&lt;br/&gt;immediate impact in helping improve the scientific discovery process.&lt;br/&gt;The involvement of graduate and undergraduate students in the project&lt;br/&gt;will provide mentoring opportunities. The PI is committed to&lt;br/&gt;recruiting minority students. The results of this project will be&lt;br/&gt;disseminated as research papers and as freely available tools at the&lt;br/&gt;project website:&lt;br/&gt;http://www.cs.utah.edu/~juliana/projects/NSF-IIS-0746500</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0746500</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Juliana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Freire</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>juliana.freire@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7684</Code>
      <Text>STRATEGIC TECHNOLOGIES FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7684</Code>
      <Text>STRATEGIC TECHNOLOGIES FOR CI</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
