<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: An Integrated and Utility-Centric Framework for Federated Text Search</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>492983</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Traditional search engines like Google typically ignore a large amount of information behind the search engines of many online text information sources. Federated text search provides one-stop access to the hidden information via a single interface that connects to multiple search engines of text information sources. Existing federated search solutions only focus on content relevance and ignore a large amount of valuable information about users and information sources. This project includes novel research on: (1) Multiple Type Resource Representation: model important information of text information sources such as search response time and search engine effectiveness; (2) Utility-Centric Resource Selection: satisfy a user's search criteria by considering multiple types of evidence such as content relevance, search results from past queries, personal information needs, and search response time; (3) Effective and Efficient Results Merging: produce accurate merged ranked results with little cost of acquiring the content information of the returned documents; (4) System Adaptation by Results Analysis: analyze the search results from past queries for more accurate federated search solutions; (5) System Development and Evaluation: build and test algorithms within research environments as well as a new FedLemur system for a real world application. The project advances the state-of-the-art of research in federated search. It will have broad impacts for other applications such as peer to peer search. The project Web site (http://www.cs.purdue.edu/~lsi/Federated_Search_Career_Award.html) will be used for results dissemination.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The education component of the project will expand information retrieval instruction to address multi-disciplinary requirements, improve the education of information technology workforce, and arouse interests of K-12 students for search technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0746830</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Si</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lsi@cs.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
