<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Object Recognition with Hierarchical Models</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>449864</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: CAREER: Object Recognition with Hierarchical Models&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Pedro Felzenszwalb&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Chicago&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CAREER: Object Recognition with Hierarchical Models&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Object recognition is one of the most important problems in computer vision. While researchers have worked on this problem for over thirty years, vision systems are still unable to recognize many common objects in cluttered images. The PI proposes to address this problem by developing new hierarchical models and efficient search algorithms for recognition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hierarchical models represent objects using parts which are themselves defined in terms of subparts. Moreover, the subparts may be recursively defined in terms of smaller components. This hierarchical organization can efficiently encode important relationships among the components that make up an object. Another important property of hierarchical models is that components can be shared among different object models. This is useful for being able to quickly recognize which of many possible objects are present in an image. It is also important for learning models from small datasets. Finally, in the most general types of models the structure of an object may be specified by a grammar instead of being fixed in advance. The number of parts that make up an object may be variable and there may be choice among different parts that can go in a particular place. All of these aspects make hierarchical models incredibly expressive.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Algorithms for object recognition typically search over large spaces encoding the pose of an object, or over correspondences between model features and features extracted from an image. The PI will develop efficient optimization algorithms for solving these problems. This will be accomplished by exploiting the structure of the search spaces defined by general classes of hierarchical models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader significance and importance: Object recognition has many important practical applications, including in robotics, human-computer interaction, image retrieval, security systems and medical image analysis. Research in object recognition can also play an important role in our understanding of human perception and &lt;br/&gt;intelligence. The proposed research will draw upon ideas from diverse areas such as computer vision, theoretical computer science, natural language understanding and mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;URL: http://people.cs.uchicago.edu/~pff/hierarchical</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0746569</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pedro</FirstName>
      <LastName>Felzenszwalb</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pff@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
