<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Magnetic Reconnection--An Observational Investigation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>475906</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020203</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ilia I. Roussev</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Principal Investigator (PI) plans to, for the first time, quantitatively determine the topology and energetics of solar magnetic reconnection from observations. She will develop and implement new techniques for analyzing state-of-the-art observations of solar flare evolution and magnetic fields, obtained by ground-based observatories (such as BBSO, NSO, and OVSA) as well as by spacecraft (such as Hinode, TRACE, RHESSI, and SoHO). The PI's observationally determined physical quantities will provide crucial constraints to theoretical models of magnetic reconnection, and will be applied to test models and study outstanding issues in solar physics, such as the magnetic structure and kinematics of coronal mass ejections (CMEs) at early stages in their evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In order to train the next generation of solar physicists, the PI will support a PhD student to conduct thesis research and engage undergraduate students in the data analysis, derivation of physical quantities, and testing of theoretical models. Also, to enhance undergraduate education in astronomy and general science at Montana State University, she will reform the existing solar system astronomy course. The PI plans to design and implement novel lab projects as an effective teaching tool, providing students with hands-on experience in obtaining astronomical observations and measurements. The PI expects the practical outcome of her innovations to be an upgraded campus observing system, a new laboratory manual, and a significantly improved astronomy course syllabus.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0748428</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jiong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Qiu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qiu@physics.montana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Montana State University</Name>
      <CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0205000</Code>
      <Name>Space</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
