<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Implementation of Sustainable Energy Related Processes in Microstructured Reactors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Burka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Alexandre F. Yokochi &lt;br/&gt;Institution: Oregon State University &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 0748280&lt;br/&gt;Title: CAREER: Implementation of Sustainable Energy Related Processes in Microstructured Reactors&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a CAREER grant to fund research and educational activities aimed at developing microreactor systems for sustainable hydrogen production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Microstructured reactors offer several advantages over conventional macroscopic reactors including simple, predictable flow paths and particle residence times, short diffusion lengths ensuring efficient mass transfer processes, fast and efficient heat transfer and others, which frequently enable simple implementation of processes that are otherwise difficult. A goal of this project is to look at microreactors where simultaneously there is reaction in the liquid phase and mass transfer between gas and liquid systems. The PI plans to examine an energy related model system, the Sulfur-Iodine Thermochemical Water Decomposition method for sustainable hydrogen production. Specifically the development of a reactor in which the Bunsen reaction is carried out in a room temperature ionic liquid will result in a system that does not require excess water or iodine, and yet still achieves the production of separate iodine and sulfur bearing streams.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This CAREER development plan will explore the development and implementation of reactive two and three phase processes, while inspiring educational understanding of the state-of-the-art of microstructured reactors and energy related issues. The project will be approached in the following manner:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Exploration of the low cost implementation of reactive systems in microreactors: This will explore the manner in which microreactors can be produced in a cost efficient manner for academic and industrial research. In particular, the application of very low cost inkjet based contact lithography and wet etching of glass to produce the desired systems will be explored, as will efficient manners to deploy catalytic materials within the reactors. Current work in the PI?s laboratory has demonstrated the initial steps in this low cost microreactor construction methodology. The development of this low cost, low infrastructure methodology will enable others to develop their own systems for their research purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Implementation of the Bunsen Reaction in an Ionic Liquid: Here, microstructured falling liquid film and bubble column reactors equipped with suitable controls and instrumentation will be constructed. Current work has shown that the Bunsen reaction can be caused to occur at room temperature in an ionic liquid with separate production of iodine and sulfur bearing streams in a batch reactor. However, determination of thermochemical parameters is essential for system identification and modeling. Using these reactors, solubility, mass transfer and reaction kinetic parameters and the effect of varying chemical conditions associated with performing the Bunsen reaction in an ionic liquid will be investigated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3. Educational Integration: The PI will strengthen the educational experience for Chemical Engineering students of all levels at OSU through 1) the introduction of modules discussing microstructured reactor issues in the senior capstone experience and 2) continuing to mentor undergraduate researchers through hosting senior project teams, Johnson scholars (college freshmen) and SESEY (high school) students in the laboratory to work on issues at the interface of process implementation in microreactors and energy production. These students will become an integral part of the research team on the work in question. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This research will result in the development of a novel method for performing the Bunsen reaction associated with the Sulfur-Iodine thermochemical cycle. The fluid processing methods proposed are fully compatible with the current process, and should greatly improve it, and would therefore be truly transformational research in the field of sustainable hydrogen production, opening a new area of research for individuals involved with renewable energy and enabling various future advances leading to the practical implementation of this method. Simultaneously, the work will be used as a platform to expose pre-college, undergraduate and graduate students (and fellow faculty!) to the issues surrounding the implementation of processes in microstructured reactors and the unusual properties of room temperature ionic liquids.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0748280</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexandre</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yokochi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alex.yokochi@orst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/19/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
