<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Hurricane Storm Surge Modeling on Petascale Computers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330679</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniel Katz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lead Proposal: OCI - 0749015 &lt;br/&gt;PI: Dawson, Clinton N&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Texas at Austin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-lead Proposal: OCI - 0749017&lt;br/&gt;PI: Hanna, Darrin M&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Oakland University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-lead Proposal: OCI ? 0746232&lt;br/&gt;PI: Westerink, Joannes J&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Notre Dame&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: "Collaborative Research" NSF PetaApps: Storm Surge Modeling on Petascale Computers&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to investigate the use of petascale computing to significantly advance the state-of-the-art in storm surge simulation, to accurately model flows at multiple, interacting scales, at resolution never before attempted, and to demonstrate that results from these simulations can be delivered in real-time to emergency managers. To achieve this goal will require the continued development and improved understand of the mechanisms involved in tightly coupled models of wind, waves, circulation and geomorphology, improvements in the description of the physical domain and adaptive resolution of all energetic flow scales, and investigation of accurate, robust and highly parallelizable numerical algorithms. Efficient implementation of these models on emerging petascale architectures will require utilizing the latest developments in parallel data management, real-time visualization, and programming tools. In this project, the&lt;br/&gt;PIs will develop high resolution, large-scale coastal inundation models coupled with regional-scale rainfall/runoff models. Robust and highly parallelizable algorithms will be investigated for solving these systems on petascale architectures. The models will be implemented on NSF Track 2 HPC systems currently under construction; furthermore, implementation of the models on novel hybrid architectures will also be explored.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Predicting and studying coastal inundation due to hurricanes and tropical storms is a problem of critical importance to the United States. Hurricane Katrina alone was the costliest and 5th deadliest hurricane in history, with most of the devastation due to wind-driven flooding during the storm. The aftermath of this event has led to a number of federally-mandated studies to determine what failed, the causes of failure, and how to prevent such catastrophes from happening again. Critical decisions will be made in the next several years on how to design better protection systems and improve emergency management practices in the event of future storms. Storm surge is caused by wind, atmospheric pressure gradients, tides, river flow, short-crested wind-waves, and rainfall. In this project, the investigators will develop an accurate numerical model of storm surge which accounts for all of these effects. This model will be tested in predictive mode as storms approach landfall for the purposes of emergency evacuation and response, and used to study the design and implementation of improved man-made and natural protection systems for vulnerable coastal areas. While storm surge models have been developed extensively over the past decade; only within the last few years have the algorithms, computational power and resolution been available to begin to model these events with any reasonable degree of accuracy. In addition to storm surge modeling, the computational methodology and simulation tools developed under this project are applicable to other problems in coastal engineering and marine science, including water quality, shipping and ports, marine ecology, naval operations, weather and climate, and wetland degradation. Furthermore, the technology developed under this project will be disseminated to government agencies such as FEMA, the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and NOAA.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0749017</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spagnuolo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spagnuol@oakland.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/24/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oakland University</Name>
      <CityName>Rochester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>483094401</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2483704116</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>530 Wilson Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7231</Code>
      <Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7552</Code>
      <Text>COFFES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7583</Code>
      <Text>ITR-HECURA</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7691</Code>
      <Text>PetaApps</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9139</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
