<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fe-mediated C-O cleavage and C-C bond forming reactions from CO2 and CO substrates</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>370000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic, and Organometallic Chemistry Program supports the work of Professor Jonas Peters at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology to investigate (phosphinoborate)iron(I) compounds that are structurally unusual by virtue of their relatively low coordination numbers and geometry. These complexes feature iron-nitrogen multiple bonds. These complexes have been found to mediate C-O cleavage pathways that effect partial or complete CO extrusion or reductive C-C coupling to produce oxalate. The synthesis of monometallic and bimetallic iron(oxo) species will also be explored particularly in terms of dihydrogen activation. Finally, the ability to activate carbon dioxide and release iron carbonyl products opens the door to using carbon dioxide as a synthon for C-C coupling reactions that exploit CO as a carbene or carbyne precursor. The synthesis and reactivities of iron(carbenes) and (carbynes) with hydrogen will also be investigated. In addition to the reductive degradation of carbon dioxide which may have important ramifications for the reduction of greenhouse gases and the development of new methods of carbon management, this research will encourage undergraduate and graduate students to become sensitive to energy conversion issues as they enter their chemical careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0750234</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peters</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpeters@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1966</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHETIC INORGANIC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9186</Code>
      <Text>RESOURCE USE AND MANAGEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
