<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multielectron Activation of Metal-Halide, Metal-Hydride and Metal-Oxo Bonds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>570000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy E. Patten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic, and Organometallic Chemistry Program supports Professor Daniel G. Nocera at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology for the exploration of efficient, and potentially economical, storage of solar energy in the form of chemical bonds. Basic chemical systems will be designed to provide multiple (usually two or four) electron equivalents for the conversion of water or hydrochloric acid and light into high energy products (hydrogen and oxygen or hydrogen and chlorine). Cobalt and rhodium Pacman (tethered diphorphyrin ligands) and Hangman (ligand architectures in which an acid group is positioned in proximity to the metal-hydride site) motifs will be examined electrochemically and photochemically, respectively, for their ability to generate dihydrogen (H2). Cobalt porphyrinogen systems will also be employed for dihydrogen generation. Dr. Nocera has been successful in raising public awareness of the global energy problem and the role that chemistry can play in addressing the energy challenge by appearing on national news, TV, radio programs, and other broadcast venues. He has made significant contributions to curriculum development by producing energy teaching modules for WGBH-TV, the CATALYST Program, and Science News for Kids.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0750239</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nocera</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dnocera@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1966</Code>
      <Text>SYNTHETIC INORGANIC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9186</Code>
      <Text>RESOURCE USE AND MANAGEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
