<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developing a Visual Semantic Query System to Enhance the Search Capability of Geospatial Data Portals</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>63191</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence Brandt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant will support the development of a novel Web-based visual semantic query system and a bottom-up semantic integration method to enhance the geospatial data search capability of the multi-agency Federal Web-based geospatial data portal, Geospatial One Stop (GOS). The efficiency and accuracy of data search will be increased with a searchable global view of semantically heterogeneous geospatial attributes. The results can be employed to other geospatial data portals and applications that need a solution to semantic integration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is interdisciplinary, involving GI Science, information science, and domain knowledge and will add visual semantic query functionality to geospatial portals and provide bottom-up semantic integration using local semantics without the need of an upper ontology or standardized terminology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broadly, this research will contribute to geospatial data integration that is an essential (but missing) component of the U.S. National Spatial Data Infrastructure. With GOS as a collaborator, a variety of users from both the public and academic community can benefit from the project results, e.g. emergency response and management activities that need a large amount of geospatial data.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0751001</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Naijun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>njzhou@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
