<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Americas Program: Topography, Elemental Ratios, and Nutrient Limitation in Tropical Montane Ecosystems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12817</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0751932&lt;br/&gt;Seastedt&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This dissertation research will examine the influence of topography and land use on nutrient availability in the tropical montane ecosystems of Amboró National Park in Bolivia. The research will be conducted in collaboration with the Foundation for the Conservation of the Chiquitano Forest (FCBC) under the auspices of Dr. Roberto Vides and the local community of Bella Vista. The interacting effects of topography and land use change on nutrient cycling will be investigated along topographically and experimentally manipulated gradients of nitrogen and phosphorus availability. The proposed project will investigate the contention that soil, foliar and microbial biomass elemental ratios (N and P) can be used to assess the nutrient limitation of an ecosystem. This study will make a significant contribution to scientific understanding of the role of nutrient limitation in tropical montane ecosystems of the Amboró region. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study aims to increase the understanding of the biochemistry of grasslands and forests of the region. Land managers and local farmers can use this information to make decisions that will extend the productivity and, in so far as possible, sustainability of such ecosystems. This proposal will support international dissertation research for one graduate student and will also provide an research experience for two undergraduate students, one from Bolivia and one from the US.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0751932</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nataly</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ascarrunz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nascarrunz@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seastedt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tims@culter.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/18/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510602</Code>
      <Name>Ecosystem Dynamics</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7731</Code>
      <Text>OTHER GLOBAL LEARNING &amp; TRNING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5926</Code>
      <Text>LATIN AMERICA, SDC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5977</Code>
      <Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
