<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Anthropology of Coltan Mining in the Eastern Democratic Republic of the Congo</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>90975</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anna Kerttula de Echave</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Jeffrey W. Mantz (George Mason University) and Dr. James H. Smith (University of&lt;br/&gt;California, Davis) will collaborate in research on the economic, political, and social&lt;br/&gt;consequences of columbite-tantalite mining in the Kivu provinces of the Democratic&lt;br/&gt;Republic of the Congo. From 1998 until 2003, this region was ground zero for what is&lt;br/&gt;widely referred to as Africa's first "world war," a conflict that pitted eight African nations&lt;br/&gt;against one another, and which has thus far cost the lives of over four million people. At&lt;br/&gt;the center of this conflict was a unique ore,columbite-tantalite or, as it is known in Africa,&lt;br/&gt;coltan. Coltan is an electrical current conductor used in the making of digital capacitors.&lt;br/&gt;Tantalum, which is processed from coltan, is crucial to all digital technologies, including&lt;br/&gt;cell phones, pagers, video game players, and digital music players. Over the past ten&lt;br/&gt;years, foreign armies and local militias have used the money they earned from the sale&lt;br/&gt;of coltan and other minerals, such as gold, to finance and extend their military&lt;br/&gt;operations throughout the region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mantz and Smith will conduct both extensive survey and intensive ethnographic&lt;br/&gt;research on coltan. They will survey a sample of mining towns and cities where coltan is&lt;br/&gt;traded to elucidate how coltan mining and exchange operate in the Congo, and the&lt;br/&gt;effects that the mining of this commodity have had on local communities and their&lt;br/&gt;surrounding environs. Using both extensive survey and intensive ethnographic&lt;br/&gt;interviewing, the researchers will investigate the relationship between coltan, conflict,&lt;br/&gt;and nation building; how coltan mining has affected the transformation and&lt;br/&gt;decentralization of political authority; and, more generally, the effects of coltan on local&lt;br/&gt;culture and social organization. In addition, they will map the structure of the process&lt;br/&gt;through which coltan is moved from rural mining enclaves, through urban Congolese&lt;br/&gt;sites of processing, and out into the world system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is important because coltan is an example of a growing phenomenon:&lt;br/&gt;locally grounded commodity chains that are central to the global digital age. The&lt;br/&gt;production and sale of these commodities have transformative effects upon not only&lt;br/&gt;local economies but also local politics and social organization. The research will&lt;br/&gt;contribute to social science theory of the intricate relations between local and global, as&lt;br/&gt;well as to better policies for economic development and conflict prevention and&lt;br/&gt;resolution.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0752262</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mantz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmantz@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/04/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Trencher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>strenche@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>George Mason University</Name>
      <CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
      <ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
