<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>New Numerical Methods for Hamilton-Jacobi and Liouville Equations; Their Applications to Geometrical Optics, Wave Propagation and Travel-time Tomography</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36563</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leland M. Jameson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigator develops novel and efficient numerical&lt;br/&gt;methods for Hamilton-Jacobi and Liouville equations. These equations arise&lt;br/&gt;from seismic wave propagation, geometrical optics, optimal control,&lt;br/&gt;travel-time tomography, medical imaging, computer vision, and material&lt;br/&gt;sciences. His previous works on computing viscosity solutions and&lt;br/&gt;multivalued solutions of Hamilton-Jacobi equations lead him to develop&lt;br/&gt;more powerful and efficient numerical methods&lt;br/&gt;for solving these equations and incorporate these new methods&lt;br/&gt;into seismic modeling and inversion, as well as other possible&lt;br/&gt;applications. Problems under consideration include continued development&lt;br/&gt;of adaptive eikonal solvers for three-dimensional isotropic and&lt;br/&gt;anisotropic media; fast sweeping methods for stationary Hamilton-Jacobi&lt;br/&gt;equations on unstructured meshes; extending slowness matching methods to&lt;br/&gt;general Hamilton-Jacobi equations for computing multivalued solutions; and&lt;br/&gt;applications of paraxial Liouville equations for geometrical optics, wave&lt;br/&gt;propagation and transmission tomography.&lt;br/&gt;This investigation advances the state-of-the-art in geometrical optics,&lt;br/&gt;wave propagation and seismic travel-time tomography.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These fields and applications are of great strategic value in the US oil&lt;br/&gt;and gas industry, in environmental sciences, and in medical imaging.&lt;br/&gt;Recently, for example, the price of gasoline soared dramatically in the&lt;br/&gt;United States. One way to reduce the cost of production of oil involves&lt;br/&gt;lowering drilling costs by advancing the seismic data processing&lt;br/&gt;techniques that oil companies use to find good drilling sites. The&lt;br/&gt;investigator's new methods expedite routine data processing, provide new&lt;br/&gt;tools for exploration geophysicists to use for ground-breaking&lt;br/&gt;applications, and enable substantial cost savings in seismic explorations,&lt;br/&gt;as the speed and reliability of the underlying computational engine allows&lt;br/&gt;``rig-site'' adjustments to both seismic survey and drilling decisions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/15/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0753797</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jianliang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Qian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qian@math.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/15/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
