<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A New Method for Understanding Mechanisms of Ice Sheet Demise Using Married General Circulation and Energy-Moisture Balance Model Simulations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>195452</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020108</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David J. Verardo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funding is provided to employ a new technique to address ice sheet disintegration through the use of paired simulations of a fully coupled atmosphere-ocean general circulation model (GCM) containing water isotopes and an energy mass balance model (EMBM) of ice sheet mass balance. The researchers will apply their new technique at discrete millennial time slices to the last deglaciation (21,000 to 10,000 years ago), when large Northern Hemisphere ice sheets disappeared. To test the skill of GCM results, the researchers will use tracers built into the model (i.e., water isotopes, cosmogenic isotopes, dust, sea salt, and wetland methane emissions) for which there are proxies in the paleoclimate record. GCM results will force the EMBM to simulate ice sheet mass balance at each time slice and will test the skill of the EMBM by comparing its predictions of ice sheet mass loss to that inferred from the geologic record of ice margin change during deglaciation. The overall research goal is to determine the minimum amount of melt water available to contribute to the small-scale processes involved in ice sheet decay. The broader impacts include the promise of providing greater insight into the mechanisms of ice sheet decay and the support of graduate and undergraduate students involved in the research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0753868</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allegra</FirstName>
      <LastName>LeGrande</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>al2035@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
