<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: REU Site in Computer Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>406501</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Todd Leen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU site seeks to increase the number of students choosing to pursue graduate studies, and ultimately careers, in computer science. The participants experience the most compelling aspects of &lt;br/&gt;graduate school in a ten week summer program. The program nurtures &lt;br/&gt;student interest in research by engaging students in the entire research process, beginning with a search of the literature, reading prior research, selecting the specific problems to be studied, working on those problems, and preparing the results for publication. The program develops research skills and improves written and oral communication skills in order to prepare students for success in graduate school.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research topics fall under the broadly scoped area of computer systems. Topics include computer networking, robot vision, computer music systems, and memory management, among others. Each project involves two or three students under the close direction of a faculty adviser whose expertise is in that area. In addition, students participate in a number of whole-group curricular and co-curricular activities. Among these activities are workshops on research methods, ethics, applying to graduate schools, careers in computer science, and technical topics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program seeks to involve students from a variety of backgrounds and particularly those from schools with limited access to research opportunities. The project includes a comprehensive local and national recruiting-outreach program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0753306</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ran</FirstName>
      <LastName>Libeskind-Hadas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hadas@cs.hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Neill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>melissa_oneill@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/05/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Harvey Mudd College</Name>
      <CityName>CLAREMONT</CityName>
      <ZipCode>917115901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9096218121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>301 Platt Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
