<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Urban Bird Gardens: Assessing the Interest of Latino Communities in Citizen Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>74613</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leslie K. Goodyear</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Cornell University will utilize planning grant funds to conduct front-end research to inform a major citizen science effort targeting Latino families in six major US cities. Partnering organizations include the New York Restoration Project (New York), Aspira of Illinois, Inc. (Chicago), Youth Policy Institute (Los Angeles), Chicanos Por la Causa, Inc. (Phoenix), the Children's Museum of Houston (Houston), and Aspira of Florida, Inc. (Miami) Project deliverables for the planning effort include culturally responsive research and subsequent dissemination of findings. The Garibay Group will create profiles of partner communities and conduct focus groups with potential project participants to examine attitudes towards science, interest in participatory science activities, tools (online bird identification, data entry, and data visualization tools), and technologies. The research will also include an analysis of existing data from interviews previously conducted by project partners. The research results will provide insights into effective strategies for engaging Latino audiences in citizen science efforts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0755280</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dickinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jld84@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bonney</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reb5@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell Univ - State: AWDS MADE PRIOR MAY 2010</Name>
      <CityName>Ithica</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502488</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
