<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Computational Materials Science: Designing Materials in a Virtual Laboratory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>312591</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070002</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carmina Londono</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site focuses on training undergraduate students in research in the field of Computational Materials science, particularly Designing Materials in a Virtual laboratory. Four of the leading public universities in Florida (University of Florida, University of South Florida, University of Central Florida, and Florida State University) will participate in this distributed REU Site. Each year twelve undergraduate students will be recruited nationwide for a ten-week summer research experience. Each of the four campuses will host three undergraduates and engage them in research projects in the general areas of biology, nanoscience, and surface science, applying a range of computational simulation methods. Since the research projects involve collaborations between research groups at the participating universities, participating REU students will perform research in a cyberspace environment and become adept with cyber-enabled research tools. All twelve students will meet in University of Florida for two days for short courses at the beginning and in another campus for the presentation of research results at the end of the program. In addition to research, students will participate in professional development and career guidance activities and attend social events to network with students in other REU programs on campus. &lt;br/&gt;This REU Site is funded jointly by NSF Divisions of Materials Research, Chemistry and Physics in the Directorate of Mathematical and Physical Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0755256</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dmitry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kopelevich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dkopelevich@che.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Aravind</FirstName>
      <LastName>Asthagiri</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>asthagiri.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/03/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate>04/08/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7222</Code>
      <Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7752</Code>
      <Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
