<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Nanoscale Science and Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>243706</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Esther Bolding</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This REU Site in Nanoscale Science and Engineering will involve ten undergraduates in hands-on nanoscale science and engineering focused research for a 9-week summer period. The program will provide undergraduates with opportunities to develop the fundamental skills necessary to succeed in careers in science and engineering including pragmatic training in public speaking, technical writing, the peer-review process, and research and laboratory skills. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The students' research experience will be enhanced by their participation in social and educational activities including technical writing and professional speaking workshops, weekly meetings/seminars, a field trip to Argonne National Laboratory, and a summer picnic. During the final week of the program, participants will work closely with their advisors to prepare both oral and written reports. Students will present their project results at a formal Closing Symposium. Also a final project report in the format of a scientific paper will be required at the end of the program. It is anticipated that some of the papers and presentations prepared by participants will be suitable for academic journals and conferences. Additional opportunities for technological transfer are possible through Nanoscape: the Journal of Undergraduate Research in Nanotechnology published by the Northwestern University Nanoscale Science and Engineering Center (NSEC).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recruitment efforts will be targeted to undergraduate students majoring in engineering or the physical sciences. Attention will be given to attracting a diverse group of students including racial and ethnic minorities, women, persons with disabilities, as well as students from smaller schools were research opportunities are limited or nonexistent.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0755375</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hersam</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>m-hersam@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/21/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
