<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site at CENS: Sensing Applications in Earthquake</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>248378</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Reppy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>REU Site at CENS:&lt;br/&gt;Sensing Applications in Earthquake and Environmental Engineering&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center for Embedded Networked Sensing (CENS), headquartered at UCLA, is a multidisciplinary research center focused on developing embedded networked sensing (ENS) technology and applying this revolutionary technology to crucial scientific and social applications. CENS infrastructure provides an ideal environment for undergraduate researchers to gain research experience and become part of a productive and collaborative research community. This REU project represents an effective approach to supporting undergraduate research experience, particularly focused on promoting long-term interest in science and engineering for women and underrepresented minorities. The Center?s approach to undergraduate education is based on our expertise in working with undergraduates, a comprehensive and longitudinal evaluation of our programs, the evolution of research, collaboration and mentoring within the Center, and a body of literature that examines undergraduates? experiences in science and engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CENS REU site experience takes a systems approach to undergraduate training, emphasizing Environment, Experience, and Engagement. This approach facilitates development of a tight-knit cohort of undergraduate researchers engaging in forefront research. Our mentoring community is vital to increasing student competence, developing collegial relationships, and improving collaborative interactions. A ten-week comprehensive program, housed at UCLA, intellectually focuses on civil and environmental engineering applications of earthquake and environmental monitoring research. Research projects engage participating undergraduates in ongoing research within this application area, while contextualizing this research within the scope of the Center. The program includes mechanisms for students to understand the commonalities and connections between their application area and the development of broader ENS technologies. Additionally, the program introduces students to data and data visualization tools that are common across the Center?s applications areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0755533</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jjay@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wallace</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wallacej@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>2860</Code>
      <Text>THEORY OF COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
