<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Environmental Sustainability Systems Analysis Including Multiple Objective and Fixed Cost Optimization of Management Decisions with Watershed and Groundwater Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>301914</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Debra Reinhart</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CBET- 0756575&lt;br/&gt;Shoemaker, Christine&lt;br/&gt;Cornell University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Environmental Sustainability Systems Analysis Including Multiple&lt;br/&gt;Objective and Fixed Cost Optimization of Management Decisions with&lt;br/&gt;Watershed and Groundwater Applications&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal study is to develop improved and computationally more efficient analysis methods that can be used to help identify the best combinations of best management practices (BMPs). The methods and analysis will focus on the control of non-point source pollution of Cannonsville watershed which provides freshwater supply to New York City. The intellectual merit of this proposal is derived from a very well characterized watershed. The PI and her group are well-qualified to carry out this ambitious project. The optimization routines are extensions of their previous work and may provide tools that speed up and reduce the cost of management procedures one of the major strengths of this excellent proposal is that the time frame extends significantly in the future (2078) so that long term trends are taken into account. The efforts to develop and extend their modeling approach are easily justified considering the need to apply such models nationwide (and likely a major effort in the Water Network). The dynamic modeling of Cannonsville watershed as proposal will also provide a test bed for future efforts as climate change affects the region. It is possible that with time the water input functions (rain) will change as may the vegetative cover. Therefore, I could envision that this modeling effort will evolve with time, as it should. In particular, the Cannonsville watershed area might provide the 'model' watershed to study so that when the model is exported to other area, the water quality monitoring can be optimized (that is the minimum number of monitoring sites employed) to maximize the data necessary for watershed modeling. If this proposal is only successful for this on watershed then it will be a success. The section of broader impacts of the proposal is also excellent and could serve a model for others.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0756575</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shoemaker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cas12@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/14/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0313010</Code>
      <Name>Air Pollution</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0313040</Code>
      <Name>Water Pollution</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0316000</Code>
      <Name>Trace Contaminants</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
