<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Interstitial dynamics of the poroelastic brain and cerebral vasculature in humans</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249987</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Athanassios Sambanis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CBET-0756154&lt;br/&gt;Linninger&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Diseases like stroke, tumors and hydrocephalus affect brain dynamics in millions of people worldwide. This project aims at advancing mathematical methods for studying soft tissue fluid interaction in the brain. The mathematical models will address large brain deformations in dynamic interaction with blood and cerebrospinal fluid motion with three salient features:an Euler-Lagrangian moving grid formulation for soft porous brain tissues; integration of cerebral vasculature into a porous deformable cell matrix.; and advancement of direct numerical solution algorithms based on inexact Newton-type methods with Krylov subspace iterations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For addressing the interdisciplinary nature of this project, the PI assembled a research team composed of biochemical engineers, two mathematicians, a neurosurgeon and an MRI physicist and biomedical engineer. Two major goals of the project are:&lt;br/&gt;Aim #1. Creation of a multi-scale fluid-structure interaction framework accounting for brain deformation mechanics with cerebrospinal fluid dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;Aim #2. We will incorporate realistic models of the cerebral vasculature.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Existing models for computing large brain deformation dynamics are still unsatisfactory. The proposed holistic model of intracranial dynamics addresses key deficiencies. Specific aims (i) bridge the gap between recent advancements in medical imaging and rigorous mathematical analysis, (ii) create novel mathematical formulations for fluid-solid interaction for deforming soft porous media, and (iii) account for dilations of the cerebral vasculature. Comprehensive multi-phase models of brain, blood and cerebrospinal fluid interaction derived from patient-specific images have never been attempted before to the best of our knowledge. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently quantitative analysis of medical images is slow, because there exists few mathematical methods for evaluating the interactions of blood, brain tissue and cerebrospinal fluid flow, distributed in the three-dimensional space and in time. Magnetic resonance imaging, angiography or computer tomography, will move forward biological and medical knowledge, when rigorous mathematical models to accurately predict transport phenomena become available. The proposed research will integrate existing medical imaging technology with mathematical modeling and scientific computing. The PI will share computational grids of human brains and symbolic codes for cerebral transport phenomena via the world-wide web. By this open internet approach, they will attract the interest of a growing scientific community. It is expected that this project will lay the mathematical foundations for a quantitative understanding of flow physics associated with the onset and progression of certain types of brain disorders. Thus, the project is prerequisite for generating better diagnostic and new treatment options in the future. The education plan provides specific steps for the dissemination of proposal outcomes and includes high school math and science education via the research experiences for teachers (RET), as well as outreach to minorities and underrepresented groups through undergraduate research (REU) mentorship.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0756154</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Linninger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Linninge@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>004E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
