<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Experimental Particle Physics at Hadron Colliders</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>959000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Randal Ruchti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests continuing support for a program of research for the Wood group at Northeastern University (NEU) in experimental elementary particle physics based primarily on the D0 experiment at the Fermilab Tevatron collider and the CMS experiment at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For the past few decades, physicists have been able to describe with increasing detail the fundamental particles that make up the Universe and the interactions between them. Much of this success has been due to the Tevatron program at Fermilab with D0 and CDF making major contributions. This NEU group has made major contributions to the D0 experiment in its construction and in the physics questions proposed as well as in many leadership roles. Wood is presently co-spokesman of D0. The group is pursuing physics topics which are important for understanding the electroweak sector of the Standard Model and physics beyond the Standard Model. These include W/Z + jets production, ZZ production, Higgs searches, and top quark properties. At the same time the LHC and ATLAS will start operation in new regimes of energy and luminosity holding even greater promise for discoveries and measurements leading to revisions of our views on how the world is constructed and the nature of the laws that govern its operation. This group is now transitioning into the CMS program where it will parlay its wealth of experience in muon detection and identification into a leadership role in muon + jets studies - a signature that is sensitive to a variety of new physics processes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On Broader Impacts, the group will continue its work within the QuarkNet program. With the strong cooperative education program at Northeastern University, the group will continue to routinely involve undergraduates in research with substantial and meaningful six-month projects at CERN. In his role and co-spokesperson of D0, Wood will work actively with the press to share with the public the excitement of the Higgs search and other potential discoveries at the Tevatron. The group plans to host and organize important conferences, and Barberis will continue to communicate the value of high energy research to the US Congress through her work with the Fermilab Users Executive Committee.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0757561</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alverson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alverson@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Emanuela</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barberis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>e.barberis@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Darien</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>darien@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1221</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1221</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
