<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel Support, First International Conference on Quantum Error Correction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Earle L. Lomon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Student Support for First International Conference&lt;br/&gt; on Quantum Error Correction&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;Quantum computation and quantum information provides a new paradigm for information processing, by exploiting the intrinsic properties of quantum systems. In the last ten years this field has exploded with a huge amount of work in quantum algorithms,communication protocols, and other&lt;br/&gt;information processing ideas. While the theory has&lt;br/&gt;progressed rapidly, experiment has advanced at a more modest pace, largely due to the great difficulty in dealing with decoherence and other sources of noise in quantum systems. Controlling this noise is the single largest obstacle to the construction of quantum computers and other information processing devices. Quantum error correction of decoherence and faulty control operations forms the&lt;br/&gt;backbone of all of quantum information processing. In spite of remarkable progress on this front ever since the discovery of quantum error correcting codes by Shor and Steane a decade ago, there remain important open problems in both theory and applications to real physical systems. The subject remains a very active area of research with a&lt;br/&gt;continuing stream of progress and breakthroughs from a wide variety of different approaches, including quantum error-correcting codes, decoherence-free subspaces and subsystems, dynamical decoupling, and noise isolation.&lt;br/&gt;This conference will bring together leading researchers in this field from all over the world to discuss the current state of quantum error correction and error suppression, both in theory and experiment. All major approaches to this problem will be represented. This is the first large-scale meeting of its kind specifically on quantum error correction. This conference will take place December 17-21, 2007 at the University of Southern California in Los Angeles. Travel support is requestedto ensure a large student participation in this meeting.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;Given the rapid growth of the field, it is no longer easy for researchers in different areas to keep abreast of each other?s work. This conference will stimulate cross-fertilization between different approaches to the problem of correcting or preventing quantum errors. It will also enable exchanges between experimenters and theorists in this area. By supporting students, this conference will foster the development of the upcoming generation of new workers in quantum information processing. Progress in quantum information processing depends crucially on the advancement of quantum error correction.&lt;br/&gt;Cambridge University Press will publish a book on quantum error correction as an outcome of this meeting. Chapter contributions have been solicited from a select group of&lt;br/&gt;speakers, and the organizers will edit a book that will form a comprehensive introduction to, and survey of, the field of quantum error correction.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0758667</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tbrun@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/11/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
