<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Highest Energy Astroparticle Physics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>990000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James J. Whitmore</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL NUMBER: 0758017&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION: University of Chicago&lt;br/&gt;NSF PROGRAM: PHY - PARTICLE ASTROPHYSICS&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR: Olinto, Angela V.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TITLE: The Highest Energy Astroparticle Physics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a proposal to continue the participation of the University of Chicago (UC) in the Pierre Auger Observatory (PAO). The observatory is designed to study the origin and nature of the highest energy particles ever observed, namely cosmic rays with energies greater than 10^19 eV, by measuring their energy, their composition, and the distribution of arrival directions with large statistics and careful control of systematic effects. The Southern PAO, nearing completion in Malargue, Argentina, is the first hybrid detector to combine the two best-developed techniques of measuring showers caused by ultra-high energy cosmic rays (UHECRs). The observatory detects shower particles that reach the surface with a surface array and the longitudinal development of the shower through the fluorescence produced in the atmosphere. This combination is essential for accurate energy measurements and reliable composition studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The integration of theory, observations, and experiments at UC into a single effort has greatly benefited both the research goals and the training of students by involving them in all aspects of science: from the construction and operation of the PAO to the analysis of its data. This project will solidify the international leadership in the analysis and interpretation of the PAO data at UC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The discovery of the origin of the highest energy particles will impact both astrophysics and particle physics. The Southern PAO has had a major impact on public education and outreach throughout the participating countries across the globe: from Argentina to Vietnam. In collaboration with the Auger Visitors Center, the Malargue Planetarium, and the Adler Planetarium, the UC effort strengthens the depth of physics and astrophysics content of the education and public outreach efforts by promoting the 3D and 2D visualizations developed at UC of the highest energy showers, their detection methods, and possible cosmic origins. In collaboration with the American Natural History Museum, the group will develop a Science Bulletin that will further provide the public access to this fascinating mystery.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0758017</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
      <LastName>Olinto</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>olinto@kicp.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cronin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwc@hep.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paolo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Privitera</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>priviter@kicp.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
