<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>P2C2: A Network of Paleo-Monsoon Rainfall Stations in Southeast Asia to Investigate Atmospheric Circulation Changes over the Past Four Centuries</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>404575</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020108</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David J. Verardo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Funding is provided to support the development and calibration of a method for reconstructing rainwater delta Oxygen-18 from cellulose extracted from the annual rings of trees that grow throughout Thailand. The researchers will measure delta Oxygen-18 tree cellulose from Khasi pine and Merkus pine trees as a means to reconstruct annual to subannual records of atmospheric precipitation at sites across Southeast (SE) Asia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers hypothesize that the increased moisture from the Indian Ocean is a response to the expansion of the continental monsoon trough eastward over SE Asia. To test this hypothesis, the researchers will extend the data base of Pine delta Oxygen-18 to sites across SE Asia in order to map the spatial pattern of precipitation delta Oxygen-18 variability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project offers the promise of helping opening tropical tree-rings to climate analysis. This is important because, at present, tropical tree cannot be used as a reliable paleoclimate archive because they do not lay down visible seasonal tree rings as do higher latitude specimens. Developing an isotopic technique for tropical trees would be a transformative breakthrough in climate analysis.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0902507</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lowell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stott@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
