<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2009 Gordon Research Conference on Liquid Crystals; Colby Sawyer College; New London, New Hampshire on Summer 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda S. Sapochak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2009 Gordon Research Conference on Liquid Crystals (June 14-19, 2009) addresses current issues in liquid crystal science, applications of liquid crystals, and areas of biology and medicine in which liquid crystal concepts are important. The coverage of the Conference is extremely broad, ranging from the latest fundamental theories and experiments into the nature of liquid crystals to the cutting-edge work on the role liquid crystals play in biological systems. Discussion topics include the synthesis and characterization of new liquid crystals, liquid crystal systems containing nanoparticles of various kinds, self-assembly and molecular aggregation in liquid crystals, state-of-the-art simulation and modeling, biaxial nematics, elastomers, liquid crystal ordering and biological function, bio-inspired materials, and modern uses of liquid crystals in biomedical imaging, photonics, lasing, electro-optics, and sensors. Invited speakers representing both academia and industry come from a wide range of disciplines, including biology, chemistry, engineering, medicine, and physics. This collection of leading investigators discusses the latest (often unpublished) results within this broad array of disciplines and explores the most pressing questions still to be answered.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2009 Gordon Research Conference on Liquid Crystals (June 14-19, 2009) addresses current issues in liquid crystal science, applications of liquid crystals, and areas of biology and medicine in which liquid crystal concepts are important. The coverage of the Conference is extremely broad, ranging from the latest fundamental theories and experiments into the nature of liquid crystals to the cutting-edge work on the role liquid crystals play in biological systems. Although there have always been a good number of participants from outside of the U.S., this biennial conference serves as the only dedicated gathering within the United States of top scientists and engineers in the field of soft matter investigating liquid crystals or related systems. Among these participants are members of the biomedical, nanoscience, and sensor communities, who are applying liquid crystal concepts and techniques in new ways. Also, significant funds are earmarked to support the participation of researchers early in their careers and researchers from traditionally underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0903155</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Collings</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pcollin1@swarthmore.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/10/2008</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
