<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Beyond the 2010 Initiative: Partnerships for Competitiveness</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01120000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>EPSCoR</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>audrey levine</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Title: Beyond the 2010 Initiative: Partnerships for Competitiveness&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: South Dakota State University &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Energy generation and conversion are critical issues at the core of this major project involving nine institutions in South Dakota: South Dakota State (lead), Augustana, Black Hills, Dakota State, Oglala Lakota, Sinte Gleska, Sisseton Wahpeton, South Dakota School of Mines and Technology, and the University of South Dakota (USD) Main Campus. The researchers will create new devices called Photo-Active Nanoscale Systems (PANS). PANS research focuses on photovoltaic and solar energy, directwrite electronics, and the use of nanostructured materials for converting solar energy into chemical fuels. The project involves a series of Grand Opportunities, each addressing research questions through a multidisciplinary approach. These include: Cost Effective Solar Cells; New Generation Luminescent Solar Concentrators (LSC) based on Metal-Surface Enhancement; Reconfigurable Antennas on Flexible Substrates-Broadband Multilayer Filters; Upconverter Based Cost-effective High Efficiency Solar Cells; Novel Tandem Polymer Photovoltaics using Printing or Roll-to-Roll Processing; Fabrications of Electrodes for Next Generation Solar Cells; and Conversion of Solar Energy into Chemical Fuels using Nanostructured Materials&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The project addresses the development of novel photoactive materials, including investigations at the atomic level as well as applications of these materials. Modeling, synthesis and fabrication of novel composites will result in solar cell materials designed for performance, with a view to economics as well. Shape and size of the composites will be optimized along with tailored chemical composition by working at the nanoscale. Biomedical applications such as photoactive therapies will be addressed as well. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Workforce development is a primary objective of South Dakota and this project. An innovative partnership will facilitate the faculty at Tribal Colleges and Universities (TCUs) in pursuing terminal degrees. The RII project will support the planning for a state-wide initiative for middle school, Science in the Middle. This initiative will provide teacher professional development to establish a cohort of qualified master science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) teachers. Connections will be established with the Deep Underground Science and Engineering Laboratory (DUSEL), including a virtual DUSEL (vDUSEL), which will provide outreach and education accessible to K-12 students and the community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0903804</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rice</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jim.rice@sdstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kellar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jon.kellar@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mberry@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>G. Melvin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ustad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mel.ustad@state.sd.us</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bentley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sayler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Ben.Sayler@bhsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>South Dakota State University</Name>
      <CityName>Brookings</CityName>
      <ZipCode>570070001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6056886696</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1015 Campanile Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7217</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7217</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
