<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference Grant: 35th Northeast Bioengineering Conference in Boston, MA from April 3-5, 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Semahat S. Demir</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0903694&lt;br/&gt;Karp&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support the 35th Annual Northeast Bioengineering Conference (Harvard University, April 3-5, 2009). The 35th NEBEC will disseminate the state of the art in Bioengineering research at all levels, discuss potential career choices that effectively prepare students for the workforce, and share information across interdisciplinary barriers. The broad tracks of the conference are biomaterials, biomechanics, tissue engineering, nanotechnology and diagnostics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader goals of the conference are: (1) to expose students to exciting, cutting edge research in biomedical engineering, (2) to encourage students to pursue careers in biomedical sciences, (3) to introduce students to research leaders and encourage interactions, and (4) to stimulate new interactions between research groups in the Northeast. The 35th Annual Northeast Bioengineering Conference will educate the next generation of undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral students in bioengineering by bringing together a number of respected researchers to inform and inspire students about progress and research opportunities in the biomedical sciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 35th NEBEC will have broad impact for the northeast bioengineering community and for engineering education. Usually 55% of attendees are students at the Northeast Biomedical Engineering conferences. Typically this conference brings together researchers from over 40 institutions in the Northeast. The knowledge gained and experiences shared from the conference will be captured electronically and broadly disseminated via abstract books, CD ROMS, and via the IEEE website.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0903694</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Karp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jeffkarp@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brigham &amp; Women's Hospital Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Boston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021156110</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8572821670</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 Francis Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>004E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
