<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Illinois Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2809750</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Martha L. James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Illinois Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (ILSAMP) focuses on broadening&lt;br/&gt;Participation by increasing the number of underrepresented students who: choose and persist in STEM academic disciplines; attend graduate school in STEM; and are prepared to obtain a professional career in STEM disciplines. ILSAMP activities enhance the growth of the STEM community and promote linkages and partnerships in undergraduate STEM education throughout Illinois to cultivate an excellent, broadly inclusive science and engineering workforce, and expand general scientific literacy. In order to accomplish these objectives, the Alliance utilize sustained and comprehensive strategies that include: 1) pre-college and community college bridge programs to ease the transition and better prepare freshman and transfer students; 2) faculty and peer mentoring to help retain students in STEM disciplines; 3) supplemental instruction to strengthen students ability to succeed in STEM courses; 4) academic year and summer undergraduate research to prepare, motivate and develop students for graduate school; 5) curriculum revision; and 6) internships. As a senior?level Alliance, particular attention is given to student persistence toward the B.S. degree and transition to graduate study; institutionalizing successful policies and procedures for attainment of the B.S. degree; reaffirming community college associations; and developing relevant international activities. ILSAMP is comprised of universities and community colleges throughout the state of Illinois and one federal laboratory, Argonne National Laboratory. The strategic location of the partner institutions throughout the state of Illinois enables the Alliance to reach a large and diverse student population and provides access to graduate and research opportunities for undergraduate students. The ILSAMP has a strong assessment component, with external evaluation and internal feedback. External suggestions and assistance will be furnished by a Technical Advisory Committee, the composition of which provides a connection with the Illinois business community, the public high schools, graduate schools, state and national policy makers, and national research institutions.&lt;br/&gt;]&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merits of the program: The ILSAMP program is well-conceived and organized to advance students? intellectual pursuits. The activities proposed are designed to accomplish the central goal of increasing the number of historically underrepresented students who select STEM disciplines, and persist and graduate from baccalaureate producing institutions; prepared to successfully matriculate in graduate schools or obtain professional positions in STEM. This alliance provides students with the academic and professional skills to function at the highest levels of competency. Staff and faculty monitoring, research lab experiences, research projects and professional interactions along with intensive evaluation protocols help to ensure that participating students will complete their degree. The addition of international activities increases students? knowledge, educational richness, and awareness of cultural diversity while increasing their scientific education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of the proposed activity: ILSAMP activities broaden the participation of historically underrepresented groups including women, ethnic and racial minorities in the STEM enterprise by providing access to research and science programs and by working diligently with the public schools, community colleges, and public institutions. We advance discovery and understanding while promoting teaching and learning by integrating research activities into training K-12 teachers, participating in assisting high school students with science fair projects and providing special mentoring for undergraduates. The ILSAMP program not only helps to close the gap created by the paucity of underserved individuals who are STEM professionals functioning creatively; it encourages others who have been reticent to attempt science B.S. level work. The advisory board will also help to broaden the impact of the program. The inclusion of an international emphasis broadens the outlook and increases the range of experiences for our both students and international populations they encounter. The program will be widely disseminated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0904024</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Westbrooks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swestb31@csu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>LeRoy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones II</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ljones27@csu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Chicago State University</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606281598</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7739952000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9501 South King Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9133</Code>
      <Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7204</Code>
      <Text>DoE-NSF LABORATORY FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
