<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI: Medium: Collaborative Research: Real-Time Continuum Manipulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>437587</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to investigate the potential of fundamentally new modes of robotic manipulation using novel continuum robots in less-structured environments with large uncertainties and even unknowns. A continuum robot, such as a trunk/tentacle robot arm, is in many senses ?dual? to a traditional robot manipulator (consisting of an articulated arm and a gripper or hand), featuring relatively low precision but high compliance: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;* Its inherent flexibility and compliance offer greater promise to enable deft manipulation under imprecise and uncertain conditions of objects over a wider range (orders of magnitude) of size and weight, of many different shapes, and with widely different physical characteristics (rigid, soft, flexible, etc.).. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;* On the other hand, its inherent lack of precision renders the traditional approaches to planning and control of robot manipulators unsuitable for manipulation with continuum robots. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project pioneers the study of the basic problem of autonomous manipulation of an object with much uncertainty by a single continuum robot. It introduces a novel and holistic approach that integrates real-time adaptive planning and robust control schemes under real-time sensing and large environmental uncertainty. It next extends the basic approach to address multiple continuum robots working in a common environment, where each robot needs not know the motion of another robot. The research combines theoretical/algorithmic development with real-world validation on an experimental test bed with real trunk/tentacle robots equipped with sensors. The results will be actively disseminated through publications, free software, and real-world demos to impact research, education, and applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0904093</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xiao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xiao@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1504</Code>
      <Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
