<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Undergraduate Research in Glass Science at Coe College; A National Model of Excellence</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>451953</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070009</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION:&lt;br/&gt;This project represents a vigorous and innovative undergraduate research program that serves as a national model of excellence. This project involves 40 students studying a mix of applied and basic science projects in glass science over the next five years. Students will undertake research focused on discovering new glass forming systems and ranges of compositions; characterizing physical properties; building patented rapid cooling devices; learning to make micron-scale gratings and optical devices; forming microspheres; working on nuclear waste incorporation into glasses; and doing atomic structure studies of these new materials. The broader impacts of this proposed work are manifold. They include: &lt;br/&gt;1) teaching large numbers of undergraduates how to do sustained research. Seventy percent of their students continue onwards to graduate school in science or engineering. The group is fully inclusive and participation is welcomed by all. &lt;br/&gt;2) serving the glass science and physics community. In this area the faculty have assumed leadership roles (examples: Prof. Affatigato is the immediate past chair of the Glass and Optical Materials Division of the American Ceramic Society, and Prof. Feller was co- president of American Institute of Physics?s Society of Physics Students) and numerous conferences in glass science and physics were organized. Also, two segments of on-line courses (co-organized by Clemson University and the NSF-International Materials Institute at Lehigh University and Penn State University) were taught in glass science (spectroscopy and properties). &lt;br/&gt;3) bringing science to the public by visiting schools; hosting student groups at Coe College; giving public lectures and demonstrations on topics such as glass-making. The signature outreach program is the Coe Playground of Science that brings 1500-2000 community members, mainly young students, for an evening of science demonstrations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS:&lt;br/&gt;This project involves a vigorous undergraduate research program that will educate 40 undergraduate students over the next five years. Much of the work will be done in-house at Coe College using very well equipped laboratories. The equipment base includes: scanning electron microscopy, atomic force microscopy, Raman and Fourier Transform infrared spectroscopies, laser-desorption time-of-flight mass spectroscopy, x-ray diffraction, much thermal equipment, chemical determination by x-ray analysis (EDXRF), and an excellent glass-making facility. The research conducted has both both basic and applied aspects, and it seeks to make substantial contributions to the field of glass science. The basic science work is focused on discovering new glass forming systems; extending glass-forming ranges; conducting atomic structure studies of these new glasses using a wealth of spectroscopic techniques available both at Coe College and around the world; and characterizing physical properties. The more applied work includes designing and building patentable state-of-the art rapid cooling devices; learning to make micron-scale gratings and microspheres using laser crystallization and flame spheroidization; and working on nuclear waste incorporation into borosilicate host glasses. A significant amount of this research is done with collaborators around the world, in particular, in North and South America, and in Europe. This expands the repertoire of techniques available to these students and facilitates the discovery of new information. These collaborations also bring new ideas and students to Coe College, enriching the educational experience for all. The impacts of the work are considerable. The science and technology created at Coe College is used by groups throughout the world and the methods of instruction serve as a model for the nation. The educational approach is innovative and undergraduate students learn to do research over extended periods (multiple years) and they participate fully in all aspects of the work. To date they have co-authored over 100 papers and have given hundreds of presentations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0904615</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sfeller@coe.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mario</FirstName>
      <LastName>Affatigato</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maffatig@coe.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Coe College</Name>
      <CityName>Cedar Rapids</CityName>
      <ZipCode>524025008</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3193998000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1220 First Avenue NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
