<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Separability and logic in geometric group theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>96339</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-0906276&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Henry Wilton&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment&lt;br/&gt;Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal investigator will pursue several lines of research&lt;br/&gt;motivated by three deep open questions in the theory of&lt;br/&gt;word-hyperbolic groups. (1) Is every hyperbolic group residually&lt;br/&gt;finite? If so, then in fact word-hyperbolic groups satisfy much&lt;br/&gt;stronger separability properties. The PI intends to investigate&lt;br/&gt;these separability properties for known examples of&lt;br/&gt;word-hyperbolic groups and related groups, including 3-manifold&lt;br/&gt;groups and relatively hyperbolic groups. (2) Is the elementary&lt;br/&gt;theory of a torsion-free hyperbolic group decidable? Together&lt;br/&gt;with Daniel Groves, the PI intends to give an affirmative answer&lt;br/&gt;by proving algorithmic versions of the results of Sela. (3) Does&lt;br/&gt;every word-hyperbolic group contain a surface subgroup? Little is&lt;br/&gt;known about this famous question of Gromov, even for some very&lt;br/&gt;basic examples of word-hyperbolic groups. The PI proposes to use&lt;br/&gt;various new techniques to find surface subgroups in examples of&lt;br/&gt;word-hyperbolic groups, including doubles of free groups along&lt;br/&gt;maximal cyclic subgroups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A group is a collection of symmetries, for example the collection&lt;br/&gt;of all translations of the Euclidean plane that preserve the&lt;br/&gt;integer lattice. This group is generated by the translations of&lt;br/&gt;one unit of length in the north, south, east, or west directions,&lt;br/&gt;in the sense that any element of the group can be obtained by&lt;br/&gt;composing copies of those four basic translations. Every&lt;br/&gt;finitely generated group carries a notion of distance between&lt;br/&gt;pairs of its elements, defined by counting the number of&lt;br/&gt;generators that must be applied to carry one element of the group&lt;br/&gt;to another. These projects concentrate on word-hyperbolic&lt;br/&gt;groups, which have many of the properties of the hyperbolic plane&lt;br/&gt;from non-Euclidean geometry and are known to be so common that a&lt;br/&gt;randomly selected finitely generated group is almost surely&lt;br/&gt;word-hyperbolic. This award is jointly funded by the programs in&lt;br/&gt;Topology and Foundations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>96339</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0906276</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cameron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gordon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gordon@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>henry.wilton@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/17/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>01/20/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
