<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Magnetic-Fluorescent Bifunctional Nanoparticles for Biomedical Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>226516</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;The novelty of this proposal lies in: (1) Fluorescent Ag nanoclusters (a few Ag atoms) are used as the fluorescent component, which can overcome the size increase issue of the current practice. (2) The capping agents of iron oxide nanoparticles are directly used as templates for Ag nanocluster formation under UV-radiation without the addition of other chemicals, which avoids tedious synthetic procedures. Besides the routine structural and physicochemical characterization of the proposed integrated nanostructures, detailed photophysical properties of Ag nanoclusters on nanoparticle surfaces will be explored with fluorescent correlation spectroscopy. Further, the structural integrity of the integrated nanostructures will be tested in biological systems. The proposed work will offer fundamental insight into the integration of multiple nanocomponents (e.g., correlations between structure-properties-performance).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;Magnetic nanoparticles have significantly advanced cancer treatments through targeted drug delivery and localized therapy and further make simultaneous therapy and diagnosis possible as magnetic resonant imaging (MRI) contrast agents. Unfortunately, these applications are limited by the expensive MRI equipments, which are not available to common research laboratories. Currently, fluorescence imaging remains the primary choice for bio-imaging because of its high sensitivity. This proposal will develop magnetic-fluorescent nanoparticles which provide a single platform with therapeutic and diagnostic functions. Beyond the new possibilities of this nanostructure in biomedical fields, further findings on the photophysics of Ag nanoclusters on nanoparticle surfaces may provide valuable information to physicists and spectroscopists. The integrated nanostructures may be used for monitored magnetic removal of the contaminants from the environment. Part of the research project will be incorporated in the junior summer laboratory course (ChBE320), a five hour laboratory operation class, promoting students? learning through hands-on experience, such as building alternating current (AC) magnetic coils to study the heat generation from magnetic nanoparticles and creating magnetic-fluorescent nanoparticle arrays on a chip to demonstrate the bio-sensing capability.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0907204</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ybao@eng.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1762</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
