<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Analysis of Non-Linear Flows in Heterogeneous Porous Media and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>221626</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pedro Embid</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Ibragimov&lt;br/&gt;DMS-0908177&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Almost all off-the-shelf industrial simulators of the&lt;br/&gt;process of filtration in porous media utilize the linear Darcy's&lt;br/&gt;approximation of the momentum equation. On the other hand,&lt;br/&gt;deviations from the assumed linear relationship between the&lt;br/&gt;pressure gradient and fluid velocity occur even at low Reynolds&lt;br/&gt;numbers, and in porous media containing fractures. Though these&lt;br/&gt;deviations are commonly attributed to inertial forces, the actual&lt;br/&gt;nature of this phenomenon is not adequately understood. The&lt;br/&gt;objective of this project is to arrive at a model that transforms&lt;br/&gt;current understanding and prediction of fluid flow in&lt;br/&gt;heterogeneous porous media. Approaches and methodologies from&lt;br/&gt;partial differential equations, computational fluid dynamics, and&lt;br/&gt;differential geometry are deployed to attain this goal. The&lt;br/&gt;models and methods involved include the following: a family of&lt;br/&gt;generalized nonlinear flow models, which spans existing models&lt;br/&gt;and forecasts new ones; a mathematical theory of the nonlinear&lt;br/&gt;Darcy equation where the permeability tensor depends on the&lt;br/&gt;gradient of pressure; a thorough study of the dynamics and&lt;br/&gt;robustness of the equations; analysis of solutions to&lt;br/&gt;Navier-Stokes-Forchheimer equations; applications of the methods&lt;br/&gt;of differential geometry to nonlinear hydrodynamic flows; a&lt;br/&gt;mathematical model for coupled flows in discontinuous fractured&lt;br/&gt;media; computational methods to investigate the stability and&lt;br/&gt;convergence of the multigrid algorithm for coupling nonlinear&lt;br/&gt;multiphase flows in highly irregular porous media. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; This project aims to better understand the complex phenomena&lt;br/&gt;of fluid filtration observed in nature or arising in modern&lt;br/&gt;technology and industry. The work provides a novel theoretical&lt;br/&gt;and numerical framework to explore a wide class of nonlinear&lt;br/&gt;flows in porous media. The methodology is based on modern&lt;br/&gt;research in nonlinear partial differential equations, real&lt;br/&gt;analysis and geometry, as well as new numerical methods in&lt;br/&gt;computational fluid dynamics. The mathematical models and&lt;br/&gt;methods are novel, and their applications are not limited to&lt;br/&gt;nonlinear fluid filtration in porous media. The research is&lt;br/&gt;integrated in educational programs spanning various special&lt;br/&gt;topics. The results of this project are disseminated not only&lt;br/&gt;through professional meetings and journal publications, but also&lt;br/&gt;through a network of collaborations and partnerships with&lt;br/&gt;industrial and reservoir engineering companies interested in&lt;br/&gt;employing the tools developed in the course of the project. On a&lt;br/&gt;larger scale, results of the project bear on the prediction and&lt;br/&gt;evaluation of complex bio-hydrodynamic processes in the lumen and&lt;br/&gt;arterial walls, transport of microorganisms in soil, new&lt;br/&gt;techniques for image processing, and management of the nation's&lt;br/&gt;groundwater and energy resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0908177</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Akif</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ibragimov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>akif.ibraguimov@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Magdalena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Toda</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>magda.toda@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hoang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>luan.hoang@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eugenio</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aulisa</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eugenio.aulisa@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
      <CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
      <ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
