<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RET Site: Nanotechnology Research Experience for Teachers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a three year continuing award to support a Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) in Engineering Site program at Rice University, entitled, "RET Site: Nanotechnology Research Experience for Teachers", under the direction of Dr. Vicki Colvin. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this RET in Engineering Program include enhancing the science and engineering content knowledge and teaching skills of 35 Houston, Texas high school teachers each year for three years. The site will combine a full semester spring content course (CHEM 570) and summer internship, followed by a set of school year activities to keep participants engaged with each other and with Rice University. The participants will improve the quality of secondary school science education through the development of inquiry-based learning activities based on laboratory research and create a community of high school and higher education teachers that can motivate secondary students towards careers in science and engineering. The program is designed not only to facilitate teacher professional development but to scale-up the research experience by forming a network of master teachers that can train new teachers. Since the innovative developments at the nanoscale are integrated across biology, physics and chemistry, this program will provide teachers with new insights on basic science that is also well-aligned with Texas State standards and targets underserved teachers and schools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Rice University will work closely with the Houston Independent School District (HISD), a large, urban, majority historically underrepresented minority school district in South Texas. This year long RET is designed to be scalable to have a large impact on science teaching via community workshops for students and teachers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0908968</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hutchinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jshutch@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vicki</FirstName>
      <LastName>Colvin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>colvin@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nichol</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cnichol@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1359</Code>
      <Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>115E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
