<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Degrading offshore permafrost as a source of methane on the East Siberian Arctic Shelf</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>558473</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henrietta N. Edmonds</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Arctic region contains a huge amount of organic carbon, referred to as the Arctic Carbon Hyper Pool, within the Arctic Ocean sedimentary basin. This area has the highest documented rates of coastal sedimentation with annual accumulation rates of about 10 million metric tons organic C per year, which approximately equals the amount of sediment accumulated over the entire pelagic zone of the World Ocean. Due to the specific features of sedimentation and lithogenesis in this area, much of this organic carbon survives decomposition, and is buried within seabed sediments. These sediments are frozen annually or seasonally, representing a substantial reservoir of potentially labile organic carbon. Global warming in the arctic region is predicted to be substantial, and possibly rapid, in next few decades. Upon the melting of permafrost, old stored carbon will be reintroduced into the modern carbon biogeochemical cycle, possibly acting as a strong source of methane to the overlying water and potentially the atmosphere. Additionally, extremely large amounts of more ancient (Pleistocene) methane are trapped as gas hydrates within and beneath the permafrost. This research aims to elucidate the present and future methane flux potential of sediments and permafrost in regions of the East Siberian Arctic Shelf. As a result of global warming, seafloor permafrost along the East Siberian Arctic Shelf may experience a pronounced change in thermal regime. Increased temperature may affect permafrost in several ways, ultimately leading to its degradation and enhanced CH4 release. An international, interdisciplinary research team will determine the distribution and stability of permafrost on the East Siberian Arctic Shelf and evaluate this area as a methane source to the arctic region. Cores from eleven locations will be obtained using dry drilling techniques. Rates of biological methane production and consumption (oxidation) will be quantified in permafrost and sediments at in situ and elevated temperatures. Natural abundance stable carbon and hydrogen isotope measurements will be used to quantify the age and source of methane collected from different sites and depths. These data will be used as input to numerical models, which will be developed to describe the thermodynamic and biogeochemical aspects of permafrost methane dynamics. Using field data and modeling, the current and future potential release of methane from offshore permafrost will be determined and a methane budget for the East Siberian Arctic Shelf will be constructed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0908788</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Samantha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Joye</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjoye@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christof</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meile</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cmeile@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Samarkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>samarkin@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5219</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SYSTEM SCIENCE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
