<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Neptune's Global Atmospheric Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>456663</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Womack</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>AST-0908575&lt;br/&gt;de Pater&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Neptune's atmosphere is one of the most dynamically active atmospheres in our solar system, and yet it is still poorly constrained. This project will gain a better understanding of the global circulation in this atmosphere using new sets of observations at near-infrared and radio wavelengths. The adaptive-optics (AO) assisted integral-field spectrometer OSIRIS at Keck will be used to determine the average cloud altitude as a function of latitude, which can then be compared to AO spectra. The team already has a long-term database of broadband infrared images which will be used to investigate possible changes in the appearance of the planet since the Voyager spacecraft flyby. The spatial distribution of hydrocarbons, determined from mid-infrared data, and the spatial distribution of CO, measured with the Combined Array for Research in Millimeter-wave Astronomy (CARMA), together will yield important information on Neptune's global dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These sorts of data often stimulate cross-disciplinary collaborations across astronomy, geo-physics, chemistry, and mechanical engineering, and between institutions. The observers make use of cutting-edge instrumentation, and help engineers debug and improve the instruments. Impacts beyond the planetary community come from the strong visual appeal of AO images, and their use when discussing the atmosphere, the origin of turbulence, and techniques to overcome blurring. As well as the usual dissemination to the scientific community, group members regularly give talks to the general public, in the US and abroad, featuring their research within a broader context.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>456663</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0908575</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Imke</FirstName>
      <LastName>de Pater</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>imke@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1214</Code>
      <Text>PLANETARY ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
