<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Natal Environments of Dense Cores: Constraints on Dense Core Evolution</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>525783</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Goodman will explore the dense core structures in molecular clouds, to better understand the interface between quiescent cores and the turbulent molecular cloud environment that contains them. This study will cover more than 200 cores located in seven separate molecular cloud complexes. It will combine information gleaned from both emission and extinction maps to create the largest sample of dust column density and temperature maps of cores that has yet been made. The newly created maps will be used to address specific open issues in star formation theory, including: i) the evolution of cores toward star formation; ii) the nature of the gravitational wells in which cores find themselves; and iii) the relation of cores to the larger molecular cloud topology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research will be made publicly available on several online interfaces, including the World Wide Telescope site and Google Sky. Dr. Goodman will participate in the development of a new science curriculum at an independent school which will incorporate these results.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0908159</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alyssa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goodman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>agoodman@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/04/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Harvard University</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
