<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Multi-Disciplinary Preparation of Next Generation Information Assurance Practitioners</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1935701</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor P. Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Computer Science (31)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project proposes to develop a pipeline of Information Assurance (IA) professionals by providing scholarships to talented students over a span of four years, with a yearly cohort of 6 to 8 students. The university is well positioned to attract high quality students who are interested in IA. The Computer Science and Computer Engineering curricula prepare students with strong technical competence in the field of Information Assurance. The MS in IA program, jointly offered by the College of Computer and Information Science (CCIS) and the College of Criminal Justice, provides students a holistic view of IA with a curriculum integrating technical, legal and policy issues. Through the IA-related course offerings, research activities, cooperative education opportunities, outreach activities and research activities, the university has established itself as the right place to further develop this expertise. The program has been certified as a Center of Academic Excellence in Information Assurance Education and Research (CAE/IAE-R) by NSA/DHS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; In addition to extensive course development, CCIS and the College of Engineering have joined together to establish an interdisciplinary research institute in Information Assurance. These efforts aim to attract interested students with diverse backgrounds, as well as researchers to participate in advancing the state-of-the-art in Information Assurance. The Cooperative Education Program, the application-oriented projects embedded in the IA curriculum, and faculty connections with IA-focused industries and research laboratories provide the students with an unique advantage in securing permanent and internship employment, particularly with the federal government. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program proposes to devote special attention to work with HBCU and HSI colleges/universities, to attract and recruit under-represented students to the field of IA. This project leverages previous experience in working with minority-serving institutions through an NSF REU summer program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0909990</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Agnes</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ahchan@ccs.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaeli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kaeli@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Riccardo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pucella</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>riccardo@ccs.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1668</Code>
      <Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7254</Code>
      <Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
