<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Chemical Dynamics in Condensed Phases and at Surfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>580000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Evelyn M. Goldfield</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;John Tully of Yale University is supported by an award from the Theoretical and Computational Chemistry program within the Division of Chemistry to engage in research to advance our atomic-level understanding of dynamical processes in large molecules, at solid surfaces and in the condensed phase. The program develops new theoretical and computational methods, and applies them to elucidate chemical behavior in complex systems of active current interest. Ring polymer path integral theory is used to introduce quantum mechanics into the next generation of molecular dynamics simulation techniques, including processes that occurs on multiple potential energy surfaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is having a broad impact on many important areas of science including photochemistry, catalysis, materials processing and biology. Women, members of under-represented minority gruops and undergradutes are actively involved in this research program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>580000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0909730</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tully</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.tully@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Yale University</Name>
      <CityName>New Haven</CityName>
      <ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
      <StateCode>CT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
