<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Combined Molecular Beam and Molecular Level Imaging studies of Surface Chemistry and Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>795000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Analytical and Surface Chemistry (ASC) program will support the research project of Prof. Steven Sibener of the Department of Chemistry at the University of Chicago. Prof. Sibener and his students will elucidate how the reactivity of adsorbed species on a surface is influenced by the local structure and ensemble configuration of adsorbates. Prof. Sibener and his students will couple variable-temperature UHV-STM instruments that have been developed in the Sibener laboratory with supersonic and hypersonic molecular beams in order to systematically explore heterogeneous reaction mechanisms at the molecular level. This ambitious program will significantly advance our understanding of interfacial and molecular reactivity, generating fundamental knowledge for refining our understanding of mechanistic chemistry. The project will provide excellent training opportunities to undergraduate students, graduate students and postdoctoral fellows who wish to develop greater understanding of heterogeneous chemical systems. Prof. Sibener and his students will promote the understanding of fundamental chemistry in K-12 students and focus their efforts on students from under represented groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0911424</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sibener</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>s-sibener@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5801 South Ellis Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
