<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: "SUPERERUPTIONS," MAGMA CHAMBERS, &amp; PLUTONIC RESIDUE: Insights from Peach Spring Tuff, Significance of Sphene</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150913</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030107</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009&lt;br/&gt;(Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: "Super-eruptions" - explosive eruptions that produce &gt;450 km3 of&lt;br/&gt;magma -arguably are the most catastrophic of all natural processes on Earth. They play&lt;br/&gt;a central role in ongoing debates about the nature of crustal magmatism. Study of&lt;br/&gt;super-eruptions may illuminate [1] the processes by which large quantities of magma&lt;br/&gt;accumulate in the upper crust, are stored and modified, and erupt; [2] the relations&lt;br/&gt;between intrusive and extrusive igneous rocks; and [3] the construction of plutons and&lt;br/&gt;batholiths. We propose a multi-faceted approach to investigate the generation and&lt;br/&gt;eruption of the &gt;600 km3 Peach Spring Tuff (PST: Miocene,&lt;br/&gt;Arizona-California-Nevada). Exposure of the extensive outflow sheet as well as a thick&lt;br/&gt;intracaldera tuff section and related granite makes this a particularly appealing target for&lt;br/&gt;study. The PST phenocryst assemblage comprises a diverse array of accessory&lt;br/&gt;minerals, notably including abundant sphene (titanite), which plays a vital role in both&lt;br/&gt;recording evolving conditions and driving trace element variation. Critical questions to&lt;br/&gt;be addressed include: [1] What environmental factors control occurrence of key&lt;br/&gt;accessory minerals - especially sphene? [2] How does growth of accessories influence&lt;br/&gt;geochemical signatures of magmas - and how can these signatures be used to&lt;br/&gt;characterize evolution of magmatic environments? [3] What are the conditions in giant&lt;br/&gt;chambers immediately prior to super-eruptions? [4] How much do conditions fluctuate,&lt;br/&gt;and are they a direct response to replenishment, eruption, or wholesale contamination?&lt;br/&gt;[5] How long do large systems last, and during how much of their lifetime is there a&lt;br/&gt;large chamber? [6] Are chambers containing super-volumes of eruptible magma&lt;br/&gt;inherently unstable, or is triggering suppressed for unusual lengths of time to permit&lt;br/&gt;accumulation of enormous quantities of magma? [7] How, and how efficiently, are large&lt;br/&gt;volumes of melt-rich magma extracted from crystal-rich residue? [8] How and where are&lt;br/&gt;highly-evolved, high-silica rhyolites generated? [9] What is the significance of similarities&lt;br/&gt;and differences between felsic intrusive and extrusive rocks? [10] Why are highly&lt;br/&gt;evolved plutonic rocks less voluminous than volcanic equivalents? [11] Do giant&lt;br/&gt;eruptions have a different relation to their residual plutonic equivalents than&lt;br/&gt;'normal'-sized eruptions? Are their chambers far larger, or do they more efficiently&lt;br/&gt;extract the eruptible material?&lt;br/&gt;This project will entail an integrated, multi-disciplinary approach involving PIs and&lt;br/&gt;collaborators with diverse expertise and perspectives. The project will combine&lt;br/&gt;extensive field work, elemental and isotopic analyses of rock, glass, mineral, and melt&lt;br/&gt;inclusion samples, dating using several complementary geochronological methods,&lt;br/&gt;quantitative textural investigations, and experimental studies aimed at elucidating the&lt;br/&gt;stability and saturation behavior of sphene. We will employ, among other methods,&lt;br/&gt;NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Proposal:0911726 PI Name:Miller, Calvin&lt;br/&gt;Printed from</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>150913</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0911728</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jonathan.miller@sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1573</Code>
      <Text>PETROLOGY AND GEOCHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
