<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Dynamic Predictive Maintenance System for Mitigating CSO &amp; SSO</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I research project develops a cost effective solution to the sewer overflow hazard within combined sewer systems and sanitary sewer systems. Specifically, the complexity and dynamic nature of the wastewater system presents significant challenges for maintenance. Underlying the maintenance policy development is an engineering trade-off: over-maintenance incurs unnecessary maintenance costs and under-maintenance incurs a greater overflow risk. The proposed solution introduces novel technology innovations which address the limitation in both the reliability and economic feasibility of current blockage detection approaches. Reliably predicting blockage locations will mitigate the risk with minimal maintenance requirements. The proposed project develops the technology innovations for implementing a Dynamic Predictive Maintenance System (DPMS) which allows municipal wastewater utilities to institute a just-in-time maintenance program for mitigating combined sewer overflows (CSO) and sanitary sewer overflows (SSO).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Based on the Environmental Protection Agency 2004 Congressional Report, well over 34 thousand sewer overflows occur annually within the United States resulting in spillage in excess of 850 billion gallons of untreated wastewater. In Charlotte, North Carolina, over 400 sanitary sewer overflows occurred in 2007 within the Charlotte-Mecklenburg Utilities service area resulting in 1.6 million gallons of wastewater overflow. The overflows are predominantly caused by blockages. The blockages cause wastewater to spill out of manholes onto streets, public/private property or into waterways. Overflows result in property damage, environmental problems, and, in severe cases, public health and safety hazards.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>100000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0912589</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Howitt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ihowitt@infosenseinc.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/05/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>InfoSense Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
      <ZipCode>282034690</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7044887488</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1800 Camden Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
