<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Automated Identification and Rapid Detection of Explosives Using Piezoresistive Micro- and Nano-Cantilever Arrays</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99776</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I research project develops an inexpensive, rugged piezo-resistive micro-cantilever sensor array for explosives and toxins detection with the ability for wireless data transmission. The sensor can identify analytes by changes in the electronic properties of the sensor material due to analyte absorption or binding. The sensitivities and detection limits are significantly improved by using ultra-compliant coated polymers that show a high degree of sensitivity and selectivity to different explosives. Ultrathin metallic piezo-resistive sensors are embedded into the cantilevers to enable both static and dynamic measurements. Compared to micro gas chromatographic systems and film based sensor arrays for detection of explosives, the sensor proposed has several advantages including a low-cost fabrication process, higher sensitivity for lower detection limits, and highly selective coating materials for absorption of chemical vapors from Improvised Explosive Devices (IED). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Remote detection systems for explosives are of great concern for homeland security. This proposed sensor can potentially enable low-cost and reliable handheld systems for remote explosive detection or help develop wireless explosive sensing networks for cargos, buildings and other security needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>99776</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0912423</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Weibin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wzhu@evigia.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Kytaro Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Miami</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331992516</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7349729348</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11200 SW 8th St.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5371</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1185</Code>
      <Text>SENSORY SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9139</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
