<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US Egypt Cooperative Research: Preparation of nano-fillers from waste materials and their application in papermaking industry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Lueck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This collaborative research project is being undertaken by Dr. Yulin Deng, Georgia Tech Research Corporation at the Georgia Institute of Technology, and Dr. Said El-Sheikh, Central Metallurgical Research and Development Institute of Egypt, on the topic of preparing nano-fillers from waste materials for use in the paper industry. The research will determine whether inclusion of nano-filler particles in paper can improve the mechanical properties (e.g. smoothness, increased surface area) without compromising paper weight or processing characteristics. Further, tailoring the shape and structure of the nano-fillers to increase surface area should reduce the overall amount of filler needed without adversely impacting tensile strength. The prepared nano-fillers will be characterized in terms of size and phase structure, surface morphology and structural properties, bond types, and nanostructural surface charge. The prepared paper with incorporated nano-fillers will be characterized in terms of optical, physical, mechanical properties. Printability will be also investigated focusing on print density, print gloss and ink transfer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scientific community and paper industry will benefit from the results of the proposed research to explore alternate materials for influencing key properties of paper processing. Nano-fillers may offer special properties of value in specific industry applications. The results may also offer insight into the dispersion behavior of fine calcium carbonate particles and how surface chemistry can be controlled to create nanoscale morphologies. There is a reasonable likelihood that useful, low-cost mineral products can be produced and that such use can help alleviate a waste disposal issue and displace more expensive mineral products. Further, the international exchange, involving green technology, may foster future progress in related fields in both countries. The collaboration is taking place between two highly skilled research institutes and involves US and Egyptian junior scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is funded under the US-Egypt Joint Fund Program, which provides grants to scientists and engineers in both countries to undertake cooperative research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0913623</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yulin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Deng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yulin.deng@chbe.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
