<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Track 1 Native Science Fellows</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199168</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jill L. Karsten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hopa Mountain, an educational nonprofit organization based in Bozeman, Montana, will pilot an innovative Native Science Fellows program for high school and college students to participate in community-based science organizations in an effort to increase their engagement in higher education and geosciences careers. There are four primary goals: (1) To increase the number of Native American students (ages 15-35) who are engaged in community-based geosciences education and careers; (2) To provide role models and work experience for Native American high school and college students interested in the geosciences; (3) To develop a career ladder network of Native students that are interested in pursuing geosciences careers; and (4) To build a network of community-based science professionals who are committed to the success of Native students and provide on-going support for personal, academic and professional success. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific objectives of the Native Science Fellows pilot program are to match promising Native American high school and college students with summer and school year fellowships that will provide them with paid, hands-on field work and professional experiences to build skills and pathways to academic and careers in the geosciences. These students will also be linked to geoscience mentors and supportive Native Science Fellows peer and professional networks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>199168</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0914520</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bonnie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sachatello-Sawyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bsawyer@hopamountain.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hopa Mountain, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597159341</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4065862455</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>234 E. Babcock, Suite E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
