<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Twenty-Fifth Fungal Genetics Conference, Asilomar Conference Center; Pacific Grove, CA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Porter Ridley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Twenty-Fifth Fungal Genetics Conference will be held at the Asilomar Conference Center from March 17-22, 2009. Approximately 850-1,000 scientists and students from around the world will attend. The conference focuses on the molecular biology, genetics, genomics, biochemistry and cell biology of filamentous fungi. This biennial conference is considered by most to be the pre-eminent meeting in the area of fungal biology, and promotes interaction between researchers interested in plant pathogens, medical pathogens, saprobic fungi and symbiotic fungi. Having everyone staying at one site facilitates the type of informal discussions that often lead to the development of new collaborations and research directions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The formal meeting will consist of four plenary sessions, four sets of concurrent sessions devoted to specialized areas, and three poster sessions. The topics to be covered in the plenary sessions are 1) genome evolution and dynamics, 2) pathogenic and symbiotic interactions, 3) gene regulation and metabolism, and 4) signaling, development and sex. Topics to be covered by the 27 concurrent sessions include 1) associations between fungi and humans, 2) associations with plants, 3) dimorphic transitions and morphogenesis, 4) secondary metabolism, 5) sex and development, 6) evolutionary genetics and genomics, 7) RNA functions, epigenetics and chromosome biology, , 8) natural products and small molecules, 9) metabolomics and proteomics, and 10) teaching fungal biology and genetics, to name a few. Based on previous meetings, the organizers expect around 700 poster presentations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;From a broader perspective, fungi are model eukaryotes that have aided in the understanding of basic biological processes beginning with Beadle and Tatum's 1940's work demonstrating, for the first time, the relationship between genetics and biochemistry. Fungi have also been important as models to help elucidate disease in animals and plants. This meeting places a strong emphasis on the participation of young scientists and students, particularly those from underrepresented groups. For many, this meeting is their first opportunity to attend a major international conference and present their research findings; such presentations are a critical part of scientists' training and professional development. Funds from this award will help defray the participation costs for students, postdoctoral researchers, and young scientists for whom these costs would otherwise be a hardship. Special emphasis will be placed on supporting women and other researchers who belong to groups underrepresented in this field of research. Funds will be distributed to successful financial aid applicants on the basis of need.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0914743</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Orbach</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>orbachmj@ag.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1112</Code>
      <Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1116</Code>
      <Text>EUKARYOTIC GENETICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
