<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI: Small: Learning Strategic Behavior in Sequential Decision Tasks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>455000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Todd Leen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Many routine, real-world tasks can be seen as sequential decision tasks. For instance, navigating a robot through a complex environment, driving a car in congested traffic, and routing packets in a computer network requires making a sequence of decisions that together minimize time and resources used. It would be desirable to automate these tasks, yet it is difficult because the optimal decisions are generally not known. Many existing learning methods lead to reactive behaviors that perform well in short term, but do not amount to intelligent high-level behavior in the long term. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is developing methods for learning strategic high-level behavior. Strategic methods need to (1) retain information from past states, (2) learn multimodal behavior, (3) choose between the different behaviors based on crucial detail, and (4) implement a sequential high-level strategy based on those behaviors. The neuroevolution methods developed in prior work solve the first problem by evolving (through genetic algorithms) recurrent neural networks to represent the behavior. To solve the remaining problems, these methods are being extended in the proposed work with multi-objective optimization, local nodes with cascaded structure, and with evolution of modules and their combinations. Preliminary results indicate that this approach is indeed feasible. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the long term, developed technology will make it possible to build robust sequential decision systems for real-world tasks. It leads to safer and more efficient vehicle, traffic, and robot control, improved process and manufacturing optimization, and more efficient computer and communication systems. It will also make the next generation of video games possible, with characters that exhibit realistic, strategic behaviors: Such technology should lead to more effective educational and training games in the future. The OpenNERO open source software platform developed in this work will be made available to the research community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0915038</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Risto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miikkulainen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>risto@cs.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
