<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Workshop on Structural Health Monitoring 2009: Transformational Change on Health Management and Materials/Structures Design</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Shih-Chi Liu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Structural health monitoring is a sensor dependent emerging technology, which integrated advanced sensors and sensing systems with diagnostics, prognostics and knowledge of material/structural damage characteristics to assess the health condition of the structures. The health monitoring can be made while the structure is in service, for prevention of man-made or natural catastrophes, to minimize down time, and sustain performance, and to reduce maintenance costs. An international workshop on Structural Health Monitoring (SHM) will be held at Stanford University Sept 9-11, 2009. The workshop aimed at examination of the state-of-the-art technology in structural health monitoring and at future research program development. Distinguished individuals in the field will be invited to attend and products and demonstrations will be exhibited.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Promotion of intellectual exchange in SHM technology development and building up the sensors technology research community across the board.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Expected outcomes include proceedings of technical presentations, formation of technical committee consisting of government, industry and academic specialists, development of guidelines and recommendations for promotion of SHM technologies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0915210</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fu-Kuo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fkchang@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
