<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NIRT: Nanoscale Engineering and Manufacture Effected Through Molecular Architecture and Structure</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/16/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>354318</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to develop technology that allows for dispersion and accurate control over assembly of nano-objects into polymeric materials for the next generation of nanostructured materials and devices. The approach is to integrate a team that has skills in synthetic chemistry, characterization, theory, computer simulation and engineering skills who can rapidly respond to recent discoveries made by the team which suggests unusual thermodynamics at the nanoscale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader educational and outreach aspects of the NIRT activities are considered critical to the ultimate success of this program and will cross several disciplines: chemistry, physics and engineering. To create a truly multidisciplinary environment in which students can thrive, integration of synthetic organic/polymer chemistry (Wooley, Hawker) with physics/theory of nanosystems (Tomanek, Frischknecht), polymer science (Celina, Assink) and engineering (Mackay) will be accomplished through a variety of mechanisms: exchange of students, an annual meeting, regular teleconferences or cyber meetings and participation in national meetings. Teaching modules in nanotechnology have already been developed by members of this NIRTeam and other courses are under development in addition to our previous successful outreach activities such as talks to elementary School children by Mackay and Wooley and a trial presentation entitled, "Nanotech Kids," is available on the web (www.nanoeverything.com). We propose to expand the outreach to K-12 and the general public by teaming with the Science Theatre located on the campus of Michigan State University to create stage shows for the public. Finally, this NIRTeam consists of dedicated researchers who will also make fundamental scientific discoveries and have the ability to translate this knowledge to industrial reality.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0915334</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mackay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mem@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1674</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1674</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
