<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TC: Small: Capsule: Safely Accessing Confidential Data in a Low-Integrity Environment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>366845</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Protecting confidential information is a major concern for organizations and individuals alike, who stand to suffer huge losses if private data falls into the wrong hands. One of the primary threats to confidentiality is malicious software, which is estimated to reside on millions of computers. Current security solutions, such as firewalls, anti-virus software, and intrusion detection systems, are inadequate at preventing malware infection.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main contribution of this project will be a novel mechanism, called Storage Capsules, that will allow users to protect confidential files on personal computers and servers. Storage Capsules are encrypted containers that will allow users on a compromised machine to securely read and write files on the container using standard applications without malware being able to steal confidential file data. Research themes include designing the system, analyzing its security and addressing the potential threats, improving its efficiency, and extending it to support user-defined access policies. Broader implications of this work include providing a new method for people to secure sensitive data on their personal computers and servers, even in the presence of malware.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0916126</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Atul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prakash</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aprakash@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
