<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Collaborative Research: Supporting unstructured peer-to-peer social networking</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0915928 - NeTS: Small: Collaborative Research: Supporting unstructured peer-to-peer social networking&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;09/01/09-08/31/12&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;G. de Veciana, PI, U.T. Austin, and G. Kesidis, PI, Penn State&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Peer-to-peer systems have seen continued growth, in terms of traffic volume, and as the architecture of choice to build new applications and network services ? notable benefits lie in their distributed design leading to higher reliability and flexibility. However as users/peers increasingly become content providers, and generally conduct more of their business on the network, privacy is a critical concern.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By leveraging peers? trust relationships through referral mechanisms based on underlying reputation systems, applications that deliver a new standard of privacy are being devised. Peer-to-peer systems that dynamically adapt, in a distributed and scalable manner, based on the outcomes of peer transactions, are being modeled and analyzed. The focus is on unstructured networks where peer-membership correlations among communities of interest can be learned to improve the search performance of reputation-biased random walks and limited-scope flooding. Content-sharing applications are being designed based that leverage this framework to incentivize cooperative behavior while enabling collaborative filtering and content pushing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Expected results include the development analysis and testing of a new framework for privacy-preserving search for large-scale, unstructured, on-line, peer-to-peer networks. Complementary incentive mechanisms resulting in improve file sharing and promoting honest referrals will be devised. The results will be disseminated through peer-reviewed venues and, where possible, industry concerns, while data and simulation tools are made available on the web.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The efforts impact will lie in contributing new ways to improve privacy and promote more honest and efficient cooperation in large-scale on-line peer-to-peer systems, for content sharing, as well as a broader set of social networking applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0916179</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kesidis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gik2@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7795</Code>
      <Text>TRUSTWORTHY COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
