<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Planning Visit to Israel to Develop a Comprehensive Survey of Youth in Intractable Conflict</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10758</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Edward Murdy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: OISE-0917658&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Phillip Hammack&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of California-Santa Cruz (UCSC)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Planning Visit to Israel to Develop a Comprehensive Survey of Youth in Intractable Conflict&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI plans to travel to Israel for two weeks to develop a collaborative project with Israeli scientists to collaboratively develop a comprehensive survey of youth in intractable conflict zones that focuses on the social psychological concept of delegitimization. The planning visit will include a faculty member and graduate student from UCSC, and three psychological scientists in Israel. Developing a&lt;br/&gt;collaborative relationship between American and Israeli social scientists will enhance the knowledge of the impact of political conflict on the psychological development of youth.&lt;br/&gt;The proposed visit to plan a collaborative project seeks to expand our knowledge in this critical area of social and developmental psychology by examining the psychological processes of youth in the context of longstanding conflict in Israel. The development of this collaboration possesses broad impacts for psychological science, responding to recent calls for attention to psychological processes in diverse global contexts. The proposed study will address the unique context of conflict and its impact on individual lives, thereby contributing to the movement within psychology to identify the impact of diverse contexts on human development. In addition, the survey to be developed through this collaboration will possess important implications for conflict resolution by specifying&lt;br/&gt;factors associated with delegitimization among youth. The project thus will provide&lt;br/&gt;valuable information to practitioners and scholars of peace and reconciliation efforts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0917658</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Phillip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hammack</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hammack@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
