<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Soft Condensed Matter Physics: Soft Meets Biology Conference: New London, NH; August 9-14, 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070013</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David A. Brant</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ID: MPS/DMR/BMAT(7623) 0917794 PI: Nelson, David ORG: Gordon Research Conferences&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Gordon Research Conference on Soft Condensed Matter Physics: Soft Meets Biology&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT: The Conference will address an interesting and timely group of topics at the interface of condensed matter physics and quantitative biology, and an exceptionally strong group of speakers has been assembled. Topics include Biophysics of Viruses, Directed Assembly of Biopolymers, Biologically Inspired Materials Science, Collective Effects in Soft Matter, Cooperative Effects in Bacteria, Genetic Regulation and Evolution, Biophysics of Lipids and Polymers, Motors and Forces in Biology, and Self-Organization and Self-Assembly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACTS: The Conference will bring together scientists from the soft matter and materials communities to encourage interdisciplinary discussion of issues of mutual interest. The organizers have given appropriate attention to the application of NSF funding to broadening participation, with a significant number of females included among the speakers and session chairs. More than 25% of the total proposed budget for the Conference is devoted to supporting participation by students, postdoctorals, and early career faculty. Female applicants and applicants from underrepresented groups will be targeted for use of these earmarked funds.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0917794</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nelson@physics.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
