<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference on Ciliate Molecular Biology to be held in Saxton's River, Vermont</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10475</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Porter Ridley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award will support the Fourteenth International Meeting on Ciliate Molecular Biology, to be held as a FASEB Summer Research Conference in Saxtons River, Vermont, from July 19-24, 2009. The ciliates are a diverse group of unicellular organisms found in many environments throughout the world. For many years, they have served as model organisms for the study of those mechanisms of cellular function and inheritance that are shared among eukaryotic (non-bacterial) species. Key discoveries made with ciliates include RNA enzymes, the structure of telomeres (the ends of chromosomes), and the first identified function of histone modification in controlling gene activity. The conference is the major international venue for ciliate scientists to present their latest research findings on these topics, as well as on genomics, evolution, cell development, motility, and signaling. Platform and poster sessions, along with workshops on current and emerging topics of particular interest, will be included. Between 120 and 150 researchers are expected to attend, most coming from within the United States, but some traveling from countries around the world.&lt;br/&gt; The ciliate research community is known for its highly collaborative nature and for its commitment to the career development of young investigators. As at past conferences, there will be a workshop devoted to the use of ciliates as tools in undergraduate classrooms and independent research environments. For the first time, this workshop will be held in concert with a platform session devoted exclusively to undergraduates' presentation of their own research results. To promote the fruitful exchange of ideas on career and research development among attendees at various career levels, discussions will be held on various themes (suggested by registrants) at special "topic tables" at selected meals. The ciliate scientific community strongly encourages the participation of young scientists, women, and minorities in the conference program. The funding obtained from the NSF will be used solely to support attendance by graduate and undergraduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and beginning investigators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0918029</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wiley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ewiley@kecksci.claremont.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chalker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dchalker@biology2.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Federation of Amer Societies For Exper Biology</Name>
      <CityName>Bethesda</CityName>
      <ZipCode>208143998</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3016347013</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9650 ROCKVILLE PIKE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
