<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RIG: The ecological constraints of methane production by microbes in natural environments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>187856</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan James Tessier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project examines the ecological constraints that govern the ability of different microbial taxa to form close partnerships with one another, in order to increase the energetic efficiency of anaerobic degradation of organic compounds. These mutualistic partnerships, referred to as syntrophy, appear to involve an active selection process by the microbe partners, but little is known about the mechanisms by which this occurs. This project will study the selection process by which the syntrophic bacterium, Syntrophus aciditrophicus, selects a particular methanogen partner from a natural environment. This project combines classical methods of enumeration, cultivation, enrichment, and isolation of strict anaerobic prokaryotes with a culture-independent molecular DNA based technique. This approach will be used to determine if S. aciditrophicus selects for a particular syntrophic partner, if that partner is the same regardless of the environmental context, and the range of methanogens that are capable of sustaining this mutualism. Results from this work will allow predictions about the potential ecological distribution of this syntrophic organism. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has significant broader relevance to the global carbon cycle. Describing the key process of selection among syntrophic microbe partners will contribute to a better understanding of energetic processes and carbon flux in anaerobic environments. This project will also enhance the quality of undergraduate education at a minority serving institution. Participating students will acquire hands on experience in laboratory and field research, and will be closely mentored on how to pursue successful career paths in the STEM disciplines. The project will also support the training of a graduate student in microbial ecology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0919065</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rios-Hernandez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>luis.rios5@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez</Name>
      <CityName>Mayaguez</CityName>
      <ZipCode>006819000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7878312065</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Call Box 9000</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
      <StateCode>PR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7487</Code>
      <Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7692</Code>
      <Text>RIG/CAA</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
