<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Physics of Life: Interdisciplinary Education at the Introductory Level</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>315515</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lee L. Zia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The reform of the Introductory Biology III: Organismal Biology to integrate physics into biology and the concurrent reform of introductory physics courses for biology majors is being conducted. A set of educational materials that covers two broad physics topics of importance in basic biology &amp; thermodynamics and transport are being developed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A combined team of education-reform-minded biologists and physics education researchers is carrying out the integration of physics into biology and the matching reform of a course in physics for biologists by using an approach to curriculum reform that focuses on issues of content, epistemology, and pedagogy. Materials developed include structured on-line readings, Peer Instruction conceptual problems for large lecture biology classes, sample problems for in-class group problem solving, sample exam problems, structured homework problems coordinated so that there are matching problems in the biology and physics classes, and in-class tutorial-style worksheets. Each item undergoes a rigorous cycle of development, review, revision, and testing to ensure the quality and effectiveness of the finished products. The resulting materials will be disseminated over the internet and described at appropriate professional forums.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0919816</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cooke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tjcooke@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Redish</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>redish@physics.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
