<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The roles of the AMP-activated kinase in metabolic homeostasis in Drosophila</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330278</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Ellis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Food availability is a dynamic aspect of most environments and places significant challenges on organisms to maintain constant energy stores. The consequences of energy shortage include changes in behavior and physiology that reflect changes in the allocation of energy. Part of the decision process on how energy is utilized depends upon the actions of the AMP-activated kinase, a highly-conserved molecule that becomes active during energy shortages. It is also clear that different cellular populations have differential responses during energy deprivation, although it is unclear the extent that the AMP-activated kinase partakes in these processes. This project takes advantage of the unique molecular and genetic tools available in the fruit fly, Drosophila melanogaster, to investigate how the AMP-activated kinase regulates behavioral and physiological changes during starvation conditions. This research will contribute new information regarding the cellular signals within defined neural and peripheral tissues that are responsible for generating specific behavioral and physiological changes to maintain energy homeostasis. The evolutionary conservation of this particular molecule, as well as the conservation of behavioral responses to starvation, indicates results of this research will have broad applications, from pest management to the development of potential novel therapeutics. In addition to offering insight into the cell-specific roles of the AMP-activated kinase, this research project will be used as a vehicle to extend research opportunities to undergraduate students and enhance professional development of faculty at a primarily undergraduate institution, Francis Marion University. Lastly, this project will involve the training of graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0920443</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johnsoec@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Wake Forest University</Name>
      <CityName>Winston Salem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>271098758</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3367585888</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1834 Wake Forest Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
