<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transcription and Translation in a Uniquely Compartmentalized Bacterial Cell</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>481808</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt; Bacteria are usually considered to be simple life forms, but some species are known to possess compartments within their cells. While some compartments serve to separate physiological processes from the rest of the cell, the function of others is undetermined. The significance of membrane-bound compartments containing genomic DNA (superficially resembling eukaryotic nuclei) is particularly elusive. Planctomycete bacteria have an unusual cell plan, with the genomic DNA and ribosomes restricted to one of two cellular compartments. Even greater complexity is found in the planctomycete Gemmata obscuriglobus, which possesses an additional network of double-layered membranes surrounding the genomic DNA. The goal of this project is to determine whether the additional G. obscuriglobus membrane network is functionally equivalent to the eukaryotic nuclear membrane. The main research focus is the potential uncoupling of transcription and translation (a hallmark of eukaryotic cell biology, but not known to occur in Bacteria), and identification of membrane transport mechanisms. The experimental approach involves localization and characterization of proteins in the different cell compartments, using electron and fluorescence microscopy, as well as physical separation of the compartments. The project provides a unique opportunity to explore an apparent exception to the rule of coupled bacterial transcription and translation, and determine whether this complex microbial cell organization can be used to support models of eukaryotic cell evolution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt; The project will promote teaching, training, and learning through classroom instruction, research training (one postdoctoral fellow, one graduate student, two undergraduate researchers), and an initiative for high school teachers. Teachers will participate in research apprenticeships and workshops, leading to the implementation of new curriculum in their classrooms. The project will therefore contribute to future science and technology capabilities in the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0920667</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Naomi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ward</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nlward@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mayes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rmayes2@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
      <CityName>Laramie</CityName>
      <ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
      <StateCode>WY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1114</Code>
      <Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1114</Code>
      <Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1132</Code>
      <Text>CELLULAR ORGANIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7465</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
