<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Characterization of Essential Fatty Acid Conservation Mechanisms in Ruminants</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>394805</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William E. Zamer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ruminants, like cows and sheep, use specialized stomachs containing fermenting bacteria to digest plant material. Some non-ruminant animals, such as kangaroos and langur monkeys, also have specialized stomachs containing fermenting bacteria. Bacteria present in the stomachs of these animals modify other nutrients from the diet including essential fatty acids. Modification by bacteria severely reduces the amounts of these fatty acids available for absorption. Ruminants have developed metabolic adaptations involving fatty acid esterification to conserve essential fatty acids, yet little is known about the mechanisms involved in the conservation of these essential fatty acids. In addition, it is not clear whether these conservation mechanisms extend to non-ruminant animals that ferment in the stomach. Mechanisms used by ruminants to conserve essential fatty acids will be revealed by identifying the tissue-specific fatty acid esterification patterns of the cow compared to a non-ruminant, the pig. Cellular factors mediating these esterification patterns will be examined by characterizing enzymes and cellular organelles involved in esterification. The presence of similar conservation mechanisms in non-ruminant animals that ferment in the stomach will be determined by characterizing the profile of essential fatty acids in plasma lipid classes. It is expected that conservation is mediated by recognition and segregation of essential fatty acids within cells and that all organs of ruminants participate in essential fatty acid conservation. Furthermore, given the presence of stomach fermentation in other non-ruminants, it is expected that these species also engage in conservation mechanisms analogous to those found in ruminants. This work will increase understanding of how fatty acids are recognized by cells and how the systemic metabolic adaptations developed as ruminants, and stomach fermenting non-ruminants, evolved fermentative capacity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As part of this research, a post-doctoral researcher will work with undergraduate researchers, thus allowing the post-doctoral researcher to further develop research skills and techniques while engaging undergraduates in comparative nutrition and metabolism research. Topics in comparative nutrition and digestive physiology will be introduced to high school students participating in summer learning programs at Virginia Tech through a wet lab experience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>394805</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0920491</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Corl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bcorl@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
