<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Physical Property Measurement System for Materials Science Research and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>401201</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sean Liam Jones</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0922997&lt;br/&gt;Philip&lt;br/&gt;Catholic U.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Catholic University of America (CUA) will acquire a new Physical property measurement system (PPMS) with AC magnetometry and vibrating sample magnetometer options to be shared with researchers at Howard University and Virginia Commonwealth University. The PPMS will be able to measure a variety of physical properties, over a range of temperatures from 2.0 - 400 K, and with magnetic fields up to 7 Tesla. The EverCool dewar completely avoids the need for liquid He transfers and to minimize helium loss from the PPMS under most operating conditions. There is automatic control of the He gas input to replenish what is lost over time and to automatically maintain optimal liquid helium levels in the dewar. The instrument provides for measurement of the magnetic moment, AC susceptibility, electrical transport, magnetoresistance and Hall effect. The acquisition of this instrument will enable: the investigation of spin injection and detection in semiconducting channels such as Si and Ge as well as the effects of interfaces on efficient spin transfer into these channels; the investigation of the large spin-dependent transport properties observed in Si-based nanowires; the study of ferromagnetic nanowires composed of FeGa for a wide range of defense and industrial applications as transducers and sensors; understanding the fundamental physics of the magnetite at the nanoscale; characterizing new spin crossover complexes that are of great interest as molecular memory devices or switches; and the development of ferromagnetic bioceramics for new bioimplants especially for bone and also for treating various diseases and delivering drugs. The acquisition of this instrument will greatly enhance our present capabilities and add a new dimension to materials research at CUA. It will also have an impact on the new initiatives in nano-biomaterials and in materials science. This new facility will bring together researchers from different areas, leading to an exchange of ideas and new joint research projects and will serve as a catalyst for further expansion in CUA?s science and engineering programs and greater collaboration with Universities in and around the District of Columbia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The advancement and understanding of materials properties are critical for developing novel next generation electronic, magnetic and spin electronic devices. The medical field also now depends greatly on innovative and nanoscale materials and devices for bioimplants, drug delivery and newer treatment options. Researchers at the Catholic University of America are actively involved in investigating the electronic and magneto-transport properties of nanoscale devices, nanoparticles, biomaterials and inorganic complexes. The acquisition of a Physical Property Measurement System with AC magnetometry and Vibrating Sample Magnetometer options will allow multiple users within the science and engineering departments to have access to electrical, magnetic and magneto-transport measurements of materials and devices. Understanding the material and the nanoscale device properties are crucial for advanced technologies that will drive our future economy. This instrument is an essential tool used to study, characterize and evaluate materials with a wide range of properties. It will be used to guide the scientists at the Catholic University in their efforts to design new nanoscale devices that will employ electron spin states to store and process information, which will pave a foundation for a dramatic improvement in computing and a new generation of low power consuming, highly dense and fast electronic circuits. Also understanding the fundamental physics at the nanoscale of certain magnetic materials (oxides of iron) are vital for new technological advances in the biomedical industry especially for bioimplants and drug delivery. It will also help researchers to investigate new materials called spin crossover complexes, which are of great interest as molecular memory devices or switches and when fully understood could lead to significant advances in the miniaturization of electronic and computer components. This instrument will provide the foundation for collaborative efforts among greater Washington area universities such as Catholic, Howard and Virginia Commonwealth University. It will be also used to train future generations of scientists through undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral research. The new capability will also help to expand our efforts in training minority and under-represented high school students from DC metro area.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0922997</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Philip</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>philip@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brewer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brewer@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pegg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ianp@vsl.cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Otto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson, Jr.</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wilsono@cua.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Catholic University of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200640001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026355000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>620 Michigan Ave.N.E.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
