<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Pre-disturbance surveys of wood loads in headwater streams of the Colorado Front Range</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30435</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Cutler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Wood plays a critical goal in regulating the flow dynamics of headwater streams in mountain areas. The pine beetle is currently making its way across the forests of the Colorado Rocky Mountains and threatens to change the amount and distribution of wood in these stream environments. The speed of beetle infestation and tree die-off makes it imperative to quickly document pre-disturbance conditions in relatively unaffected headwater streams, not least because the recovery times of these streams are likely to be at least a century. The presence of numerous standing dead trees will initially increase wood load to adjacent stream channels, but the lag created by slow forest regrowth will eventually result in substantial decreases in wood load. Creation of baseline inventories of wood loads now, prior to widespread beetle die-off enable an analysis of the effects of forest changes on stream flow and geomorphology. This research will focus on a widespread survey of existing wood loads along undisturbed headwater streams of the Colorado Front Range. Additional objectives are to relate observed variations in wood load to geomorphic and ecological variables and to develop guidelines for use of wood in restoration of streams following timber harvest of beetle-killed trees. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since wood is so important in regulating the environment of headwater streams, stream restoration following timber harvest is likely to include artificial reintroduction of wood to channels. This project will provide needed information about optimal restoration strategies by carrying out a widespread survey of existing wood loads in a range of undisturbed headwater channels during summer 2009. The primary objective is to document wood loads along undisturbed headwater streams of the Colorado Front Range. Additional objectives are to relate observed variations in wood load to geomorphic and ecological variables and to develop guidelines for use of wood in restoration of streams. The project will conduct basic wood surveys along 20 stream reaches, each of which is 10 km in length. The significance of this project includes: development of the first extensive regional database for the semarid Rocky Mountains on spatial variations in wood load within undisturbed headwater streams; education of students; development of guidelines for management and restoration of instream wood; and outreach to the public regarding the effects of beetle kill and timber harvest on headwater streams.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>30435</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0922589</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wohl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ellen.wohl@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7458</Code>
      <Text>GEOMORPHOLOGY &amp; LAND USE DYNAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
