<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-RUI: Acquisition of a Spinning confocal Microscope to Advance Interdepartmental Research and Training at Missouri State University-Springfield</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>248350</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A grant has been awarded to Missouri State University (MSU) to acquire a laser spinning confocal fluorescence microscope equipped with a Yokogawa spinning confocal scanner and four laser lines for research and teaching at the university and in the region. This instrument will not only allow researchers to achieve significantly improved quality in microscopic imaging but will also afford them the opportunity to perform advanced techniques such as fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP), fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET), optical sectioning of specimens, and dual-channel real-time imaging. All participants including the PI and Co-PIs represent an interdepartmental group of faculty who, despite diverse research interests, possess commonalities in their employed approaches and instrumentation. Foreseeable outcomes from the research activities include advancement of interdisciplinary research, training, and collaboration. This new system will offer researchers the exciting opportunity to pursue several up to date research avenues including: 1) uncovering the roles of dynamin-like proteins in endocytosis, 2) characterizing anti-inflammatory signaling networks downstream of interleukin-10, 3) revealing the role of ATAF1 in plant resistance to powdery mildew pathogens, 4) understanding the role of actin cytoskeleton reorganization during the defense responses by grapevine to powdery mildew pathogens, 5) monitoring the delivery of carbon nanotubes in cells, 6) monitoring fluorescent biosensors based on conducting polymer nanowires, 7) studying neuron-glial cell communication, 8) investigating fecal coliform growth in biofilms derived from freshwater streams, and 9) studying P2 nucleotide receptor function at the molecular level. Employment of the confocal microscopy in multiple classroom settings at the university and in the region will broaden the impact of the instrument. Training with the instrument will be incorporated into the curriculums for five of our academic departments, both in traditional classes and student independent research. Acquisition of the spinning confocal system will impact many facets of the MSU community and beyond. An immediate outcome will be the expanded investigative capacity of the major users and students. As a result, faculty in several departments will be better positioned to (i) contribute to the scientific community by way of conference presentations and peer-reviewed publications and (ii) compete for external research funding. A heightened research profile at MSU will aid in the recruitment and retention of high-quality faculty and students. Furthermore, the establishment of the proposed system will broaden interdisciplinary collaboration with local universities. Collectively, greater success in these areas will increase student research opportunities and heighten the quality of undergraduate and graduate education in the region. The availability of this instrument will also contribute greatly towards the outreach programs in the local community to educate families and motivate young people to pursue careers in science and engineering. Outcomes of the research projects will be communicated through presentations by students and faculty at regional or national meetings, in peer reviewed journal publications, and on the internet.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>248350</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0923024</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lifeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>LDong03@hamline.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Steiert</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgs617f@vma.smsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laszlo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kovacs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>laszlokovacs@missouristate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kyoungtae</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kkim@missouristate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weaver</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brianweaver@missouristate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Missouri State University</Name>
      <CityName>Springfield</CityName>
      <ZipCode>658970027</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4178365972</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>901 South National</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
