<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a State-of-Art X-Ray Diffraction System for Investigation of Nano/Micro/Bio-Materials and Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>292886</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0923335&lt;br/&gt;Cheng&lt;br/&gt;Auburn U.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary: The research activities at Auburn University and Tuskegee University have shifted toward nano-/micro-structured materials and devices, which requires an instrument capable of characterizing the local structure, orientation and residual stress in thin films and textured materials. The objective of this proposal is to acquire a state-of-the-art X-ray diffracto-meter to fulfill the diverse and urgent needs of researchers at both institutions. In particular, the proposed system will generate an X-ray beam that can be focused into a sub-millimeter spot to provide spatial resolution of crystal structure and orientation. The system is equipped with a multiwire proportional chamber area detector capability of detecting both strong and weak diffraction features. The system software is capable of analyzing the 2-D diffraction patterns, phase identification, pattern indexing, texture mapping/pole figure analysis and strain/particle size analysis. The system is also equipped with a high temperature stage capable to allow XRD experiments to be performed at temperatures up to 900°C. The proposed instrument will impact a wide variety of research projects with a total funding level of nearly $25M and involving more than 80 faculty members and 250 stu-dents/postdocs. Some examples of projects impacted by the new instrument include the development of micro/nano-electromechanical system (MEMS/NEMS) devices for applica-tions such as energy harvesting and memory devices. The project will also impact activities related to the development of sensors for improving public safety in both the food and transportation industries as well as clean energy conversion technology, including the development of coating materials for extending the life of solid oxide fuel cells (SOFC) and improved catalysts for proton exchange membrane (PEM) fuel cells. In addition, x-ray diffraction is part of the laboratory training at the undergraduate and graduate levels, so the instrument will also enhance the educational programs at Auburn and Tuskegee Universities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Layman Summary: The research activities at Auburn University and Tuskegee University have shifted toward nano-/micro-structured materials and devices, which requires an instrument capable of characterizing the local structure, orientation and residual stress in thin films and textured materials. The objective of this proposal is to acquire a state-of-the-art X-ray diffracto-meter to fulfill the diverse and urgent needs of researchers at both institutions. The proposed instrument will impact a wide variety of research projects with a total funding level of nearly $25M and involving more than 80 faculty members and 250 students/postdocs. Some examples of projects impacted by the new instrument include the development of micro/nano-electromechanical system (MEMS/NEMS) devices for applications such as energy harvesting and memory devices. The project will also impact activities related to the development of sensors for improving public safety in both the food (Auburn University Detection and Food Safety Center) and transportation (FAA Center of Excellence in Cabin Environment Research) industries. The instrument will support clean energy conversion technology, including the development of coating materials for extending the life of solid oxide fuel cells (SOFC) and improved catalysts for proton exchange membrane (PEM) fuel cells. In addition, x-ray diffraction is part of the laboratory training at the undergraduate and graduate levels, so the instrument will also enhance the educational programs at Auburn and Tuskegee Universities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0923335</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>German</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mills</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>millsge@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Auad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>auad@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fergus</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwfergus@eng.auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shaik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jeelani</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jeelanis@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>ZhongYang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chengzh@eng.auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Auburn University</Name>
      <CityName>Auburn University</CityName>
      <ZipCode>368490001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 Samford Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
