<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a Computational Mathematics Cluster</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>91065</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dean M. Evasius</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funds for the purchase of a 128-core Computational Mathematics Cluster, to support computationally demanding research and educational projects in mathematics at San Diego State University. The proposed research encompasses projects in the following areas. (1) Modeling coupled nonlinear navigational devices. This NSF-funded project focuses on the theoretical and physical development of a new generation of navigational sensors based on a combination of global positioning technology and coupled gyroscopes and accelerometers. The resulting system offers superior sensitivity and resistance to interference. (2) Reaction-diffusion equations on fluxional grids. The nonlinear dynamics of flame pattern formation will be extended to model the effects of temperature and mechanical perturbations, applying new methods in bifurcation theory. (3) Simulation of high-speed combustion engines. An increasingly popular engine design, employing a fine mist of liquid fuel droplets in a carrier gas, will be modeled by particle-source-in-cell methods on unstructured grids. (4) Coastal current simulations. Simulations employing curvilinear coordinates will be carried out in order to forecast ocean currents in Monterey Bay and other coastal waters. The model will ultimately include geologic, chemical, and biological influences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The cluster will support graduate and undergraduate student research projects, including projects that have led directly to student fellowships and subsequent employment. Roughly 20% of the computing capacity of the requested cluster will be dedicated yearround to undergraduate projects, including (1) senior thesis research projects in applied mathematics and statistics; (2) in-class and homework projects for new courses in mathematical modeling, simulations, and biomathematics; (3) undergraduate research carried out under an existing, externally funded fellowship program. SDSU occupies a strong position for making these opportunities available to minorities underrepresented in mathematical research, as one of the top ten campuses in the nation granting bachelor?s degrees to ethnic minorities, and with 14 distinct programs to promote the participation of underrepresented groups in the sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0923278</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Castillo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jcastillo@sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Palacios</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>palacios@euler.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blomgren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>blomgren@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gustaaf</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gjacobs@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Diego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
