<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Tapping Finger Identification for Efficient Mobile Input</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>750000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glenn H. Larsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project aims to further develop the Tapping Finger Identification (TFI) technology investigated in Phase I. As mobile devices become more powerful and ubiquitous, text entry remains a major bottleneck to the wider adoption of mobile computing. To address this urgent need in lack of an acceptable solution, this TFI technology enables high-speed input in mobile devices and gaming applications using conventional typing techniques and keyboard layouts. In addition to demonstrating the feasibility of TFI during Phase I, the project will develop an IP strategy and a set of tools essential to future research and development. To date, one prototype has been implemented and a license agreement to commercialize some portion of the TFI technology was reached with an external partner. Completion of the Phase II research in two years will pave the way for commercialization of this innovative technology as we transition toward mobile computing. The technology developed could potentially impact a broad range of application areas, including mobile computing, gaming, military, and mobile security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mobile devices are becoming more powerful and ubiquitous. According to the IDC, convergent mobile devices grew 51% in 2007, and will grow from 124 million to 376 million in 2012. Data entry, however, remains a major bottleneck to the wider adoption of mobile computing. Most users are frustrated with existing input methods on portable devices, such as phones and mobile PCs. Much less a paragraph of text, simply entering a website's URL in a phone or mobile PC would be a burden for many. To address this urgent need in lack of an acceptable solution, the outcomes of this project projects the enablement of high speed, efficient mobile input using conventional typing techniques and keyboard layouts.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>500000</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0924574</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dongge</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>derek.li@zienon.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/11/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Zienon, LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606144511</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8476974310</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2148 N Lincoln Ave. A2</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
