<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Suction Feeding Evolution: Functional Morphology, Biomechanics and Performance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>813811</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Ellis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Suction feeding is believed to be the ancestral method of prey capture in bony fishes and is used by the majority of aquatic feeding vertebrate animals, including most bony fish and many aquatic amphibians, turtles and mammals. Although suction feeding is a very evolutionarily conserved mechanism, it supports unparalleled diversity in feeding habits because of its effectiveness and versatility for prey capture. This research is aimed at identifying major innovations in the mechanical design of suction feeding systems in animals and how this system has been modified during evolution to produce the extensive diversity that suction feeders represent. This will be accomplished by focusing on the fluid mechanics of two major mechanisms whereby some suction feeders amplify the hydrodynamic forces they exert on prey items, and by using data from high-speed video recordings and water-flow visualization techniques as the basis for studies of evolutionary patterns in feeding behavior across seven major fish radiations. This research will measure the impact of several mechanisms in shaping the diversification of this complex mechanical system. The results will lead to a deeper understanding of how breakthroughs in function impact subsequent diversification and how constraints such as trade-offs and modularity of design can both limit and facilitate evolution. It is hoped that general design mechanisms will be identified whereby evolution has been able to overcome fundamental mechanical trade-offs and these may have applicability in human-designed mechanisms. This project will also focus on the recruitment and training of young scientists, including a postdoctoral researcher, a doctoral graduate student and four undergraduate students per year. Outreach activities will include the development of a Youtube channel where the public can view suction feeding videos, a research blog aimed at undergraduate students, and participation in television documentaries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0924489</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wainwright</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pcwainwright@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
