<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Urbanization and Parental Investment among Fijians</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>219971</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Dawn Brown Neill (California Polytechnic State University) will undertake research on how urban ecology effects changes in children's diet, education, and activity levels, through a focus on parental investment in urbanizing ecologies. High levels of internal migration to urban centers are occurring throughout the developing world. Urban expansion introduces novel ecological conditions that produce shifts in diet, education options, and work and fertility patterns. Research has demonstrated a strong link between urbanization and increasing overweight in children and adults. Similarly, demographic transition theory has linked modernization to decreases in offspring quantity. By focusing on parental behavior, this research will contribute to understanding how demographic transition, nutrition transitions, and urbanization are interconnected. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researcher will test the proposition that ecological conditions associated with urbanization will stimulate different patterns of nutritional and educational investment in children, given individual-level costs and benefits. She will carry out the resarch as a cross-sectional study in village, peri-urban, and urban areas of Fiji. The environmental variables will be elements of urbanization and the responsive behavioral traits will be parental investment outcomes that impact the quality and quantity of offspring, given the socio-cultural context of Fijian urban and village life. The researcher will examine parental investment decision-making by collecting cross-sectional quantitative data on diet, anthropometrics, family size, land use, remittances, education, and work activity measures of children and adults. These data will be complemented with qualitative interview data on migration, identity, and kinship and family practices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is important because its findings can inform public health and policy programs on intra-household dynamics involved in the linkages between nutrition, education, and reproductive decisions, on the one hand, and and child welfare, on the other. It also will help to develop more ecologically sensitive theory for understanding parental decision-making. Results of this study will shed light on the dynamics of internal migration and urbanization and the related consequences to population health and rural development policy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0924649</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbneill@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/13/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Polytechnic State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Luis Obispo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>934070830</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8057562982</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Grand Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
