<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase II: Abrasion Resistant Ultrahydrophobic Coatings for Corrosion, Erosion and Wear Resistance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>455854</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase II project aims to further the development of abrasion resistant, environmentally friendly, ultrahydrophobic coating formulations. The ultrahydrophobic property is created by optimizing the coating matrices to generate a so-called "lotus leaf" structure that robustly repels water, preventing water penetration and accumulation. In addition to super water repellent activity, the self-cleaning coatings have a superior corrosion protection function. These properties reduce failure rates, increase life time, and effectively lower maintenance and replacement costs of the coated material. A major objective of the project is to refine the formulations to improve the performance properties. This ultrahydrophobic coating will be optimized for application on specific commercially important substrates such as plastic, concrete, asphalt, wood, glass, fabrics, and metal. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of multi-functional coatings will be to provide improved, abrasion resistant ultrahydrophobic coatings for commercial applications in a variety of different areas such as shipping, automotive, building and aviation industries. These multi-functional coatings are environmentally compatible and will have a significant societal and environmental impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)."</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>455854</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0924684</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schultz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david@seashelltech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuliang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yuliang@seashelltech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/08/2009</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chisholm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bret.chisholm@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Seashell Technology</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920371807</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8586380315</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3252 Holiday Court #115</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
