<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dual-Layer Cooperative Error Control for Reliable Nanoscale On-Chip Interconnection Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>290095</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to investigate energy-efficient cooperative dual-layer (data link and network layers) error control methods for nanoscale networks-on-chip. The approach is to combine hop-to-hop error detection at the data link layer with adaptive routing and end-to-end forward error correction at the network layer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to intellectual merit, this research addresses the problem that, with aggressive technology scaling, interconnects become increasingly susceptible to noise and they emerge as the critical bottleneck in meeting reliability and energy constraints in nanoscale systems-on-chip. Research in reliable interconnects has typically investigated solutions at a single layer, e.g. physical or electrical. This research considers the hardware efficiency of switch-level error detection combined with the reliability performance of network-layer forward error correction, with the goal of simultaneously improving reliability and energy use. In particular, this research seeks to: (i) create new efficient codes for error detection and correction across layers in a network-on-chip; (ii) devise innovative methods, using configurable spare wires and adaptive routing, to manage intermittent and permanent errors; and (iii) examine and develop methods to mitigate the impact of faults in the encoder/decoder circuits themselves.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to broader impact, this research has the potential to create a new reliable interconnect design approach that can accelerate advances in scalable multi-core systems-on-chip. This breakthrough could have significant societal and economic impact with the realization of reliable energy-efficient integrated systems for numerous applications, ranging from infrastructure monitoring to health care. Knowledge generated is disseminated through workshops, lectures and a public website. This research actively engages underrepresented minority and female students and extends outreach through international collaborations to broaden the global perspectives of U.S. students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0925993</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ampadu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ampadu@ece.rochester.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Rochester</Name>
      <CityName>Rochester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>518 HYLAN, RC BOX 270140</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7423</Code>
      <Text>Energy collection &amp; storage</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
