<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Single molecule light emitting device</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>john zavada</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: Organic optoelectronics is a rapidly advancing field, but most studies to date are focused on measurements of thin films involving a large ensemble of molecules. The present project aims at studying how the optoelectronic properties of these systems change when the device is decreased to nano- and molecular-scales, and exploring single molecule light emitting&lt;br/&gt;device and optical sensing applications. Such studies will lead to new insights into charge transport mechanisms, carrier energy dissipation processes and electrode-molecule contact effects in molecular-scale junctions, determine the interplay between the charge transport and optical properties, and provide the basic knowledge and necessary skills to develop novel device&lt;br/&gt;applications.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The project will also have an important impact on a variety of other fields, including biophotonics and photosynthesis, as well as thin film-based optoelectronic devices, such as organic photovoltaics and organic light emitting diodes. In addition, it will expose engineering undergraduates to research opportunities in emerging fields. To this end the PIs will work together with the outreach program at Fulton School of Engineering and Biodesign Institute to recruit minority students. The proposed research and training activities will also help graduate students develop important teaching, management and communication skills. As part of the outreach plan, international collaborations with research groups in Germany and Japan will be&lt;br/&gt;developed to provide students with international experience. The interdisciplinary research has potential transformational impacts on the next-generation of scientists and engineers, and on the next-generation organic optoelectronics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0925498</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hihath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>josh.hihath@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nongjian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nongjian.tao@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>100E</Code>
      <Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>101E</Code>
      <Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>103E</Code>
      <Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
