<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BRIGE: An Exploration Into Concrete Surface Preparation Using Dry Ice Bombardment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>188865</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this BRIGE award is to investigate the viability of bombarding concrete with dry ice as a means of preparing the substrate to receive coatings and composite overlay. The specific goals are to (a) examine the effectiveness of removing corrosion byproduct from substrate, (b) identify whether dry ice bombardment induces damage within the substrate, and (c) explain how the fresh and hardened properties of concrete contribute to these behaviors. Diversity, education, family, and science will be united by creating parent-student teams to carry out a portion of the research activities. Close involvement of faculty, parents, and students in research will allow families from underrepresented groups to embrace the technology being investigated. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will explain the fundamental relationships between basic substrate properties and their influence on cleaning efficacy and potential to cause substrate damage from dry ice bombardment. Significant achievement also prevails by adapting well-established, scientific protocol to investigate this unusual, yet unexplored blasting technique. Among such protocol include non-destructive inspection (NDI) using ultrasonic resonance, and Laser Scanning Confocal Microscopy (LSCM). From an environmental perspective, dry ice blasting could reduce the time and cost of surface preparation as well as lessen the negative impact on the surrounding environment and personnel carrying out the construction. Moreover, the dry ice supply is derived from reclamation of CO2 gas byproduct from existing manufacturing processes, thus, contributing to its sustainability. Potential energy-related implications could lead to an important research thrust in academia and industry in the future. Furthermore, the results generated from this research could be applied to other topical areas and material systems such as corrosion and lead-based paint removal from steel bridges, mold remediation in urban housing, and biofilm removal from timber piles or bridge piers located in thriving, yet delicate, marine ecosystems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0926794</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Giancaspro</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwgiancaspro@miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami</Name>
      <CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7741</Code>
      <Text>BROAD PARTIC IN ENG (BRIGE)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>080E</Code>
      <Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>NONE</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE FOR SBS COMP (NSF-99-32)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>025E</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
