<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Regulating Current Through a Nanoparticle Necklace by Microorganism: A Transformative Technology for Biofuel Cells and Biosensors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>391056</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Charging a nanoparticle by a single electron can significantly modulate the passage of current through the particle. The goal of the study is to leverage this single electron phenomena to design and study an electronic hybrid bio-nano device where the biochemical process in a living microorganism charges (or discharges) the nanoparticle(s) to turn the current ON/OFF through the particle(s), i.e., bio-gating. The bio-nano device will be a two dimensional network of 10 nm size Gold particles that behaves as a single-electron-device interfaced with microorganisms. The bio-gating will be accomplished by modulating the current through the network of necklace by stimulating the microorganism with nutrient. To impact practical applications and manufacturability, issues on integration with conventional microelectronic circuitry will be addressed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed bio-nano device integrated to electronic circuit will represent a paradigm of hybrid bio-nano devices with a broad range of applications, such as a highly specific sensor where the cell detects the moiety and has the sensitivity to flip the ON/OFF switch of the nanodevice to produce a digital signal; or the hybrid bio-nano device could function as an energy conversion system to produce electricity as the cell is exposed to nutrients. The project will train a graduate student in the area of sensors, nanotechnology and biophysics. Demonstration of the device will be part of an out reach program called ?Bright Lights? and ?Big Red Summer Camp? administered by Lincoln Public School and University of Nebraska ? Lincoln to introduce middle and high school students to science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>391056</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0926381</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ravi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Saraf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rsaraf@unlnotes.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1788</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>084E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
