<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Performance-Based Design Guidelines for Integrating Phase Change Materials in Buildings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249986</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>lawrence bank</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Phase change materials have the ability to store excess heat in buildings and release it at a later time, thereby reducing temperature fluctuations as well as heating and cooling loads. However, their integration in a given building requires generally an extensive engineering study with its associated added expense. The primary long-term objective of this project is to develop a design methodology based on a complete understanding of the impacts, benefits and limitations of phase change materials when integrated in building construction materials. The approach will combine numerical modeling and experimental testing to perform extensive parametric studies from which design guidelines will be drawn. The research will be conducted through a true interdisciplinary approach by a team of students and faculty from Architecture and Materials Science and Engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through the study of phase change materials integrated in construction materials and assemblies, the proposed work addresses many aspects targeting different audiences. Therefore, this project has the potential to reach out to a very large group of academicians and professionals and will have significant influence in encouraging designers to consider phase change materials as a means to reduce energy consumption in buildings. The proposed work will provide opportunities to train students who can enter the workforce with both numerical and experimental skills enhanced by the interdisciplinary approach. The design rules and guidelines will provide a low cost alternative and not only facilitate the building design process but, more importantly, will enable and ultimately democratize the use of phase change materials in building design.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0927962</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vincent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blouin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vblouin@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clemson University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1635</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>067E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>068E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1037</Code>
      <Text>DETERIORATION SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9148</Code>
      <Text>TOOLS &amp; TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
