<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Using Numerical Models of Poroelastic Fluid Flow to Constrain the Permeability Structure of Young Oceanic Crust</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>152909</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bilal U. Haq</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>New seafloor is created at a global network of mid-ocean ridges, where seawater circulating through the newly-formed crust causes hydrothermal alteration. Most of the world?s copper deposits formed in this way; indeed copper mined from hydrothermal deposits on the island of Cyprus fueled the advancement of western civilization. Hence, understanding hydrothermal circulation at mid-ocean ridges has fundamental scientific importance. Fluid flow is controlled principally by permeability, a property that is difficult to measure. However, it has been observed that, because they affect fluid pressures in the sea floor, tides trigger small earthquakes. It can be reasonably argued that the relationship between tides and the occurrence of these earthquakes depends on the permeability. This project is an innovative attempt to infer the permeability of new seafloor from tides and earthquake data from the East Pacific Rise. Funding this effort will improve our understanding of the working of the Earth, and support a promising young investigator.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0928181</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crone@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
