<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Micro-Optics Based 3D Microfabrication System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>267999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhijian Pei</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to establish an innovative and affordable process for creating complicated three dimensional microstructures on nonplanar substrates using an optical projection system based on nonconventional micro-optical structures. These micro-optics are precisely fabricated on an arbitrary surface that can be used to project micro and meso scale structures on a pre-defined nonplanar substrate where a layer of photoresist is spin coated. After proper exposure and development, the desired micro or meso pattern will be created on the photoresist layer. The research plan includes two fundamental components: (1) three-dimensional micro-optics fabrication by use of a slow tool servo ultraprecision machining process, (2) design and analysis of a three-dimensional projection lithography system for micro and meso scale structures on nonplanar substrates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will result in a high volume and low cost manufacturing process for true three-dimensional micro and meso scale structures. This process complements conventional photolithography in many applications and the results of the research can be easily converted to producing optical components with micro and meso size features for optoelectronic applications. The major benefits of this research to society will be demonstrated by its impact on several other areas in optical manufacturing, including waveguides, micro and diffractive optics for telecommunication, laser and solar concentrator applications. The results from this research will potentially provide an alternative process for fabricating components with three-dimensional micro size channels, pumps and reservoirs for biomedical and medical applications as well as many other additional consumer products.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0928521</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Allen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yi.71@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6142923732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
