<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Large-Scale Fabrication of Thin Polymer Nanocomposite Films</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>189001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Collaborative Research: Large-Scale Fabrication of Thin Polymer Nanocomposite Films&lt;br/&gt;PI: Howard Wang (SUNY Binghamton) and Cheol Park (NIA)&lt;br/&gt;Abstract &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to investigate fundamental materials processing issues associated with the large-scale fabrication of functional polymer nanocomposite films (PNFs) on flexible plastic substrates. Particularly, slot die coating (SDC) methods will be explored since SDC is one of a few industrial processes for precisely coating high quality films from liquid suspensions, and is compatible with roll-to-roll (R2R) manufacturing. More specifically, the research will investigate the challenges and possible solutions in coating PNFs using two representative materials systems: (1) polyimide containing single walled carbon nanotubes, (2) Pd-nanoparticle/polycarbonate composites. This large-scale SDC for these new functional nanomaterials has never been attempted and innovative external field (electrical or magnetic) induced morphology alteration is also proposed. With better understanding the dispersion and metastability in nanocolloid/polymer solutions and films, technologically meaningful methods to control equilibrium, metastable and non-equilibrium structures that lead to optimum device performance will be investigated. Furthermore, the degradation of the PNFs and the release of nanomaterials into the environment will be investigated by controlled UV radiation and through various materials characterization techniques. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this collaborative project will have a profound impact on broader materials challenges in the emerging industry of nanotechnology and flexible electronics. Particularly, (1) critical scientific and technological issues in large-scale fabrication of PNFs, such as the structure and dynamics of complex fluids and their responses to flow and force fields, will be addressed; (2) new understanding and better control of non-equilibrium and metastable structures arising due to the competing thermodynamic/dynamic driving forces in complex fluids and PNFs will be obtained; (3) a processing/morphology/property/performance database will be constructed as a part of materials informatics effort that will enable the development of constitutive equations and computational fluid dynamics models; and (4) the degradation and environmental impact of PNFs will be assessed. This project will engage in the BU?s NSF-funded undergraduate nanotechnology education program in ?Nanotechnology for Manufacturing Flexible Electronics?, and participate in the Go Green Institute which involves middle school students and teachers from 15 school districts in the southern tier of New York State. By introducing the basics of nanotechnology and flexible electronics to middle and high school students including minority and underrepresented ones, and providing the opportunity for them to gain hands-on experiences in real industrial settings in local electronics and materials companies, this program intends to help students of all backgrounds to capitalize on intellectual, career and commercial promises of nanotechnology and flexible electronics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0928839</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cheol</FirstName>
      <LastName>Park</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pcheol@nianet.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/13/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Institute of Aerospace Associates</Name>
      <CityName>Hampton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>236666147</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7573256711</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 Exploration Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>083E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
