<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Project: Arabidopsis 2010: Transcriptomes for Functional and Evolutionary Studies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>737804</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>kent chapman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A basic challenge in the life sciences is to understand how genetic variation among individuals (DNA sequence differences) leads to variation in traits, for example, eye color in animals or crop yield in plants. Ultimately, trait differences among individuals result from differences in the kind or amount of molecules (for example, RNA and protein molecules) produced by cells. In this project, the investigators will generate a resource to address the fundamental question of how differences in DNA sequences among individuals lead to the production of different RNA molecules, which in turn affect protein types, levels, and whole-organism traits. To do this, the investigators will exploit newly developed technologies, including so-called 'second generation' DNA sequencing methods, to characterize in a highly cost effective manner the majority of RNA molecules from 19 diverse strains of the model plant, Arabidopsis thaliana, for which sequenced genomes are available. &lt;br/&gt;A general outcome will be an understanding of how genetic variation affects RNA levels, and hence how DNA differences lead to trait differences. Specifically, the resource will allow investigators from around the United States and the world to understand the regulation of genes relevant to a multitude of traits of critical importance for agriculture in the coming century. The resource of sequence data that will be generated by the project will be released publically via the deposition in the DNA sequence database of the USA National Center for Biotechnology. Internet links to these data, and a description of the project, will be available on website of the lead project investigator within the public University of Utah website. Hands-on training will be provided to each of the undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral researchers involved in the project. The project will expose trainees to advanced biological technologies and analysis methods of ever increasing importance in biology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0929262</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Toomajian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>toomajia@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clark@biology.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
