<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>HBCU-RISE: Modeling and Design of Robust and Scalable Network Architecture for QoS Assured Multi-Service Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>992706</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor A. Santiago</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The HBCU-RISE proposal by PVAMU has an underlying theme to improve the efficiency of secure multiservice and multi-rate communications in wireless networks through careful consideration of cross-layer design principles and end-to-end network optimization. This has brought together faculty from two minority (HBCU) institutions (PVAMU and Tuskegee University) with expertise in communications theory, wireless networking, signal processing, and control theory to apply their joint expertise to solve the proposed research problems in wireless ad-hoc networks. It is anticipated that the outcomes of this research will fill some important gaps in the current understanding of the fundamental limits and design trade-offs in MANET and sensor networks, enabling this growing field to fully realize its potential.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given that the next-generation military and commercial wireless communication systems need to support a multitude of services with a wide range of data rates, reliability, latency, and security requirements, we believe that successful implementation of the research project will have a wide ranging impact in the design of future wireless networks. The proposed project will also provide educational training to students and professionals through research and hands-on experience. It will support enhancement and increase the production of graduate (MS and Ph.D)theses/dissertations and undergraduate senior design projects in electrical and computer engineering at PVAMU. The proposed collaborative research with Tuskegee University will strengthen the existing collaborations among faculty and students at these two HBCUs and will further improve the knowledge base of women and minority students at the undergraduate, master?s and doctoral levels of engineering education so that they can compete in the job market in industry, academia and government.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0931679</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Siew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Koay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>s_koay@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Warsame</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ali</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whali@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dhadesugoor</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vaman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>drvaman@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Annamalai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Annamalai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aaannamalai@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9131</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
