<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CPS: Medium: A Logical Framework for Self-Optimizing Networked Cyber-Physical Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1494776</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Logical Framework for Self-Optimizing Networked Cyber-Physical Systems&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to develop foundations for the newly emerging&lt;br/&gt;generation of networked cyber-physical systems. The approach is based on a&lt;br/&gt;distributed logic of cyber-physical systems together with distributed&lt;br/&gt;cross-layer control and optimization strategies to enabled local actions to&lt;br/&gt;maintain or improve the satisfaction of system goals. The framework will be&lt;br/&gt;implemented first in simulation, then on one of SRI's robot platforms, and&lt;br/&gt;demonstrated in the context of networked mobile robotic teams, a particularly&lt;br/&gt;challenging application.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Networked cyber-physical systems present many intellectual challenges&lt;br/&gt;not suitably addressed by existing computing paradigms. They must&lt;br/&gt;achieve system-wide objectives through local, asynchronous actions,&lt;br/&gt;using distributed control loops through the environment. A key&lt;br/&gt;challenge is to develop a robust computational foundation that&lt;br/&gt;supports a wide spectrum of system operation between autonomy and&lt;br/&gt;cooperation to adapt to uncertainties, changes, failures, and resource &lt;br/&gt;constraints, in particular to limitations of computational, energy, &lt;br/&gt;and networking resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results will have a variety of applications including distributed&lt;br/&gt;surveillance, instrumented pervasive spaces, crisis response, medical&lt;br/&gt;systems, green buildings, self-assembling structures, networked&lt;br/&gt;space/satellite missions, and distributed critical infrastructure&lt;br/&gt;monitoring and control. There is also potential for integration&lt;br/&gt;into SRI's commercial robotic platform. Results will be publicly&lt;br/&gt;available from a project web site, and tutorial material will be&lt;br/&gt;developed for students and researchers. A multi-disciplinary research&lt;br/&gt;seminar will be sponsored by SRI. The coPI is female with a strong&lt;br/&gt;record of mentoring female students and young researchers, including&lt;br/&gt;the project's female postdoc.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0932397</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Talcott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clt@cs.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark-Oliver</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stehr</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mark-oliver.stehr@sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SRI International</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508592651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
