<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Jasper Ridge: Facilities for Understanding Wildland/Suburban Boundaries</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249582</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter H. McCartney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Stanford University is awarded a grant to upgrade environmental monitoring capabilities at its Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve (JRBP). This proposal requests funds for infrastructure to implement a revised mission for the preserve, to better understand and manage the urban/wildland interface, especially it biological diversity. The requested funds will: a) expand broadband network infrastructure to extend connectivity to at least 80% of JRBP lands, b) install an array of soil moisture sensors in grassland habitats for monitoring habitat conditions known to affect native biodiversity, c) install and test fire detection units near the boundaries of the preserve, along with cameras to monitor mammals at the perimeter and interior of the preserve, and d) document the condition of various habitats in an efficient, low-impact, standardized way using close-range remote sensing. These technologies will help JRBP monitor the urban/wildland interface, engage surrounding landowners in preserving local biodiversity, and help offset external impacts with internal policies. It will allow JRBP to conduct more vegetation management and restoration activities in a research context, while still protecting both longterm and new research that is strictly observational. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve is a 482 ha protected natural area contiguous with and owned by Stanford University. The preserve is distinguished by a combination of four features - a history of fundamental and influential discoveries, a balanced emphasis on research, education, and conservation, a high biotic diversity relative to its size, and a location on the campus of a major university near a metropolitan area. JRBP is used as a research site by faculty and students from Stanford as well as many other universities. In recent years, the site has hosted 55 to 68 research projects at any time. The site is used by many college classes, with 1200 to 2600 Stanford student visits per year, plus approximately 500 by students at other colleges. JRBP is also active in K-12 education, regional land management coordination, and public education. The equipment to be installed with funds from this award will support Stanford and non-Stanford research, class experiences, interactions with land managers, K-12 education, and outreach to the general public. Further information about Jasper Ridge may be found at http://jrbp.stanford.edu/.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0934210</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Field</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cfield@dge.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
