<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Relative hyperbolicity and asymptotic invariants of groups</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10350</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is devoted to the study of relatively hyperbolic&lt;br/&gt;groups and their applications in low--dimensional&lt;br/&gt;topology. It consists of three main parts. First part deals with&lt;br/&gt;small cancellation theory over relatively hyperbolic groups.&lt;br/&gt;Namely we intend to use methods elaborated by the PI to construct&lt;br/&gt;new groups with 'exotic' properties that solve some long--standing&lt;br/&gt;problems in the classical theory of groups. The second part is&lt;br/&gt;motivated by the Virtual Haken Conjecture and is based on a&lt;br/&gt;generalization of Thurston's hyperbolic Dehn surgery theory in the&lt;br/&gt;context of relatively hyperbolic groups. The third part concerns&lt;br/&gt;new results about group embeddings. The ultimate goal here is to&lt;br/&gt;obtain a relatively hyperbolic version of the Higman embedding&lt;br/&gt;theorem. Our approach to these problems is based on a new methods&lt;br/&gt;related to asymptotic and combinatorial analysis of van Kampen&lt;br/&gt;diagrams.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The notion of a relatively hyperbolic group was first proposed by&lt;br/&gt;Gromov in 1987 to generalize many examples of algebraic and&lt;br/&gt;geometric nature. Since then the theory has been elaborated from&lt;br/&gt;different points of views and now it is one of the most prominent&lt;br/&gt;parts of the group theory. The class of relatively hyperbolic&lt;br/&gt;groups encompasses many examples of interest such as fundamental&lt;br/&gt;groups of finite volume hyperbolic manifolds, geometrically finite&lt;br/&gt;convergence groups, mapping class groups, fully residually free&lt;br/&gt;groups, etc. Rather than just generalizing the theory of&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic groups to the relative case, this project is aimed at&lt;br/&gt;the study of new and sometimes unexpected phenomena which are&lt;br/&gt;invisible in the context of ordinary hyperbolicity. The close&lt;br/&gt;interaction between the theory of relatively hyperbolic groups and&lt;br/&gt;geometry, low-dimensional topology, the theory of dynamical&lt;br/&gt;systems, provides a rich source of problems and motivations for&lt;br/&gt;our project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0934107</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Denis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Osin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>denis.osin@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/02/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
      <CityName>Nashville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
