<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fourth Biennial Symposium on "Current and Future Challenges in Mechanics and Materials", to be held at Univ. of Colorado, Boulder, August 3-6,2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glaucio H. Paulino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The fourth biennial symposium on Current and Future Challenges in Mechanics and Materials at the University of Colorado at Boulder, in August 2009. Researchers from the US and abroad will participate, representing the scientific forefront in areas of mechanics/materials including theory, experiment, and simulation. The four-day symposium will focus on intersections of Mechanics and Materials with contemporary issues in a) Biotechnology/biomedical, b) Nanotechnology, and c) Energy. The symposium will involve 50 minute presentations, followed by extensive discussion of modern issues and emerging challenges in research as well as in graduate education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium will provide an excellent environment for the thoughtful exchange of ideas and open discussions that allow for the presentation of the state-of-the-art in various areas of mechanics and materials. Additionally, it will permit in-depth discussion of current and future challenges that will help advance research and graduate education frontiers in the field, with a view toward identifying activities that can maximize societal impact. The symposium will serve as an opportunity to showcase research performed at universities and national laboratories in the Rocky Mountain region and will permit valuable interactions among regional students and leading researchers in the field. The interactions among researchers and students at the symposium are expected to lead to future collaborations in mechanics and materials research and education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0935238</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Martin.Dunn@Colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1630</Code>
      <Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7479</Code>
      <Text>Biomechanics &amp; Mechanobiology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>022E</Code>
      <Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
