<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>GSE/RES: Gender Differences in the Foundations of Sense of Belonging: Effects on Achievement, Aspirations, and Learning in STEM Disciplines</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jolene K. Jesse</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: This research focuses on two key social factors that are important predictors of women's math performance: negative stereotypes about women's math abilities and perspectives on the nature of math ability as being either a fixed trait or a developable skill. The researchers are particularly interested in how a sense of belonging (SOB)--feeling like an accepted member of an academic community whose contributions are valued--can buffer women against the negative impacts of negative stereotypes or fixed concepts of math ability. The PIs will conduct a series of four studies designed to test hypotheses about how SOB emerges from various sources: a) experiencing high achievement; b) having friends in the domain; or c) exerting high effort. The PIs predict that effort-based sense of belonging will mitigate gender differences in math achievement, aspirations and learning, particularly those due to stereotype threat and fixed-ability learning environments. Hypotheses will be tested by experimentally manipulating both SOB and either stereotype threat or theories of intelligence and data will be analyzed through ANOVAs on math achievement, math aspirations, course-taking behaviors, and math learning. The study will involve both college freshmen and middle school students as they transition to high school. Research sites include Baruch College and middle schools in Montclair, NJ.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The proposed research addresses two key moments in students' educational lives--transitions to high school and college. Educational experiences at these points lay the foundation for future interest in STEM domains, and thus influence decisions about future career paths. If findings support the notion that effort-based sense of belonging decreases the effects of stereotype threat and messages of fixed ability for females, then fostering effort-based sense of belonging may address pipeline issues for women in STEM fields and redress the persistent gender gaps in these domains. Specifically, educators who emphasize effort (rather than high achievement) as a key determination in students' belongingness in STEM may help eliminate the culture of "talent" and the mentality of the "weed-out system" that pervades many STEM classrooms and that can undermine women's STEM outcomes. Specifically, environments that foster a culture in which anyone who develops their skills through effort and engagement is considered a member of the community may encourage many more females to pursue STEM degrees. In addition, the methods of increasing SOB are easily implemented in any classroom setting. Although this study focuses specifically on sex differences in math outcomes, the findings may apply to any STEM discipline and to members of any group who face negative stereotypes and messages of limited ability, such as Black and Latino Americans.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0936769</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Good</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Catherine.Good@baruch.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mangels</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jennifer.Mangels@baruch.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Baruch College</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100105526</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6463122205</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Bernard Baruch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1544</Code>
      <Text>RES ON GENDER IN SCI &amp; ENGINE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
