<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Changes in Surface and Ground Water in the Tarim River Basin, Urumqi, Xinjiang</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>87655</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Clive Woods</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Dr. Vladimr Aizen of the University of Idaho and Dr. Ding Yongjian of the Lanzhou Cold and Arid Regions Environmental Engineering Research Institute proposed a U.S.-China Workshop on changes in surface and ground water in the Tarim River Basin. This workshop will be held in September, 2009 in Urumqi, Xinjiang Province, China. The topic for this workshop is important for NSF and the conference will include 10 U.S. scientists at an early stage in their careers. This is an extreme climate sensitive area of the globe and is the world?s largest and most densely populated arid-region, closed-drainage, basin. This workshop is opportune and can lead to the cooperation in addressing some of the pressing water use issues in this basin. The goal of this workshop is to produce an integrated research agenda targeted on science that will support the efforts of the participating countries to address the important water resources management issues of this region. This workshop will be supported jointly by the National Natural Science Foundation of China and the U.S. National Science Foundation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0936264</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aizen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aizen@uidaho.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aizen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eaizen@uidaho.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/15/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Idaho</Name>
      <CityName>MOSCOW</CityName>
      <ZipCode>838443020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2088856651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Idaho</StateName>
      <StateCode>ID</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
