<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: New Technologies for Probing the Diversity of Brown Dwarfs and Exoplanets; Shanghai, China; July 20-24, 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jeffrey R. Pier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Conference support for the meeting "New Technologies for Probing the Diversity of Brown Dwarfs and Exoplanets" to be held in Shanghai, China July 20-24, 2009.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most exciting fields of astronomical research in recent years has involved the discovery and study of "exoplanets" orbiting stars other than our sun. A wealth of information has been gathered on these objects which range in size from planets to larger objects called "brown dwarfs" - stars that are not quite big enough to shine as more massive stars do. An international conference to share information about these objects will be held in Shanghai, China from July 20 - 24, 2009. The conference theme is "New Technologies for Probing the Diversity of Brown Dwarfs and Exoplanets." Dr. Ge is well known for his research in the field and for the instruments he builds to discover and study these objects. He and three other American scientists are among the conference organizers. The NSF will provide funding so that travel grants can be offered to graduate students, postdoctoral associates, and invited speakers from U.S. institutions to enable them to attend the meeting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0937427</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ge</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jge@astro.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
