<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Computer Supported Cooperative Work Doctoral Research Colloquium 2010</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25018</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Crowston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports a Doctoral Colloquium (DC) at the 2010 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW) to be held February 6-10, 2010 in Savannah, GA. The CSCW conference brings together researchers from the fields of organizational behavior, information systems, social informatics, information sciences, and human-computer interaction (HCI). As such the conference is a critical link between the research communities supported by IIS and the broader social, behavioral, and management sciences. The primary intellectual contributions of this project lies in bringing together a diverse set of advanced PhD students from across the range of research represented in CSCW. This workshop enables both close mentoring and the development of a group of future intellectual leaders within the CSCW community. Furthermore, bringing together these students in close contact with key CSCW researchers, both during the workshop itself and during conference poster presentations, will support the development of interdisciplinary dialogs, creating an environment for exchange and conversation that will further enable progress on the projects in the DC. There are short and long-term benefits from this work. In the short term, we will provide significant feedback to the specific students participating in the DC and more general feedback that can spread amongst other student attendees of the conference. In the long-term, we expect that students who have participated in the DC will then give back to the community by engaging as mentors to undergraduate students, and in the future to doctoral students. Furthermore, we expect these exceptional students to be the future leaders of the CSCW community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0940080</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gillian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hayes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gillianrh@ics.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7367</Code>
      <Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
