<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CCLI: Bringing a Field Station into the Classroom</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>249271</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katherine J. Denniston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Biological Sciences (61). Through development of web-based resources that facilitate access to its large number of databases, the Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory (RMBL) is in essence bringing a field station into classrooms across the United States. Founded in 1928, the RMBL is a non-profit research institution that promotes field research; approximately 150 students and scientists use its facilities each year, leading to over 1300 peer-reviewed publications. The ecosystem around Gothic, CO is thus one of the best understood in the world. Although thousands of students have gone through the RMBL and have had a life-changing experience, because it is in a remote location and is snowed in for much of the year, many students will never have the opportunity to work there (or any other field station). In recent years the RMBL archived and documented a large number of datasets, and actively manages and makes available through its website, research plans, research data, collections information and photos, map information, publications, and environmental data. This project is creating a bridge between these digital data resources and classrooms by generating web-based resources that facilitate access by students and educators to long-term datasets. These include natural history pages that describe different species and web-based modules that provide examples of how data can be used in the classroom. Another major goal of this project is to help students explore how the world is changing. The RMBL has one of the largest collections of long-term research programs in the world, and is establishing a network of weather stations along an elevational gradient. Consequently, students and educators using the RMBL's resources have the ability to explore how weather and climate are changing, and to relate that information to long-term biological trends. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: By providing students with tools to work in a data-rich environment, the project seeks to improve their scientific discovery skills, including their ability to frame interesting questions, work with data, and access primary literature. Additionally, because the project entails embedding of data in rich contexts, such as popular articles and biographies of the scientists, it increases the potential willingness and ability of students to engage with science beyond the classroom. Finally, this project is training the next generation of scientists by providing them the skills they need to effectively use online digital repositories. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: A collaboration with Chaffey Community College is helping to ensure that the materials being developed are effective in a 2-year college setting. Additional collaborations with existing projects (e.g., BioQUEST Curriculum Consortium) are helping to prove the developed materials through their portals. Consequently, the project is increasing the number of scientific datasets available to educators for use in the classroom. Because the materials use open source tools, the platform can be transferred into other field station contexts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being co-funded by funds from the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Emerging Frontiers Division.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0941875</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Billick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ibillick@rmbl.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
      <LastName>Floyd</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>FLOYDCH@uwec.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cosand</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Diana.Cosand@chaffey.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laurel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hartley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>laurel.hartley@ucdenver.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Donovan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sdonovan@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory</Name>
      <CityName>Crested Butte</CityName>
      <ZipCode>812240519</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9703497481</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8000 County Rd. 317</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7972</Code>
      <Text>Transforming Undergrad Bio Ed</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
