<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Request for Graduate Travel Support to Attend the Nanoelectronic Devices for Defense $ Security (NANO-DDS) Conference 2009. To be Held Sept 28-Oct. 2, 2009 in Ft. Lauderdale FL.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anupama Kaul</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this proposal is to support graduate student attendance to the Nanoelectronic Devices for Defense &amp; Security (NANO-DDS) will be held at the Bahia Mar Beach Resort in Fort Lauderdale, FL during the weeks of September 28 to October 2, 2009. The approach is to recruit students in the science and engineering areas related to nanoelectronic devices research and development with the aim that their attendance will broaden the impact of the meeting to the education experiences and education of future scientists and engineers. There will be a formal reporting procedure that includes a narrative that explains their estimation of the benefit in attending the conference that all student attendees will be required to complete. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The conference has been organized as a formal bi-annual meeting for the purpose of reviewing research and development (R&amp;D) activities in the arena of nanoelectronic devices that have direct relevance to critical capability needs for national Defense &amp; Security in the future. The charter of this special conference is to unify and focus the very broad array of nanoelectronic and supporting nanotechnology activities that are currently engaged in reaching the long expected applications payoffs in core defense and security related areas such as sensing, data processing, computation and communications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The scientific and technological information and the resulting nanoscale devices and systems Roadmap will be widely disseminated throughout academia/universities, government and industrial institutions and the public at-large (including the entire international community). The conference has made diligent effort to recruit student attendees from underrepresented groups from the nanoscience, nanomaterials, nanofabrication and nanoengineering communities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0941118</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tripp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ctripp@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maine</Name>
      <CityName>ORONO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5717 Corbett Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maine</StateName>
      <StateCode>ME</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
