<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Statistical Content Helping to Empower Mathematicians at Two-Year Colleges (SCHEMATYC)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>62120</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard A. Alo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Mathematical Sciences (21)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is using workshops and a distance-learning course to improve the statistical expertise and pedagogical knowledge of instructors of introductory statistics at 2-year colleges. The project is conducting a series of eight traveling workshops, each held in conjunction with a regional meeting of the American Mathematical Association of Two-Year Colleges (AMATYC), to disseminate best practices and statistical content knowledge to an audience of instructors who may have limited backgrounds in statistics and limited opportunities for professional development. In addition, the project is conducting a 2-day workshop in conjunction with the 2010 national AMATYC meeting, is offering a distance learning course, and is establishing online discussion groups for instructors of introductory statistics. All of these activities are aimed at 2-year college instructors and are addressing both statistical content and pedagogy following recognized national guidelines. This project is preparing faculty at 2-year colleges to effectively teach introductory statistics by providing access to exemplary resources. The workshops, distance course, and discussion groups are affecting substantial change in the way introductory statistics is taught at 2-year institutions, and are building a stronger community of introductory statistics instructors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0942456</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gould</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rgould@stat.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
