<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Template-Based Undergraduate Education in Wireless Application Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199614</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Don L. Millard</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Engineering - Electrical (55)&lt;br/&gt;This project is developing learning modules in the area of software application development for wireless mobile devices. The modules are being developed such that they can be incorporated into conventional communication systems and technology courses or offered as components of independent-study or senior design courses. The learning modules are also incorporating active and collaborative learning strategies. The specific goals of the project are (1) to develop a wireless application library for cellular phones where each application can serve as a template for students to develop their own projects, (2) to develop associated learning modules to teach students the process of developing, compiling, and embedding applications in cellular phones, and (3) to develop cellular phone applications that allow students to explore a variety of fundamental communications and signal processing principles, including convolution and the fast Fourier transform. The project is also developing a cellular phone application that enables students to use cellular phones, rather than single purpose clickers, as part of a classroom response system. The wireless application library and associated learning modules are being made available for free download from the project's website. The project includes formative and summative evaluation plans for all aspects of the project coordinated by an independent evaluator.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0942852</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Akopian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>david.akopian@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
      <CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7494</Code>
      <Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
