<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: High-Rate Low-Power Wireless Telemetry System for Medical Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project proposes to demonstrate the feasibility of an efficient high throughput video broadcast system over the Medical Implant Communication Service (MICS) band for camera pill and micro robot technologies while maintaining ultra low power consumption. Current camera pill designs have relatively low data rate and high power consumption. The proposed system is designed to significantly improve the specifications over the existing systems in use. The intellectual merit of the proposed research lies in the design of an integrated circuit for camera pill applications which combines advanced digital broadband technologies like orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM), low density parity check (LDPC) code, and diversity combining with the state of the art VLSI architecture designs. Major expected advantages of this technology include: ultra high throughput, super low power and compact transmitter, low cost transmitter, long distance spec, real-time transmission, accurate synchronization algorithms, frequency bandwidth efficiency, and interference avoidance. Furthermore, if this high throughput system is used with other low rate devices, the remaining throughput can be turned into additional power saving automatically.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project lies in its potential of spawning new less invasive vision sensor based diagnosis and treatments which lead to smaller scar, less risk, less pain, less discomfort, less anesthesia need, and less recovery time for patients. Because of the challenging specs, the project also has significant impact on VLSI design and wireless communication technology. The low power and low price disposable transmitter will make endoscopy affordable and give patients more freedom. The high quality high data rate video from different advanced sensors will give doctors more detailed information in medical treatment and diagnosis. If this technology is successfully developed, micro-robots can become a convenient and reliable tool for less invasive diagnosis or surgery. A device like this can give patients more convenience and make them more willing to take an exam.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0944654</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jianhung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jianhung@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/26/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate>03/10/2010</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Te-Lung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kung</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aric511@hotmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Leanics Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>OSSEO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>553113762</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6122204647</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6600 FOUNTAIN LN NORTH</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
