<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research at Undergraduate Institutions: Development of an On-line GIS Repository of Geological Data from the Ford Ranges, Marie Byrd Land, &amp; Application to Cenozoic Paleogeography</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49545</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexandra Isern</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;This work will create a GIS-based repository of geological data sets from the Ford Ranges that will be made available via the Internet in both GIS and interactive web format. The proposed project will integrate the products of geological research with WorldView imagery and high resolution TMA photography available from the Antarctic Geospatial Information Center. The aims of the project are: 1) to develop an internet-based system for sharing of geological data, 2) associate these data with high resolution photography and imagery to extend analysis from areas of rock exposure to completely glaciated areas, and 3) to provide undergraduates with an exciting context in which to acquire fundamental skills and analytical experience in GIS together with an understanding of physical-chemical principles. The research will use GIS for inquiry and interpretation of a geological-glacial setting that has significance for climate, ice sheet, or tectonics in West Antarctica, augmented by in-depth study of published geological literature, through which students will learn to think critically, problem-solve, and experiment with methods and data sets in order to find solutions to contemporary scientific questions. This compilation of geological data and bedrock physical parameters is needed for the quantitative analysis of past paleotopography by ANTscape and Antarctic Climate Evolution scientists, and may be used as input data for continually more refined climate evolution and ice sheet models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: &lt;br/&gt;As part of this work three undergraduates pursing senior theses will develop proficiency in GIS while exploring research questions about Antarctic climate evolution. This work will enable the scientific community to access an on-line repository of geological data from the Ford Ranges, West Antarctica that will be placed within the larger geospatial framework offered by satellite imagery. Interpretations of paleoelevations for selected regions and time intervals will be of broad use for climate/ice sheet modelers and glacial geologists. Petrological, geochronological, and structural data will be of value for solid earth scientists conducting work in segments of the former accretionary margin of Gondwana.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0944777</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Siddoway</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>csiddoway@coloradocollege.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado College</Name>
      <CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
      <ZipCode>809033243</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7193896318</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>14 E. Cache La Poudre St.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
