<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Cellular Stress Response in Cold-adapted Organisms: Building Novel Mechanistic Links between Heat Stress, Cell Cycle Arrest and Apoptosis in Antarctic Fishes.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>464474</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles Amsler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research will investigate a novel mechanism by which cold-adapted fishes of the Southern Ocean sense and respond to elevated temperatures. It is hypothesized that sub-lethal heat stress may induce cell cycle arrest and/or programmed cell death through apoptosis. The study will use genome-enabled technologies to examine the environmental control over gene expression in Antarctic species and will build direct mechanistic links between the expression of a specific signaling pathway gene and heat-induced changes in cells. Prior results support the hypothesis that heat stress results in cell cycle arrest and, in some cases, programmed cell death in Antarctic fishes. If so, this represents a novel, modified version of the well-conserved cellular stress response found in essentially all other species and suggests that warming ocean temperatures may have profound cellular and physiological impacts on these extremely stenothermal species. The P.I. conducts outreach activities with the Oregon Museum of Science and Industry, will be involved in developing a science curriculum for the Native American Youth and Family Center (NAYA) Early College Academy in Portland, and supports the educational and professional development of both undergraduate and graduate students at Portland State University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0944743</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buckley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbuckley@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Portland State University</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
