<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: BioBased Coatings for Corrosion Protection</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Josephine Yuen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project is designed to prepare and evaluate novel biobased corrosion protection coatings derived from modified soy oil that quickly cures upon exposure to atmospheric moisture yielding smooth protective films. This cure mechanism is based on the well known room temperature vulcanization of the reactive silicone and is applied here by grafting reactive silane onto the unsaturated fatty acid residues of the oil triglycerides. This approach provides a convenient one-component package and does not require reactive diluents, UV or oxygen for cure initiation. It does not incorporate alkyds or require epoxidized soy oil. Preliminary results show that crosslinking occurs relatively fast without requiring any volatile coalescing agents and the films are completely cured. Good adhesion to stainless-steel was observed and physical properties (hardness, tensile strength, elongation, etc.) of the coatings are expected to be easily controlled by the concentration of the grafted silicone component. The presence of reactive silane is particularly suitable for corrosion protection since it acts as a moisture scavenger as well as improving the adhesion with the metal surface. It is anticipated that successful completion of this work will replace petroleum-based materials with biobased materials in corrosion protection technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to provide permanent, organic coatings derived from renewable resources to offer clean technologies to the public. These biobased coatings are targeted for corrosion-prevention applications such as gas and liquid transmission pipelines, construction rebar for bridges and buildings, industrial equipment, etc. Corrosion of metallic structures has a significant impact on the US economy. Results of a NACE study (2002) shows that the total annual estimated direct cost of corrosion in the U.S. is a staggering $276 billion - approximately 3.1% of the nation's Gross Domestic Product. Successful implementation of Phase I &amp; II of this project will have the following technical, commercial, environmental and economical impacts: improved corrosion protection and ease of application, low capital investment, reduction in VOC/HAP and carbon footprint, preservation of fossil fuel resources, reduction in corrosion related costs to the industry, and creation of up to an additional five jobs for sales, manufacturing, and technical support of this newly developed product.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0945200</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>SHILPA</FirstName>
      <LastName>MANJURE</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smanjure@ntic.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/22/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northern Technologies International Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Circle Pines</CityName>
      <ZipCode>550140069</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7632256600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4201 Woodland Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
