<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: International Workshop on the Impact of Control: Past, Present, and Future, held in Berchtesgaden, Germany on October 18-20, 2009.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Radhakisan S. Baheti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An International Workshop on the impact of control entitled ?International Workshop on the Impact of Control: Past, Present, and Future, is proposed to be organized October 18-20, 2009 in Berchtesgaden, Germany. The Workshop is being sponsored by the Institute for Advanced Study (IAS) at the Technische Universitaet Muenchen and the IEEE Control Systems Society. The objective is to bring together a group of leading researchers and practitioners in control science and engineering to broadly address the issue of the impact of control. There will be a particular emphasis on problems where controls had a lasting impact in the application domain. Examples of application domains include and are not limited to the following: automotive, aerospace, process industries, manufacturing automation and robotics, networked systems, biomedical devices, smart grids and renewable energy sources. Several panel discussions on these applications and the impact of control therein will be carried out. Breakout sessions on thematic topics such as Controls Education, Outreach and visibility, Industry-Government-Academia collaboration, and Market studies and analysis for control will also be organized. A panel report summarizing the deliberations of the Workshop as well as recommendations for cross-institutional collaborations in controls, specifically targeting industrial, academic, and governmental cooperation will be produced subsequent to the Workshop. This award will support a group of 8 U.S. researchers to participate in this three-day international workshop on the impact of control.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The US organizers are Anuradha Annaswamy PhD., Senior Research Scientist, MIT, Tariq Samad PhD, Honeywell and President of the IEEE Control System Society, and Professor Gary Balas, Department of Aerospace Engineering and Mechanics, at the University of Minnesota. Professor Martin Buss of the Institute for Advanced Study (IAS) at&lt;br/&gt;the Technische Universitaet Muenchen is the German organizer of the workshop.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the workshop is to identify the past and present impact of control in the engineering and science communities, along with the future directions where control will have a high impact and common theoretical and computational challenges facing the controls community. Many of the leading international control researchers plan to participate in the workshop.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the workshop will include a report on the past and present impact of control and future direction and potential impact of control in the areas of automotive, aerospace, process industries, manufacturing automation and robotics, networked systems, biomedical devices, smart grids and renewable energy sources. A journal article in the IEEE Control System magazine is also planned. The report and article will highlight new opportunities for follow-on research and education activities specifically for junior researchers and graduate students in the controls field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0946741</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Balas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>balas@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0112000</Code>
      <Name>System Theory</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
