<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2009 Biomedical Engineering Society Annual Fall Meeting to be held at Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA Oct 7-10, 2009</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Semahat S. Demir</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0946267&lt;br/&gt;Borovetz &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BMES Annual Fall Meeting is a multidisciplinary scientific event sponsored by the Biomedical Engineering Society (BMES). This year's meeting is also co-sponsored by several other societies such as the Whitaker International Fellows and Scholars Program, among many others. This annual meeting will be held in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, from October 7-10, 2009. The conference theme, "Bridging the Three Rivers of Biology, Engineering and Medicine", will highlight the importance of Biomedical Engineering as the intersection of Biology, Medicine and Engineering. Attendance to the meeting is expected to be more than 2000 delegates from all over the world. The BMES meetings bring together academic leaders, students, and industrial representatives once a year. At this conference, two extremely high quality plenary speakers are scheduled at a time with no other activities such that all conference participants would attend these talks and several workshops as well. The conference format will be 12 parallel sessions of oral presentations. Approximately 2/3 of the accepted papers will be presented in poster format. A booklet will provide program details to the participants of the conference. All technical presentations will be one-page abstracts and compiled in a CD format, distributed to all registrants. Copies of this CD will also be provided to all cosponsoring societies. The CD will serve as the only technical proceedings of the meeting. The budget request of $15,000 to NSF is to aid in reducing student registration fees, help in reimburse some of the student travel costs, student paper competition awards, and to cover in part the publication costs of the program booklet and CD.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0946267</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harvey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borovetz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>borovetzhs@upmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/06/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
