<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ocean Acidification</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Ocean acidification is increasingly being recognized as a threat to marine ecosystems and resources. While there has been a great deal of scientific research on this subject in recent years, there is still much to be learned and many challenges surrounding the management of ocean resources in the face of ocean acidification. In recognition of these challenges, key ocean agencies within the federal government, including NSF, are currently developing an interagency strategic plan for ocean acidification monitoring and research that will allow for impacts assessments and the development of adaptation and mitigation strategies. The National Research Council study will assemble an expert committee, representative of the broader research community, to provide expert advice to help frame this strategic plan. This committee will not only synthesize the existing research, but move beyond the natural science to provide advice on high priority issues for natural resource management. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will provide a comprehensive review of the current knowledge on ocean acidification and will serve as a reference for the scientific community. It will help to frame research priorities in the context of high-priority needs for adaptation and management strategies. The recommendations in the report will provide valuable input to the interagency working group in its preparation of a national strategic plan for ocean acidification.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0946330</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Roberts</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sroberts@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Park</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spark@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5418</Code>
      <Text>OCE SPECIAL PROGRAMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1382</Code>
      <Text>OCEAN ACIDIFICATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
