<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: PHYSICAL SYSTEM DYNAMICS FOR THE CHARACTERIZATION AND CONTROL OF COMPLEX WIRELESS NETWORKS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149687</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George Haddad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This EArly-concept Grants for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project addresses the need for wireless networks to autonomously reconfigure themselves to adapt to changes in the network or in the requirements of the supported applications. The approach utilizes physics-based models for characterization and control that are inspired by the dynamics of multiple-connected atoms forming a molecular network. The research considers two-tiered heterogeneous networks with ad-hoc networks using omni-directional communication links interconnected by a directional wireless backbone network that utilizes radio frequency or free-space optical links.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to intellectual merit, the research uses a multidisciplinary approach to model and control robust, self-organizing heterogeneous networks. The models and methods for analysis and operation have the potential to deal with the growing complexity and dynamical behavior of such networks. The research could lead to models that would enable: (i) energy minimization through topology control in complex networks by assessing network robustness and strategies for driving a network topology to a minimum energy configuration; (ii) characterization of link breaks and reconfiguration mechanisms in dynamic networks, including the cost of link breaks that can lead to network partitions; and (iii) evaluation of network evolution through mechanisms including network degradation, network congestion, and node and link failures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With respect to broader impact, the research has the potential to transform the analysis and operation of next-generation dynamic wireless networks. Such dynamic wireless networks have a number of important applications including personal and commercial communication, disaster and emergency response, and tactical military communications. The project contributes to ongoing efforts, including a summer internship program, for broadening participation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0946955</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stuart</FirstName>
      <LastName>Milner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>milner@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
