<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>In-situ High-pressure Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) Measurement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300206</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030107</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sonia Esperanca</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The interior of Earth controls many features and hazards at its surface. These include mountain ranges and ocean basins as well as dynamic effects like volcanoes and earthquakes. It is thus important to understand the behavior of minerals within Earth's interior. However, the available experimental techniques required to produce the elevated pressures and temperatures that occur deep within Earth are limited (e.g., extremely large steel presses, diamond-anvil cells combined with laser heating) that are costly and difficult to use. More importantly, they allow only limited examination of the materials at high-pressure and -temperature conditions. Instead, the products must be removed from the equipment in order to examine them using advanced methods such as electron diffraction and high-resolution imaging using a transmission electron microscope (TEM) that allows the examination of details of structure and reaction. In fact, some materials that form under extreme conditions are unquenchable, meaning they change structure and thus behavior when examined at room pressure and temperature. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is designed to solve this problem by developing and refining a way of looking at materials at high pressures and temperatures in place within a TEM, where we can examine them down to the atomic level. It is planned to make use of the remarkable properties of carbon nanotubes (CNTs), which we will use as the containers of the minerals that we wish to study at elevated pressures and temperatures. It was shown recently that CNTs will contract when bombarded with an energetic electron beam. They can thus serve as microscopic high-pressure cells that can be studied within a TEM. Therefore, all the superior capabilities of such microscopy can be fully transplanted to in-situ high-pressure research. The preliminary research to be supported will be devoted to developing methods of placing materials of interest into the tiny CNTs. The team will start with materials such as single elements and simple oxides and salts in order to properly test and calibrate the technique. They will then extend the work to examining more complex minerals that are thought to be abundant in Earth's interior and that influence or control behavior within the deep crust and mantle of the planet. Wüstite, an iron oxide that is only stable at high temperature and is abundant in the deep Earth in the form of magnesiowüstite, forms the long-term focus of this study since it may disproportionate at extreme conditions and have profound effects on the history of our planet. Overall, the results will provide fundamental new knowledge about a high-pressure experimental technique that is new to the earth sciences as well as about the nature of geologically and geophysically important minerals under extreme conditions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0948535</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Buseck</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pbuseck@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1573</Code>
      <Text>PETROLOGY AND GEOCHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
