<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>OPUS: A synthesis of 55 years of research on the monarch butterfly</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>141576</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan James Tessier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In the last half century the monarch butterfly, Danaus plexippus, has become an important model organism for research on mimicry, plant-herbivore interactions, chemical ecology, physiological ecology, and migration. In addition, the charismatic insect has proven to be an appealing entry point into the world of science for both children and adults. Much of the research that has made this a model organism has been conducted by Lincoln Brower, who will be supported to write a book targeted to scientists, graduate and undergraduate students, and science-curious general readers. The book will address the monarch butterflies' chemical defense against predators, the ecological chemistry of the butterflies' interactions with their milkweed hostplants, the physiology, ecology and behavior of the butterflies as they cope with the microclimate in their Mexican wintering sites, and the butterflies' unique migration and wintering biology that illustrate timely conservation issues. The intellectual merit of the book for scientists will be in its presentation of data, critical review of evidence, and extensive bibliography. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An important broader impact of the project will be the archiving of original datasets in a digital data registry. Explanations of the significance of these data and including unanswered questions in each chapter will help to spark new research. The book will enhance non-specialists' and students' understanding of diverse methodologies that can be used to address ecological questions, and their appreciation of the value of long-term studies and the collaborative nature of many discoveries. Copious illustrations will engage the reader and tell the story, so that the non-expert is prepared to understand data and how experiments in both the field and laboratory were actually conducted.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0949650</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lincoln</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brower</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brower@sbc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Sweet Briar College</Name>
      <CityName>Sweet Briar</CityName>
      <ZipCode>245955001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4343816100</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>134 Chapel Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1171</Code>
      <Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7565</Code>
      <Text>OPUS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
