<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Early Career: Acquisition of a Computer Cluster</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>73771</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030202</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Beghein&lt;br/&gt;0949255&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funding for a new Linux computer cluster for seismological research at UCLA for an early career PI. The cluster will be incorporated into the campus-wide cluster so that unused cycles can be shared. Research will involve both forward and inverse modeling. Forward modeling will focus on seismic velocity and anisotropy, and quantitative model uncertainties. Solving the non-linear inverse problems will over-challenge current computing resources. Earthscope USArray Transportable Array data will be processed using the new cluster. Future work constraining seismic anisotropy in the mantle and core will involve full spectral coupling, which is computationally demanding. Wave propagation code will also be used to test models. Three-dimensional core structure models will assist in defining an inner inner core, phase and/or compositional changes within the inner core, and defining density changes at the core boundary, ultimately furthering our understanding of the geotherm. Other study areas for the new cluster include mantle deformation geometry, plate motion-sub-lithospheric deformation coupling, asthenospheric deformation versus fossil lithospheric deformation, mid-ocean ridge spreading, surface tectonic signatures of upper mantle processes, crust, upper mantle lithosphere and the asthenosphere interactions, and thermal versus compositional nature of the mantle at various depths. The new cluster will benefit researchers from many different fields, in Earth Sciences, Astrophysics, Physics,Biology, and Computer Sciences as it will be incorporated into the existing campus-wide cluster. The cluster will provide data on basic Earth system functioning. New modeling techniques and scientific results will be published, and models will be freely disseminated over the internet. The cluster will be used for student training both in Geosciences and within other disciplines - producing a new generation of scientists with the ability to understand forward modeling and parallel computer programming. The cluster will be incorporated into the campus-wide shared cluster. UCLA Academic Technology Services (ATS) then provides maintenance and installation at no cost. ATS also provides system administration including OS maintenance and upgrade, hardware resolution and scheduling. ATS also provides training. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0949255</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Caroline</FirstName>
      <LastName>Beghein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cbeghein@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7255</Code>
      <Text>GEOINFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
