<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Molecular Characterization of Black Widow Spider Silks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>458749</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Spiders spin a variety of high performance fibers with mechanical properties that are unparalleled in the environment and comparable to the best synthetic materials produced by modern technology. There is considerable interest in the production of protein-based structural polymers through genetic engineering for a wide range of applications, including protective clothing and equipment, ropes and nets, tissue engineering, and materials for the automobile and aerospace industry. These studies implement multidisciplinary approaches to identify proteins assembled into aggregate gland-produced silk fibers, as well as reveal regulatory switches and factors that control silk gene expression for aggregate and tubuliform silk proteins in the black widow spider, Latrodectus hesperus. This project has a common goal of advancing technologies to position scientists to manufacture synthetic silks for human applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the research will include training graduate, undergraduate, and high school students in a wide range of modern molecular and biochemical techniques. Disadvantaged minority undergraduate students will be targeted from introductory, as well as upper division biology and chemistry classes to gain educational experiences through research participation. Local high school students will also be recruited for summer internships through a connection with the Project SEED, a summer research experience program directed by the American Chemistry Society that targets economically disadvantaged students. A strong component of the research program will also involve the general public. Individuals from the local community will learn about the extraordinary properties of spider silk fibers through interactions with research team members during routine spider collections. Individuals from the local community will also receive education on the spider silk biology research through Pacific's Center for Professional and Continuing Education Program. Additionally, findings generated by this project will be disseminated in peer-reviewed scientific journals, local high schools, newspapers, and local and national research conferences. In summary, the research project will enhance our understanding on spider silk biology and provide rich training for a wide range of individuals at various educational levels.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0950372</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vierra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cvierra@uop.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of the Pacific</Name>
      <CityName>Stockton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>952110110</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2099467706</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3601 Pacific Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
