<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: Herbivory-Boosted Photosynthesis: Elicitors from Tupiocoris notatus Saliva Induce Changes in Plant Metabolism</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>456690</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Irwin Forseth</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Contrary to conventional wisdom, not all insect herbivores impose negative fitness consequences on their plant hosts and not all induced plant responses affect the attacking insects negatively. This project hypothesizes that the underlying recognition and signaling mechanisms of the plant are subject to a co-evolutionary arms race between plants and insects, so that specifically induced plant responses could be to the benefit/disadvantage of both sides; the responding plant and the herbivore manipulating the plant. Previous studies suggest the existence of compensatory regulation mechanisms that may specifically influence both primary and secondary metabolism to increase plant defense without decreasing photosynthesis and growth. This project will elucidate the function of induced changes in plant primary and secondary metabolism of the wild tobacco Nicotiana attenuata when attacked by the mirid bug Tupiocoris notatus, evaluating fitness consequences for the plant and the insect and uncovering the underlying physiological mechanisms of those responses. Integrative functional analysis of plant responses to herbivory are used to understand the ecological mechanisms that drive plant-insect co-evolution. The manipulation of such a plant defense mechanism in crop and horticultural plants would allow the development of more sustainable, yet cost efficient methods of pest control. Moreover, identifying mechanisms that increase photosynthetic activity is a major opportunity to increase agricultural productivity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The project's broader impacts involve the professional development of two young scientists and combine research foci of both laboratories, one of which focuses on the analysis of plant photosynthesis processes and the other on herbivore-induced plant defenses. Undergraduate students will be involved in all stages of the project and will be able to gain academic credit for their involvement in practical research courses in both academic institutions. The geographic proximity of Cornell and Ithaca College allows the students to take advantage of the research environments of both institutions. Under the framework and guidance of the new Molecular and Chemical Ecology Initiative of Cornell aspects of this project will be used to develop undergraduate and graduate educational curriculum. In addition to undergraduate education this project will include the training of a postdoctoral associate and a graduate student.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0950225</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andre</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kessler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ak357@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
