<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Regional Workshops on Increasing the Enrollment of Male Undergraduates in STEM Disciplines at Minority-serving Institutions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>267259</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Quality Education for Minorities (QEM) Network's project is conducting three regional workshops focused on increasing the enrollment of male undergraduates in STEM disciplines at Minority-serving Institutions (MSIs). The three regional workshops will take place during March and April 2010. The goals of the project are to conduct a workshop series focused on effective strategies and best practices for increasing male student enrollment at MSIs, particularly in STEM; to identify potential reinforcing pipeline options; and to prepare and disseminate a Summary Report on the best practices and key workshop findings. Collectively, the three workshops will provide a broad spectrum of representation, experiences and perspectives from representatives of two and four-year Hispanic-serving Institutions (HSIs); Tribal Colleges and Universities/Alaska Native-Serving Institutions (TCUs/ANSIs); and Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TCUs/ANSIs, HSIs and HBCUs all share the quiet crisis of limited enrollment of males in STEM disciplines and all will benefit from the expanded knowledge base resulting from the workshops. Significant societal benefits, including an enhanced STEM workforce, will result from greater participation in STEM of all underrepresented groups, including minority males.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0951625</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shirley</FirstName>
      <LastName>McBay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smmcbay@qem.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>QUALITY EDUCATION FOR MINORITIES NETWORK</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200362406</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2026591818</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
