<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Multiscale Travel Time Tomography of the Mantle to 1000 km Depth Beneath the Western USA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>97880</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gregory J. Anderson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Teleseismic data recorded across the western U.S. provide information on the structural nature of the mantle beneath North America, a volume of Earth's interior that has been shaped by a complex history of subduction of oceanic lithosphere. Tomography images high-velocity structures that are commonly attributed to subducted slabs but which are not as simple as expected from our current understanding of the geologic history of subduction. Hence, such images hold key information on the actual subduction history, the fate of young subducted slabs, and convective flow in the upper mantle and across the transition zone to the lower mantle. The area affected by the Laramide orogeny is now experiencing small-scale convection beneath most of the western U.S., and a presumed Yellowstone plume is (probably) interacting with subducted slab and small-scale downwellings. Understanding this richness of geological processes and resolving the individual structures from one another requires careful and accurate seismic imaging. The goal of this project is to test specific hypotheses about the complex history of the western U.S. by creating a comprehensive 3-D P-wave velocity model extending from the base of the crust to ~1000 km depth. The seismic modeling will combine all available local, regional, and global travel-time datasets with newly available constraints on crust and transition zone structure. In addition, it uses finite frequency techniques (where useful) and 3-D wave propagation techniques. This work supports two graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0952194</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eugene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Humphreys</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ghump@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>017F</Code>
      <Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
