<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: The molecular mechanisms governing fate decisions of human embryonic stem cells</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven L. Klein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This CAREER proposal aims to integrate the PI's research in human embryonic stem cells (hESCs) with the creation a new undergraduate course, training of next generation of scientists, community outreach and sharing knowledge and current information of hESCs with the research community and the general public.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: hESCs have been well recognized as a source for derivation of differentiated human cells for therapeutic purposes, but their enormous potential for understanding human development and many fundamental biological questions have been severely under-appreciated and under-explored. The goal of the proposed research is to explore the potential of hESCs as a developmental system and define the molecular programs that govern fate decisions in hESCs. Based on the findings from genomic and chemical screens, the PI proposes to apply a combined multidisciplinary approach including cell biology, genomics, proteomics and chemical genetics to decipher the signaling networks underlying the control of pluripotency and differentiation. The proposed research, if successful, will significantly improve our knowledge of the molecular basis of early human development. In addition, the results from this proposed research will contribute to the overall knowledge of cell growth, differentiation and plasticity.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Research on hESCs has generated much interest and public debate. As science and technology continue to advance, so do ethical viewpoints surrounding these developments. The lack of overall and technological understanding of hESCs has severely hindered hESC studies. The PI plans to play an active role in advocating, educating and exploring the issues, both scientifically and ethically. The investment of some time in educational and outreach efforts will help to transform people's understanding of hESCs, alleviate their concerns, and stimulate their interest. This in turn will impact very positively on the advancement of this nascent and promising research field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0953267</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>feiwang@life.uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/04/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1119</Code>
      <Text>ANIMAL DEVELOPMENTAL MECHANSMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
