<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Dielectric-Filled Nanowaveguides for Advanced Imaging and Sensing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>407901</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0953645&lt;br/&gt;Xu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the proposed integrated research and educational activities are to advance a novel approach for super-resolution imaging and sensing using dielectric-filled nanowaveguides and to make opportunities in science and engineering education more accessible to all students, especially historically underrepresented minorities in science and engineering through undergraduate mentoring, curriculum development and outreach activities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will focus on the study of optical properties of dielectric-filled nanowaveguides and the application of these nanowaveguide devices to super-resolution imaging and single molecule spectroscopy. The objectives of this research are to: (1) fabricate silicon-filled nanowaveguides and explore the possibility of other filling materials, (2) characterize in detail the far-field transmission properties and near-field intensity profiles of the nanowaveguides, (3) engineer nanowaveguide devices and test them on a near-field optical scanning microscope, and (4) apply these devices to biomedical and biotechnological research to solve challenging problems in these fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the educational activities is to make opportunities in science and engineering education more accessible to all students, especially historically underrepresented minorities in science and engineering. To accomplish this, the following approaches will be taken: (1) undergraduate research mentoring via one-on-one interaction between students and the PI, (2) new course development and curriculum innovation that incorporates research into teaching, and (3) outreach activities through mentor participation in programs like the Harlem Children Society and the New York State Education Department's Science &amp; Technology Entry Program (STEP).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0953645</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Huizhong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>huizhong@sfsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/01/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Saint John's University</Name>
      <CityName>Jamaica</CityName>
      <ZipCode>114399000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7189902920</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8000 Utopia Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7236</Code>
      <Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>005E</Code>
      <Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>014E</Code>
      <Text>NANOBIOTECH AND NANOTOXICOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
