<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Surface-engineering of monocytes for anticancer drug delivery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>472813</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michele Grimm</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0954957&lt;br/&gt;Yang&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The long-term objective of this CAREER research project is to develop a novel hypoxia-targeted delivery system to enhance penetration of anticancer drugs into solid tumors. Particularly, this new delivery system will be explored by hybridizing monocytes with dendrimer nanoparticles through cell surface engineering, in which the nanoparticles immobilized on the cell surface are intended for anticancer drug loading. Dendrimers have highly branched nanoscale structures with a number of functionalizable surface groups. They are capable of delivering a high drug payload as well as a variety of therapeutics and functional entities through proper chemical modifications, encapsulation, or surface interactions. Monocytes are able to both migrate to and accumulate in hypoxic areas of tumor. However, most anticancer drugs cannot be directly loaded into monocytes because of their inherent toxicity. Drug delivery through the cell surface-immobilized nanoparticles will potentially minimize the toxic effects of anticancer drugs to the monocyte vehicle and represents a transformative way to utilize the best aspects of both cellular and nanostructured carriers. The new treatment modality derived from this project may eventually serve as a complementary means to surgery and/or conventional chemotherapy and radiotherapy, helping to eradicate metastasis, improve survival rate, and increase quality of life for cancer patients. &lt;br/&gt;To generate a broader impact, a nanoscience research-based learning platform will be established to educate students of different academic levels, enable them to conduct novel research and increase their knowledge in the emerging scientific area of nanomedicine, and provide new opportunities for women or underrepresented minorities particularly African Americans to pursue careers in engineering and nanoscience. The outreach program will reach K-12 students by establishing a summer research program for local high school students, providing on-site displays to introduce fundamentals of nanotechnology through Science Museum of Virginia, and using 2-D tactile graphics and a portable haptic feedback device to teach the concepts of nanotechnology to those K-12 students who are blind or visually impaired.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0954957</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hyang2@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
      <CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>004E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>008E</Code>
      <Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>017E</Code>
      <Text>Cellular and Tissue Engineering</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
