<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Graph Information System: Deciphering Complex Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>495536</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jun Huan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Graphs and networks are ubiquitous, encoding complex relationships &lt;br/&gt;ranging from chemical bonds to social interactions. Hidden in these&lt;br/&gt;networks are the answers to many important questions in biology,&lt;br/&gt;business, and sociology. In order to analyze complex networks, users &lt;br/&gt;have to master sophisticated computing and programming skills. It &lt;br/&gt;indeed becomes a pain point for many scientists and engineers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is to change the state of the art by developing a &lt;br/&gt;general graph information system, which is able to address the needs &lt;br/&gt;of searching and mining complex networks. Real-life networks are &lt;br/&gt;complex, not only having topological structures, but also containing &lt;br/&gt;heterogeneous contents and attributes associated with nodes and &lt;br/&gt;edges. The mixture of structures and contents raises two challenges &lt;br/&gt;that require new solutions for smarter and faster graph analysis. &lt;br/&gt;First, new types of graph search and mining operations, such as graph &lt;br/&gt;aggregation, graph association, and graph pattern mining, are &lt;br/&gt;emerging. Second, when graphs become complex and large, most of &lt;br/&gt;existing graph mining algorithms cannot scale well. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses these challenges and performs a &lt;br/&gt;comprehensive study of a general graph information system. &lt;br/&gt;The system includes three major components: complex graph search, &lt;br/&gt;graph pattern mining, and graph indexing. &lt;br/&gt;It covers emerging structure queries in social, &lt;br/&gt;biological, and information networks, new graph mining operators &lt;br/&gt;such as graph summarization and association, and innovative indexing&lt;br/&gt;methodologies, e.g., differential graph index.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is tightly integrated with education through student &lt;br/&gt;mentoring and curriculum development. Publications, software and &lt;br/&gt;course materials resulted from this project are disseminated on the &lt;br/&gt;project website: http://www.cs.ucsb.edu/~xyan/gis.html.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0954125</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xifeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xyan@cs.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9215</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
