<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER (IDBR): Novel Quantitative Second-Harmonic Generation Microscope for Fundamental Study of Collagen Fibers in the Eye</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>620420</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher Sanford</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this CAREER award is to develop a non invasive, quantitative microscopy method with enhanced spatial resolution and depth penetration for the study of collagen fibers in living biological systems such as the cornea. The method, second-harmonic generation microscopy, is a nonlinear optical process that allows detailed imaging without the need for stains or contrast agents. The microscope would combine second harmonic nonlinear scattering with three dimensional control of light polarization and software analysis methods. The resulting system will enable noninvasive determination of the spatial organization of collagen fibers, allowing differentiation between fibrillar collagen types and assessment of collagen fiber spatial orientation and spacing.&lt;br/&gt;The educational objective of this award is to promote optical science and engineering education to the general public. To accomplish this, an online educational YouTube series ("Photonics TV") on optics for high-school and college students will be established. A hands-on optics module ("Optics Circus") will be developed for middle school students, and a Minority Contributions to Science and Technology Series set for use in the local community. More information is available at http://probe.mechse.illinois.edu</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0954155</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kimani</FirstName>
      <LastName>Toussaint</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ktoussai@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/23/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1108</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1108</Code>
      <Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
