<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Fundamental and Device-Oriented Approach to Energy Efficient Carbon Nanoelectronics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>418000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nadia El-Masry</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to examine fundamental aspects of energy dissipation in novel devices and nanomaterials, with focus on carbon electronics. The approach will study en-ergy loss and switching mechanisms in carbon nanotubes and graphene, which have great intrin-sic electrical and thermal properties, yet must be understood within in a device context.&lt;br/&gt; Intellectual Merit: Energy use in electronics today ranges from mobile devices (mW) to massive data centers (GW). Energy dissipation begins with nanoscale transistors, which are sur-prisingly inefficient and waste significant power as heat. This work will examine energy dissipa-tion in carbon nanoelectronics by (1) studying the role of remote phonons to find the most energy-efficient dielectrics, (2) exploring avalanche as an alternative switching mechanism, (3) developing models for Joule heating and thermal breakdown, and (4) validating them against electrical measurements and infrared thermal imaging. The fundamental knowledge derived from this research will also extend to all charge-based nanoelectronics.&lt;br/&gt; Broader Impacts: Optimizing energy dissipation in electronics will impact a wide range of technologies, and up to 10% of U.S. electricity use today. Progress in this area is crucial in a post-CMOS world, and has great environmental implications as well. This project will train students to think about fundamentals of energy dissipation, will engage minorities and women, and encourage undergraduates to publish. Work with local teachers and the Engineering Open House will engage local K-12 students, while a collaboration with the nanoHUB will reach a global audience. A remote (web-enabled) probe station will be built for testing nanoelectronics in class, eventually allowing access for anyone in the world to do cutting-edge device meas-urements.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0954423</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pop</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>epop@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/28/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>091E</Code>
      <Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>094E</Code>
      <Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>101E</Code>
      <Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>103E</Code>
      <Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>107E</Code>
      <Text>Magnetics and spin electronics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
