<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Combining research on dynamic metastability and hydrodynamic limits with a multifaceted outreach plan</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>42983</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Westdickenberg&lt;br/&gt;DMS-0955051&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator takes up problems in the areas of (i) slow&lt;br/&gt;coarsening or dynamic metastability of gradient flows, and (ii)&lt;br/&gt;logarithmic Sobolev inequalities (LSI) and the hydrodynamic&lt;br/&gt;limit. In the first part, the investigator and collaborators&lt;br/&gt;apply the abstract sufficient condition for dynamic metastability&lt;br/&gt;developed by Felix Otto and the PI to the Cahn-Hilliard Equation&lt;br/&gt;and then develop new but related methods to tackle the more&lt;br/&gt;applied problem of coarsening rates in two-dimensional epitaxial&lt;br/&gt;growth models. In the second part, the investigator and&lt;br/&gt;collaborators push forward their two-scale method for LSI and the&lt;br/&gt;hydrodynamic limit to prove convergence of the microscopic&lt;br/&gt;entropy to macroscopic entropy under general sufficient&lt;br/&gt;conditions. The educational and outreach component of the&lt;br/&gt;proposal encourages and supports women in mathematics and&lt;br/&gt;disseminates knowledge on multiple levels both in coordination&lt;br/&gt;with the research plans detailed above and through four explicit&lt;br/&gt;initiatives headed by the PI. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The work of this project focuses on understanding the way&lt;br/&gt;that energy (or entropy) and energy dissipation (or entropy&lt;br/&gt;dissipation) affect the nonlinear dynamics of a physical system. &lt;br/&gt;In general, science has a good understanding of global minimizers&lt;br/&gt;but a very weak understanding of local minimizers and pathways&lt;br/&gt;between them -- where many physical systems spend all of their&lt;br/&gt;time. A broader understanding of multiscale energy landscapes is&lt;br/&gt;of both scientific and practical importance; for instance,&lt;br/&gt;epitaxial growth models have implications for nanotechnology and&lt;br/&gt;semiconductor development, technology with impact in medicine,&lt;br/&gt;communications technology, and other fields. The education and&lt;br/&gt;outreach component of the proposal addresses a critical need to&lt;br/&gt;recruit and keep more women in mathematics, increase diversity in&lt;br/&gt;the sciences, and build international ties between the scientific&lt;br/&gt;communities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0955051</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Westdickenberg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maria@math.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
