<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Greener Herbarium for the Botanical Research Institute of Texas Herbarium (BRIT-SMU-VDB): Compactorization for Generations to Come</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499574</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne Maglia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An award to the Botanical Research Institute of Texas (BRIT) will support the purchase and installation of mobile storage units and herbarium cabinets for the BRIT-SMU-VDB Herbarium, which contains over one million specimens representing much of the Earth's plant diversity. These specimens are widely used by students and professionals as well as the general public. Compactorization of the collections with modern storage equipment will allow the incorporation of a large backlog of boxed specimens of great scientific value and will provide a safe environment for their preservation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this project include greatly improved accessibility to BRIT's collections for the scientific community and students, as well as new opportunities to engage the public. Expanded educational programs and rotating exhibits will illustrate the value of systematic herbarium collections. The expansion of the herbarium made possible by the construction of BRIT's new, "green," LEED-certified building will facilitate long-term growth of the collections and create a superior environment for herbarium research, education, and outreach. A fully compactorized herbarium, with a smaller footprint, using recycled steel and manual power, is a "green" herbarium. This award presents a timely and relevant opportunity to engage the public and increase appreciation for science in the service of conservation of biodiversity and natural resources.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956247</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aneill@brit.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Botanical Research Institute of Texas</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Worth</CityName>
      <ZipCode>761073400</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8173327432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 University Dr.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
