<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Coenzyme B12-Dependent 1,2-Propanediol Degradation by Salmonella</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>679999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susanne von Bodman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bacterial microcompartments are simple organelles used to optimize metabolic processes by sequestering toxic or volatile pathway intermediates. They consist of a protein shell that encases metabolic enzymes. The research will focus on understanding the structural and assembly principles of bacterial microcompartments as well as the mechanism by which the encapsulated enzymes are supplied with needed cofactors. The production of toxic pathway intermediates is a problem in the production of certain green chemicals by bacteria. Microcompartments are a natural system that solves this problem. Hence, understanding their molecular principles could lead to the genetic engineering of designer microcompartments for the improved production of green chemicals. A second focus of the research is to elucidate the biochemical properties of proteins required to activate vitamin B12 to coenzyme B12. This process is required for the activity of coenzyme B12-dependent enzymes which are widespread in nature and play important roles in the environment and in biotechnology. Thus, an improved understanding of vitamin B12 activation could result in better methods for the production of green chemicals and for bioremediation of contaminated habitats.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two graduate students, one post-doctoral fellow, and two undergraduates will carry out the research under guidance for the principle investigator. This will provide students with extensive training in the area of bacterial metabolism and genetics. This field is expected to be increasingly important as the need to engineer microbes for the production of chemicals and biofuels from renewable resources grows in the coming years. The PI will also work with the Iowa State University Carver Foundation to provide summer research opportunities to two minority undergraduate students per year.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956451</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bobik</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bobik@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
