<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Developing Resources for Research on Mollusks by Renovating Collection at Carnegie Museum of Natural History</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>486382</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne Maglia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Research on mollusks relies on long-term access to collections such as those maintained by the Section of Mollusks at The Carnegie Museum of Natural History (CMNH). This project will significantly enhance present and future access by improving storage of this research collection. To improve storage, this project will move specimens from current perilous conditions, caused by normal acidic off-gassing from wooden cabinets, into more accessible archival metal storage cabinets with archival specimen boxes. This project will increase the present and future availability of the collection and associated specimen data to support collection-based research by biodiversity conservation organizations and agencies at the federal, state, and local levels. This project will increase public education by making specimens more readily available to science-based public outreach programs, including tours, exhibits, and collaborative activities with other museum components. The project will educate and train volunteers and undergraduate work-study students, who are likely to include members of underrepresented groups (the PI's 7-year track record shows that 20% of 142 volunteers have been from underrepresented minority or ethnic groups, and 7% have had disabilities). The mollusk collection at CMNH is a major resource of international significance, being the largest collection of northern Appalachian non-marine mollusks and one of the top five freshwater mussel collections. Historically significant, the collection vouchers 100 years of research. Examples of recent collection use include molecular and morphological systematic studies (including five by students), environmental monitoring, training for mussel surveyors, and museum exhibits. Any thorough study of North American mollusks would refer to this collection. Information on the CMNH Collection of Mollusks can be found at http://www.carnegiemnh.org/mollusks/collection.htm.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956264</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pearce</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pearcet@carnegiemnh.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Carnegie Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152134080</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126223232</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
