<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Energy Storage and Conversion- Coupling the Direct Electrodeposition of Crystalline Intermetallics with Targeted Outreach to Elementary Schools</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>607712</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project, supported by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry (SSMC) program will develop direct electrodeposition of crystalline transition metal antimonides, a class of materials that exhibit a wide range of physical properties critical to many advanced technologies. A central focus of this work is on developing robust preparations of materials for high capacity anodes in Li-ion batteries. The high-temperature methods traditionally used to synthesize the target compounds are plagued by lack of control over the stoichiometry of the final products. Electrodeposition, in contrast, is a low-temperature method, which will lead to greater control over the stoichiometry and hence, improved physical properties. The ultimate goal is the direct electrodeposition of a range of anode materials from water at room temperature. The resulting films and nanowires will be directly deposited onto a current collector with no need for binders prior to battery testing. The outreach portion of this proposal will focus on adding renewable energy (in the context of transportation) to the popular Harry Potter based outreach shows that the undergraduate Chemistry Club at Colorado State University has already developed. By building on a wildly successful program, the proposed outreach will reach a wider range of students with an approach that promises to have high impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research program is the development of robust synthetic methods for materials with applications as anodes in Li-ion rechargeable batteries. The synthetic approach chosen, electrodeposition, is amenable to industrial scale production, is inexpensive, and can be performed in nontoxic solvents such as water. The direct result of the integrated research and teaching goals proposed will be manifested in the quality of training that graduate and undergraduate students obtain, both in the synthesis and characterization of materials critical to state-of-the-art energy research and in curriculum development and mentoring in the context of the proposed outreach shows. State-of-the-art research is crucial for recruiting and retaining a talented, diverse group of students. The shows described in the education section of this proposal will be used to increase the knowledge base of and excitement for science and renewable energy for fourth and fifth grade elementary school children throughout Colorado.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956011</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prieto</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alprieto@lamar.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/11/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1762</Code>
      <Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
