<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal: Workshop on Sensing and Prognostics for Scalability of Nanomanufacturing, held in Boston, October 27-28-2009.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>37256</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell Barton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides support for a workshop on Sensing and Prognostics for Scalability of Nanomanufacturing. The goal of the proposed workshop is to develop a national agenda and a road map for sensing and prognostics research to address the quality and reliability issues encountered in scaling up lab-based nano processes to high volume nanomanufacturing. It will bring together academic experts, industry and national laboratory leaders, and government policy makers to look at currently available field data and to develop a research agenda. Current research is focused on the science and engineering of the nano processes and there is an urgent need to address production issues now in order for high-rate/high-volume nanomanufacturing to become a reality. The outcomes of the workshop can be used nationwide to promote sensing and quality/reliability programs in nanomanufacturing and to stimulate related research activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The expected outcomes of the workshop are an examination of the current landscape and research in nanomanufacturing so as to identify the sensing and quality/reliability research needs in nanomanufacturing and the development of a national agenda and roadmap for nano sensing and quality/reliability research in nanomanufacturing. This will allow for the field to move from the lab to commercialization. The results will be widely disseminated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0956532</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ibrahim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zeid</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zeid@coe.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sagar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kamarthi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sagar@coe.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northeastern University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173732508</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
