<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of geophysical tools and software for subsurface imaging</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>102690</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell C. Kelz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0958710&lt;br/&gt;Bradbury&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation Recovery and Reinvestment (MRI-R2) Program grant supports acquisition of optical and acoustic borehole visualization tools to facilitate characterization of subsurface sedimentary features, fractures, and dissolution features in hydrological studies and resource assessments for the State of Wisconsin. The requested imaging tools would be part of an established subsurface investigations program undertaken by Wisconsin Geological and Natural History Survey (WGNHS) scientists and staff. The WGNHS is a special-mission unit of the University of Wisconsin-Extension, and undertakes research, resource evaluation, teaching, and outreach related to the water, rocks, and minerals of Wisconsin. Survey scientists conduct their own research but also collaborate with universities, state and federal agencies, communities, and the private sector throughout and beyond Wisconsin. The PIs of the proposal hold affiliate appointments with and are active participants in the hydrogeology program at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. WGNHS scientists also collaborate with regional faculty and their students from other UW campuses such as UW-Milwaukee, UW-Oshkosh, UW-Green Bay and UW-Stevens Point, as well as other regional institutions including Beloit College. The equipment would also support collaborative projects between WGNHS scientists and U.S. Geological Survey, Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources, Wisconsin Department of Agriculture, Wisconsin counties, and other agencies. Borehole televiewers to be acquired will support a range of scientific research themes including fractured rock hydrogeology, contaminated water transport, aquitard hydrogeology and groundwater resources of broad local, national, and international interest. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>102690</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0958710</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>djhart@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Madeline</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gotkowitz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbgotkow@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>McLaughlin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pimclaughlin@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bradbury</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krbradbu@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Extension</Name>
      <CityName>Madison</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537061498</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082655917</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 Extension Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
