<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Acquisition of a Direct Write Electron Beam Lithography System for Exploring Mesoscale Science, Materials, and Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1389500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Objective: The ability to control and manipulate matter at a few tens of atoms allows researchers to investigate a regime between the atomic-scale where quantum mechanics dominate and the bulk-scale. The availability of this capability is critical to the success of both academic and industrial researchers who are making devices or studying physical effects at these scales. This project addresses this need through the acquisition of a high resolution electron-beam lithography system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The University of Minnesota is conducting leading edge research in magnetics, mesoscale superconductivity, nanoelectronics, nano electromechanical systems, quantum dot devices, nano scale imaging, surface enhanced Raman, and other areas. All of this work is critically dependent on the ability to write extremely fine lines. This proposal seeks funding for the acquisition of a 100 keV field-emission electron-beam lithography system for the Minnesota Nano Fabrication Center (NFC). NFC supports a large and growing group of users with innovative projects from across the nation and has proven its ability to operate and maintain complex systems for its user base.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Minnesota is a key node in NSF?s National Nano Infrastructure Network with more than 600 users last year. Enhancing graduate education of these researchers will be a major impact. NFC is also a central hub for Nano-Link, a regional center for nanotechnology AAS education. The proposed tool will be used as part of the Nano-Link effort to demonstrate cutting edge pattern definition and quantum effects that can be readily understood by technical education professionals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>1389500</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0959622</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Campbell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>campb001@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leger@ece.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crowell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crowell@physics.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
