<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Acquisition of a Structural Dynamics and Surface Characterization System for Research and Educational Activities on Micro-scale Structures and Devices</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>449362</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christina L. Bloebaum</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this Major Research Instrumentation (MRI-R2) award is to acquire a state-of-the-art fully-integrated Micro Systems Analyzer (Polytec MSA-500). This tool allows quantitative three-dimensional measurements of the vibration modes of structures and devices ranging from centimeter down to nanometer scale, including micro and nanoelectromechanical systems (MEMS/NEMS), micro-fluids and biological systems. Measuring and quantifying the response of small-scale materials and structures to applied dynamical loads is essential in a variety of research fields. Such experiments are often complicated by a number of stringent requirements, such as non-contact technology, quick scanning of the entire surface of the object, very high displacement resolution, and ability to characterize samples immersed in aqueous solutions. This Micro Systems Analyzer meets all these requirements and will be transformational in a number of existing projects, ranging from the development and characterization of MEMS resonant devices (e.g. gyroscopes and micro-load cells) and bio-MEMS platforms, to fundamental fluid mechanics research on jet breakup and micro-fluidic systems, and physiological studies of the human ear.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Micro Systems Analyzer will critically impact nearly every research endeavor that studies or utilizes microstructures or microdevices. By complementing a fully equipped clean room, a state-of-the-art microscopy center and a modern materials characterization lab, this tool will provide the University of California, Irvine with a unique opportunity to propel itself to the forefront of micro and nano systems research. The acquired instrument will be made available to a variety of external users from UC sister campuses, private educational institutions and local businesses. Further, this Micro Systems Analyzer will open a variety of exciting educational opportunities: besides being readily integrated into existing courses, it will enrich undergraduate research opportunities through a variety of established initiatives. Most importantly, it will play a substantial role in training the next generation of researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>449362</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0960315</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abraham</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aplee@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrei</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shkel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ashkel@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Guann</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gpli@calit2.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lorenzo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Valdevit</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>valdevit@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Derek</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunn-Rankin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddunnran@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/15/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7217</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9148</Code>
      <Text>TOOLS &amp; TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
