<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Global Positioning Satellite Monitoring for High Risk Sex Offenders in San Diego: Implemenitation and Outcome.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9611</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Scott Barclay</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The introduction of surveillance technology to the United States' criminal justice system is arguably the most significant development in criminal justice policy in the last 30 years. Forms of surveillance technologies, including Electronic Monitoring (EM) and Global Positioning Systems (GPS), are quickly becoming a standard criminal justice tool used for the continuous control and punishment of offenders. It is, therefore, necessary to understand how technology is used in current criminal justice legislation and policy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using California, Florida, Idaho, and Massacusetts as study sites, this dissertation will use a multi-method research design that includes archival analysis of offender legislation and offender management documents as well as analysis of interviews with parole officers, administrators, and offenders. Findings from the analysis of this data will help to answer the following questions: 1) What is meant by the "electronic monitoring" of paroled offenders as a criminal justice policy? 2) What is the relationship between the legislative intent and reality of electronic monitoring of paroled offenders? 3) How is GPS surveillance technology, allied with criminal justice policy, reshaping the (a) lives of parolees? (b) lives of parole officers? (c) operation of parole? and (d) operation of other criminal justice agencies?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The findings from this research will deepen understanding of the relationship between surveillance technology and the criminal justice system. They will be informative for the development of policies regarding the use of such technologies in pursuit of the goals of the criminal justice system.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0961803</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
      <LastName>Troshynski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>etroshyn@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elliott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Currie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ecurrie@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/25/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1372</Code>
      <Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7603</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
