<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Revitalization of University of Florida Helium Liquefaction and Recovery System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1834243</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Guebre X. Tessema</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will revitalize and enhance the capability of the University of Florida Helium Liquifaction facility. The installation of new compressors and storage capacity will upgrade the current facility to the next generation infra-structure to support research of both large scale users and the widely distributed small scale users across campus for the next 15 to 20 years, expanding the total volume of liquid delivered and recovered annually from 89,000 liters to 135,000 liters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will enhance infrastructure for research by providing low cost helium supply. The University of Florida supports curricula in cryogenics and trains more than 60 undergraduate and graduate students and post doctoral associates each year in classes and research laboratories in this area. The training is integrated with research activities throughout the laboratories including safety instruction on handling low temperature liquids, and is unique in training students in low and ultra-low temperature techniques. In addition, the University provides technical consults to many other universities and laboratories both national and international. The investigators who use the liquid helium will be mentoring many undergraduate students in summer programs (undergraduate research programs in physics, chemistry and materials research) and give lectures at elementary and middle schools throughout north-central Florida, and at the NHMFL Summer School. Research and educational activities supported by liquid helium research are expected to increase training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students in this field and increase retention rates. In addition, a webpage will be set up for outreach activities and this site will provide information about the facility including a photo tour of the facility and the complete list of research, educational projects and community activities that could benefit from the facility.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>1834243</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0962743</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sullivan@phys.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ihas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ihas@phys.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yoonseok</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yoonslee@phys.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joanna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Long</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jrlong@mbi.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gail</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fanucci</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fanucci@chem.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9155</Code>
      <Text>ACADEMIC RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTU</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
