<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Quantifying Particulate Matter Emission Factors from Prescribed Burning with Application to Mitigating the Impact on Air Quality</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399396</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objectives of this project are to improve the PM2.5 (particles smaller than 2.5 micrometer diameter) emission factors (EFs) for burning of common southeastern U.S. vegetation types, test for effects of fire conditions on EFs, and evaluate improvements in the method for estimating EFs. The hypotheses to be tested are that current methods over-estimate EFs and that climate and fire fuel conditions are major factors controlling PM2.5 EFs. The methodology will involve collection of PM2.5 samples followed by measurements of composition using a Multi-Element Scanning Thermal Analysis (MESTA) technique developed recently by one of the principal investigators that can be used to distinguish biomass burning aerosol (BBA) from background aerosol. The BBA mass measurements will be combined with measurements of the stable carbon isotope composition of carbon dioxide generated by the fire. The carbon isotope ratios can be measured in real-time using a commercially available laser-based system and can be used to quantify carbon dioxide emitted by the fire. The ratio of BBA to fire carbon dioxide is the EF.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results will be used to assess the validity of the current fire PM2.5 EF database, which is the basis for all fire PM2.5 emission prediction and modeling. The research will likely establish a new standard for future PM2.5 EF measurement, which would improve calculation of EF and estimates of PM emission nationally and globally. Products generated from the project will be delivered directly to other scientists and to state and federal regulators, which will lead to improved prescribed fire application and air quality policy in order to protect the health and safety of the general public. At least two workshops will be held to provide direct training and information transfer regarding the developed methods of PM2.5 and fire carbon dioxide emissions and calculation of improved EFs. A post-doctoral associate and minority graduate and undergraduate students from Florida A&amp;M University, a Historically Black University, will have the opportunity to be trained and mentored in areas of air quality research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0962970</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Robertson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krobertson@ttrs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yuch-Ping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hsieh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yhsieh@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Glynnis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bugna</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>glynnis.bugna@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University</Name>
      <CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323073200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8505993531</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lee Hall Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1524</Code>
      <Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
