<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Core Support for the Board on Life Sciences at the National Academies of Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>244658</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds renewed support for the Board of Life Sciences (BLS) at the National Academy of Sciences. The BLS serves as the National Academies' focal point for a wide range of scientific, technical and policy topics in the life sciences, including infrastructure, bioterrorism, genomics, biodiversity conservation, and key topics in basic biological and biomedical research. It organizes and oversees studies that provide advice to government and the scientific community on the biological sciences and their impact on society. Further, it maintains expertise in and understanding of the full spectrum of life science disciplines, from molecular genetics to ecology. This enables it to deal with issues of both basic science (e.g., knowledge gaps, research priorities, needed investments) and the higher level policy concerns that flow from or build on the basic science. The Board also oversees important studies on the improvement of biology education, particularly at the undergraduate level, and the maintenance of a strong life sciences workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0962445</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frances</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharples</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fsharples@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1157</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY POSTDOC RSRCH FLW-NEW</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7226</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
