<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Climate Control of Eaton/Lansing Research and Research Training Labs</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1087832</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tanja Pietraß</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal seeks funding to extend an existing chilled water loop to the Eaton/Lansing science complex at Hobart and William Smith (HWS) Colleges. The complex serves 35 research laboratories, 5 research and teaching laboratories, and related support space. Air handling for each space will be integrated into the campus-wide HVAC control system. Constructed in 1954, the building was not designed for summer research and originally did not contain dedicated research spaces. Since the facility was opened, laboratory climate control was addressed on an ad hoc basis and incorporated window-mounted A/C units. As a result, the climate control infrastructure is inadequate to meet the needs of research-active faculty and their students at this primarily-undergraduate institution.The faculty of HWS, and in particular the most recently hired faculty, run federally and privately supported research programs. Adequate research facilities will enable more productive (uninterrupted) research, especially with students, and help to attract research active new hires. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research to be undertaken in the renovated facility will include utilizing zooplankton to resolve questions concerning species establishment and community composition; developing new molecular wire candidates incorporating materials that may be used to replace current silicone chip technology; and researching topics of thermal noise and higher-order statistical noise in gravity wave detectors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will enhance infrastructure for research. The renovation will improve research facilities with a positive effect on research productivity. Heightened research productivity is expected to increase the number of students involved as well as to lengthen the duration of the summer research program. Instrumentation is expected to operate more reliably in a stable environment, thus also increasing research productivity and competitiveness.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>1087832</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0963014</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>deDenus</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dedenus@hws.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Penn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>penn@hws.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Curtin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>curtin@hws.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Deutschlander</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>deutschlander@hws.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Hobart and William Smith Colleges</Name>
      <CityName>Geneva</CityName>
      <ZipCode>144563397</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3157813754</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>337 Pulteney Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9155</Code>
      <Text>ACADEMIC RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTU</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
