<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Renovation of the Graduate Center for Materials Research at Missouri S&amp;T</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1829800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Guebre X. Tessema</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will provide partial funding for the renovation and modernization of the heating, ventilation and air conditioning (HVAC) system, updating the electrical system, improvement of fume hoods and abatement of asbestos in the Graduate Center for Materials Research (MRC) at Missouri University of Science and Technology. This building is routinely used by over 150 personnel, including staff members, graduate and undergraduate students, post-doctoral fellows, and visiting scholars. In 2009, 125 different projects were carried out at this Center. Research topics include bioactive glasses, corrosion coatings for construction and transportation, electrodeposited chiral films for spintronic devices, biosensors, and ultrahigh temperature ceramics. However, lack of good temperature and humidity control in the building is seriously affecting the productivity and timely completion of these projects. To meet modern safety and environmental standards, many of the lab fume hoods need to be updated, and asbestos containing materials will be removed from the building. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MRC faculty members mentor many undergraduate student in research activities that are supported by external funding through such programs as the "Opportunity for Undergraduate Research Experience." As part of outreach activities, MRC staff members mentor and provide research training to over 1,300 K-12 students per year through the Office of Pre-College Programs. The MRC staff also hosts a number of tours of the MRC facilities and equipment by community and industrial groups. Another outreach activity involving the MRC faculty is the ASM Teacher Materials Camp held every summer during the last few years.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>1829800</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0963050</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Switzer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jswitzer@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brow</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brow@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fahrenholtz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>billf@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Keefe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjokeefe@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chang-Soo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ckim@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/09/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Rolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 W 12th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9155</Code>
      <Text>ACADEMIC RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTU</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
