<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Algebraic and Combinatorial Approaches to Representation Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49829</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric Sommers</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Representation theory of Lie algebras, quantum groups and algebraic groups represent a major area of mathematical research in the twenty-first century with numerous applications in other areas of mathematics (such as: geometry, number theory, combinatorics, finite and infinite groups, etc.) and mathematical physics (such as: conformal field theory, statistical mechanics, integrable systems, etc.). A conference on Algebraic and Combinatorial approaches to Representation Theory is proposed to be held at Bangalore, India during August 12-16, 2010. This conference will precede the International Congress of Mathematicians 2010 held at Hyderabad, India. It will provide a unique opportunity for specialists in representation theory from Asia, Europe and United States to interact, share ideas, and report on recent developments in this important area of research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant will provide support for airfare of about seventeen mathematicians from US Universities and full support for about nine US graduate students to participate in this conference at Bangalore. Local support (room and board) for US mathematicians will be provided through a grant from International Center for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS), India. The conference will provide an excellent opportunity for mathematicians and graduate students from the United States to interact with researchers around the world. In particular, it would provide an opportunity to develop cooperation and collaboration with many well-established research institutes in India. These interactions should help US universities to attract strong international graduate students and ultimately strengthen the pool of mathematicians in the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0963910</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vyjayanthi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chari</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chari@math.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kailash</FirstName>
      <LastName>Misra</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>misra@math.ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
