<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Upgrades to Storm Peak Laboratory, A High Elevation Atmospheric Research and Education Station</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>587767</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5). Atmospheric research has been conducted at the Desert Research Institute's Storm Peak Laboratory (SPL) at 3220 m ASL in northwestern Colorado for nearly 30 years. The last major renovation of SPL was done in 1995. This award will fund renovations that will allow air sampling, chemical and biological measurements under up-to-date conditions in warm and cold laboratories. A chemistry laboratory with laminar flow benches and chemical hood will meet current and future needs for preparation of aerosol filters, cloud water and snow samples. Cyberinfrastructure will be improved by upgrading SPL's internet connection to a high-bandwidth, direct microwave connection. Expanded capabilities for atmospheric sampling will be enabled through construction of five new air-handling manifolds that will allow contamination free collection of natural, anthropogenic, and biogenic aerosols and gases under well characterized aerodynamic conditions. A climate-control system will be added to ensure proper functioning of temperature-sensitive instruments. The proposed improvements will transform science at SPL by enhancing the ability to conduct atmospheric research and creating new opportunities in atmospheric biogeochemistry for research and research training.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SPL's remote continental location, year-round access, and extensive instrumental facilities allow measurement in the free atmosphere by scientists from the Desert Research Institute, eight national laboratories, and nineteen other universities in the U.S. and Europe. Research activities at SPL always involve participation by undergraduate and graduate students and post-doctoral fellows. SPL hosts atmospheric science field courses from a multitude of universities for both undergraduate and graduate students. In 2009, SPL hosted 43 undergraduate, graduate, and high school students via field courses. These classes give students experience in all facets of atmospheric science, from development of the research proposal to experiment and project planning plus final reporting. The renovations will expand the scope and focus of research conducted at SPL and thus provide additional opportunities for field training.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount>587767</ARRAAmount>
    <AwardID>0963558</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Obrist</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>daniel.obrist@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCubbin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ian.mccubbin@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/02/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lowenthal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dougl@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCubbin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ian.mccubbin@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/02/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Duane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Duane.Moser@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anna Gannet</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hallar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gannet.hallar@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/02/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Nevada System of Higher Education, Desert Research Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7756737444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2215 Raggio Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9155</Code>
      <Text>ACADEMIC RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTU</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6890</Code>
      <Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
