<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2010 Gordon Research Conference on the Biology Post-Transcriptional Gene Regulation to be held July 18 through July 23, 2010; Newport, R.I.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan Porter Ridley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on "The Biology of Post-Transcriptional Gene Regulation" will be held at Salve Regina University in Newport, Rhode Island, from July 18th to July 23rd, 2010. This meeting is the fourth in a GRC series that has been held every other year since 2004. The goal of this series is the elucidation of the fundamental mechanisms and regulation of RNA biogenesis. The emphasis is on post-transcriptional transactions involving the generation and metabolism of mRNA, but this extends to transcriptional coupling, and to factors involved in translation and its control, including tRNA and non-coding (e.g., micro) RNAs. Representing key areas of post-transcriptional gene regulation, the speakers will include a number of internationally known experts in this field, along with more junior speakers chosen on the basis of the content of their submitted abstracts. Approximately 150 participants are expected for the five-day meeting. The program will consist of nine morning or evening sessions that broadly address cutting-edge issues in the areas of coupling between transcription and RNA processing; genomics and evolution of RNA-processing signals and factors; RNA splicing catalysis, fidelity, and regulation; RNA turnover, including nonsense-mediated mRNA decay; RNA transport and localization; non-coding RNA; translational control; and RNA-protein interactions. In addition, four small poster sessions will enable all participants to contribute to, and learn about, these topics. Free early-afternoon and late-evening periods in the relatively isolated summer setting of Salve Regina University should stimulate productive, informal discussions among established and more junior investigators, postdoctoral trainees, and graduate students from the U.S. and abroad. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Gordon Research Conference has a unique format that brings together sets of researchers - graduate students, post-doctoral fellows, principal investigators at all career stages, grant administrators, scientists from the pharmaceutical and publishing industries who, despite converging interests, have only infrequent opportunities to meet as a group. The resulting intellectual cross-fertilization will help define critical areas and thus help propel this field forward. Understanding the basic mechanisms of post-transcriptional gene regulation is essential for a full understanding of the organization, function, and evolution of genomes. Speakers for this conference include 17 females and five underrepresented minorities. The selection of attendees from the pool of applicants will employ the principles of affirmative action with respect to minorities, women, and junior scientists. Funds from the National Science Foundation will support the attendance of young investigators working in U.S. laboratories, including graduate students, post-doctoral fellows, and beginning principal investigators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0964990</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ares</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ares@biology.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lynne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maquat</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Lynne_Maquat@urmc.rochester.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
