<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Studies of Supersolid Phenomena in Solid Helium</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniele Finotello</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>****NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most exciting recent discoveries in condensed matter physics has been the observation of the so-called "supersolid" state at temperatures only a few tenths of a degree above absolute zero. This supersolid state has the remarkable property that a fraction of a helium solid can actually pass through itself as a frictionless flow provide the temperature is low enough. This property of the supersolid is counterintuitive and is at odds with our instinctive concept of a solid. The supersolid may be another example of a superfluid system to take its place beside the previously know superfluids; superfluid 4He and superfluid 3He, superconducting electrons, and the superfluids observed in low density trapped atomic gases. One of the most important questions that must be addressed is whether the supersolid phenomena thus far observed is actual evidence for a true superfluid state in solid helium. This research project will address this question on two fronts. The approach asks the question, does the superfluid obey superfluid hydrodynamics? The second approach will examine the nature of the phase transition to the supersolid state by an ultra sensitive heat capacity measurement utilizing state-of-the-art superconducting technology. These projects will involve several undergraduate students and will give them a head start in scientific research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The recent discovery of a "Supersolid" phase in solid 4He at temperatures below 200 mK by the Eunsong Kim and Moses Chan provides the realization of a prediction made more than a quarter of a century ago. The initial suggestion for a supersolid state in crystalline 4He is based on the possibility that Bose-Einstein condensation might occur in solid helium at sufficiently low temperatures. It is crucial to establish whether or not the supersolid state represents a new type of superfluid. This individual investigator award supports an attempt to clarify this issue using several approaches. First, the hydrodynamics of the supersolid will be examined in non-circular geometries where the predicted behavior based on ordinary superfluid hydrodynamics is clear. Second, the question of an actual phase transition to the supersolid state will be addressed through measurement of the possible heat capacity anomaly associated with the transition utilizing ultra sensitive SQUID technology. This project is expected to involve two undergraduate students who should profit greatly from working in a fast evolving area at the current forefront of condensed matter research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0965698</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reppy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdr13@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
