<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Ivy Adhesive Nanoparticles for Biomedical Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>328792</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Athanassios Sambanis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0965877&lt;br/&gt;Zhang&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research is to study properties of organic nanoparticles secreted from English ivy (Hedera helix), and develop a nature-based organic nanoparticle for biomedical applications. It was recently discovered by the PI that ivy secretes nanoparticles for surface affixing. The adhesive force from the combination of the ivy nanoparticles and the mucopolysaccharide secreted from ivy has been demonstrated in the literature to be one of the largest forces per area in natural surface adhesion. By characterizing the role and discovering the chemical structure of the ivy adhesive nanoparticles, we will develop a nature-based nanoparticle for medical adhesive. Previous research undertaken by the PI regarding ivy nanopartciles has led to a prototype method to isolate the ivy nanoparticles, and to determine the adhesive strength of the nanoparticles using atomic force microscopy. These studies indicated that the adhesive had properties that could be translated into a nature-based nanoparticle for medical adhesive. This proposal aims to advance the preliminary studies, to completely characterize the nanoparticles, to understand toxicity of the nanoparticles and to investigate a prototype approach for synthesizing the ivy nanoparticles. The specific aims of this research are to 1) isolate nanoparticles from aerial rootlets of English ivy, 2) characterize the adhesive properties and toxicity of the ivy nanoparticles for medical applications, and 3) investigate a prototype approach for synthesizing the ivy nanoparticles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: A great amount of research is currently being undertaken on the use of nanoparticles for a variety of biomedical applications including targeted drug delivery, molecular imaging and high strength biomaterials. By biomimicking the role of ivy nanoparticles for adhesive, this research introduces the first nature-based organic nanoparticle that can be used for a variety of biomedical applications including medical adhesive, sunscreen cancer prevention and targeted drug delivery. At present, nearly all nanoparticles synthesized are metal nanoparticles that have inherent toxicity in mammalian systems. A biological nanoparticle will be able to avoid much of the toxicity associated with metal-based nanoparticles and expand the application of nanoparticles to medicine. In addition, this research will provide a protocol approach for isolating nanoparticles from a variety of biological species including ivy, sundew and marine mussels. Finally, this research will contribute to the development of nanoparticle enhanced polymers for high strength nanocomposites, and provide useful information on a biological method for creating nanocomposite for strong adhesives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This research has broad impacts on biomaterial design through biomimetics, naturebased organic nanoparticle manufacturing and biomedical applications of nanoparticles for skin cancer prevention as well as drug delivery. Pharmaceutical fields have long recognized the importance of observing natural processes, to find the simplest and the most efficient way to develop drugs. Biomedical engineering is turning to biomimetics for finding ways to synthesize and develop complex nanostructure and devices for medicine. The fields benefitted by this research include material sciences, molecular biology, plant biology, bioengineering and nanomedicine. The results of this research will be used to extend our departmental curricula into nanomedicine and biomimetics for biomedical engineering innovation, and to be integrated into one of the core biomedical engineering graduate courses entitled nano bio-systems and biomimetics. This project will also be used as a foundation for local educational outreach in middle and high schools, and to draw interest into interdisciplinary sciences at early ages. Already these studies have encouraged both graduate students and undergraduates working in the labs to take interdisciplinary courses. We expect to develop an interdisciplinary curriculum across the university with the goal of training an interdisciplinary core of researchers. The PI's lab commits strongly to minority student training.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0965877</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maozi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maozi_liu@agilent.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mingjun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zhang.4882@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neal</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stewart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nealstewart@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
