<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Ultra-low Loading Platinum Alloy Cathode Catalysts for PEM Fuel Cells: Theoretical and Experimental Studies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ram Gupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0966956&lt;br/&gt;Popov&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will establish a scientific and engineering basis for the development of proton exchange membrane (PEM) fuel cell cathode catalysts having ultra-low Pt loadings and increased durability for the oxygen reduction reaction (ORR). These catalysts are expected to have fast reaction rates and good stability that are essential for developing next generation fuel cells for sustainable energy systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hybrid cathode catalysts (HCC) will be synthesized using a carbon composite catalyst (CCC) with an ultra-low loading of Pt. The CCC has a high content of active pyridinic nitrogen sites, and will be used as a support for ultra-low loading of platinum instead of carbon black, which is currently used in the commercial catalysts. Besides its own contribution to the overall catalyst activity, the noble metal free CCC will enhance the activity of Pt and Pt alloys (e.g., Pt-Co/CCC, Pt-Fe/CCC, Pt-Ni/CCC) through synergistic effects. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A first-principles mathematical model and density functional theory (DFT) calculations will be used to help understand the oxygen reduction kinetics on the HCC catalysts. Structure-property relationships will be established using a wide range of electrochemical and surface characterization techniques. These studies will create a framework for the development of novel synthesis procedures to prepare highly active and stable catalysts for ORR with ultra-low Pt loading. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the world's low platinum reserves (30,000 tons of unproven reserves), the hybrid cathode catalyst (HCC) proposed in this study has the potential to reduce both the cost of the PEM fuel cell and consumption of this precious metal. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Interdisciplinary courses at both the graduate and undergraduate levels in quantum chemistry &amp; material surface characterization, as well as materials science &amp; electrochemical engineering, will be developed. Programs will be developed to accelerate the transition from passive learners to scientists and engineers by training students in group-based problem solving, helping students acquire technical and time management skills, and by challenging them to complete a project related to electrocatalysts for oxygen reduction. In addition, the program will increase community awareness of next-generation energy technology and career opportunities, and promote the involvement of students from under-represented groups in these activities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0966956</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Prabhu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ganesan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ganesan@cec.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heyden</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>heyden@engr.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Branko</FirstName>
      <LastName>Popov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>popov@engr.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/16/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>046E</Code>
      <Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
