<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Model and Testing of Enhanced Cutaneous Perfusion to Manipulate Heat Convection between Skin and the Body Core</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>324995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sumanta Acharya</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0966998&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Diller&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research involves the design of novel devices and development of new models to take advantage of a recently observed phenomenon capable of rapidly reducing body core temperatures. The research builds upon observations that arteriovenous anastomoses (AVAs) in glabrous skin become mechanically distended when a small negative pressure (about 40 mm Hg) is applied to the body. When negative pressure is utilized in conjunction with surface cooling of the skin, body core temperatures can be rapidly lowered due to increased blood flow rates between the skin and the body core. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The intellectual focus of this project is to build a predictive model of heat transfer between the skin and body core via enhanced blood perfusion through distended AVAs. The model will be used to design devices and identify appropriate protocols for manipulation of human thermoregulatory function. Specifically, the complex AVA control mechanisms will be measured and characterized by way of human testing and the corresponding constitutive models will be incorporated into the Wissler thermoregulatory model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The broader focus of the research is to develop a new technology that can rapidly reduce core temperature from hyperthermic (heat stress) states for industrial, military and athletic needs and from normothermia to hypothermic states for medical needs (therapeutic hypothermia). The research may also lead to new treatments of stroke, cardiac arrest and concussion. Outreach to local minority-serving high schools will be a key component of the activity. New educational materials will be developed in conjunction with the research and will be disseminated in the archival learning science and engineering education literature. Experimental and modeling outcomes of the research will also be incorporated into supplemental learning materials of a new biotransport text.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0966998</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Diller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kdiller@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/06/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
