<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Illinois State University Computer Science/Information Systems (CS/IS) Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599843</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Yvette Weatherton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>To help address the nationwide decline in enrollment in computer science and information systems (CS/IS) programs, this S-STEM program is 1) providing 33 scholarships (18 full scholarships of up to 4 years, and 15 transfer scholarships) to academically-talented, financially-disadvantaged students majoring in CS/IS or in mathematics with a CS/IS minor; 2) enhancing the educational experience and increasing retention among the S-STEM scholars; and 3) assisting the S-STEM scholars in finding employment opportunities. The program components are thus being implemented to foster a transformative R-E-P process (Recruitment, Education/Retention, Placement) that supports the S-STEM scholars while building on existing community-academic-industrial ties. The project in particular is building on strong connections with the Chicago Public School system to recruit scholars from amongst a large urban population that includes students from low-income communities and groups that are underrepresented in CS/IS. Recruitment activities include workshops at the high schools and on-campus open houses held throughout the year. Support structures for scholars include small-sized course sections, tutoring centers that provide "program debugging" assistance for all programming-related courses, numerous community-building activities, optional (but encouraged) research experiences and internships, special seminars and symposia, sponsored visits of scholars to information technology departments of local employers, and assistance with job placement. The project's evaluation plan addresses specific objectives and outcome measures that are related to the overall goals of recruitment, education, retention, and placement, and is being used to inform the process of developing a strong, transformative program. Results achieved through the scholarship program are being presented to the CS/IS community at national and international meetings, and published in professional journals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0966226</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Saad</FirstName>
      <LastName>El-Zanati</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>saad@ilstu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hunter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whunter@ilstu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pruthikrai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mahatanankoon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmahata@ilstu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/10/2009</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Illinois State University</Name>
      <CityName>Normal</CityName>
      <ZipCode>617901000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3094382528</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 S Fell Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
