<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BiSn/CNT Nanocomposite as Novel Thermal Interface Material</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0966908&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Chen&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Thermal interface material (TIM) is used to bond electronic devices to heat spreaders for thermal management purposes. Desirable attributes of TIM include a low melting temperature, necessary for device protection during bonding, good bonding strength, and low thermal resistance. This research will develop a BiSn/carbon nanotube composite material to meet these design requirements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: An electrochemical deposition process will be developed for which uniformly-distributed carbon nanotubes and good interfacial bonding can be achieved. The BiSn/carbon nanotube material will be blended to meet the design requirements and to tailor the coefficient of thermal expansion so as to promote durability of the bond. Experimental approaches will be taken to measure the resultant properties of BiSn/carbon nanotube composite material. Both microscopic observations and quantum calculations will be carried out to understand the pertinent thermal conduction mechanisms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The proposed bonding material and method can improve the thermal management of advanced electronics including but not limited to integrated circuitry, power electronics, and various laser systems. The research will be integrated into both undergraduate and graduate courses. Graduate and undergraduate students will be involved in the research. Existing K-12 outreach programs will be leveraged while a new summer camp for high school teachers will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0966908</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Quanfang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>qchen@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>065E</Code>
      <Text>Radiation heat transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
