<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanoscale (Sub-Wavelength) Rolled-Up Quantum Dot Lasers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>354270</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to design, epitaxially grow, fabricate, characterize, and analyze optically pumped and electrically injected subwavelength nanoscale rolled-up In(Ga)As quantum dot 1.3µm lasers that can demonstrate ultra low threshold (&lt; 100µA) at room temperature. The inherent advantage offered by quantum dot tunnel injection heterostructure for nanoscale laser operation, such as large gain, low threshold and high quantum efficiency will also be investigated. The transformative impact of this research is the availability of a low power and compact laser for interconnects and for spectroscopy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is the first demonstration of nanoscale rolled-up subwavelength sized laser on GaAs, that can be optically or electrically pumped. Demonstration of a reliable room temperature nanoscale laser on GaAs/InP is also transformative and is considered as a milestone in optoelectronics. The rolled-up technique and associated device fabrication are more simple than other techniques for nanoscale lasers that are currently being explored.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the proposed research include social, economic and educational benefits. Ultra-low power light sources reduce energy consumption and help in transmitting information efficiency and at faster rates. The interdisciplinary nature of the program will provide an excellent training ground for graduate and undergraduate students - our future work force in several critical areas. Training of women and underrepresented minorities in summer programs in the general areas of optoelectronics and lighting will be a priority. K-12 outreach will include demonstrations during visits and creating a broader awareness for science and mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0968346</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pallab</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bhattacharya</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pkb@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
