<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Aspects Of Non-Local Dynamics In String Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marc Sher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-local dynamics is an emerging interest in physics across many disciplines, from condensed matter physics to particle physics to quantum gravity. This project explores the effects of non-local dynamics as realized in the context of a certain class of string theory models of particular interest to cosmology. The string theory embedding of these models assures that the exotic frameworks encountered are physically and logically self-consistent. Yet, such non-local systems remain poorly understood, with many counter-intuitive features and apparent paradoxes. This project aims to unravel general features of non-local dynamics as they arise in this class of string theory models, and apply these results to modeling the primordial plasma of the universe. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project also involves undergraduate education as an integral part. This is achieved through a two-pronged approach: (1) through the direct participation of undergraduate students in the research within a program that has already proven to be highly successful in involving undergraduate seniors in string theory research; and (2) through the development of a senior-level undergraduate course and textbook to help prepare students for competitive graduate programs in theoretical physics. The project also includes a multi-pronged community outreach component involving a web-based instructional resource, and a public lecture series on current topics at the frontier of theoretical physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0968726</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vatche</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sahakian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sahakian@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Harvey Mudd College</Name>
      <CityName>CLAREMONT</CityName>
      <ZipCode>917115901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9096218121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>301 Platt Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
