<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Security and Software Engineering Research Center (SSERC)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>228000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0968959 Ball State University (BSU); Wayne Zage &lt;br/&gt;0968939 Iowa State University (ISU); Doug Jacobson&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this proposal is to start a new I/UCRC "Security and Software Engineering Research Center (S2ERC)" with a focus on improving the management of the software engineering process, the productivity of software engineers, and the security, quality and timeliness of software engineering products. The lead of the proposed Center will be Ball State University (BSU) with a site location at Iowa State University (ISU).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center (S2ERC) plans to investigate integrated methods of engineering practical software systems that are able to meet emerging security requirements in addition to encompassing traditional software engineering objectives. This goal is of great importance to both industry and government in order for them to be able to confidently deploy real-world software systems that meet their mission goals even in the face of a broad range of security attacks. The proposal introduces a high-level framework to capture and guide the research focus of the Center on issues germane to effective software engineering techniques as well as high security assurance. The S2ERC researchers include national prize winners, NSF Career Award winners, conference best paper winners, IEEE Fellows, journal editors and distinguished professors. The collaborations with various prospective company members have suggested many promising research initiatives for the proposed Center. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center will be an intellectually nurturing environment where discovery and understanding is advanced to its faculty, students and prospective members. The proposed Center will provide faculty and students the unique opportunity to work on research teams in real world security and software engineering applications. The proposed semi-annual S2ERC showcases will provide an excellent opportunity for all the students to interact with industrial partners and get a first-hand understanding of emerging challenges and opportunities in their careers. The faculty and students will be a programmatically diverse group from departments such as CS, EE, Industrial Engineering, Management, and Systems Engineering. The diversity of the researchers is enhanced further by women faculty.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0968939</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jacobson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dougj@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/21/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/13/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Daniels</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>daniels@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/13/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/30/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zambreno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zambreno@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5761</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1049</Code>
      <Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>122E</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
