<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: LIGO Detector Characterization and Optical Scatter Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Most of humanity's astronomical knowledge has been obtained through electromagnetic radiation. Gravitational waves, one of the most dramatic predictions of Einstein's theory of general relativity, will provide an entirely new way to observe the Universe. This award supports research by the Gravitational-Wave Group at California State University Fullerton (CSUF) contributing to the search for gravitational waves with the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO). The research will focus on i) improving LIGO's sensitivity to transient astronomical events such as black hole collisions and supernovae explosions through a reduction of non-stationary noise in the detector data, and ii) expediting the success of Advanced LIGO by studying the optical properties of samples of its core and auxiliary optics. These projects will have significant student involvement and help train the next generation of physicists. CSUF is a hispanic serving institution. The research activities funded by this award will provide enhanced opportunities to students traditionally underrepresented in scientific research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0970147</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
      <LastName>Smith</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>josmith@fullerton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2010</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State University-Fullerton Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Fullerton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>928313014</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6572782106</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1121 North State College Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1252</Code>
      <Text>LIGO RESEARCH SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7483</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
