<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Stress Distributions Determined in Short T2 BioMaterials by MRI-based Finite Strain and Mathematical Modeling</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to use a combination of medical imaging and mathematical modeling to determine and characterize the mechanics of biomaterials. Medical imaging modalities, such as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), can noninvasively visualize internal strains throughout the volume of materials and tissues. Mathematical modeling extends the strain data to determine spatially-dependent stresses and material properties. Studies conducted under this award will determine the extent to which rapid MRI techniques can characterize the mechanics of a broad range of biomaterials that, in particular, exhibit short spin-spin (T2) relaxation times and are challenging to image. Mathematical modeling will further be developed to relate strains and stresses through the incorporation of MRI data with mixture theory and nonlinear constitutive relations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, these studies would significantly advance the characterization of materials and enhance the design of novel bio-inspired materials. The knowledge gained from results would additionally enable the evaluation of tissue damage and degeneration, and the characterization of tissue remodeling and implanted biomaterial integration. Research will be disseminated through publications and presentations. Integrated education and outreach activities arise as a natural and creative outgrowth of mechanics studies, and are designed to provide an interactive and problem-solving approach toward learning. Undergraduate courses in tissue mechanics will be augmented with new imaging-based modules. Emphasizing education and outreach activities will promote higher education in science and engineering from an early age through interactions with the Indianapolis Children's Museum.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1100554</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Corey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Neu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>corey.neu@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nauman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>enauman@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7479</Code>
      <Text>Biomechanics &amp; Mechanobiology</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>027E</Code>
      <Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>028E</Code>
      <Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
