<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Modulation and Statistical Detection Methods for Underwater Acoustic Communications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>103164</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zhi Tian</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to develop and explore a new generation of modulation and statistical detection methods for Underwater Acoustic Communications (UWA) communications. The proposed approach is based on a class of filter bank multicarrier (FBMC) techniques, a statistical detection method, and novel channel estimation algorithm that will enable substantially more robust means of modulation and detection in the presence of the doubly spread ocean acoustic environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The following 4 elements summarize the intellectual of the proposal: (i) Development of channel models that will facilitate an in-depth study of the proposed methods during the course of this project and also in future studies; (ii) Development and study of signal processing techniques, including novel channel estimation algorithms, Doppler compensation methods, and high performance detection algorithms; (iii) Design of channel codes that are tuned to the characteristics of UWA channels and the FBMC modulation techniques; (iv) Extension of the designs to multiple-input multiple-output channels. The proposed algorithms will be tested with data collected during underwater acoustic field experiments of opportunity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will contribute to significant advancement in Underwater Acoustic Communications. The results of the proposed research will be directly integrated into coursework at both the involved Universities. Results from this effort will be broadly disseminated through publication and presentations. Online resources that will make the contributions accessible to a broad audience will be developed. Research results will also be shared with high-school students who attend the annual Engineering Open Houses on both campuses. Advanced undergraduate students involved in the project will attend the Summer Student Fellow program at WHOI where they gain practical experience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1102156</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Preisig</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpreisig@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
      <CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
