<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Leveraging SUNY LSAMP to Build Better STEM Pathways and Prepare Global STEM Scholars (Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation - Senior Level Alliance)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2521815</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Martha L. James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The State University of New York at Stony Brook (SUNY-Stony Brook), lead institution for the SUNY Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (SUNY LSAMP) will leverage existing infrastructure, networks, and lessons learned to build better pathways to increased student preparation in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) disciplines targeted to historically underrepresented minority populations, especially first generation college students. Recruitment emphasis will be placed on the community college to 4-year college transition during the project period. SUNY-LSAMP will also increase the number of LSAMP students prepared for entry into STEM graduate programs and ultimately the STEM workforce, particularly the professoriate. The alliance will engage in building better STEM pathways by:&lt;br/&gt;--working to support seamless transitions at critical junctures (high school to college, lower division to upper division, 2- year to 4-year, UG to graduate, graduate to professional) with special emphasis on increasing and improving transfers from 2 to 4 -year colleges.&lt;br/&gt;--providing innovative integrated academic and disciplinary socialization experiences for historically underrepresented minority STEM students designed to encourage and then support them in undertaking a STEM undergraduate/graduate course of study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Additionally, the project will prepare global scholars by implementing new activities to strengthen the alliance and individual institutions and promote transformative change at the local, state and national level by;&lt;br/&gt;--continuing to increase other sources of financial support for SUNY-LSAMP so that the program can continue after NSF funding ends; and,&lt;br/&gt;--taking a leadership role in key New York State initiatives aimed at reforming UREP STEM curriculum and pedagogy, disseminating best practices in UREP STEM education, improving transfer success and increasing and improving international research opportunities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1102005</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stacie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nunes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nuness@newpaltz.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Letitia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thomas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lthomas@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stanley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>samuel.stanley@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Teoh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hteoh@verizon.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ferguson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>David.Ferguson@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9133</Code>
      <Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7204</Code>
      <Text>DoE-NSF LABORATORY FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
