<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Model for Improved Technological Education in Northern New Mexico.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>873985</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Yvette Weatherton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of New Mexico-Los Alamos (UNMLA), in partnership with Los Alamos National Laboratory (LANL) and Santa Fe Community College, is redesigning the Applied Technologies (AT) associate's program to include degree concentrations in electromechanical, solar, and nano-technology as an effort to prepare more highly skilled technicians to support the region's emerging need for high-tech employees in these areas. This critical need is given special urgency based on the State of New Mexico's vision and plan for the development of a new "green" economy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project involves an equipment overhaul, in addition to rigorous curriculum and instructional improvements in the three content areas noted above. Targeting high school students and teachers, the project articulates a career pathway for underrepresented students that leads to participation in advanced technical education, as well as opportunities at four year institutions . Problem-based learning incorporating engineering design principles and an interdisciplinary thematic approach guide the strategy for teaching and learning. The project also supplements instruction with authentic internship experiences at supporting companies and national laboratories. A total of 65 students will have moved through the program at its completion. The project takes advantage of UNMLA's pilot faculty share program supported by LANL and Santa Fe Community College as a means to build institutional capacity and sustain the efforts of the work. Thus, this important initiative serves as a model for revising and enhancing a pre-existing degree program, specifically targeting underrepresented student populations. The support and commitments at the state and local level ensure the efforts to build capacity to meet the demands of the participating institutions and the growing needs of the new economy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1104286</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gioia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gioiaj@lanl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maxwell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmaxwell@lanl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bernardin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bernardin@lanl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>d.davis@laschools.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Irina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alvestad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>irina@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
