<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Investigation of Strongly Correlated Electron Behavior in Rare Earth Related Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>255000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>********Technical Abstract********&lt;br/&gt;This project will support experimental research in the strongly correlated electron phenomena in rare earth related materials. These phenomena arise from a subtle interplay between competing interactions, either electronic or magnetic, which can be controlled through tuning the experimental parameters such as temperature, magnetic field, chemical composition, and reduced dimensionality. The primary focus of this research is on the effect of magnetism on unconventional superconductivity in the filled skutterudite substitution system Pr1-xNdxOs4Sb12, the investigation of the electronic structures of near-by compounds NdOs4Sb12 and CeOs4Sb12 for understanding the quantum critical behavior and superconducting pairing mechanism in PrOs4Sb12, and the effect of reduced dimensionality on magnetism in gadolinium and neodymium nanoparticles. Through the synthesis of high quality specimens and the establishment of transport and thermodynamical properties of these rare earth materials, they can be used as model systems to probe the localized and itinerant nature of the electron states and test the existing theories for strongly correlated electron phenomena. The research experience and practical placement provided by this project will help undergraduate and MS program students pursue Ph. D degrees and start their careers in industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;*******Non-Technical Abstract*******&lt;br/&gt;This project will support material science research of rare-earth related materials at an undergraduate institution. The primary focus of this research is on the synthesis and characterization of superconducting materials and magnetic nanoparticles, with the goal of understanding their underlying mechanisms. These materials promise useful technical applications in diverse fields such as energy conservation, energy storage, digital information storage, and medical imaging. This project will allow direct participation by undergraduate and MS-program students in the experiments, giving them hands-on experience at the early stage of their academic life. The opportunities provided through this work will encourage students to pursue higher education and careers in the STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1104544</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pei-Chun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ho</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pcho@csufresno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California State University-Fresno Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Fresno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>937261852</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5592780840</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4910 N. Chestnut Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1710</Code>
      <Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7644</Code>
      <Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
