<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Cybersecurity Camps</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is increasing the awareness and interest of high school students in the exciting and emerging field of information security and promoting their involvement in the next steps towards an educational career pathway. Activities focus primarily on program development and improvement, and curriculum and educational materials development. The project builds on activities of Cyber Watch. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The project is developing and implementing the following strategies: (a) providing outreach and resources to local high schools, (b) offering high school students Cybersecurity Camps at the college, (c) providing and supporting College CIS Program mentors for students, and (d) sponsoring culminating Cyberdefense Competitions. High school students are being exposed to information security scenarios through hands-on activities and cybersecurity camps and competitions at the college. Bringing high school students and educators into the information security arena is broadening participation and promoting understanding of this critical field. It is strengthening relationships between local county high schools and the college. Student participation is an integral component to this project, and peer mentoring is foundational to activities in the Cybersecurity Camps and Cyberdefense Competitions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project is increasing the depth of understanding and skill level among students preparing for information security jobs or other jobs in information technology that need knowledge of information security. This project is advocating for females and underrepresented populations to be involved in the camps and competitions and to consider information security as a possible career. Materials and developed for the high school cybersecurity camps and competitions are being made available to other institutions. Information is being disseminated both state-wide and nationally. This project is helping to support national security by cultivating an interest in high-school students who can further their education in information security and become part of the pipeline to a well-equipped workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1104192</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Corrinne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sande</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>csande@whatcom.ctc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Maier</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lmaier@whatcom.ctc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>05/10/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
      <LastName>Walker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwalker@whatcom.ctc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Whatcom Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>982269050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3603833235</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>237 W. Kellogg Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
