<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Successful Academic and Employment Pathways in Advanced Technologies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1196790</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Connie K. Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In light of the growing need for highly trained workers in engineering technology, a collaboration of higher education institutions in Florida is examining the progression of students from high schools into advanced technology programs at community colleges and into the workforce. Researchers from the Departments of Sociology and Anthropology at the University of South Florida are teaming up with the Florida Advanced Technological Center (FLATE) at Hillsborough Community College, Polk State College, and the State College of Florida to examine student pathways from high school through community college to industry. The mixed method study integrates secondary data analysis of student-level longitudinal data from the Florida Department of Education PK-20 Education Data Warehouse and state employment data with ethnographic case studies. The quasi-experimental research study with case studies is designed to answer three overarching questions. Who enrolls in engineering technology programs at community colleges out of high school? How do students become engineering technology graduates? How do engineering technology students benefit from enrollment and associate degree attainment? The study contributes to a growing body of knowledge on advanced technician education and to the overall mission of the Advanced Technological Education Program by (1) increasing understanding of recruitment and pathways into engineering technology programs; (2) providing information to improve the education of engineering technicians; (3) discovering promising practices that increase the visibility of engineering technology programs at community colleges; and (4) providing information about practices that produce qualified science and engineering technicians to meet workforce demands.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1104214</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Borman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>borman@cas.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/26/2013</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tyson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wtyson@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boyette</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mboyette3@hccfl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lakshmi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jayaram</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ljayaram@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2013</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7412</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1032</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
