<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>West Coast Algebraic Topology Summer School</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS-1106865&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Dev Sinha, Ralph Cohen&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal organizers will be program organizers for a&lt;br/&gt;one-week summer school program in algebraic topology, to be&lt;br/&gt;hosted at the University of Oregon. This summer school will bring&lt;br/&gt;thirty graduate students and early-career mathematicians together&lt;br/&gt;for an introduction to an area in topology which is ripe for&lt;br/&gt;investigation, and whose techniques will inform and inspire&lt;br/&gt;developments throughout topology. This summer school will use a&lt;br/&gt;unique blend of pedagogical tools, combining elements which have&lt;br/&gt;been successful in other settings. Younger researchers will be&lt;br/&gt;involved with both organizing and giving talks. Attendees will be&lt;br/&gt;encouraged to work problems, fill in background, and do reading&lt;br/&gt;together in addition to attending lectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The West Coast Topology Summer School continues a series that&lt;br/&gt;began in summer 2010 and will strengthen the knowledge base of&lt;br/&gt;topologists and others who use topology and build a cohort of&lt;br/&gt;junior researchers familiar with recent developments in the&lt;br/&gt;subject. The program organizers of the Summer School are the&lt;br/&gt;principal investigators, together with Alejandro Adem of the&lt;br/&gt;University of British Columbia and the Pacific Institute of&lt;br/&gt;Mathematical Sciences (PIMS). PIMS is a partner in the project,&lt;br/&gt;which will bring together US--based graduate students, largely&lt;br/&gt;from the western United States, and Canadian graduate students&lt;br/&gt;sponsored by PIMS. In its role as a basic study of shape,&lt;br/&gt;topology has significant ramifications in other areas of&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, from basic counting problems (combinatorics) to&lt;br/&gt;solutions of equations (algebra) to applications and extensions&lt;br/&gt;of the calculus (analysis). More broadly, knowledge of topology&lt;br/&gt;is essential for example in studying the structure of the early&lt;br/&gt;universe, in designing a robot arm with a minimal number of&lt;br/&gt;controllers, and in searching large data sets for meaningful&lt;br/&gt;groupings as successfully done recently for study of breast&lt;br/&gt;cancer. This summer school will strengthen the ties between basic&lt;br/&gt;areas of theoretical mathematics. Mathematicians from&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented backgrounds will be vigorously recruited.&lt;br/&gt;Graduate students and post-docs will gain hands-on experience&lt;br/&gt;with some of the most important developments of contemporary&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, preparing them to be future leaders of the field.&lt;br/&gt;Participants will enlarge their professional networks, which is&lt;br/&gt;especially critical given the geographical distances faced by&lt;br/&gt;mathematicians in the western half of North America. Organizers&lt;br/&gt;and participants will also have the opportunity to reflect upon&lt;br/&gt;the array of pedagogical tools employed, and might employ some&lt;br/&gt;themselves in training graduate students and undergraduates or&lt;br/&gt;reaching out to fellow scientists and the general public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1106865</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ralph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cohen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ralph@math.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dev</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sinha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dps@math.uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
