<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Second Conference on Graduate Education in Physics; January 30-February 1, 2013 at the American Center for Physics in College Park, MD.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports a two-day conference to focus national attention on current issues in graduate education in physics. The conference is organized jointly by the American Physical Society and the American Association of Physics Teachers. The conference will take place at the American Center for Physics in College Park, MD in January 2013, and will bring together about 100 participants including those in a position to implement changes and those in a position to provide informed recommendations for change. The conference is motivated partly by the success of the first conference on graduate education in physics in January 2008. The topics to be discussed at the conference include curriculum; exam/exam structure; climate and diversity; admissions; advising and mentoring; non-academic careers; developing "soft" skills including oral and written communication; team building and leadership; multi-disciplinary coursework and degrees; outcome assessment of graduate programs; and shaping a holistic and effective graduate education experience. The conference will continue the conversation started four years ago and give the physics community an opportunity to brainstorm ideas about graduate education so that graduate programs in physics can continuously improve to maintain their world class excellence. In addition, the conference will provide a forum to learn about the progress made in various graduate programs since the first conference and find ways to identify, adapt, and implement best practices within local constraints.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1107258</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hodapp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hodapp@aps.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marvin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marshak</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marshak@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chandralekha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Singh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>clsingh@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Physical Society</Name>
      <CityName>College Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207403841</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3012093220</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Physics Ellipse</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
