<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Track 1: Climate Change Scholars at San Francisco State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>197904</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jill L. Karsten</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Climate Change Scholars program is working to increase the number of students completing Bachelor's degree programs at San Francisco State University in fields related to climate change studies, overall, and specifically from underrepresented groups. Climate Change Scholars participate in activities structured around scientific collaboration, academic enrichment, and close mentorship connected to the study of climate change. The Climate Change Scholars are matched with a mentor from the SFSU Climate Change Working Group and participate in a core series of activities intended to build community among the Climate Change Scholars; these mentors help to connect the Scholars to the research world of climate change, with the intent of improving the Scholars' academic success rates. Scholars participate in a variety of required activities that include: frequent contact with and guidance from a faculty mentor; attending a monthly climate change seminar; meeting regularly as a cohort to work on professional development; and, participating in supplemental instruction and tutoring, as appropriate. Scholars are also given special optional opportunities for professional development, such as: living in a science-themed community at SFSU; participating in genuine climate change research and related summer internship experiences; teaching science; and, participating in professional organizations. The SFSU College of Science and Engineering has a rich tradition of supporting meaningful research experiences for undergraduates across all disciplines of science; the Climate Change Scholars will be part of an multidisciplinary group of engaged students and accomplished researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1108347</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hsu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>erichsu@math.sfsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
      <LastName>White</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lwhite@sfsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tendai</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chitewere</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tendai@sfsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Francisco State University</Name>
      <CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>941321722</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4153387090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Holloway Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1697</Code>
      <Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6891</Code>
      <Text>CLIMATE CHANGE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1697</Code>
      <Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
