<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Atmospheric Hydrocarbons at GEOSummit, Greenland, as Tracers for Climate Change, Air Pollution Transport, and Oxidation Chemistry in the Arctic</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>462251</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Ambrose</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This study is a contribution to the Arctic Observing Network (AON). It will undertake 4 years of continuous measurements of atmospheric methane, and non-methane hydrocarbons (NMHC; ethane, ethyne, propane, iso-butane, n-butane, iso-pentane, n-pentane, benzene, toluene) at the Greenland Environmental Observatory at Summit (GEOSummit). An existing monitoring system that has previously been operated at Summit for two seasons will be deployed. This gas chromatography instrument is specifically tailored towards operation at this remote arctic site, as it is fully automated and remotely controllable. This instrument uses a minimal amount of power and does not require cryogen and compressed gas supplies, which make it highly favorable and cost efficient for Summit conditions. A second analytical channel will be added to include monitoring of the important climate gas methane with the same instrument. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merits: This project will deliver 4 years of continuous atmospheric concentration data of methane, with approximately 2 hour time resolution, and nine C2-C7 NMHC at low parts per trillion sensitivity (for NMHC) at Summit. These data will expand upon the previous 2008-2010 NMHC measurements from Summit, and will provide an overall 8 year (with a 2 year gap) record for these gases. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: These measurements will be highly complementary to the NMHC monitoring within the NOAA-INSTAAR global flask sampling program, which, for the past 7 years, has provided bi-weekly NMHC data for five arctic sites. The much higher resolution in-situ data from this study will add value to the interpretation of the NMHC flask records. By applying chemical transport modeling, the in-situ data will allow researchers to decipher air pollution transport into the Arctic and contributions from different emission source region contributions at lower latitudes. The methane and NMHC monitoring will make a pivotal contribution to the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) Global Atmospheric Watch (GAW) Volatile Organic Compound (VOC) program, as it will provide the only high time resolution in-situ NMHC site in the Arctic. This observational activity will also be presented in class room teaching and seminars and be incorporated in INSTAAR?s outreach program, i.e. on the ?Ozone and Snow? educational website. This project will promote a new collaboration between INSTAAR at the University of Colorado and atmospheric researchers at EMPA, Switzerland.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1108391</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Detlev</FirstName>
      <LastName>Helmig</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>detlev.helmig@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5293</Code>
      <Text>AON IMPLEMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5219</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC SYSTEM SCIENCE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
