<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Comparative genomic analysis of the Compositae, focusing on Carthamus tinctorius L. (safflower)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Scheiner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Studies of crop domestication have the potential to provide insight into the genetic basis of agronomically-important traits. Comparative analyses further afford researchers the opportunity to investigate whether or not similar traits have arisen in different crop species as a result of selection upon the same or different genes. The Compositae, which is the largest family of flowering plants, contains numerous important crop species. To date, much of the crop-related research in this family has focused on sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.) and lettuce (Lactuca sativa L.). The research outlined herein seeks to utilize cutting-edge DNA sequencing technologies to develop the first high-density genetic map of safflower, (Carthamus tinctorius L.), which is a third crop species within this family. This map will facilitate subsequent comparative genomic analyses between safflower, sunflower, and lettuce, thereby enabling an investigation of the potential for parallel genetic changes across three crop species. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Beyond providing fundamental insights into the genetic basis of crop-related traits, this work will provide valuable molecular tools for the safflower breeding community, both in developed and developing worlds. In addition to contributing to the training of a female graduate student, this work will also provide University of Georgia undergraduates with hands-on research experience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1110350</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Burke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmburke@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pearl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pearlsa110@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
