<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Testing the Pleistocene aggregate island complex (PAIC) model of diversification in co-distributed avian lineages</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14866</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maureen M. Kearney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An intense concentration of biodiversity, combined with complex yet well-understood geologic and climatic histories, make the Philippines an ideal system for phylogeographic studies. This research will evaluate the relative effects of Pleistocene climate changes, geological history, and complex topography on the process of diversification in a suite of island bird species. The project integrates diverse sources of data, including mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences, earth history data, spatial modeling, ongoing field research, and study of museum collections. The results of this study will broadly apply to questions of how periodic climate-associated sea level changes influenced diversification and the geographic distributions of organisms in island systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Philippines is considered a "megadiverse country" and a "global conservation hotspot", yet traditional recognition of bird species has greatly underestimated diversity and obscured biogeographic patterns. Gene flow estimates from this study will provide an interesting new perspective on species limits across an island archipelago, and will likely elucidate novel evolutionary patterns and highlight under-appreciated centers of avian endemism in the Philippines. The project will also provide opportunities for undergraduates at the University of Kansas to gain experience in biodiversity research techniques, including DNA sequencing and analysis, and to develop research skills such as scientific writing and public presentation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1110619</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moyle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>moyle@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hosner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hosner@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/10/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>KS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7374</Code>
      <Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9159</Code>
      <Text>DDF - DISTRIBUTED DESIGN AND FABRICATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
