<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The 6th USA-China Chemical Engineering Conference, Beijing, China, October 30-November 3, 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Luke Achenie</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI: Yang, Ralph T. and Norman N. Li&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Michigan Ann Arbor&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1110146&lt;br/&gt;Title: The 6th USA-China Chemical Engineering Conference, Beijing, China,&lt;br/&gt;October 30-November 3, 2011&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant is to provide travel funds for U.S. speakers, authors of papers, and particularly young academic participants to The 6th USA-China Chemical Engineering Conference, to be held in Beijing, China, on November 7- 10, 2011 (the dates have been changed since the proposal was submitted). The theme of the conference is: Chemical Engineering for Clean Energy. The Conference is co-sponsored by the Chinese Academy of Engineering, Chinese Academy of Science, the Chemical Industry &amp; Engineering Society of China (CIESC), and the American Institute of Chemical Engineers (AIChE). The purpose of the Conference is to provide a forum for U.S. Chemical Engineers to meet their counterpart in China to discuss the latest advancements, exchange research ideas and discuss opportunities for collaboration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The $30,000 will provide for approximately 30 partial travel grant awards to U.S. speakers, authors of papers, particularly young academic participants at the Conference. Travel awards will be made based on the following considerations: (1) scientific or technological merit of the speaker/participant; (2) professional qualifications relative to age and position; (3) institutional and geographical distribution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Global issues such as new and renewable energy sources, clean fuels and environment will be among the focal points of discussion that will be beneficial to the U.S. participants. The direct communication will facilitate development and expansion of the potentially vast markets in China for U.S. chemical products.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1110146</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ralph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yang@engin.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nlchem@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
