<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Integrating morphology, molecules and information technology for the taxonomic revision of Signiphoridae (Hymenoptera)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11733</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010206</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas Ranker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant is for the improvement of the taxonomic revision of a family of parasitic wasps, Signiphoridae (Chalcidoidea), which are natural enemies of scale insects, mealybugs, psyllids, and flies. The project is based on a comparative study of material collected worldwide. The species will be classified and new species will be described (at least 25 new species). Evolutionary relationships will be inferred from morphological and molecular data, using state-of-the-art analytical methods. The award will also be used to develop tools to manage the large amounts of data produced (specimen information, descriptions, images, DNA sequences), prepare it for public delivery, and to visit two institutions with valuable material from the Brazilian savannah (cerrado), Atlantic Rainforest, and Amazon.&lt;br/&gt;Besides enhancing significantly the depth of the study, this grant provides training for a graduate student in three areas (comparative morphology, molecular studies and bioinformatics) which are essential to taxonomists in the 21st Century. Training of taxonomists is important given the increasing scarcity of such professionals. This study will facilitate the use of these insects in the control of insect pests, provide tools to other scientists in taxonomy, provide opportunity for undergraduate student workers, and contribute to the knowledge of the fauna of the New World tropics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1110631</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Woolley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jimwoolley@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ana</FirstName>
      <LastName>DalMolin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>adalmolin@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
