<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Spin Chemistry and Radical Dynamics in Confined Environments: From Nanocrystals to Nanobubbles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>636190</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program supports Professor Malcolm D. E. Forbes at the University of North Carolina- Chapel Hill who seeks to continue his exploration of radical chemistry and dynamics in confined environments. Using time-resolved and steady-state magnetic resonance techniques, he will carry out spectroscopy on free radicals, extracting g-factors, hyperfine coupling constants, and fine structure splittings. From line shape analyses and modeling of time-dependent spectra he will obtain dynamic information such as diffusion coefficients, rotational correlation times, and spin relaxation rates. His interests are broadly based in polymers and in nano-environments such as micelles and reverse micelles. In this work, activities are expanded to the study of nano- and microbubbles, nanocrystals, and polymer nanoparticles. The underlying theme is the control of radical reactions, not just in terms of reaction rates but also the control of radical location in organized assemblies. The results of this study will have potential utility for nanomedicine (photodynamic therapy), polymer synthesis (adhesion and coatings), polymer degradation (light pipes) and the development of new catalytic reactions (glycolization, water splitting, and CO2 reduction).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the support of the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program in the Chemistry Division at the National Science Foundation, Professor Malcolm D. E. Forbes will pursue a strategy of maintaining core competencies in spectroscopy and physical organic methodology as applied to kinetics, structure and mechanism. Professor Forbes' laboratory trains researchers in small molecule and polymer synthesis, structural analysis, photochemistry and laser spectroscopy, magnetic resonance (including microwave engineering), molecular and macromolecular dynamics, surface and colloid chemistry, and catalysis. The broader impacts of the proposed work are exemplified by continuing efforts in community outreach for science education, scientific interactions with the general public, international collaborations, and by addressing diversity in the field of chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1111873</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Redinbo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>redinbo@unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Malcolm D.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Forbes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>forbesm@bgsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/21/2011</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
      <CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
      <ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1944</Code>
      <Text>BIMOLECULAR PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9161</Code>
      <Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
