<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Broadening PIRE Success in Southeast Asia to Test Hypotheses of the Origins of Coral Triangle and Sunda Shelf Marine Biodiversity and Build Collaborations in Vietnam and Thailand</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>26888</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nancy Sung</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1112636&lt;br/&gt;Carpenter&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a planning visit to enable Professor Kent Carpenter at Old Dominion University in Norfolk, Virginia to meet with Dr. Si Tuan Vo, Vice Director, Institute of Oceanography in Vietnam and Dr. Pholpunthin, Director, Center of Excellence for Biodiversity in Thailand. They will be testing hypotheses of the origins of the Coral Triangle and Sunda Shelf Marine Biodiversity. The majority of marine species have a pelagic larval phase with the potential to disperse great distances, yet the true magnitude of this exchange, the dynamic physical processes that shape dispersal, and the evolutionary consequences of the interplay of larvae and their physical environment remain largely unknown. For several years Professor Carpenter has been undertaking research in the Coral Triangle. His joint field sampling and laboratory work has been successful in the Philippines and Indonesia. Results have emerged that show concordant phylogeographic patterns consistent with physical and oceanographic features in the region, suggesting additional hypotheses that can be tested with expanded research activity across the South China Sea and Sunda Shelf to Vietnam and Thailand. This proposal seeks to develop a program expanding research and education partnerships to enable U.S. researchers, graduate students and undergraduate students to work closely with collaborators in residence in Thailand and Vietnam. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is sufficient overlap of interests between researchers in the U.S., Vietnam and Thailand to indicate that they can successfully pursue the activities proposed, and that the interaction will benefit both sides. In addition, the involvement of a postdoc, two U.S. graduate students and one undergraduate student will enable them to gain a valuable international perspective and insight. They will also participate in discussions on future collaborative activities with the researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1112636</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Carpenter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kcarpent@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
