<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Low-cost and Resuable Functional Polyaniline for CO2 Sequestration and Fertilizer Production</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>179975</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project seeks to develop a novel and sustainable approach to capture emitted CO2 from the fossil fuel based electric industry and convert the captured CO2 directly into useful by product, fertilizer using functionalized conducting polymer in a continuous dual chemical loop process. Reducing CO2 release to protect our environment is an urgent issue faced by our society, while world wide food shortage in the near future will require a lot amount of fertilizer. The objective of this project is to develop an affordable material/process that can quickly capture emitted CO2 from the industrial sources and turn it into fertilizer. We utilize functionalized polyaniline (FPAN), a low-cost material that can be reused repeatedly at harmful conditions, to capture CO2 at low temperature and high speed. With the presence of ammonia and water, the process can also easily convert CO2 into nitrogen fertilizers and allow the re-use of FPAN. If developed successfully, our process may permanently remove emitted CO2 and generate products valuable for agriculture, particularly food industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to revolutionalize the current CO2 sequestration and storage approach. Turning environmentally harmful CO2 release into useful fertilizer production in a low-temperature and low-cost process represents a great commercialization opportunity in both green energy and food industries in the US and worldwide. The low-cost fertilizer produced from CO2 release may also impact the forest and biomass industry. Furthermore, this will significantly grow the overall share of functional materials in the industry. Successful commercialization of the proposed novel products will have a significant impact on global warming, environmental protection and energy generation. This award will enhance the United States global leadership position in green industry. Societal benefits include healthier living environment and improved use of conventional fossil fuels that contribute to global warming. Educational and scientific benefits relate to the pioneering nature of nanocomposite technology and the opportunity this project will provide to advance frontiers of knowledge and the training of future scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1113706</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Min</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yongm86@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Nanomaterial Innovation Ltd.</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432204949</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7405226617</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1109 Millcreek Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
