<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PFI: A platform-based approach to developing and delivering nanoparticle antivirals for disease control in farmed shrimp</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599907</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Partnerships for Innovation (PFI) project from Iowa State University (ISU) is based on the overarching goal of developing an effective and adaptable system for disease control in farmed shrimp. The project emphasizes two emerging technologies RNA interference--(RNAi) and nano-structured materials--to function in concert as an antiviral effector molecule and delivery system, respectively. Infectious diseases caused by viral pathogens account for substantial mortality in farmed Pacific white shrimp (Litopenaeus vannamei) and result in devastating financial losses. The aim of this project is to rapidly develop highly specific RNAi-based antiviral molecules to protect individual shrimp from emerging viral infections. These antiviral molecules will be combined with a nanoparticle substrate so that the antiviral can be delivered orally to individual shrimp during the rearing process. The goals and predicted outcomes of this project will result in a platform system that can be rapidly adapted to respond to ever-evolving and emerging infectious disease issues in shrimp farming. Therefore, the project has strong potential for sustained innovation and to transform disease control for this industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project, beyond those for the partners, are economic benefits to the U.S., including the following: 1) Stable or even lower consumer prices for a high protein seafood product supplied from an industry that would dramatically increase its supply, if vaccines were available; 2) benefit to U.S. companies that export wheat and soybeans-- the two main ingredients in shrimp feeds--along with U.S. feed companies that export high tech microencapsultated larval feeds to shrimp hatcheries worldwide; 2) producers of breeding stocks of shrimp, 3) sustainable and predictable harvests for domestic shrimp producers, and 4) positioning the U.S. as the leader in the aquaculture biotechnologies needed for shrimp/fish farmers to supply future increases in demand for seafood that the capture fisheries cannot meet. Broader impacts will also be witnessed through training junior scientists at the undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral levels in a manner that will advance their capacity to practice science in an environment of entrepreneurialism--balancing bench work and scientific advancement with the demands and timelines of business. Trainees will benefit from academics and professional development mentoring at the lead institution and from regular interactions and time with the employees and leadership at the associated knowledge-enhancement partner companies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partners at the inception of the project are all part of the Knowledge Enhancement Partnership (KEP) unit, consisting of Iowa State University (Department of Entomology) and two small businesses: Harrisvaccines (HV) (Ames, IA) and Liquidia Technologies (LT) (Research Triangle Park, NC).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1114370</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lyric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bartholomay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lyricb@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sharron</FirstName>
      <LastName>Quisenberry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sharronq@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/08/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Iowa State University</Name>
      <CityName>AMES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
