<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Complex Singularities in Numerical Analysis and Nonlinear Dynamics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>264998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the precise analytic form of the complex singularities of&lt;br/&gt;the Lorenz system, the figure-eight solution of the three-body problem, and signals obtained&lt;br/&gt;from the Navier-Stokes boundary layer. Both analytic and numerical techniques&lt;br/&gt;will be used. Research on the Lorenz system has the aim of understanding the analytic&lt;br/&gt;continuation of the Lorenz solutions to the entire complex plane. With regard to the&lt;br/&gt;figure-eight solution, the project will show that the complex singularities of this system&lt;br/&gt;have an appealingly simple structure. The Navier-Stokes boundary layer has been&lt;br/&gt;studied primarily using techniques from spectral analysis. We will locate and elucidate&lt;br/&gt;singularities of the analytic continuation of the signal in the complex plane, and and&lt;br/&gt;obtain a measurement as well as an understanding of the time scales imposed by the&lt;br/&gt;outer flow.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project endeavors to benefit the public in two respects. Firstly, we aim to obtain&lt;br/&gt;new insights into the Navier-Stokes boundary layer which is of immense importance in&lt;br/&gt;engineering and meteorology. As an example of its importance, we mention that a&lt;br/&gt;major part of the energy intake of automobiles is dissipated in the boundary layer.&lt;br/&gt;Secondly, we will write a new book that puts computer architecture at the heart of&lt;br/&gt;scientific computing. This book will introduce a style of scientific computing that is&lt;br/&gt;deeply informed by recent progress in computer architecture to a wider audience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1115277</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Divakar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Viswanath</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>divakar@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
