<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CIF: Small: Collaborative Research: Distributed Detection Algorithms and Stochastic Modeling for Large Monitoring Sensor Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>235000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cozzens</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Operational and safety goals for the built environment demand robust, scalable and reliable large&lt;br/&gt;scale monitoring for infrastructure systems. High performance real-time event detection and decision making&lt;br/&gt;requires models and algorithms to process large amounts of data from dense sensor networks deployed&lt;br/&gt;in these systems. Despite advances in the development of detection algorithms for such networks, there are&lt;br/&gt;two widely recognized and conflicting obstacles: detection rules need to be sufficiently complex to adapt to&lt;br/&gt;the spatiotemporal changes in the environment, requiring the sharing of data; but rules are constrained by&lt;br/&gt;statistical performance guarantees and computation and communicational budgets imposed by the network.&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses these challenges by developing a fundamentally new approach that jointly accounts&lt;br/&gt;for statistical detection, communication constraints and distributed computation.&lt;br/&gt;This research develops a framework that integrates the distributed computation and communication constraints&lt;br/&gt;of the underlying network infrastructure with flexible stochastic modeling and learning algorithms&lt;br/&gt;with spatiotemporal data. The modeling and algorithms enable simultaneous and sequential decision making&lt;br/&gt;at many local sites, by borrowing information across the network in a statistically coherent and computationally&lt;br/&gt;efficient manner. Combining the formalism of sequential change point detection, nonparametric and&lt;br/&gt;probabilistic graphical models and spatiotemporal statistics, the project develops distributed and sequential&lt;br/&gt;message-passing algorithms for detecting changes in the underlying distributions generating network data.&lt;br/&gt;The models developed also offer new theoretical understanding of the trade-offs between statistical model&lt;br/&gt;complexity, distributed computation efficiency, and structure of communication constraints within the network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This interdisciplinary research brings together students and researchers from different areas, utilizing&lt;br/&gt;and developing knowledge and cross-disciplinary skills in the fields of computer science, statistics, signal&lt;br/&gt;processing and civil engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1116377</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ram</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rajagopal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ramr@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7797</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7936</Code>
      <Text>SIGNAL PROCESSING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
