<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CIF: Small: Efficient Satellite Relaying</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>340955</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>phillip regalia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Data networking via satellite relays remains an important means of linking globally-distributed network terminals for both commercial and governmental applications, especially in remote regions. Modern applications demand both spectrum and power efficiency in the network. The archetype network model in such networks is one with two terminals wishing to exchange data via a single satellite transponder. Relative to traditional time-sharing or frequency-sharing for the bidirectional communication paths, information-theory reveals that spectrum efficiency gains of up to 100% can be obtained for a given set of link power resources. These gains are possible when non-orthogonal transmission methods are adopted, and the decoders exploit side-knowledge on previously-transmitted information. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project codifies various protocols appropriate to this two-terminal data exchange model, including amplify-forward, as well as protocols that involve satellite decoding/re-encoding. The possible gains depend on link resources as well as the desired bidirectional rate targets. Existing research for this problem presumes perfect synchronization and side-information at both terminals, but practical issues of large round-trip delay, carrier phase/frequency synchronization, and symbol synchronization are important obstacles to achieving the promise of information theory. So the investigators develop realistic synchronization protocol designs that approach the ideal information-theoretic limits. In addition, the project studies a new decode-and-forward relaying protocol based on nested LDPC coding on downlinks that is flexible in terms of rate-asymmetry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1116997</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Toby</FirstName>
      <LastName>Berger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tb6n@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sgw@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/04/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7797</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION FOUNDATIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7935</Code>
      <Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
