<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SHB: Small: Social Tools for Everyday Adolescent Health</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>485694</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The increasing numbers of overweight and obese adolescents is a key health challenge in 21st century&lt;br/&gt;America. Since the 1980s, rates of overweight adolescents have doubled, and rates of obese adolescents&lt;br/&gt;have tripled; adolescent obesity is now the single biggest predictor of adult obesity. At the same time,&lt;br/&gt;adolescents are spending increasing portions of their lives interacting with video games and social&lt;br/&gt;network sites, incorporating computing into their leisure and social communication practices on a large&lt;br/&gt;scale. This project uses computing technology to address adolescent obesity through the&lt;br/&gt;development and study of social tools to promote sustained everyday healthy practices by adolescents.&lt;br/&gt;The research demonstrates how social computing&lt;br/&gt;can enable offline healthy behaviors, using peers as motivators in contrast to "top-down"&lt;br/&gt;approaches. The work is in partnership with DeKalb County Schools, Georgia's&lt;br/&gt;most urban school district and a leading awardee of research-focused programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research in this project is exploring the effects of various social computing&lt;br/&gt;tools and features on a set of validated outcome measures grounded in our previous work and best&lt;br/&gt;practices. During the school year the project deploys a series of pedometer-based social health&lt;br/&gt;applications and games for 8th graders in two middle schools. In the summers between deployment cycles, a small subset of participants takes part in design sessions for the next school year.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research focuses on three main topics:&lt;br/&gt;1. The role of online social identity presentation in intrinsic motivation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. The ability of social computing interventions to facilitate offline rituals and habits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3. The impact of collective experiences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will contribute to our understanding of the connections between social&lt;br/&gt;media activity and offline behavior. It will also demonstrate improvements in health behaviors and attitudes for adolescents. Moreover by deepening the connection between the&lt;br/&gt;Dekalb School System in Atlanta and Georgia Tech, the project enriches the educational environment&lt;br/&gt;of these middle school students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1116801</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mynatt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mynatt@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8018</Code>
      <Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8018</Code>
      <Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
