<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>HBCU Grant Writing Outreach Intervention: A Continuous Improvement Approach</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>335613</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Celestine Pea</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: This project aims to help Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) to more successfully compete for funds that support STEM education. To achieve this aim, the Capstone Institute at Howard University proposes to conduct a needs assessment of and develop an intervention plan to help level the playing field. The goal ensures that HBCUs become a vital part of grant application and funding processes available through federal agencies and private and public foundations. The Capstone Institute offers 25 of 105 HBCUs an opportunity to participate in grant-related activities that include: a comprehensive needs assessment, customized workshops based on the outcomes of the needs assessment, access to experienced grant writers and expert mentors, and technical assistance through extensive follow-up interactions and services. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: To broaden participation and improve STEM opportunities more evenly, the Capstone Institute intends to help build capacity on participating HBCU campuses. The big idea is to enable HBCUs to contribute more successfully to rapidly expanding STEM fields while promoting awareness and interests of their students in STEM careers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1116165</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>A.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boykin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aboykin@howard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Howard University</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200599000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2028064759</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2400 Sixth Street N W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7625</Code>
      <Text>REAL</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
