<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSR: Small: Nested Distributed Software Transactional Memory: Protocols, Mechanisms, and Java Package</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>481600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, protocols, mechanisms, and a Java implementation of &lt;br/&gt;nested distributed transactional memory (TM) are developed. Distributed TM promises &lt;br/&gt;to alleviate the programmability, scalability, and performance challenges of lock-based &lt;br/&gt;distributed concurrency control. Emerging distributed TM implementations export &lt;br/&gt;a simple programming interface that precludes locks and are yielding performance &lt;br/&gt;comparable to, or better than lock-based distributed concurrency control. Nesting is &lt;br/&gt;essential to distributed TM for composability, functionality, fault-management, and &lt;br/&gt;performance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is developing protocols and mechanisms to support closed and open &lt;br/&gt;nesting in distributed TM. Closed nesting allows a nested transaction to be aborted &lt;br/&gt;without aborting the parent transaction, but not vice versa. Open nesting allows a &lt;br/&gt;parent transaction to be aborted without aborting the nested transaction, and vice &lt;br/&gt;versa, permitting greater concurrency. To support these nesting models, the project &lt;br/&gt;is developing distributed transactional conflict resolution protocols, distributed &lt;br/&gt;cache coherence protocols, and mechanisms for transparently executing &lt;br/&gt;compensating transactions to undo the effects of committed transactions. The &lt;br/&gt;project is implementing these techniques in the open-source, HyFlow distributed &lt;br/&gt;TM Java package (hyflow.org). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is also transitioning this technology (techniques and HyFlow &lt;br/&gt;implementation) to US Navy's Aegis Combat System, which uses distributed &lt;br/&gt;concurrency control. Additionally, the project's results are being incorporated into &lt;br/&gt;advanced graduate courses at Virginia Tech that includes students at Blacksburg, &lt;br/&gt;VA, scientists and engineers at US Naval Surface Warfare Center Dahlgren Division &lt;br/&gt;(NSWCDD), VA (through Virginia Tech's graduate outreach program at NSWCDD), &lt;br/&gt;and students in the Middle East and North Africa through Virginia Tech's VT-MENA &lt;br/&gt;program at Egypt.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1116190</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Binoy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ravindran</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>binoy@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
