<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RI: SMALL: Modeling Voice Source Transformation in Monolingual and Crosslingual Non-parallel Voice Conversion Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>252637</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tatiana D. Korelsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Voice conversion (VC) systems transform segments of speech from a given source speaker so that it&lt;br/&gt;can be identified as spoken by a specified target speaker. Currently, standard VC systems require&lt;br/&gt;parallel training on extensively labeled sets of speech data where the source and target speaker share&lt;br/&gt;equivalent content for building direct mapping models. This project builds on the concepts of nonparallel&lt;br/&gt;VC systems reducing the need for labeled and shared speech content between source and target&lt;br/&gt;speakers as well as allowing for both intra-lingual and cross-lingual conversion scenarios. This project&lt;br/&gt;focuses on two main areas: (1) Building a framework for non-parallel VC without explicit phonetic,&lt;br/&gt;sound, word, or sentence level labels, and (2) Providing effective target speaker mapping to obtain&lt;br/&gt;converted speech with as good as or better quality compared to current VC systems. The VC&lt;br/&gt;framework consists of three main components: (1) A speaker independent language model; (2) An&lt;br/&gt;algorithm for model adaptation to target speaker; (3) A speech synthesis block to generate converted&lt;br/&gt;speech from a target-adapted language model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide a broad framework for applications such as personalization of assistive textto-&lt;br/&gt;speech (TTS) systems, foreign language learning, and as a possible component in speech-to-speech&lt;br/&gt;translation systems. This project will support graduate student research and provide results for&lt;br/&gt;community distribution through conference and journal submission. Additionally, an open-source&lt;br/&gt;software toolset will be developed and freely distributed. The project will also be used in outreach for&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented groups in Science Technology Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1116475</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elliot</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>em80@mail.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7495</Code>
      <Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
