<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AF: Small: Collaborative Research: Active DNA Assembly of Aperiodic Structures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>295750</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>AF: Small: Collaborative Research: Active DNA Assembly of Aperiodic Structures&lt;br/&gt;PIs: N.C. Seeman, N. Jonoska&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The science of computing and information processing is rapidly proliferating within established disciplines that at first glance appear unrelated. Examples include&lt;br/&gt;biochemistry and biology through the areas of bioinformatics and algorithmic molecular assembly, or physics, through quantum computing. Current top-down photolithographic methods of electronic component construction are likely to encounter severe barriers as miniaturization requires features at very small sizes. An alternative approach to such construction is programmable bottom-up assembly on the molecular scale. The most popular basis for bottom-up assembly is DNA self-assembly, because DNA contains information through which assembly can be controlled in a variety of ways. This approach has been explored by a variety of laboratories in recent years, but was pioneered by the PI Seeman's laboratory roughly thirty years ago. Robust DNA motifs can be self-assembled into objects, lattices and devices, using the information content inherent in the DNA molecules (or their analogs) themselves. Notable milestones include the self-assembly of DNA polyhedra, the self-assembly of 2D DNA periodic lattices, the self-assembly of high-resolution 3D DNA crystals, the development of clocked and autonomous cascade-like DNA walkers, the development of DNA origami, and the construction of 1D and 2D algorithmic assemblies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to combine several of these developments to produce robust aperiodic structures that will enable nano-scale construction of computational machinery. The goal of the project is to introduce a new paradigm in the self-assembly of nano-scale devices by DNA self-assembly: active (rather than passive) recursion-based assembly of aperiodic structures. The project will incorporate elements of DNA walkers into DNA origami-based tiles as signals that guide hierarchical active assembly of aperiodic arrays. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed hierarchical algorithmic assembly would be the first demonstration of recursion in molecular self-assembly that can be seen as a physical incarnation of programmed recursion. It is known that self-similar and fractal-like structures have advantages in material design, heat exchange and information processing, e.g., the very significant advances obtained by miniature fractal-like antennas. Consequently, the possibilities for self-similar arrangements at the nano-scale can be expected to advance further the design of materials and electronics, while decreasing the costs involved in their construction.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1117210</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nadrian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seeman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ned.seeman@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7798</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7923</Code>
      <Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7931</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7946</Code>
      <Text>BIO COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
