<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CRPA NSF Collaborative Research: The Ultimate Cosmic Experiment-Chemistry Labs at the Far Edges of the Universe</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25093</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul W. Jennings</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This CRPA award addresses the exciting contemporary chemical science that occurs in interstellar space. The new interferometers coming online this year will enhance this new area of science and further intrigue those who engage. The plan in this award is to build an exhibit that will interest the audience with the space-based aspects, but will also engage them in understanding the chemistry that occurs in space. This is a collaborative effort between the University of Virginia and the Harvard-Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The exhibit is relatively small facilitating its mobility. Thus, the authors will travel the exhibit to smaller venues in rural areas and embrace citizens who are typically under-served by educational opportunities of ISE venues. The target audience is 12-15 year old youths. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Clearly, this project is meant to engage the public in both Space science and Chemistry with the ultimate hope that some individuals will even think about careers in the joint science field that is emerging from these types of behaviors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1118577</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dussault</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdussault@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2014</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
      <LastName>Griswold</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>agriswold@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/26/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>08/28/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Smithsonian Institution Astrophysical Observatory</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021381516</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6174967924</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>60 Garden St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
