<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Support for Conferences and Mentoring in Political Methodology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>188034</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lee Walker</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project supports the Society for Political Methodology's efforts to support underfunded graduate students, expand mentoring and networking efforts for women and members of underrepresented groups, as well as to develop new inclusive programs for making the subfield more accessible to groups with historically lower participation in the activities of the subfield. During the award period the project will: (1) ensure that qualified, but insufficiently-funded graduate students can attend and participate in our highly successful Summer methodology meetings, (2) continue holding small thematically oriented meetings that emphasize particular technical skills and foster a high level of networking and mentoring, and (3) continue a series of small meetings for women methodologists that deliberately mix senior leaders in the subfield with young, emerging scholars who can benefit substantially from such close personal interaction. This includes maintaining and developing multiple venues for presenting, discussing, and advancing quantitative methods in political science, with a direct focus on finding, mentoring, and enabling under-represented groups in political methodology. Since all of the programs and initiatives in this proposal are targeted at individuals in these circumstances, the effect is to dramatically widen the access to the intellectual breadth of methodology. The summer meeting is well known in the discipline for faculty-student interaction, network formation between junior and senior faculty, and revealing the process of creating new knowledge in quantitative political science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Methodology plays a special role in the large, diverse field of political science, since it reaches across other areas of research in the discipline, with a history of providing knowledge and tools that help researchers who are not themselves self identified as methodologists. Thus the planned investment in graduate students and increased inclusion of underrepresented groups from this support will have an impact that stretches across the discipline.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1120976</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Franzese</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>franzese@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeff</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gill</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgill@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1371</Code>
      <Text>POLITICAL SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1333</Code>
      <Text>METHOD, MEASURE &amp; STATS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
