<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Institutions and Dominance within Social Movements: How Legal Strategies Shape the Agendas of Movements for Social Change</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14922</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>susan sterett</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Although litigation plays a central role in the strategies of many contemporary social movements, surprisingly little is known about the conditions under which social movement actors adopt litigation strategies or how litigation shapes a movement's substantive agenda. Existing research has shown that litigation attracts enormous publicity and political attention, increasing the visibility and standing of movement actors who use it. However, litigation may simultaneously detract attention from movement actors who use extra-legal strategies, marginalizing their perspectives and claims. This research project investigates what factors cause social movement actors to pursue litigation over other tactics (e.g., legislative lobbying, service provision, or protest) and how litigation, as a social movement tactic, shapes movements' priorities and their substantive goals. The project is theoretically situated in the recent law and social movement literature. The research plan involves coding of organizational, institutional and government documents as well as interview with social movement actors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The data generated through this project will expand knowledge regarding strategic choice in social movements. Furthermore, by examining how litigation comes to dominate other strategies for social change, this research is poised to illumine larger theoretical questions about how social movement actors can reinforce existing legal institutions, even as they deploy litigation as a strategy of resistance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1124534</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gwendolyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Leachman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gwendolyn@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edelman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ledelman@law.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1372</Code>
      <Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
