<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an SEM-EDS-CL for interdisciplinary research and training in materials imaging and chemical analysis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>295424</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) grant supports the acquisition of equipment to develop a new electron microscopy facility at The University of Montana that focuses on materials imaging and chemical analysis. This funding provides support for a variable pressure scanning electron microscope (SEM), energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS) for micro-chemical analysis, a live color cathodoluminescence (CL) detector for imaging of luminescent materials, and a sputter coater for sample preparation. The user group includes scientists from the Departments of Geosciences, Anthropology, Chemistry &amp; Biochemistry, Physics, Geological Engineering, and Forestry. Research applications include the petrologic examination of geologic materials, materials-based archaeology studies of lithic tools and resource transport strategies, imaging and analysis of nano-scale magnetic devices, studies involving the effect of fire ash on the hydrologic system, and documenting the nature and compositions of metal contamination in river sediments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The faculty involved in this project are committed to recruiting a diverse group of researchers and have a track record of working with Native American undergraduate and graduate students. Undergraduate students will use this state-of-the-art technology in courses at all levels of the curriculum and for senior research projects, forming the foundation for a hands-on, active learning environment. Exposure to these techniques will better prepare students for careers in industry that rely on high resolution microscopy for materials characterization. Outreach will be accomplished through established collaborations involving the PI, co-PIs, and the K-12 community. The scanning electron microscopy facility is unique within the state of Montana and will thus operate as a regional facility for research collaboration with scientists from other universities, and regional state and federal agencies, such as the Montana Bureau of Mines and Geology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1126717</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Staub</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james.staub@umontana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hendrix</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>marc.hendrix@mso.umt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baldwin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>julie.baldwin@umontana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prentiss</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anna.prentiss@umontana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schneider</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael.schneider@mso.umt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Montana</Name>
      <CityName>Missoula</CityName>
      <ZipCode>598120001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4062436670</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>32 CAMPUS DRIVE MAIN HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
