<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a THz Frequency On-Wafer Probe Station</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>362000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>john zavada</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The objective of this program is to develop the first terahertz frequency (&gt;0.5 THz) on-wafer probe station in the world. The proposed instrument development plan will assemble a full two-port terahertz frequency vector network analyzer (VNA) system with frequency extension modules mounted to a probing platform. The wafer probes, fabricated by the University of Virginia, will be mounted directly to the frequency extension modules in order to realize a complete terahertz-frequency on-wafer probe station operating from 500 to 750 GHz.&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is that the terahertz frequency range has enormous potential for both scientific discoveries in the areas of radio astronomy, chemical spectroscopy, and material characterization as well as applications in atmospheric ozone monitoring, concealed weapons and chemical / biological hazards detection, and compact-range radar systems. However, a significant hurdle has been the inability to rapidly characterize circuits and devices through on-wafer testing. Current test procedures involve time-consuming development of connectorized prototypes or free-space measurements.&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are benefiting the wider scientific and engineering communities by enabling the rapid advances in device technology required in order to realize terahertz integrated circuits for advanced imaging systems, stand-off detection of harmful chemicals and explosives and short-range communication that is far beyond what is now possible. In addition, the development of a terahertz frequency probe station will provide a tremendous opportunity for motivating young prospective engineers to enter the field of engineering by demonstrating the progress that can be made towards critical applications through an engineering education.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1126677</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weikle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rmw5w@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicolas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>barker@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arthur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lichtenberger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>awl1l@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>105E</Code>
      <Text>RF/Microwave &amp; mm-wave tech</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
