<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a DSC (Differential Scanning Calorimetry) System for R&amp;D at CESUR (Center for Efficient and Sustainable Use of Resources) of Arkansas State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>138288</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award is to acquire a DSC (Differential Scanning Calorimetry) system to measure the temperature and heat flow corresponding to the thermal performance of materials, both as a function of time and temperature. The DSC instrument provides qualitative and quantitative information on endothermic/heat absorbing (e.g. melting) and exothermic/heat releasing (e.g. solidification of fusion) processes of materials. The DSC system will be shared and utilized under interdisciplinary collaboration by eight faculty members' multiple research groups. Some of the key research that will be supported by this equipment includes: 1) experimental study of advanced heat transfer fluids for renewable/nuclear/fossil power plant applications and computational study of thermodynamic modeling to predict phase transition behaviors of novel multicomponent mixtures; 2) study of characterization of TICPET (Thermally Induced Condensed Phase Electron Transfer) and metal halide salt chemistry; 3) identification of various oils and fats through experimental stability analysis by detection of crystallization shift; 4) investigation of phase transitions and crystalline transitions of ionic or other nonaqueous liquids in the absence of applied electric field; and 5) determination of heats of combustion in solid biofuels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The DSC system will provide opportunities to establish a collaborative, cross-disciplinary research team exploring a set of studies related by their interest in complex salts, ionic liquids, and other energy related projects. In addition to the novel material development, the DSC system will provide advanced research experience to many students over time, enhancing their competitiveness in the thermal/fluids/energy, chemistry, and food science areas. The DSC system will be an important addition to existing equipment supporting a wide variety of research projects funded by NSF and other federal agencies. Furthermore, the DSC system will enhance R&amp;D capacity and skills for faculty and researchers at the Center for Efficient and Sustainable Use of Resources (CESUR) at Arkansas State University (ASU).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1126899</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Engelken</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bdengens@astate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Draganjac</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdraganj@astate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Soohyoun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ahn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sahn82@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kwangkook</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jeong</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kjeong@astate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brad</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edgar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bedgar@astate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arkansas State University Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Jonesboro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>724672760</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8709722694</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>504 University Loop East</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
