<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>AIR: Carbon Dioxide and Hydrogen Sulfide Clean-up of Gases</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>158000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed work is based on the successfully completed NSF sponsored project pertaining to membranes for carbon dioxide removal from low pressure (1 4 atm) gases. The specific objectives of this work are to fill the technological knowledge gaps needed for the successful translation of the proposed game-changing gas cleanup membrane technology to commercial development. This work will demonstrate the scale-up of the membrane, fabricate prototype membrane modules from the scale-up membrane and conduct the proof of concept (POC) on the carbon dioxide and hydrogen sulfide clean-up of low pressure gases using the membrane module. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The novel amine-containing membrane has a high removal rate for carbon dioxide and hydrogen sulfide and results in a simplified separation process, which can reduce capital costs and energy consumption. There are many potential markets for the novel membrane technology, such as hydrogen purification for fuel cell applications, and biogas purification. The mentoring and training for the graduate students participating should provide opportunities for interaction with industrial researchers and for learning how to translate fundamental research results into commercialization strategies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1127812</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Winston</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ho</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ho.192@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
