<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Low-Profile, Multi-Polar Energy Generator (MEG) for Small Scale Power Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>602434</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project proposes to create high performance energy harvesting products using EcoHarvester?s Multi-Pole Energy Generator (MEG) technology. The novel platform technology will answer the need for power in the mili-watt to several watt ranges and will be possible to serve multiple markets. Phase II will focus on miniaturization of the MEG technology, system level integration of wireless light switches, and modification of the MEG technology for application to a user-actuated portable electronic device charger. The self-generated light switches will eliminated the cost and time spent on wiring or changing batteries. The user-actuated chargers will eliminate the need to buy disposable batteries for smart phone power back-up.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this research are further investment in energy harvesting and accelerate the adoption of energy harvesting technologies to replace/supplement batteries. In addition to the great economic and performance advantages of our technology for end users, there are compelling motivations to promote this technology for reasons of sustainability and waste reduction. Locally generated power is highly desirable due to the inherent inefficiencies of transmission and storage. As our world becomes increasingly wired, the demand for environmentally burdensome batteries and copper wires has skyrocketed, creating problems related to material extraction, processing, and disposal. The limitations of batteries also constrict the useful life of many devices and limit some applications due to the need to be able to service and replace components.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1127526</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Takahashi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eritaka@ecoharvester.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/17/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>EcoHarvester, Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947041152</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106655563</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>46 SHATTUCK SQ STE 10</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
