<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium: Prof. John Chato Memorial Symposium on Progress and Challenges in Biotransport at 2011 Summer Bioengineering Conference in Farmington, Pennsylvania - June 22-25, 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ashok S. Sangani</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal ID: 1128490&lt;br/&gt;PI: Ram V. Devireddy, Louisiana State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed symposium to be held in Farmington, Pennsylvania as part of the 2011 Summer Bioengineering conference, will provide a venue for researchers, educators and graduate students to identify challenges and opportunities pertaining to biotransport. This symposium will highlight and honor the contributions of Prof. John Chato to the field of bioheat transfer and his mentoring of young researchers over his long and fruitful career. Topics for the symposium include but are not limited to: (1) bioheat transfer models, (2) biomaterial thermophysical property measurements and (3) optimizing thermal therapies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides support for approximately 2 keynote speakers and 10 students to attend the workshop. The agenda will include technical presentations and panel sessions culminating in archival review article identifying specific scientific and engineering challenges pertaining to biotransport. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop topic has broad application to a wide array of biological transport problems. Since, transport processes impact biology and medicine at every stage of life, their analysis will serve to innovate and optimize diagnostic and therapeutic interventions. The broad impacts of the grant are in enabling the participation of students and early career scientists in the symposium, thereby providing the education and training opportunities for next generation scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1128490</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ram</FirstName>
      <LastName>Devireddy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>devireddy@me.lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>064E</Code>
      <Text>Convection heat and mass transfer</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>150E</Code>
      <Text>Conduction/Diffusion</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
