<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Experimental and Computational Simulation of Progressive Collapse of Buildings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150010</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kishor Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project involves physical testing of three existing buildings that are scheduled for demolition on the campus of The Ohio State University in Columbus to study the progressive collapse characteristics of building structures. To study the building collapse vulnerabilities as recommended by the current design guidelines, the structural columns in the first stories will be removed and response of the buildings will be monitored. This study will provide much needed experimental data on full-scale buildings to validate the results of computational studies reported in the literature and to verify the methodologies prescribed in the design guidelines. The project will improve understanding of progressive collapse process by addressing: 1) redistribution of loads within the building following loss of columns, 2) contribution of slabs and transverse and longitudinal beams in bridging over the failed column, and 3) structural system characteristics that determine how a structural collapse mechanism forms. The experimental data will be used to validate and refine advanced nonlinear analysis tools and to develop simplified models and analysis procedures that can be used by practicing engineers. The results of this research will enable more accurate assessment of collapse potential of buildings and, as a result, will lead to more efficient design of new buildings and retrofit of existing buildings. Simulation data will be used to evaluate the amplification factors recommended by the design guidelines for linear static analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is expected to provide scarce full-scale experimental data of immense value to advance engineering understanding about progressive collapse of buildings. The project will involve graduate, undergraduate students from underrepresented groups in science and technology education. Hands-on demonstrations will be given and competitions will be conducted at high school level.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1130397</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Halil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sezen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sezen.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1637</Code>
      <Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>039E</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>040E</Code>
      <Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>043E</Code>
      <Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
