<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Frontiers of Electron Microscopy in Materials Science 2011 (FEMMS 2011; Sonoma, CA; September 18 - 23, 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric Taleff</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY: The 13th conference on Frontiers of Electron Microscopy in Materials Science (FEMMS) 2011, will be held in Sonoma, CA, September 18 to 23. FEMMS is a biennial meeting focused on the most recent developments in the use of electron microscopy (primarily TEM) for materials science. This year's meeting is timely given the recent revolution in the development of aberration correctors and the increasing interest in the use of in-situ and ultrafast TEM methods. In this year's conference 46 speakers have been invited to discuss topics that include high resolution imaging and spectroscopy, ultrafast and in-situ microscopy, 3-D imaging techniques and various microscopy applications in nanoscience, including materials interfaces/defects and organic materials in bioengineering. The conference also features a distinguished lecturer, Professor Archie Howie, who has been selected for his long outstanding and exceptional contributions to the field of electron microscopy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY: The conference is typically attended by about 100 participants. Details about the location, organization and history of the FEMMS conference can be found on the conference website: http://femms2011.llnl.gov/. The proceedings of this year's conference will be published in Ultramicroscopy and Microscopy and Microanalysis (depending on the content). Publication of the proceedings provides not only benefits to the conference attendees, including graduate students, but also provides opportunities for others who cannot participate in the conference. NSF support for this conference will be used to cover the registration and accommodation support for 10 graduate students. A main goal of the NSF proposal is to provide support for underrepresented graduate students (women and minorities) to learn about the latest capabilities in electron microscopy and to establish contacts and possible collaborations with leaders in the field.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1132020</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Masashi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Watanabe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maw3@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lehigh University</Name>
      <CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
      <ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1771</Code>
      <Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
