<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Biodegradable Nanomaterials by Thiol-Ene Miniemulsion Reactions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>315470</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Burka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal Number: 1133737&lt;br/&gt;PI: Cheng, Chong &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Polymeric nanoparticles (NPs) and nanocapsules (NCs) have attracted significant interest for potential applications in biomedical and other areas. Controlled cross-linking within nanoscopic templates has allowed the synthesis of these nanomaterials with three-dimensional covalent architectures. Correspondingly, synthetic efficiency depends not only on the reaction or polymerization techniques but also on the template conditions. Relative to other templating approaches, miniemulsion-based methods typically are facile and eco-friendly, but may suffer deficiency in precise control over the resulting nanostructures. Particularly, although NCs can be readily obtained by miniemulsion interfacial cross-linking, dramatic interfacial destabilization may occur to yield ill-defined products. This project is to develop a state-of-art miniemulsion technology for the highly efficient and environmentally friendly preparation of well-defined NPs and NCs. The synthetic strategy incorporates three major design considerations: 1) UV-induced thiol-ene click chemistry is combined with transparent miniemulsions to achieve high synthetic efficiency; 2) interfacial destabilization is minimized by selective cross-linking of polymer blocks in the dispersed phase to exert accurate structural control of NPs and NCs; and 3) biodegradable nanomaterials are produced using environmentally benign reagents and reaction conditions. In the initial proof-of-concept studies, biodegradable NPs and NCs were obtained by thiol-ene cross-linking of precursor polymers, i.e. allyl-functionalized PLA and PEO-b-PLA, using short (30 min) UV irradiation of transparent miniemulsion reaction systems. Nearly complete extent of reaction was confirmed by FTIR analysis for each trial. Well-defined nanostructures of the NPs and NCs were verified by DLS, TEM, and AFM characterizations. Their biodegradability was also proven through enzymatic degradation study. Systematic studies on the synthesis of these nanomaterials are planned towards the goal of exerting accurate control over their nanoscopic dimensions, internal crosslinked structures, and functionalities. A broad variety of functional NPs and NCs, including these with cationic groups, will be prepared via thiol-ene functionalization strategy. The processing method and conditions will be optimized to further improve synthetic efficiency. Colloidal stability, degradation and encapsulation/release behaviors of these nanomaterials will be studied. To further evaluate the viability of these nanomaterials as carriers for biomedical delivery, in vitro cellular uptake and cytotoxicity studies will be conducted, and transfection efficiency of complexes of siRNA with cationic NPs and NCs will be examined. In principle, besides alkene-functionalized polymers, multifunctional small molecule alkenes may also be readily converted into nanomaterials by thiol-ene reactions in transparent miniemulsions. The results from this research could further provide an important guide for thermally-induced thiol-ene miniemulsion reactions, as well as thiol-ene reactions in other emulsion systems. Transparent miniemulsion templates developed in this work potentially may be applied for other types of photoinduced reactions to achieve high synthetic efficiency.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The research program may bring transformative impacts in the research area of material synthesis and processing. The resulting biodegradable nanomaterials may be utilized to make significant benefits to society by helping to improve national health and maintain environment. Particularly, the PEO/PLA-based NCs with acid-labile cross-linkages may be very useful as scaffolds to create anti-cancer nanomedicines; the cationic NPs and NCs may be employed for the co-delivery of drug and gene. The research findings of this project will promote the interdisciplinary collaboration of the PIs? groups on biomedical applications of polymers, and potentially lead to the commercialization of the thiolene miniemulsion technology based on collaborative efforts with industrial partners. In order to broadly disseminate polymer synthetic technologies, videos on polymer preparation will be created and on-line broadcast. A new graduate course on polymeric nanomaterials will be developed to enhance material education and research at SUNY-Buffalo. Outreach will be conducted to promote the education and preparation of local middle and high school students in science and engineering fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1133737</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ccheng8@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paras</FirstName>
      <LastName>Prasad</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pnprasad@acsu.buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
      <CityName>Amherst</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1403</Code>
      <Text>PROCESS &amp; REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>047E</Code>
      <Text>REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7237</Code>
      <Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
