<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Salmonid behavior and hydraulics of Engineered Log Jams: Experimental observations and field verification</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>338535</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1134596 (Tullos). This research will document the hydraulic interactions between two Engineered Log Jam (ELJ) architectures and a river's flow patterns and intensity, leading to better understanding on how ELJ characteristics influence the locations and magnitude of forces and energy loss. The results will advance existing research on fish ecology by making direct observation of fish behavior using new visually-based approaches, by linking bioenergetics to the hydraulic environment, and by improving understanding of how fish perceive the ecological benefits of ELJs. This work will develop a novel dataset by employing state-of-the-art techniques for observing fish and fluids and will apply innovative analytical techniques for extracting detailed information on fish behavior and hydraulic structure, scale, and intensity. This interdisciplinary collaboration is supported by experience in river engineering and restoration, aquatic ecology, fish behavior, experimental- and field-study design and measurements, and quantitative data analysis, as well as by existing research facilities and resources. The research targets (a) restoration practitioners designing log jams, and (b) students at the high school, undergraduate, and graduate level. Targeting practitioners, a video on fish use of ELJs will be developed and applied concepts (e.g. drag coefficients, force distributions around structures) relevant to the design of ELJs will be investigated. This project will give students at the high school, undergraduate, and graduate level the opportunity to participate in a multi-disciplinary research environment and to receive training in advanced methods for observations of hydraulics and fish in rivers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1134596</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Desiree</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tullos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>desiree.tullos@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon State University</Name>
      <CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
