<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Full STEM: Creating Dedicated Science and Math Teachers for a Sustainable Future</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Terry S. Woodin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Through this Capacity Building Grant the SUNY College at Oswego is developing the means necessary to increase the number of secondary education teachers in the STEM disciplines in high-need schools in their area. The school districts involved include: the Central Square Central , the Altmar-Parish, the Mexico Central, the Fulton City, the Oswego City, and the Hannibal school districts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is developing the following: 1) a teacher preparation program designed so that students majoring in STEM disciplines can receive a master's degree in teaching and complete their science major within a five year period; 2) programs that expose STEM majors to teaching possibilities early in their academic careers through internships and student teaching opportunities; 3) online versions of some of these classes to expand the reach of the program; 4) articulations with regional community colleges that allow transfer students to complete their degree and certification within the same timeframe as students who start as freshmen on the four year campus; 5) partnerships with local, regional and state middle schools and high schools to place and support Noyce teachers as they begin their professional careers; 6) a campus infrastructure to support the grant distribution process, including mechanisms for ensuring that scholarship recipients are meeting the expectations of the program; and 7) a robust assessment process that ensures the goals of the Robert Noyce Scholarship Program are being met and that provides formative feedback for program improvement. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project anticipates recruitment of three types of students: upper division students at SUNY Oswego presently majoring in STEM disciplines (including transfer students from community colleges and technical colleges) to complete the undergraduate degree in their STEM discipline and a master's degree in teaching (MST); those who have graduated with a degree in a STEM discipline who will be recruited into a fast-completion MST program that allows for completion of the master's degree within a one year plus one summer timetable; and those students early in their careers as STEM majors who will have experiences that allow them to determine whether a career as a teacher is an appropriate choice for them. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The program draws on an established body of literature as to what makes for an effective STEM teacher. It uses the findings from a variety of successful programs to develop a unique model that includes a quality educational experience for future teachers, field experiences and orientations that help students to develop innovative pedagogical techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This model has the potential to be easily used by other institutions with strong science programs and histories of quality teacher education. The interaction between the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences and the School of Education combines a dedication to discipline with strong and active pedagogy.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136350</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bruch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bruch@oswego.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/14/2014</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diann</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jackson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>diann.jackson@oswego.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY College at Oswego</Name>
      <CityName>Oswego</CityName>
      <ZipCode>131263514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3153122884</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSP</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
