<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Consortium of Resonance and Rayleigh Lidars</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>159248</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Meriwether</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is a collaborative award to advance mesosphere and lower thermosphere (MLT) science by developing and operating advanced upper atmospheric lidar instruments. The Consortium of Resonance and Rayleigh Lidars (CRRL) includes six universities: the University of Colorado (CU) hosts the CRRL director and the unique CRRL Technology Center (CTC); the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign in collaboration with Embry-Riddle University operates the Andes Lidar Observatory (ALO) in Cerro Pachón, Chile; Northwest Research Associates/CoRA Division contributes to the operation of the Arctic Lidar Observatory for Middle Atmosphere Research (ALOMAR) in Norway; and Utah State University (USU) in collaboration with Colorado State University (CSU) operates a sodium lidar in Utah. The increasing number of middle and upper atmosphere observing stations around the globe, and the recent increase in data assimilation schemes for numerical models, indicates the growing movement in the community to address the middle and upper atmosphere as a global system requiring studies spanning a wide range of spatial and temporal scales. The Na resonance wind and temperature (Na W/T) lidar technique, central to CRRL, provides fundamental measurements of the MLT region at temporal and spatial resolutions that are difficult to achieve by other means. As a result, Na W/T lidars have yielded fundamental advances in our understanding of MLT dynamics, thermal structure, chemistry, and microphysics that were previously impossible. They are, therefore, key instruments for achieving the community goals of whole atmosphere modeling and system science studies. The effort will consolidate and advance middle and upper atmosphere lidar systems leading to 1) improved coordination, performance, and scientific productivity of the three Na lidars currently at low, middle, and high latitudes, 2) more rapid and more efficient advances in lidar technology developments, implementations, and transfers, 3) active education and training, guest investigator, and outreach programs to educate future researchers and broaden the lidar user base in the upper atmosphere community, and 4) a coordinated vision and plan for the upper atmosphere lidar community. The expanded measurement capabilities and community involvement anticipated within RRL, especially the ability of the Na lidars to measure both temperature and winds day and night, and the ability of the lidars to support and enhance correlative instrumentation at key sites, will ensure the maximum scientific benefit and the broadest possible applications of these systems. Finally, CTC technology developments will strive to ensure the most efficient and comprehensive utilization of advancing technologies to the benefit of lidar research within and outside of CRRL. The CRRL activities will have a broad impact 1) by enhancing the infrastructure for middle and upper atmosphere research and 2) by defining a new means of educating, managing and coordinating correlative research activities. The greatest research benefits will occur through comprehensive and coordinated studies that merge multiple data sets and diverse scientific interests which will enable the greatest scientific return on the research investment. CTC technology developments will also benefit from, and be of benefit to, technology developments currently outside the Aeronomy community. The anticipated CRRL education, training, and guest investigator programs will ensure a group of talented and enthusiastic users to pursue lidar developments and applications in the future.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136082</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chiao-Yao</FirstName>
      <LastName>She</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>joeshe@lamar.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krueger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>krueger@lamar.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>4202</Code>
      <Text>UPPER ATMOSPHERIC FACILITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
