<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>University of Maryland Noyce Scholars Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1198251</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen B. Bergin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The College of Education is committed to doubling the number of STEM teacher candidates by 2013. In support of this goal, the Noyce Scholars Program is attracting and preparing a talented, diverse cohort of University of Maryland (UM) students to effectively teach mathematics in high needs middle and high schools. In an effort to increase freshman and sophomore interest in teaching mathematics, program activities include employing freshman and sophomores as tutors in local middle schools and providing freshman and sophomore summer internships with a focus on mathematics teaching and learning. Noyce Scholars receive scholarships, engage in preparation specific to high needs contexts, and, in their final year, are being placed in year-long internships in high needs schools with highly effective mentor teachers. Prince George's County Public Schools serves as district partner for this effort. During employment in their first two years, Noyce Scholars are being supported through an induction program consisting of collaborative, online study of Noyce Scholars' records of practice and virtual mentoring. The project is expected to produce a total of 32 teachers from both the undergraduate math degree with secondary certification and the integrated masters programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The UM Noyce Scholars Program builds on program development work in mathematics teacher education and it enhances the infrastructure for mathematics teacher education at UM. The program adds to UM's ability to recruit, prepare, diversify, and support secondary mathematics teachers in the State of Maryland and beyond.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1136277</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hunt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bhunt@ipst.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lmclark@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1795</Code>
      <Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
