<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop: Princeton-CEFRC Summer School on Combustion Summer Workshop, June 26-July 1, 2011, Princeton, NJ</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Arvind Atreyae Atreya</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1137883&lt;br/&gt;Law&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Princeton's Combustion Energy Frontier Research Center's Summer School in Combustion is an intensive one-week seminar series held annually at Princeton University, during which advanced graduate students and researchers in combustion and energy will take two courses of 15 hours each. The participants are outstanding senior graduate students sent by their respective supervisors, from all across the country, as well as faculty members and research staff from government and industrial labs. These participants hold strong potential to be leaders in the combustion and energy R&amp;D community. Scholarships are available to students enrolled in U.S. academic institutions to cover local expenses. The 2010 session drew in more than 120 participants. Videos of the 2010 lectures by Professor Norbert Peters on Combustion Theory, and by Drs. Stephen J. Klippenstein and Charles K. Westbrook on Combustion Chemistry are available at iTunes University and the Princeton University website at:&lt;br/&gt;http://deimos.apple.com/WebObjects/Core.woa/Browse/princeton.edu.4746982603.04746982605 and http://www.princeton.edu/engineering/video/combustion-2010/ respectively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2011 session is scheduled to be held on June 26 to July 1. This year the number of applicants has surpassed last year?s and we have thus far admitted 133 with a growing waiting list, which we intend to accommodate. We shall continue to offer the two foundation courses of Combustion Theory and Combustion Chemistry, but have commissioned alternate lecturers so that returning students can get a different perspective of the same topics. Furthermore, we have added a third course, on Combustion Laser Diagnostics. The lecturers are Professor Moshe Matalon from University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign on Combustion Theory, Professor Michael J. Pilling from the University of Leeds, UK on Combustion Chemistry, and Professor Marcus Aldén from Lund University, Sweden on Combustion Laser Diagnostics. The week-long lecture series will again be professionally videotaped and made available to the public. Lecture notes and course materials will be prepared and distributed to the participants for advanced reading before commencement of the Summer School. More information on the Summer School is available at: http://www.princeton.edu/cefrc/combustionsummer-school/.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1137883</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chung</FirstName>
      <LastName>Law</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cklaw@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
