<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Workshops to Facilitate Engineering Research Related to 2011 Tohoku-Kanto Earthquake and Tsunami</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>39989</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kishor Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Tohoku-Kanto earthquake of March 9, 2011 and the tsunami that followed it, though unfortunately devastating, are very unique events of unparalleled scientific and engineering interest. This earthquake has caused extensive damage to built environment, yet there are examples of structures that have survived the strong shaking. Apparently, Japanese researchers have already collected some information about the damaged and undamaged structures and are willing to share this information with their US counterparts. Much can be learnt from further in-depth analysis of this information to understand the causes of failures and survivals of these structures with the objective of preventing this from happening in future events. This project will support the travel to Japan of a team of researchers to enable them to meet with Japanese engineers and researchers to gather data and information about the damage caused by this earthquake and tsunami that can be shared with US researchers. The team will hold workshops and meetings with Japanese researchers to gather information about what data of research interest is available, and disseminate this information to the wider research community in the US through webcast seminars, Webex-type workshops, and meetings. This is expected to lead to future international research collaborations between the US and Japanese researchers for in-depth scientific investigations about the performance of the built environment during strong earthquakes, with the final objective of mitigating the impact of such mega-events and disasters.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1137811</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mahin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mahin@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
      <CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5106428109</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
