<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Symposium - Adaptations for Salt and Water Balance in Vertebrates, Nagoya Japan, May 31 - June 5, 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Ellis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>These funds support participation of graduate students, post-doctoral fellows, and young&lt;br/&gt;investigators at the International Conference on Comparative Physiology and Biochemistry&lt;br/&gt;(ICCPB 2011), to be held in Nagoya, Japan. Participants will build world-wide connections and&lt;br/&gt;gain cross-cultural exposure to institutions interested in global environmental effects on animals.&lt;br/&gt;Advances in understanding how animals adapt to environmental changes will support goals of&lt;br/&gt;safeguarding biodiversity at all levels. Funds will support individuals who have demonstrated&lt;br/&gt;exceptional aptitude and potential for advancing the field of epithelial fluid and solute dynamics&lt;br/&gt;and its regulation. A select group of individuals will present talks in a symposium focusing on&lt;br/&gt;concepts essential to understanding the role of epithelia in water and solute balance this&lt;br/&gt;balance has an overarching role in maintaining all life's basic functions. Epithelia are found in all&lt;br/&gt;organs, and exist as sheets of cells, assembled together by precisely arranged junctional proteins&lt;br/&gt;that lie between cells. Notably, the dynamics of water and solute flows through cells of the&lt;br/&gt;epithelial sheet are highly integrated with flows through junctions of the epithelial sheet, in a&lt;br/&gt;regulated, but poorly understood fashion. The symposium speakers will stress the importance of&lt;br/&gt;how and why cell-to-cell contact and plasticity of these systems are fundamental to appropriate&lt;br/&gt;tissue water and solute dynamics for all vertebrates. Other individuals supported by this grant&lt;br/&gt;will have the opportunity to present their research findings, face-to-face in poster sessions, with&lt;br/&gt;scientists from nearly every continent who work in widely diverse biological fields. A major goal&lt;br/&gt;will be to identify and select women and individuals of underrepresented ethnic minority&lt;br/&gt;background as recipients of these travel funds. Funding for student and trainee initiatives at&lt;br/&gt;ICCPB 2011 will play a key role in attracting and retaining the brightest and best-trained&lt;br/&gt;comparative physiologists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1137275</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pannabecker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pannabec@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7658</Code>
      <Text>Physiolg Mechansms&amp;Biomechancs</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1228</Code>
      <Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
