<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CREST: Center of Excellence in Nanobiomaterials Derived from Biorenewable and Waste Resources</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5200000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Victor A. Santiago</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Tuskegee University will initiate a 5-year Center of Research Excellence in Science and Technology project to develop new nano-bio-materials derived from bio-renewable and waste resources. The research focus areas of the center are: (a) synthesis of nanofibers; (b) production of bacterial cellulose fibers from soy waste products (c); synthesis of nanoparticles from biodegradable sources like egg shells and their use as nano-fillers in advanced composites; (d) synthesis of biopolymers; (e) development and characterization of advanced green nanocomposites using these materials with natural fibers; and (f) product design, prototyping and commercial feasibility studies. The project will include a robust education and outreach program to train/educate K-12 and community college students and teachers. The proposed Center will also provide significant boost to the PhD program in Materials Science and Engineering at Tuskegee University. The program will include active partnerships with Cornell University, the University of Alabama at Birmingham, and Auburn University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will be organized around the following subprojects:&lt;br/&gt;1. Synthesis and characterization of nanobiomaterials.&lt;br/&gt;2. Synthesis and characterization of biopolymers and nanobiocomposites&lt;br/&gt;3. Processing, Performance Evaluation, and technology transition of Advanced Green Nanobiocomposites to products&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs and their students will extract bacterial cellulose fibers from waste sugars obtained from defatted soy flour and calcium carbonate nanoparticles from egg shells. They then make use of them along with biopolymers to make composites. Calcium carbonate nanoparticles have many potential applications in polymer composites as fillers and property enhancers. They are also considered as materials for biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current generation of composites materials utilize petroleum based polymers and man-made fibers like glass and carbon which are energy intensive to produce. These materials have two significant disadvantages. First, they are based on petroleum feedstock, a non-renewable resource. Second, they are not biodegradable. At the end of their service life, about 95% are discarded in landfills while a small fraction is incinerated or crushed into powder for use as filler. These alternatives energy intensive and potentially environmentally hazardous. Another class of materials that end up in land-fills includes egg shells. Hence, there is an attractive potential to develop materials that are environment-friendly and biodegradable at the end of their design life. The materials so developed will provide alternative to the current generation of high performance "advanced" composites materials, which could have a positive impact on landfill use and lead to a wide range of new green technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merits lie in the fact that the development of biodegradable nanofibers, nanoparticles, nanobiopolymers and their characterization, processing and characterization of advanced green composites will provide significant knowledge that can be used to develop new applications in automotive and building industries. The processes and knowledge developed through the three subprojects will help in diversifying the research portfolio into other fields like drug delivery, packaging, wound healing, and pharmaceuticals that will result in sustaining the center beyond the funding period. The materials developed will provide an environment-friendly alternative to currently used synthetic, non-biodegradable, petroleum based fiber reinforced composites. A diverse group of nationally and internationally recognized scientists and engineers has been assembled to pursue state-of-the-art research and education endeavors through three synergistically linked subprojects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project include production of a large number of graduates with BS through PhD degrees, including, a significant number of minorities and women. These graduates will be adequately trained in emerging areas of nano-bio science and technology with excellent communication and interpersonal skills. They will interact with researchers outside of USA through participation in international conferences abroad and working in the laboratories on partnering institutions in Brazil and India. Such graduates will become excellent role models for many young students and help bring much-needed diversity to the nation's advanced technological workforce. Broader societal impact includes reduced dependence on petroleum products, utilization of waste products to produce engineering materials and products, and a partial solution to landfill problems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1137681</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Anil</FirstName>
      <LastName>Netravali</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ann2@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mahesh</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hosur</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hosur@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vijaya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rangari</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rangariv@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shaik</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zainuddin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>szainuddin@mytu.tuskegee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/15/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Tuskegee University</Name>
      <CityName>Tuskegee Institute</CityName>
      <ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3347278233</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 W Montgomery Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alabama</StateName>
      <StateCode>AL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9131</Code>
      <Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1594</Code>
      <Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
