<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Expansion of Metadata Management, Visualization and Data Processing Functionality of OBIS-SEAMAP</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>314269</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Proposal was submitted to the National Ocean Partnership Program (NOPP) Broad Agency Announcement 10-024 titled "Marine Mammal Detection and Monitoring" and selected for funding by NSF.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's request funding to create a three-tiered hierarchical framework to process and disseminate passive acoustic monitoring (PAM) data. The PI's will expand the capabilities of OBIS-SEAMAP to allow better metadata management, easier access to available data, and improved visualization and processing tools. Currently the availability of raw and processed acoustic data is not easily accessible from a centralized location. The expansion of OBIS-SEAMAP proposed by the PI's would provide the tools for researchers and managers to obtain data, and process it to obtain usable results (e.g. maps of animal locations relative to oceanographic features, animations of animal locations over time).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The developments from this study would benefit users of OBIS-USA, iOBIS and GBIF networks. A technical workshop will be organized by the PI's to discuss developing improvements in OBIS SEAMAP functions with input from passive acoustic experts. The resulting improvements to OBIS SEAMAP will become publicly available and the improvements in data visualizations can be used for both research and educational purposes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/29/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1138046</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
      <LastName>Halpin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>phalpin@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
