<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Identifying activity areas at ancient Maya salt works, Belize</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Under the supervision of Dr. Heather McKillop, E. Cory Sills will conduct dissertation research to clarify the organization of craft production at one Early Classic (A.D. 300-600) and one Late Classic (A.D. 600-900) ancient Maya salt work in Paynes Creek National Park, Belize. Ms. Sills seeks to identify evidence of salt production and/or other activities. Were the sites dedicated to a single activity, household workshops, or used in "multicrafting"? Ms. Sills conducted her dissertation fieldwork as part of the ongoing NSF "Ancient Maya Wooden Architecture and the Salt Industry" project directed by Dr. McKillop. Wooden architecture and ceramics are preserved underwater on the sea floor in a peat bog at the Paynes Creek salt works. The peat has preserved wood, botanical remains, and large ceramic vessels, but not bone. Ongoing research indicates the sites were salt works identified from the large quantities of briquetage - pottery used to boil brine over fires to make salt. This evidence suggests that the salt works may be specialized and not associated with households, an interpretation that will add a new aspect to the study of economic production and distribution for the ancient Maya and other ancient civilizations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In a broader context the research is significant because it will provide insight into the intersection of economic and social realms in a traditional society and how these changed over time. Archaeology provides the ability to examine change over long time scales - centuries and millennia - and thus discern patterns which might otherwise be invisible. In many traditional societies in the world today, production proceeds in a family context and the results of this research may provide increased understanding of such situations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The importance of salt production in the ancient Maya economy is known. In order to evaluate the organization of production, transect excavations were conducted at two of the Paynes Creek salt works by Ms. Sills in June of 2010. In this NSF grant, Ms. Sills will use chemical analysis of marine sediment along excavated transects to detect if there is evidence of household waste not preserved in the peat. Neutron activation analysis will identify if the pottery is of local or non-local manufacture. The results of the compositional analysis of ceramics will aid in determining if the salt works were organized locally or integrated into a larger production and exchange system. The 3D imaging of pottery sherds will help to define the shapes and sizes of containers. Clusters of wooden posts from both sites will be radiocarbon dated to refine site chronology since the briquetage is not temporally sensitive.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are multiple. Project participants will promote the results of the project within the United States and internationally. The researchers will publish reports and data obtained in their project to a diverse array of interested stakeholders including both public and professional audiences. Public outreach efforts in Belize will include producing replicas of artifacts for displays in Punta Gorda, Belize as part of an Archaeological Institute of America Site Preservation Grant to Dr. McKillop. These efforts will seek to improve public understanding of the ancient Maya through the development of science, archaeology, and anthropology. This project will further the mentorship and scientific training of undergraduate and graduate students working in the archaeological lab and Digital Imaging and Visualization in Archaeology (DIVA) lab at Louisiana State University by involving them in the analysis of artifacts and development of public outreach in southern Belize.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1139178</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
      <LastName>McKillop</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hmckill@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sills</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>e.corysills@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/02/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1391</Code>
      <Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
