<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Rapid: Activation of the Inner Continental Shelf In Response to the Great Mississippi/Atchafalaya River Flood of 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bilal U. Haq</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Mississippi River and Atchafalaya River are experiencing a historic flood of major geological significance. South Louisiana has one of the fastest land loss rates on any region on Earth, with much of the loss due to a lack of sediment delivery into the coastal zone. This flood is likely to deliver large amounts of sediments to the coastal zone, and therefore could potentially contribute to land building along the South Louisiana coast. This research is a rapid response to investigate whether the massive release of freshwater from the Atchafalaya River in late May, 2011 will lead to the development of a freshwater-dominated continental shelf environment and whether sediments released by the flood will initiate the development of a large mobile mud belt that will extend from the mouth of the Atchafalaya River westward along the Chenier Plain Coast. These hypotheses are being tested by examining the physical and geological oceanography of the inner continental shelf and determining the patterns of recently deposited sediments. The proposed research provides a rare opportunity to study the critical processes of sediment supply and land building in a coastal ecosystem. Broader impacts include support of two institutions in EPSCoR states and student training.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1140307</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chunyan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cli@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/06/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1620</Code>
      <Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
