<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Going Further: An Integrative Approach to a more Research-oriented, Exploratory Junior-level Lab</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>174547</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nicole Bennett</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project in the Department of Chemistry is developing a junior-level, studio-style laboratory to replace traditional labs associated with Physical Chemistry I and II, Instrumental Analysis, and Inorganic Chemistry. The collaborative, in-depth experience being provided by this guided inquiry approach is bridging the gap, in a deliberate continuous chain-of-engagement method, for students as they transition from a multi-week synthesis project at the end of their sophomore year to the year-long original research project conducted in their fourth and final year of study. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is increasing student learning opportunities by adding isothermal titration calorimetry and zeta-potential measurements to both the Chemistry and Biochemstry curricula. The instruments being purchased through this grant and the experimental measurements they allow, are providing students with cutting edge experiences in nanotechnology and in biochemistry, and are equipping students with advanced technological understanding and enhanced scientific skills. The project is a part of a deliberate and systematic plan that is preparing students to perform research independently. The three semester long projects being added to the studio lab are: (1) examining the formation reaction dynamics, stability and properties of colloidal zinc sulfide and suspended polypyrrole; (2) using vibrational spectroscopy, particularly Raman, to analyze the different parameters related to the synthesis and characterization of nanoparticles; and (3) an examination of the kinetics, thermodynamics, and non-covalent interactions for an enzyme-substrate pair.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The studio laboratory approach is addressing a need for enhanced mentor-mentee relationship and is bolstering team working skills by enabling peer interactions in a more-open lab environment. The project is an intentional effort in sustaining and growing curricular choices that have proven effective in not only recruiting and retaining minority and/or women students, but also in encouraging students to consider further education and, ultimately, working in the STEM disciplines. The project is providing valuable insight into the conversion of advanced labs into studio-labs that will aid those in the broader community as they seek to implement similar conversions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1140008</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Caryn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seney</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>seney_cs@mercer.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Goode</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>goode_dr@mercer.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dale</FirstName>
      <LastName>Moore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>moore_de@mercer.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mercer University</Name>
      <CityName>Macon</CityName>
      <ZipCode>312070001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4783012700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1501 Mercer University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
