<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transforming Linear Algebra Education with GeoGebra Applets</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>164235</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ron Buckmire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is developing twelve interactive applets that use 2-D and 3-D animation to help students visualize concepts in linear algebra (e.g. vectors, vector spaces, linear transformations, eigenvalues, eigenvectors, determinants, and orthogonality). The project is using GeoGebra, a free, easy to access and use software package that is compatible with multiple platforms including mobile phones and computer tablets, and has wide use nationally. Accompanying each applet are directions for use and an instructional module with examples and learning exercises usable both in formal classes and independently by students and teachers. Each module also includes an example STEM-application to provide context for the use of the corresponding applet. The intellectual merit of this project is grounded in research that indicates helping students visualize mathematical processes promotes better understanding of the concepts involved. Moreover, by focusing on linear algebra with its extensive applications in chemistry, physics, engineering and similar fields, the project is filling a gap within the larger collection of educational applets that promote learning of mathematical concepts. The perspectives of a set of beta testers and reviewers are informing the development work, and a well-considered experimental design is being used to assess the applets' impact on student learning. With respect to broader impacts, the project is using an aggressive dissemination plan featuring conference workshops and mini-courses, a dedicated web server for exploring and downloading the applets, plus the GeoGebraWiki to facilitate interactions among developers and users. The flexibility of the GeoGebra software and its adaptability for use on multiple platforms including mobile devices also contribute to the project's potential for broad impact and support from a growing community of GeoGebra developers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1141045</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Factor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>james.factor@alverno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pustejovsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>susan.pustejovsky@alverno.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Alverno College</Name>
      <CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
      <ZipCode>532343922</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4143826347</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 S 43rd Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7513</Code>
      <Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
