<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Reconstruction of Near-Surface Tornado Wind Fields from Forest Damage Patterns in Complex Terrain</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99575</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020105</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>A. Gannet Hallar</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The recent 27 April 2011 tornado outbreak spawned three long-track tornadoes that passed across heavily forested landscapes and mountainous regions. One tornado rated EF-4 passed over the western portion of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, and two other tornadoes, rated EF-2 and EF-3, crossed the mountains of northern Georgia in the Chattahoochee National Forest. Given that this tornado outbreak caused severe economic and human losses to the nation, a prompt and thorough scientific investigation is imperative.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project combines observed forest damage in complex terrain with simulated vortices in an effort to reconstruct the near-surface wind field during the passage of tornadoes. The objectives are to 1) retrospectively characterize surface wind fields for three strong, long-track tornadoes in heavily-forested landscapes, and 2) determine the aspects of rugged topography that may influence the low-level wind field of strong and relatively rare tornadoes in the mountains. These objectives will allow a test of the hypothesis that significant topographic variations influence the strength and behavior of tornadoes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit:&lt;br/&gt;Because of the difficulties inherent in obtaining direct or remotely-sensed observations of tornadoes in the mountains, alternative approaches that retrospectively characterize the near-surface wind fields must be sought. This rare and notable event provides a unique and valuable opportunity to assess a tornadic wind field along the entire path of the tornado in a heavily forested and mountainous area. Each tornado track through a national forest creates a research opportunity consisting of tens of thousands of trees, each of which provides information on the ambient wind speed and direction when it fell. Combined with information on the physical surroundings, such as slope, topographic position, soil types, and surface elevation, these trees in a tremendous variety of surroundings provide a perfect scenario with which to implement a wind field reconstruction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To date, no studies incorporate terrain into numerical models of low-level tornado dynamics. Thus, the importance of observational studies that characterize the near-surface tornadic wind field in complex topography remains paramount. Damage surveys relying on aerial photography, with confirmation by ground surveys in a portion of the study area, will reveal tree characteristics, location, and orientation data for use as input to a simulation of the interaction between an idealized vortex and trees.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:&lt;br/&gt;The broader benefits to society are plentiful. Results of the research may aid risk assessments by the insurance industry, emergency managers, and forest authorities. The analyses may highlight areas that are more vulnerable to tornadoes in the mountains and will thus shape future structural engineering and geographical placement guidelines for schools, storm shelters, or trailer parks. The tree damage model may reveal characteristics of trees that could eventually lead to improvements in vegetation damage indicators for the Enhanced Fujita scale. Lastly, the PIs expect to educate the general public through online and local news releases regarding the study and its results, with emphasis on the fact that strong tornadoes can and do occur in the mountains. This effort will enhance general awareness of the threat of tornadoes in areas where the public may not recognize the dangers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, the research will train both graduate and undergraduate students. The PIs and students will participate in various national conferences and workshops. The project will also promote interdisciplinary collaborations from areas such as meteorology, forestry, ecology, environmental engineering, geography, and social sciences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1141926</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
      <LastName>Peterson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chris@plantbio.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Godfrey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cgodfrey@unca.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1525</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
