<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Graduate Student Travel Support for the 11th North American Masonry Conference (NAMC) of The Masonry Society (TMS); Minneapolis, Minnesota, 5-8 June 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kishor Mehta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides funds to enhance graduate student participation in the 11th North American Masonry Conference (NAMC) of The Masonry Society (TMS). The 11th NAMC brings together experts from diverse fields with a strong interest in masonry structures. One of the focal points of the 11th NAMC is the investigation of new applications of mechanics in enabling future advances in masonry technology. Academics, industry representatives and students from many fields (civil engineering, engineering mechanics, architecture and others) have committed to presenting research results on a wide range of topics relayed to masonry structures and mechanics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These funds will allow the conference organizers to attract graduate students to the 11th NAMC to present their work. The students will present their work to an international audience of academics and researchers, they will learn about the most recent advances in the field of masonry structures, and they will be inspired to continue working in and contributing to the field. The conference participation will also facilitate cross-pollination between the disparate fields that comprise the masonry research community, as well as between the US research community with those in other countries. The 11th NAMC forum will help foster an environment that allows for the anticipation of new challenges that engineers face with regards to masonry structures, thereby facilitating professional growth to ensure that the challenges are met.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1142128</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arturo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schultz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schul088@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
