<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: High-throughput 3-D Insect Data Capture Enabling Large Scale Specimen Digitization and Machine Species Identification</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I is directed toward high-throughput robotic&lt;br/&gt;imaging and data capture of 3D physical insect specimens with applications to national intelligence and&lt;br/&gt;security, vector epidemiology, agriculture, biodiversity research, and museum curation. Natural history&lt;br/&gt;museums are vast, largely untapped sources of biological data for addressing complex questions ranging&lt;br/&gt;from tracking terrorists to climate change. Yet ~1 billion U.S. specimens remain in museum drawers and&lt;br/&gt;cabinets, their characteristics, associated data, and even their existence hidden. Insects preserved on&lt;br/&gt;pins represent a significant proportion, with the ten largest collections housing over 100 million. While the&lt;br/&gt;scope of collections is immense, the expertise needed to identify insects of importance is in decline as&lt;br/&gt;taxonomists retire and university positions close. For some insect groups, few or no experts remain&lt;br/&gt;capable of identifying species. The proposed technology will radically accelerate the pace of insect&lt;br/&gt;specimen digitization. It will capture critical data from museum specimens and revitalize taxonomy by&lt;br/&gt;providing datasets for computer-automated insect identification efforts. The project demonstrates robotic&lt;br/&gt;handling of pinned specimens is feasible, enabling a high-throughput system capable of manipulating&lt;br/&gt;pinned specimens, partitioning the 3D scene, photographing specimens, and extracting database&lt;br/&gt;information with OCR rendering of specimen labels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project spans myriad applications. Insects vector&lt;br/&gt;important diseases of humans, livestock, and crops. Annually, malaria is implicated in a million human&lt;br/&gt;deaths worldwide and aphids and their viruses cost US farmers over one billion dollars. New invasive&lt;br/&gt;insects regularly arrive on our shores undetected. Insects also have forensics applications, locating&lt;br/&gt;events in time and place and calculating times of death. Tools to quickly and efficiently identify insects&lt;br/&gt;have immediate application in vector epidemiology, agricultural and environmental monitoring, border&lt;br/&gt;security and port inspection, law enforcement, and intelligence. Spatial-temporal data associated with&lt;br/&gt;field collection of insect specimens are crucial for geolocation forensics, tracking climate change and&lt;br/&gt;range expansion of invasive species, and locating geographic sources of potential biological control&lt;br/&gt;agents for exotic pests. Current technologies and specimen digitization practices take too much time, cost&lt;br/&gt;too much money, and simply cannot image most specimens. Semi-automated systems address only&lt;br/&gt;microscope slide- or paper-mounted specimens. Currently no technology exists to even partially&lt;br/&gt;automate the digitization of individual pinned insect specimens. Potential customers include insect&lt;br/&gt;collections, museums, agribusinesses, epidemiologists, and agents in homeland security, port inspection,&lt;br/&gt;environmental monitoring, and national intelligence. Enormous secondary commercial potential exists&lt;br/&gt;with value-added online databases.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1143119</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sieracki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>NSFContact@sr2group.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SR2 Group, LLC</Name>
      <CityName>Laurel</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207072915</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3016040001</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>14900 Sweitzer Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
