<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for U.S. Graduate Students to Participate in EDBT/ICDT 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The purpose of this project is to promote student participation in the long-running EDBT/ICDT conference series, to be held in March 2012 in Berlin, Germany. This will be the 15th EDBT and 15th ICDT, and will be the 4th year continuously that the two conferences are run as a joint one. These two conferences are internationally leading database systems and theory conferences, and have been well attended by the leading researchers in the area from all over the world. Being in Europe, the joint conference tends to attract more European researchers than other database conferences do. This student travel grant will encourage the interaction of the US students with their counterparts and senior researchers from Europe and elsewhere, increasing the international awareness of the participating US students. Students participation of international scientific discussion forums is always an important part of their education and a great way to build a mature work force in scientific research. The project will also emphasize on recruiting under-represented groups of students in this effort.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1144371</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Elke</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rundensteiner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rundenst@cs.wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
