<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Effects of population genetic diversity on colonization success</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>310822</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saran Twombly</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Why do some species introductions fail and some succeed? Answers to this question are critically important to the fields of ecology, invasive species biology, ecological restoration and biological control. While larger numbers of propagules (e.g. seeds or eggs) are known to increase colonization success, how much of this effect is due to propagule number alone or to the greater genetic diversity usually contained within larger colonizing populations remains a puzzle. This project will experimentally decouple genetic diversity from propagule number to test whether genetically diverse colonizing populations are more likely to succeed than genetically depauperate ones. Using the model plant, Arabidopsis, the investigators will manipulate both genetic diversity and seed number in natural environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study will significantly advance our understanding of the basic ecological principles governing colonization events and provide valuable insights for controlling weedy and invasive species. It will also inform ecological restoration and biological control efforts, which require decisions about how many individuals and genotypes to introduce. It will provide training for one early-career postdoctoral researcher and six undergraduate research assistants; many of the undergraduates will be recruited from underrepresented groups in the sciences. Lastly, this project will be used in teaching modules that will be developed and implemented in partnership with a Houston public high school and then made freely available to other educators online.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/12/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1146203</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whitney</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whitneyk@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hovick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hovick.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/12/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tom.miller@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
