<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Stereotype Endorsement in Achievement Settings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tamera Schneider</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A large literature documents the pernicious influence of stereotypes in performance contexts. When stereotypes are made salient, targets of these stereotypes tend to underachieve, and distance themselves from domains in which stereotypes are relevant. The aim of the proposal is to investigate a novel means by which stereotypes become salient and may spread within these settings. Building on attribution theory, self-handicapping, and stereotype threat research, Dr. Scott Eidelman (University of Arkansas) proposes that performers sometimes endorse stereotypes against their group to discount potential failure, and that doing so may shield the self from performance deficits otherwise experienced. In other words, by agreeing with aspects of certain stereotypes, people can (ironically) protect themselves from the sting of failure or feel particularly good about themselves when they succeed in a domain in which stereotypes about their group are highly prevalent. These predictions will be tested by manipulating factors known to instigate both discounting motives and stereotype threat effects (e.g., test importance), as well as the opportunity to endorse stereotypes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research has theoretical and practical implications. It weaves several research areas to test the ecologically valid but provocative claim that performers sometimes endorse stereotypes against their group to protect their own personal standing. By delineating a sharp distinction between awareness and endorsement of stereotypes, this research addresses when the performance of underrepresented groups may suffer from the pernicious influence of group expectations while also identifying factors that may offset or even reverse this process. This research also promises broader impacts: it provides a bridge between the fields of psychology and education and provides opportunities for under-represented groups to take part in all aspects of the research process. Results of these studies will be disseminated widely to scholars and the public, including students and educators, so that all may be informed of the impact of stereotypes in achievement setttings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1146081</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eidelman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eidelman@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/28/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
      <CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1332</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1332</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
