<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RAPID: Deploying VentCam as a Data Collection Base Station for the Axial Seamount SensorBot Array</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36724</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI requests funds to repurpose the VentCam seafloor camera system to act as a data receiving base station during a test of the SensorBot array at Axial Seamount on the Juan de Fuca Ridge during August of 2011. The SensorBot array is a set of optically communicating and fluorescently sensing polycarbonate spheres that measure diffuse hydrothermal fluid properties using novel fluorescent polymers developed originally for use in human health applications. The redeployment of this technology will involve a substantial rewrite of the VentCam control software, and minor changes to hardware. This project represents a low-cost opportunity to demonstrate the versatility of the VentCam, and maximize its benefit to the seafloor scientific community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will also demonstrate the versatility of the VentCam system and the potential applicability of this system to address a variety of seafloor instrumentation problems. There will be several undergraduate students joining this cruise who will work alongside scientists, engineers, and the ship?s crew to gain experience using oceanographic instrumentation and to conduct their own research. As an early career scientist, this project will support the PI?s efforts to develop novel seafloor</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1147104</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>crone@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1680</Code>
      <Text>OCEAN TECH &amp; INTERDISC COORDIN</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7914</Code>
      <Text>RAPID</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
