<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Distributed Resource Allocation and Interference Management for Dense Heterogeneous Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>328810</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This NSF collaboration project investigates the design and optimization of dynamic resource allocation and interference management strategies for spectrally efficient wireless heterogeneous networks that provide multi-level coverage and services. This research project is motivated by the recent advances in 4G wireless systems on the deployment and standardization of heterogeneous networks (HetNet). Such networks provide services to mobile subscribers of different priorities and dynamic quality needs. As more and more advanced physical layer schemes and medium access protocols are being integrated into wireless standards, future performance gain and progress in wireless networks have to rely more on intelligent resource allocation and interference management strategies that are dynamical and are adaptively responsive to location-and-time specific environment. In this project, the research team will address critical deployment issues that arise in HetNet by focusing on the development of distributed and effective mechanisms for resource allocation and interference management in order to facilitate low complexity and decentralized network operation in heterogeneous environments. The project methodology is based on novel optimization frameworks for interference control and suppression in HetNet. The research goal is to develop robust and reliable solutions for practical implementations of HetNet. The project results will facilitate novel technological directions that transcend multiple networks and multiple network layers. In particular, the results will assist the near term deployment of wireless HetNet, including the broad application of femtocell deployment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technical impacts of this international collaboration project are broad both domestically and internationally. Results from successful execution of the project are expected to significantly impact the design, deployment, and operation of future wireless networks. The plan to disseminating research findings at quality journals and technical conferences will contribute directly to the wireless industry by providing critical information on interference control and management for high spectral efficiency and user satisfaction. The project outcomes can also establish new research directions for the international telecommunications community. The project activities will lead to new analytical tools and discoveries that can impact other science and engineering research fields. The project will further contribute to the training of highly qualified personnel for the hi-tech industry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1147930</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>liu@cs.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ding</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zding@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7363</Code>
      <Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
