<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The 1st Symposium on Large Data Analysis and Visualization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9637</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In many areas of science, simulations and experiments begin to generate many petabytes of data, with some sciences facing exabytes of data near term. Similarly, the collection of information about the Internet applications and users for a variety of purposes is generating only more data. Our ability to manage, mine, analyze, and visualize the data is fundamental to the knowledge discovery process. That is, the value of data at extreme scale can be fully realized only if we have an end-to-end solution, which demands a collective, inter-disciplinary effort to develop. We are in need of an international venue to gather researchers and practitioners from government agencies, universities, industry, and oversea to exchange ideas and experience, layout research directions, and establish collaborations. The first symposium on large data analysis and visualization is founded to serve those purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed symposium, held during October 23-24 in conjunction with VisWeek 2011, aims at bringing together domain scientists, data analytics and visualization researchers, and users, and fostering the needed exchange to develop the next-generation data-intensive analysis and visualization technology. Attendees of the symposium are introduced to the latest and greatest research innovations in large data management, analysis, and visualization, learn how these innovations impact data intensive computing and knowledge discovery, and also learn about the critical issues in creating a complete solution through both invited and contributed talks, poster presentations, panel discussion, and a large data visualization contest that provides massive data and supercomputing time to contestants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1147363</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kwan-Liu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ma@cs.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7364</Code>
      <Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7942</Code>
      <Text>HIGH-PERFORMANCE COMPUTING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
