<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Energy Efficient Cognitive Networking</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>171450</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Wenjing Lou</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project addresses two of the grand challenges of the next decade: green wireless communication systems and spectrum efficiency, through a collaborative research and education plan utilizing optimization theory, and involving researchers from the U.S. and Finland. This project considers energy efficiency for cognitive radio networks and introduces a novel optimization-based methodology. It builds on existing results to establish a new focus on green cognitive networking. The way in which energy is consumed in cognitive networks provides unique opportunities for exploiting the cognitive process to save energy and for using energy reduction techniques to modify and improve the performance of cognitive networks. A unique feature of this project is the introduction of an optimization-based methodology for establishing and attaining ultimate performance limits. In this project, PIs develop energy performance bounds that yield insights for design of general networks, derive optimal tradeoffs between fundamental performance criteria, use optimization formulations for establishing and achieving ultimate performance limits, and design protocols that are optimal in the presence of temporal cognitive systems evolution. Research results of this work will be widely promulgated through the usual means of publication and dissemination and will have significant impact on energy efficiency of spectrum-efficient wireless systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1147603</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alhussein</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abouzeid</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abouzeid@ecse.rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/30/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
