<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: SI2-SSI: Open Source Support for Massively Parallel, Generic Finite Element Methods</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1311834</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajiv Ramnath</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Partial differential equations are used in a wide variety of applications as&lt;br/&gt;mathematical models. Their numerical solution is, consequently, of prime&lt;br/&gt;importance for the accurate simulation and optimization of processes in the&lt;br/&gt;sciences, engineering, and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;The last decade saw the emergence of large and successful libraries that&lt;br/&gt;support such applications. While these libraries provide most of what such&lt;br/&gt;codes need for small-scale computations, many realistic applications yield&lt;br/&gt;problems of hundreds of millions or billions of unknowns and require clusters&lt;br/&gt;with thousands of processor cores, but there is currently little generic&lt;br/&gt;support for such problems, limiting access to the many large publicly&lt;br/&gt;supported computing facilities to experts in computational science and&lt;br/&gt;excluding scientists from many fields for whom computational simulation would&lt;br/&gt;be a useful tool. This project intends to build the software infrastructure that will allow a&lt;br/&gt;wide cross section of scientists to utilize these large resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project intends to support the software infrastructure for the&lt;br/&gt;large-scale solution of partial differential equations on massively parallel&lt;br/&gt;computational resources in a generic way. It will build on two of the most&lt;br/&gt;successful libraries for scientific computing, the finite element library&lt;br/&gt;deal.II, and Trilinos that provides the parallel linear algebra capabilities&lt;br/&gt;for the former. Specifically, we will: (i) Make support for massively parallel&lt;br/&gt;computations ubiquitous in deal.II; (ii) Research and develop seamless support&lt;br/&gt;for problems with billions of unknowns in both libraries and improve the&lt;br/&gt;interaction between the two; (iii) Exploit intra-node parallelism on today's&lt;br/&gt;clusters; (iv) Ensure the applicability of our work on a broad basis by&lt;br/&gt;implementing two real-world applications. &lt;br/&gt;Both deal.II and Trilinos have large, active and diverse developer and user&lt;br/&gt;communities, and this project will actively engage these communities through&lt;br/&gt;user meetings, short courses, regularly taught classes, mailing lists, and&lt;br/&gt;direct contact in focused projects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1148116</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wolfgang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bangerth</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bangerth@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yassin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hassan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>y-hassan@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454321</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798458600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8004</Code>
      <Text>Software Institutes</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7433</Code>
      <Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8009</Code>
      <Text>Scientifc Software Integration</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8004</Code>
      <Text>Software Institutes</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
