<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Integrated Research and Education on Microscale Ferrohydrodynamic Manipulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>442000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Shubhra Gangopadhyay</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Objective: The objective of this program is to combine theoretical, numerical and experimental studies to investigate ferrofluid hydrodynamics and its applications in manipulating non-magnetic objects (such as molecules, particles, cells and droplets) at the micro-scale for lab-on-a-chip applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The intellectual merit is a multi-disciplinary research program that incorporates colloidal chemistry, magnetism and fluid mechanics, combining fundamental modeling and analysis with application-oriented experiments. It results in testable theoretical predictions and a physical understanding of ferrohydrodynamic manipulation of molecules and particles that enables practical and useful applications in microfluidic devices. A novel approach involving ferrofluids will be used to provide a magnetically uniform environment for molecules and cells, which can be transported with controlled speed and direction via external magnetic fields. Fast mixing of molecules and efficient manipulation of cells within ferrofluids will be enabled through this research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The broader impacts are: (1) this program will not only advance the fundamental understanding of coupled nano-scale magnetic phenomena and fluid dynamics, but also produce a transformative magnetic manipulation platform that is applicable to a broad range of areas such as microfluidic biosensors, diagnostic chips, blood cleansing devices, and single cell studies; (2) this program will integrate research with lectures and laboratory assignments for undergraduate and graduate students, increase minority and female students? participations in science and engineering, and bring awareness of scientific concepts to K-12 students using ferrofluids through a ?Summer Institute? for K-12 teachers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1150042</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leidong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mao</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mao@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/26/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7564</Code>
      <Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>090E</Code>
      <Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
