<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Ultrafast Dynamics of Interfacial Water</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>712080</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this CAREER project, supported by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program of the Chemistry Division, Prof. Poul Petersen of Cornell University will examine the ultrafast dynamics of interfacial water with new advanced nonlinear optical spectroscopic methods. A wealth of phenomena encompassing reactions in the atmosphere, biological processes, and proton transfer in fuel cells take place on/at wet hydrated surfaces. While it is increasingly recognized that water is not a passive solvent but plays an integral role in such processes, we do not have a good understanding of either the structure or the dynamics of interfacial water and how these are influenced by the chemical nature of the surface. This research program aims to attain such an understanding by directly measuring the ultrafast dynamics of interfacial water. This goal will be reached by developing coherent surface-specific two-dimensional infrared spectroscopy. This technique is able to directly measure the couplings and dynamics of the OH stretching vibration of interfacial water molecules, which are a sensitive measure of the hydrogen-bonding dynamics. Using a scaffold of self-assembled monolayers, the chemical nature of the interface will be tuned to obtain the structure-function relationship between the surface properties and the interfacial water dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The result of this research program will impact a diverse set of areas involving chemical processes at wet surfaces. The graduate and undergraduate students involved in the research will be trained in both highly technical optical instrumentation and chemical functionalization of surfaces. Given the majority of female students in the research group, this research program will, in addition, contribute to train and retain female scientists. The hands-on outreach component of this program will target middle and high school students and teachers. Drawing on the optical expertise of the PI, a microscopy/optics module will be developed to engage and excite students and teachers about using light to examine the world around us.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1151079</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Poul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Petersen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pbp33@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9101</Code>
      <Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURE, DYNAMIC &amp; MECHANISM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
