<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Liquid Microjet Studies of Collisions and Reactions at the Surfaces of Aqueous Solutions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>505483</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Colby A. Foss</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics, and Mechanisms Program of the Chemistry Division, Prof. Gilbert Nathanson of the University of Wisconsin-Madison will couple liquid microjets with molecular beams to explore collisions and reactions at the surfaces of volatile aqueous solutions. These gas-liquid scattering experiments will be performed by directing a beam of atoms or molecules at the surface of a liquid jet in vacuum and monitoring the identities, energies, and reaction times of the products with a mass spectrometer. Liquid microjets are narrower than a human hair and are surrounded by only a thin vapor blanket, permitting scattering experiments to be carried out using pure, basic, and salty water solutions with vapor pressures up to several Torr. The proposed research is dedicated to learning how acidic gases such as DCl and oxidizing gases such as F2 react with water molecules and ions at or near the surface. The long term objective is to develop a molecular picture of gas-water reactions by exploring the interfacial analogs of bulk solvation, the "like dissolves like" rule, proton transfer, acid dissociation, and oxidation-reduction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program benefits society through its research, mentoring, and outreach activities. Scientifically, this program will help reveal the ways in which gases and aqueous solutions react industrially and in the environment. It will concurrently provide a setting to mentor graduate and undergraduate students from a wide range of backgrounds. The familiarity gained in this research will further be used to improve General Chemistry classes on aqueous chemistry and to engage K-12 students and their parents through hands-on surface chemistry workshops.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1152737</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gilbert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nathanson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nathanson@chem.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>6879</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURE, DYNAMIC &amp; MECHANISM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
