<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EAGER: Bio-Beams - Functionally Graded Rapid Design &amp; Fabrication</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>106840</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Collopy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The research objective of this EArly concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER)is the creation of a research-driven framework for developing, integrating, and evaluating digital fabrication technologies with biologically inspired form generation to support sustainable construction. Functionally Graded Rapid Fabrication (FGRF) is a novel design approach and technological framework enabling the controlled spatial variation of material properties through continuous gradients in functional components. The work will provide research-based evidence for variable-property form generation informed by environmental performance criteria such as variable-density concrete beams and variable-elasticity polymer panels. Spatial variations of material properties are traditionally achieved as discrete delineations in physical behavior by fabricating multiple parts comprised of different materials, and assembling them only after the fabrication process has been completed. Recent advances in Computational Topology Design (CTD) and Solid Free-Form Fabrication (SFF) are promoting the creation of building components with controlled micro-, and macro-architectural features. The FGRF approach will combine a novel software environment with a mechanical output tool designed as a 6-axes, 3-D printer to allow computer control of material distribution within a monolithic structure. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the project will advance the ability of machines to fabricate with variable properties, and will enable the control of their variation according to the desired environmental input. The new approach will expand current fabrication platforms and will be a significant first step toward variable property digital fabrication. Being the first FGM construction technology, the project has the potential to lead to a line of new research. This interdisciplinary award makes contributions to the fields of digital fabrication, computer-aided design, material science and mechanical engineering. As a novel research platform, the FGRF approach has the potential for reaching a large number of designers, engineers and scientists operating at the intersection of digital design innovation and sustainable construction. Through far-reaching collaborations applying new expertise and engaging novel interdisciplinary perspectives across MIT, the investigator will not only invent these tools and discover how to use them, but lead their translation into design applications while evaluating their contribution to a radically new approach in sustainable design &amp; construction. Long term, this research is also expected to contribute to understanding the theory and practice of sustainable rapid fabrication of variable-property construction. Results will be distributed in all of these communities through peer-reviewed publications and conference presentations, as well as through physical installations and demonstrations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1152550</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Neri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Oxman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>neri@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1464</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING DESIGN AND INNOVAT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1630</Code>
      <Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1635</Code>
      <Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>024E</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>036E</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>067E</Code>
      <Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7916</Code>
      <Text>EAGER</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8025</Code>
      <Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
