<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Interactive Systems in Healthcare 2011</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Crowston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This is funding to support a one day interdisciplinary Workshop on Interactive Systems in Healthcare 2011 (WISH 2011), to be held on October 22, 2011 in conjunction with the 2011 Annual Meeting of the American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA). The workshop will bring together a diverse set of researchers from a range of disciplines, all of whom do research relevant to the development of Interactive Systems for Healthcare but who rarely have opportunities to interact. Attendees will include specialists in medical informatics, nursing informatics, medical sociology, human-computer interaction, and related fields. The goal is to promote interdisciplinary exchange of ideas about this important area of research and to advance the development of new healthcare technologies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participants will be selected through a peer review process based on materials submitted in response to the call for papers. The submission materials include a five-page paper in the AMIA submission format, including an abstract and a description of the participant¨Vs research. The papers for accepted participants will be available as part of the WISH proceedings. Selected papers will be presented as either short talks or interactive posters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: Addressing the complex interplay between human, organizational, and technological systems in healthcare is an important research area with the potential to impact quality, safety, efficiency, and effectiveness of health care in America. The workshop will improve attendees' current research projects through interdisciplinary feedback from other workshop participants, promote this area of research more generally through its visibility at the AMIA conference, lead to new interdisciplinary collaborations that can advance medical informatics, and help educate graduate students and post-doctoral fellows who want to work in this area. A workshop website and proceedings will make the content widely available to other researchers and the general public.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1152556</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Olena</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mamykina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>om2196@cumc.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
