<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2011) Student Travel Awards</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Voyles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests travel funds from NSF to assist 50 US students to participate in IROS 2011, which will be held in San Francisco, CA, Sep. 25-30, 2011. The purpose of this Group Travel Grant Proposal is to make it possible for US students and postdocs to attend the conference, present their work, and forge connections with colleagues from around the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This year mark the 50th anniversary of robotics. In addition to the regular conference, IROS 2011 will feature interactive presentations, robot demonstrations, thematic plenary sessions on design, bio-robotics, and intelligent transportation, and special-topic symposia celebrating 50 years of robotics. As part of this award, students will also have the opportunity to participate in these historical events and learn more about the field of robotics. Travel funding will be in the form of partial airfare reimbursement and full reimbursement for student registration to approximately 50 U.S. students who plan to present at least one paper at the Conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The "big two" major international robotics conferences were outside of North America this past year, so demand should be very high from American students and professors to attend this major robotics event. The benefit to student learning and mentorship by encouraging attendance of students by direct monetary means brings large dividends in student confidence, knowledge and expertise.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1153994</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dylan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dshell@cs.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/07/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
      <CityName>College Station</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7484</Code>
      <Text>IIS SPECIAL PROJECTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1640</Code>
      <Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7752</Code>
      <Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7918</Code>
      <Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
