<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BioScholars II: Supporting Women from Underserved Communities in the Study of Biological Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>599968</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Connie K. Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>BioScholars II, a program of scholarships for 20 academically talented but financially needy students at Pine Manor College, builds on the successes of its predecessor, BioScholars I. It supports such students not only financially, but also academically and personally, to enable them to continue their studies of biology, to graduate, and to enter the workforce or continue in their scientific studies. As a small, all-women's school enrolling a majority of local, low-income, ethnic minority students, Pine Manor targets its support in demonstrably effective ways. In particular, all students are expected to complete a capstone internship, and for BioScholars, this is expected to involve research at one of the colleges, universities, or industries in the Boston area. Teaching postdoctoral fellows from Sackler School of Biomedical Science at Tufts University offer seminar courses in advanced biomedical subjects to BioScholars and other interested students. Talks by visiting speakers, a Science Club, a Sophomore Honors Colloquium, peer and faculty mentoring, and early intervention for students experiencing difficulties round out the program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1154143</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bear</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bearsusan@pmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/07/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pine Manor College</Name>
      <CityName>Boston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021672332</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6177317000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>400 Heath Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
