<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Bellarmine S-STEM Scholars Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: The purpose of this project is to award up to 20 scholarships each year for 4 years to recruit, retain, and graduate academically talented and financially needy undergraduate students majoring in Physics, Chemistry, Computer Science, Computer Engineering, and Mathematics. The objectives of the S-STEM project are to (a) increase enrollment in the targeted STEM fields from underrepresented groups (women, ethnic minorities and first-generation students); (b) increase retention to degree achievement by providing improved educational opportunities in the targeted STEM fields so that the S-STEM scholars can achieve their best academic performance; (c) support these scholars through degree completion with a variety of structured institutional support programs, high quality enrichment activities, and partnering with potential employers to facilitate student career placement in the STEM workforce; and (d) prepare well-educated skilled STEM graduates and increase the number of STEM graduates who enter and remain in the workforce in a STEM-related professional job or enter graduate school in a STEM discipline. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The University is located in a region with a sizable low-income economically disadvantaged African-American inner-city population. The S-STEM leadership team is recruiting students from the local and regional high schools and from low-income families residing in both urban and rural areas, including the distressed counties as designated by the Appalachian Regional Commission. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific support services that are available for these S-STEM scholars to ensure that they excel academically are: an S-STEM scholar orientation program, peer tutoring, faculty mentoring, professional development, and S-STEM living and learning community (which provides an opportunity for S-STEM scholars to live together). S-STEM scholars also have the opportunity to acquire valuable research skills by taking part in faculty-mentored research projects in their respective STEM disciplines, leading to presentations at professional conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1154454</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Akhtar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mahmood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amahmood@bellarmine.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Bellarmine University</Name>
      <CityName>Louisville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>402050671</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5022728263</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2001 Newburg Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
