<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research in DRMS: Integrating construal level theory into risk communication</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10947</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Individuals can perceive the same risk in different ways, construing it either more abstractly or concretely. It is currently not known how one's level of construal affects behavioral response to risks in the real world. The objective of this project is to test if the effects of construal level on decision making found in the laboratory can be replicated with personally relevant risks and environmental problems. Specifically, we are studying if presenting an abstract risk more concretely increases behavioral change and risk perception by presenting the risk of radon in the home in a message frame that reduces psychological distance. Additionally, we are examining if putting the decision maker into an abstract construal level increases behavioral change and risk perception by including a construal level manipulation prior to the risk message to ensure that the risk is being presented on a congruent level of abstraction. Finally, the research is determining which is more effective at bringing about behavioral change by focusing on the risk or the mitigating behavior required by testing two different message frames in an experimental survey. The research demonstrates the most effective way to use construal levels in risk communication to increase their effectiveness and paint a fuller, more nuanced picture of the role of construal levels in real world decision making. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is producing real and meaningful benefits to both public and environmental health. The general framework tested here (encouraging individuals to incur a short term cost in exchange for a greater long term gain) is the same for a myriad of other health risks such as smoking, HIV testing, and sun exposure. An improved method of communicating these risks may result in an increase in the adoption of healthier behaviors, leading to more lives saved and healthier lives lived.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1154305</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wilson.1376@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zwickle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>zwickle.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
