<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Addressing the Gulf Coast Region's Graduation Rate Crisis in Mathematics and Computer Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>583096</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stephanie August</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Addressing the Gulf Coast Region's Graduation Rate Crisis - ASCENT in Mathematics and Computer Science is a collaboration between the Department of Mathematics and Department of Computer Science at Lamar University. The main goal of ASCENT is the graduation of outstanding mathematicians and computer scientists by providing scholarships to community college students who transfer to Lamar University and to current upper level students to complete bachelor's degrees in these two disciplines. Each student receives a scholarship of $10,000 annually for two years. In particular, three cohorts of eight ASCENT Scholars each are served in this five year project. The awarding of these scholarships is complemented by extensive academic support including a Summer Bridge and Enrichment program, undergraduate research, multi-level mentoring, and post-graduation placement. ASCENT is designed to address not only the intrinsic difficulties of degree completion when faced with financial instability, but also the well-known difficulties that transfer students experience as they transition to four-year college life. ASCENT is contributing to the human capital needed for STEM-based industrial growth in Southeast Texas and the Greater Houston Area. In addition, the cohort building aspects of this project can be extended to other student groups. ASCENT is contributing to increase the number of well-educated and skilled employees from diverse backgrounds, including minority and first-generation college students, by helping them graduate in a timely manner.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1154606</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Osborne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ljosborne@my.lamar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dale</FirstName>
      <LastName>Daniel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Dale.Daniel@lamar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Andrei</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sandrei@cs.lamar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kumer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Das</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kumer.das@lamar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/01/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lamar University Beaumont</Name>
      <CityName>Beaumont</CityName>
      <ZipCode>777055748</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4098807011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4400 Port Arthur Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
