<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Training in Redox Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>278500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Sites award has been made to the University of Nebraska-Lincoln that will provide research training for 10 students, for 10 weeks during the summers of 2012-2014. This award is supported by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program, Division of Biological Infrastructure in the Directorate for Biological Sciences, and the Division of Chemistry in the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences. The program focuses on redox biology which involves oxidation-reduction linked biological reactions, redox signaling and regulation, and cellular defense mechanisms that minimize oxidative damage/stress. The summer program will enable students to explore fundamental redox processes related to biotechnology and the environment. The goal of the training program is to involve undergraduate students in broad-based research and significantly impact their career decisions. REU participants will conduct individual research projects under the guidance of a faculty mentor in the Redox Biology Center. The mentors offer a breadth of multidisciplinary approaches and share a common goal of understanding critical redox-active processes. Students will receive experimental training in a variety of areas including molecular biology, microbiology, biochemistry, biophysical chemistry, and protein crystallography, and will utilize state-of-the-art equipment and facilities. In addition, students will attend journal club meetings, career development seminars, lunch discussion groups, and social activities to enhance their cohort experience. The program will conclude with students presenting their research findings at a poster session. Participant selection will be based on academic achievements, research interests, and career goals. Students at smaller institutions with limited research opportunities and those from underrepresented groups are encouraged to apply. REU participants receive a stipend, full room and board, and travel assistance. Information about the program will be assessed by various means, including use of an REU common assessment tool and an alumni database to track the accomplishments and career paths of former participants. More information is available by visiting http://redoxbiologycenter.unl.edu/summer, or by contacting the PI (Dr. Donald Becker at dbecker3@unl.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Julie Stone at jstone2@unl.edu).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156692</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Becker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dbecker3@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stone</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jstone2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/11/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1986</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>K629</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>l644</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>N532</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7736</Code>
      <Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
