<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site for Increasing Diversity in Engineering at Duke University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>233860</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The three-year renewal REU site program for Increasing Diversity in Engineering at Duke University will provide interdisciplinary and interdepartmental research opportunities for 8 undergraduate students for nine weeks each year. The program will involve all departments of the Pratt School of Engineering at Duke: Biomedical Engineering, Mechanical Engineering and Materials Science, Civil and Environmental Engineering, and Electrical and Computer Engineering. This REU program has as its intellectual focus opening the whole field of engineering for the full inclusion of all individuals, in particular underrepresented populations - women, underrepresented minorities, and persons with disabilities. The Principal Investigator is in a unique school-wide position directing educational programs which have placed many hundreds of undergraduates in research opportunities with almost every professor in the school, and can provide projects across all disciplines with experienced, strong advisors and trained mentors. Duke University's Biomedical Engineering Department at the Pratt School of Engineering consistently ranks in the top 5 in the nation. Due to the strength of this area, the Pratt REU Program will provide approximately half of its projects in biomedical engineering and bioengineering areas, ranging from biomedical cardiovascular engineering to biochemical engineering, biomechanics of cells and hard and soft tissues, cellular and biosurface engineering, and electrical activity of the heart and brain. Multiple projects in materials science including those on biologically inspired materials and material systems, mechanical, electrical, computer, civil, and environmental engineering will also be offered. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The Principal Investigator of this REU site program aims to recruit over 75% of its students from underrepresented groups. This program will include at least 25% disabled students. The emphasis in this program is recruiting students who would not have the opportunity to do such challenging research and placing them in a nurturing environment which addresses their weaknesses in moving into and staying in STEM areas. This program will change students' live, by developing research competence and confidence and encouraging them to continue on to graduate school and pursue careers in STEM areas. This REU site program will have a major impact on students' career possibilities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156686</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Absher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mabsher@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
