<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: MAA National Research Experiences for Undergraduates Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>566484</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this award, the Mathematical Association of America (MAA), through its Strengthening Underrepresented Minority Mathematics Achievement (SUMMA) initiative, proposes to support the National Research Experiences for Undergraduates Program (NREUP). NREUP fosters participation of mathematics undergraduates from underrepresented groups in focused and challenging research experiences. The need for increased participation of U.S. citizens in the mathematical sciences requires that we identify and nurture students from underrepresented groups, both to serve as professional mathematicians and to serve as role models and mentors for future generations. With support of faculty mentors and the focused peer-group experience shared by students participating in this program, the MAA National Research Experience for Undergraduates program encourages and supports broadened participation of these students in graduate studies and careers in mathematics. Moreover, by supporting faculty at a diverse group of institutions to direct summer research programs, this project simultaneously supports the development of a community of skilled faculty mentors who are expected to provide ever-increasing opportunities for undergraduate research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NREUP will continue its track record of increasing students' interest in obtaining advanced degrees in mathematics. SUMMA proposes to build on its experience in conducting NREUP in Summers 2003 - 2011, which supported 368 student researchers at a total of 86 sites. NREUP is designed to reach minority students at a critical point in their career path - midway through their undergraduate programs - through an undergraduate professor with whom they have a strong connection. The program reaches students at the transition point between lower division and upper division studies. NREUP provides key components to encourage students to pursue graduate studies and careers in mathematics: enriching and rewarding mathematical experiences, mentoring by active researchers, and both intellectual and social networking with peers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156582</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Braddy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lbraddy@maa.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William Anthony</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hawkins</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whawkins@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pearson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pearson@maa.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/24/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/20/2012</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mathematical Association of America</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200361358</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2023875200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1529 18th St NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7335</Code>
      <Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
