<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Program in Molecular Biosciences</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>343500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An award has been made to Colorado State University to continue an REU Site program that will provide research training for ten undergraduates for 10 weeks, during the summers of 2012-2014. Students will participate in a program that exposes them to a broad range of research areas and approaches in biochemistry and molecular biology. Students will work with mentors from College of Natural Sciences (Biochemistry and Molecular Biology). Students will be involved in their own research project where they learn how to formulate and test hypotheses, design and execute experiments, analyze results in the context of the hypothesis, and use state-of-the-art techniques and instrumentation. Interactions with faculty, graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and professional research staff provide a mechanism for learning about the latest advances in biochemistry and molecular biology. Students receive a stipend, free housing in a university residence hall or apartment building, a meal allowance, and an allowance to defray travel to/from the site. At the end of the program, students will present their research results orally and through a poster, and produce a final report in manuscript form. In addition to research, students will engage in activities that will enhance their knowledge of the environment such as an educational hike in the Rocky Mountain National Park. Field trips to nearby government labs and biotech companies as well as workshops on GRE preparation, the ethical conduct of research, and scientific careers are also planned. The program will use the BIO REU Sites common assessment tool to obtain feedback and assessment data for improving the program. Students with limited opportunities for research and those from groups under-represented in science are especially encouraged to apply. For further information, students may visit http://www.bmb.colostate.edu/reu.cfm, or contact Yvonne Bridgeman at 970-491-5602 or reubiochem@colostate.edu, or the Program Director, Paul Laybourn, at 970-491-5100 or Paul.Laybourn@colostate.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156329</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pui</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ho</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Shing.Ho@ColoState.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Laybourn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Paul.Laybourn@ColoState.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
