<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: The UNC CAP (Computational Astronomy and Physics) Program: UNCCAPing Enthusiasm for Computational Careers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>381999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sushil Prasad</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill will host a ten-week Computational Astronomy and Physics (CAP) Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) summer program, starting with a "beta-plus" program for local UNC and North Carolina Central University students in 2012 followed by a fully funded national program running for three years from 2013-2015. The CAP Program will address the acute need for computational science training opportunities for undergraduates, providing both hands-on seminars on computational methods and individual research experiences involving techniques ranging from numerical simulation to visualization to computationally intensive data modeling to remote instrument control. Specific projects will build on UNC faculty research efforts in astrophysics, bio/medical physics, condensed matter physics and nanotechnology, fluid dynamics, and nuclear/particle physics. Students will gain professional skills by preparing poster and talk presentations and written reports, as well as by attending seminars on research ethics, literature search strategies, and communication skills. For more information, please visit http://www.physics.unc.edu/cap or contact capprogram@unc.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156614</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sheila</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kannappan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sheila@physics.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/17/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
      <CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
      <ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
