<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Hard and Soft Materials in Nanoscience Technology Driven Energy Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>335172</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;This three year REU site program will be hosted by the NanoScience Technology Center (NSTC) at the University of Central Florida (UCF). Ten undergraduate students will be engaged in research and education activities for 10 summer weeks each year. The program will include the following: (1) introductory coursework on the basic principles of engineering energy, nanotechnology; (2) research seminars by faculty and industry leaders; (3) industrial visits to the numerous industries in Central Florida; (4) seminars, workshops and discussion sessions on ethics in engineering research, group projects to foster interdisciplinary research; and (5) monitoring, evaluation, and tracking of the students' progress via weekly discussion groups and (6) preparation of students to pursue careers in STEM areas. Participants will learn to manufacture and study new functional nanomaterials and devices for energy applications under the guidance of faculty from multidisciplinary programs. The research will involve experimental work as well as computer based modeling. The students will be trained in technology commercialization of nanomaterials for enabling technology in collaboration with UCF's Technology Incubator. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;This REU site program will engage faculty from Materials, Engineering, Optical and Physical sciences. It will foster intercollegial relationships between STEM faculty and students with an opportunity to investigate new teaching paradigms. This experience will aid students in formulating their career paths in STEM areas and will create a multicultural rich environment for the students to enable them to understand the intercultural dynamics in a research and educational setting. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This program will encourage these students to pursue graduate studies in science and engineering with a nanofocus. These undergraduate students will gain the skill set to become leaders in the development and commercialization of nanotechnology-based materials and device technologies for the energy economy of tomorrow, which is of strategic importance to the Central Florida area as well as to the United States to support its position as a global economic and technological leader. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"The site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program."</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156747</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sudipta</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seal</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sseal@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andre</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gesquiere</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>andre@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/09/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>K629</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>L644</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>N532</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7736</Code>
      <Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>115E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9177</Code>
      <Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
