<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Modern Optics in the City of Light: An International REU Site in Paris</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>365893</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports an international Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site which will bring 8 undergraduates to Paris each summer to conduct collaborative researc with faculty at the University of Michigan's Center for Ultrafast Optical Sciences (CUOS) and several Parisian research institutions: Ecole Polytechnique, Ecole Nationale de Techniques Avancées (ENSTA), the Institut d'Optique Graduate School, Université Paris-Sud 11, and Ecole Normale Supérieure de Cachan. The students will be put into research teams that include the student, a faculty member at UM and a faculty member in one of the Parisian institutions. The students will spend one week in Ann Arbor followed by 9 weeks in Paris. Each student will keep weekly on-line research diaries to aid in communication. The research in all projects will involve the use of ultrafast lasers to discover very current, state-of-the art phenomena in a wide range of fields including relativistic optics, plasma physics, materials spectroscopy, nano-machining, art restoration and conservation, patterned biological cell templating, high power fiber lasers, plasma x-ray sources, dynamics of nano-magnetic materials, terahertz imaging, biomedical imaging with shaped pulses, fatigue life studies of materials, and similar projects. The site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1156620</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yalisove</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>smy@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/31/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9134</Code>
      <Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>K629</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>L644</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>N532</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7736</Code>
      <Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
