<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Discrete and Topological Models in Molecular Biology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29072</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Ann Horn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>"Discrete and Topological Models in Molecular Biology" is a workshop to be held at the University of South Florida on March 12-14, 2012. In recent years it has become clear that mathematical tools from algebra, group theory, combinatorics, and topology play essential roles in understanding vital biological processes at the molecular scale. These include applications of (a) polynomials over finite fields in systems biology; (b) combinatorics and graph theory in secondary and ternary RNA structures, mRNA, as well as in protein folding and protein-protein interactions; (c) combinatorics, algebra and tiling theory in the modeling of viral capsid assembly; and (d) spatial graphs and topology in DNA-DNA, and DNA-RNA interactions and splicings. There are a number of intriguing connections between these techniques, and they are all essential tools in developing a better understanding of structures and processes in molecular biology, especially nucleic acids and proteins. This meeting will bring together researchers with complementary expertise, who are interested in very similar biological processes and molecular interactions. New collaborations will be initiated through the exchange of ideas and development of new models and mathematical techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will bring together a wide range of speakers; from leading theoretical mathematicians through mathematicians who actively collaborate with experimentalists to molecular biologists and biochemists whose experimental work depends on theoretical observations. A large component of the workshop will be aimed toward junior-level researchers and graduate students through tutorials, poster sessions, panel discussions and software demonstrations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1157242</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Natasa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jonoska</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jonoska@math.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Masahiko</FirstName>
      <LastName>Saito</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>saito@math.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/08/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of South Florida</Name>
      <CityName>Tampa</CityName>
      <ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3702 Spectrum Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7334</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
