<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Summer Research Conference in Statistics and Biostatistics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigator and his colleagues will organize and conduct a Summer Research Conference (SRC) in statistics and biostatistics at Jekyll Island, Georgia June 3-6, 2012. The SRC is an annual conference sponsored by the Southern Regional Council on Statistics (SRCOS). Its purpose is to encourage the interchange and mutual understanding of current research ideas in statistics and biostatistics, and to give motivation and direction to further research progress. The project will focus on young researchers, placing them in close proximity to leaders in the field for person-to-person interactions in a manner not possible at most other meetings; these leaders, if from the southern region, pay their own way and contribute their time. Speakers will present formal research talks with adequate time allowed for clarification, amplification, and further informal discussions in small groups. Under the travel support provided by this award students and young faculty who do not have financial support for their travel will attend and also present posters to be reviewed by more experienced researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Southern Regional Council on Statistics is a consortium of statistics and biostatistics programs in the South, stretching as far west as Texas and as far north as Maryland. It currently has 43 member programs at 39 universities in 16 states in the region. This project will fund student and young-investigator travel to the 2012 Summer Research Conference (SRC) sponsored by SRCOS; see http://www.sph.emory.edu/srcos/research.htm for an archive of many recent SRCs. The meeting is particularly valuable for students and faculty from smaller regional schools at drivable distances, affording them the opportunity to participate and interact closely with internationally-known leaders in the field without the cost of travel to distant national or international venues. It will strengthen the research of the statistics and biostatistics community as a whole, and particularly in the underdeveloped southern region.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1157813</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Edwards</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>edwards@stat.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/14/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1269</Code>
      <Text>STATISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
