<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>I-Corps: Pilot Production Of Large Area Uniform Single-Crystal Graphene Films</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Errol Arkilic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Innovation-Corps project will explore the commercial feasibility of production of high quality, uniform large-area graphene films, translating into new products the knowledge that resulted from prior NSF-funded fundamental studies. The team submitted for patent a low cost, large-scale graphene synthesis technology with key advantages including: 1) no need for vacuum and high temperature during synthesis, thus enabling flexible, economical design and operation; 2) graphene film size not limited by furnace dimension with the proposed roll-to-roll processing concept; 3) production of graphene films with high electronic quality (large grain size, high carrier mobility, low sheet resistance); and 4) a continuous production method that is easily modified to industrial scale. The proof-of-concept demonstration to be achieved by this project is production of an ultra-compact, low power vapor sensor device for sensitive and selective detection of ethanol in breath. This will reflect the fact that the carrier mobility of the graphene will exceed 5000 cm2/V-s, a level suitable for numerous next-generation electronic applications. Successful completion of the project will result in a clear go/no go decision on the technology and a plan for commercial transition to market if appropriate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Graphene is an emerging "super material" with numerous proposed applications including flexible transparent conductors for touch screen displays and solar energy systems; high frequency electronics for communications; and advanced sensors for medical diagnostics, analysis of food and water purity, and environmental monitoring, all in real-time. Availability of high quality "wafer-scale" graphene material in industrial quantities will thus enable the development of these applications and others by the business community, with substantial potential benefit to society. The technology proposed will have advantages of cost, quality, and design flexibility over competing concepts. Successful completion of this I-Corps project will enable technology transition from the lab to the market place.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/28/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1158721</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johnson@dept.Physics.Upenn.Edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/28/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
