<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: Operando IV at Brookhaven National Laboratory, Upton, NY, April 29 - May 3, 2012</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George J. Antos</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;1159396&lt;br/&gt;Sievers&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In situ and Operando spectroscopy have become the cutting edge of catalysis research. Probing the physicochemical properties of catalysts while simultaneously measuring the catalytic activity and selectivity provides unprecedented insights into catalytic structure ? activity/selectivity relationships. The development of such fundamental structure ? activity relationships allows for the design of advanced catalysts for targeted reaction products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal requests support for the 2012 Operando IV conference at Brookhaven National Laboratory, April 29 through May 3, 2012. The objective of the meeting is to create an environment for fruitful discussions between researchers from universities, national laboratories and industry. Operando IV will cover all aspects of operando spectroscopy for catalysts including heterogeneous and homogeneous catalysis. Areas of interest include application of theory, new experimental approaches and techniques, time and spatial resolution, and various combinations of techniques. It is expected that there will be an emphasis on fuel cells, electrocatalysis, and catalysis related to the production of biofuels, and other energy related areas where catalysis is playing a major role in renewable energy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The requested funds will enhance the educational impact of Operando IV by supporting the participation of graduate and undergraduate catalysis researchers, as well as young faculty members, from U.S. institutions. Operando IV will be the first operand meeting in North America. This meeting will provide American researchers with a unique opportunity to be exposed to the latest developments at the cutting edge of catalysis research and also a chance to present their research work to global leaders in this subfield of catalysis.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1159396</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carsten</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sievers</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>carsten.sievers@chbe.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
