<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Unlock the Potential of Three-Dimensional (3D) Cell Cultures as Sensing Elements in Label-free Impedance Biosensors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>255882</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Yang&lt;br/&gt;1159871 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is to develop 3D cell culture-based impedance biosensors to provide label?free, non-invasive and real-time analytical tools for cellular analysis and drug discovery applications. This is based on the fact that 3D cell cultures resemble more accurately the actual in vivo microenvironment than the conventional 2D cell culture, thus 3D cell culture-based biosensors are expected to provide more biologically relevant and predictive data for in vivo responses. The project will design a microcavity array-based microchip for constructing the impedance biosensor and testing two types of 3D cell cultures--spheroids and cells embedded in 3D matrixes as the sensing element. The research tasks include the following: (1) studying the feasibility of such 3D culture-based biosensors for sensing drug-induced cell signaling pathways; (2) comparing the dose response range and IC50 of the 2D and 3D cell?based biosensors to drugs with different action mechanisms; (3) testing three different prostate cancer cell lines with different adherence characteristics (adherent, poorly adherent, non-adherent) for constructing 3D cultures as sensing elements and comparing their responses to drugs in comparison with traditional 2D cell culture tests. The project will evaluate the capability of the proposed 3D culture-based biosensors in reflecting the difference between 3D and 2D cultures, and to determine the potential of such 3D culture-based impedance biosensors in providing more biologically relevant information.&lt;br/&gt; This project will particularly address the research and training needs for students from underrepresented groups at North Carolina Central University (NCCU). NCCU is one of the historic black college and universities (HBCU). The education activities include (1) integrating research into course development; (2) providing research opportunities for undergraduate students through lab modules, summer internships, and external training opportunities; (3) broadening students? research vision by inviting external speakers to the interdisciplinary seminar series; (4) working with two existing outreach programs, the BRITE Futures and the Summer venture program, to educate k-12 students by exposure to research. The goal is to broaden students? knowledge in the fast developing biosensor and biochip related analytical technologies, and make students aware that real-life contemporary biological problems can be addressed by engineered microdevices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1159871</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liju</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lyang@nccu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina Central University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277073129</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195307333</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Fayetteville Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7909</Code>
      <Text>NANO-BIOSENSING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>019E</Code>
      <Text>SENSORS AND SENSING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>142E</Code>
      <Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9229</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9141</Code>
      <Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD. INST - EQUIP</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
