<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CSR: Medium: Collaborative Research: Architecting Performance Sensitive Applications for the Cloud</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Cloud computing offers IT organizations the ability to create&lt;br/&gt;geo-distributed, and highly scalable applications while providing&lt;br/&gt;attractive cost-saving advantages. Yet, architecting, configuring, and&lt;br/&gt;adapting cloud applications (latency-sensitive web applications and&lt;br/&gt;bulk data processing applications) to meet their stringent performance&lt;br/&gt;requirements is a challenge given the rich set of configuration&lt;br/&gt;options, shared multi-tenant nature of cloud platforms, and dynamics&lt;br/&gt;resulting from activities such as planned maintenance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is developing novel methodologies, algorithms, and&lt;br/&gt;systems that can enable application architects to (1) judiciously&lt;br/&gt;architect applications across multiple cloud data-centers while&lt;br/&gt;considering application performance requirements, cost saving&lt;br/&gt;objectives, and cloud pricing schemes guided by performance and cost&lt;br/&gt;models of cloud components; (2) automatically learn effective&lt;br/&gt;application configurations and configuration-to-performance prediction&lt;br/&gt;models through statistical machine learning techniques; and (3) create&lt;br/&gt;applications that can adapt to ongoing dynamics in cloud environments&lt;br/&gt;through transaction reassignment over shorter time-scales, and&lt;br/&gt;application migration over longer time-scales.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The impact of this research is multi-fold: (1) Enable IT organizations&lt;br/&gt;to significantly reduce costs by optimally moving their operations to&lt;br/&gt;the cloud; (2) create benchmarks based on operationally deployed&lt;br/&gt;applications and collecting workload traces which will be made&lt;br/&gt;available to the research community; (3) make developed algorithms and&lt;br/&gt;systems widely available as open source software; (4) inform the&lt;br/&gt;design of a nation-wide health-care cloud in Thailand; (4) introduce&lt;br/&gt;cloud computing related topics in the undergraduate and graduate&lt;br/&gt;curriculum; and (6) train multiple Ph.D., M.S., and undergraduate&lt;br/&gt;students, with explicit effort to recruit and train students from&lt;br/&gt;under-represented minority groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1162270</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>T. S. Eugene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eugeneng@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2012</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7354</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7924</Code>
      <Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
