<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: "4th ASM Conference on Cell-Cell Communication in Bacteria"; to be held November 6-9, 2011 in Miami, FL</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susanne von Bodman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The American Society sponsors the 4th Conference on Cell-Cell Communication in Bacteria held at the Hyatt Hotel in Miami FL, Nov. 6-9, 2011. The objectives of the meeting are to: 1. encourage and support the developments of new research directions; 2. foster multi-disciplinary interactions, and create research training opportunities for the next generation scientists; 3. expose the community to cutting edge technical advances including high-throughput methods in bacterial genetics and phenotyping, cryo-EM tomography, microfluidics, and single cell microscopy. 4. foster collegial interactions and discussions between scientist from different fields and at different stages of their scientific careers. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. The organizers have made an effort to be inclusive and pay attention to diversity and broadening participation. The funds requested will help support the travel of student and early career attendees. The ASM conferences have a tradition in disseminating conference highlights in a review published in the journal of Bacteriology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/24/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1162518</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Heidi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaplan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Heidi.B.Kaplan@uth.tmc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/24/2011</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>American Society For Microbiology</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200362904</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2027373600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1752 N STREET NW</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
