<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Integrality, Blowup Algebras and Multiplicities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>208506</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Passing from an affine algebra or an ideal to the integral closure&lt;br/&gt;is a fundamental operation. The investigator intends to examine&lt;br/&gt;computational aspects of this process. While there exist algorithms&lt;br/&gt;for computing the integral closure of an affine domain, little is&lt;br/&gt;known about the complexity of such calculations. To address this&lt;br/&gt;problem the investigator intends to find estimates for the number&lt;br/&gt;of algebra generators of the integral closure and for the degrees&lt;br/&gt;of these generators. In the case of ideals on the other hand, one&lt;br/&gt;still has no efficient method for computing integral closures. In&lt;br/&gt;view of this lack of an algorithm, the investigator intends to&lt;br/&gt;express, or at least approximate, the integral closure of an ideal&lt;br/&gt;by a sum of colon ideals that are more readily accessible. The core&lt;br/&gt;of an ideal is a counterpart of the integral closure: it encodes&lt;br/&gt;information about all possible reductions of a given ideal, i.e.,&lt;br/&gt;all ideals over which the given ideal is integral. The investigator&lt;br/&gt;intends to work on a conjectural formula that, if proved, would give&lt;br/&gt;an explicit expression for the core of a large class of ideals.&lt;br/&gt;Continuing the somewhat computational theme the investigator proposes&lt;br/&gt;to establish bounds for the Castelnuovo-Mumford regularity of&lt;br/&gt;embedded projective varieties in terms of their defining equations.&lt;br/&gt;The known results require strong assumptions on the singularities of&lt;br/&gt;the variety which the investigator hopes to weaken. In this vein he&lt;br/&gt;intends to show that rational singularities persist under generic&lt;br/&gt;linkage of ideals in the linkage class of a complete intersection.&lt;br/&gt;In continuation of his earlier work on blowup algebras the&lt;br/&gt;investigator plans to study the rings representing special fibers of&lt;br/&gt;blowups. These `special fiber rings' describe, for instance, images&lt;br/&gt;of rational maps, including secant varieties and Gauss images. The&lt;br/&gt;investigator intends to study the Cohen-Macaulayness of special fiber&lt;br/&gt;rings, estimate their depth and compute multiplicities. Suitable&lt;br/&gt;depth estimates would have a bearing on a conjecture by Mazur that&lt;br/&gt;originates in Wiles' work on deformations of Galois representations.&lt;br/&gt;Formulas for the multiplicity on the other hand would lead to an&lt;br/&gt;extension of the Teissier-Pluecker formula for the degrees of certain&lt;br/&gt;dual varieties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator works in the area of Mathematics called "Commutative Algebra," which deals with the qualitative study of systems of polynomial equations in several variables. Such systems arise in numerous applications outside mathematics. Over the past two decades commutative algebraists have become more concerned with computational aspects, thereby emphasizing connections to applied areas such as computer algebra, robotics, cryptography and coding theory. This project addresses both theoretical and computational aspects of commutative algebra.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200858</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bernd</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ulrich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ulrich@math.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
