<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>9.4T a Micro-Imaging Spectrometer for High Field Imaging</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080101</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gerald Selzer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support to a consortium of faculty from the University of Massachusetts Medical School (UMMS) and Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI) for purchase of an ultra-high field magnetic micro-imaging device to be used for biological research. The instrument includes a 9.4T, 89 mm bore, actively shielded, superconducting magnet, console, dual fullband RF system, gradient amplifier, two gradient coils, and five RF probes for multi-nuclear spectroscopy from 20 MHz to 480 MHz. The instrument is made cost effective by the small bore, a constraint that contributes to enhanced gradient performance and field homogeneity. Ultra high-field, large bore systems used for medical research and diagnosis cost millions of dollars and push the limits and performance of gradient coils. Ultra high-field microimagers give unprecedented anatomical and functional images, allow multiple and single voxel spectroscopy, and have the potential to determine up to eighteen neurochemical signals simultaneously in vivo. The microimager is expected to provide research and training opportunities for students in 1) MR imaging, 2) data acquisition, management, image processing, and informatics, 3) development of radiofrequency electronics, and 4) neurophysiological and biological experimental design and implementation. The planned biological applications include: imaging functional brain activity, quantitative developmental neuroanatomy, imaging brain metabolism, and imaging brain receptors with ligand specific contrast agents, all using small animals. The success of these studies will require new developments in electronics, computer science and chemistry. Hence there is a natural collaboration between engineers, computer and biological scientists at WPI and neuroscientists at UMMS.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200575</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
      <LastName>King</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jean.king@umassmed.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sergey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Makarov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>makarov@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Medical School</Name>
      <CityName>Worcester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>016550002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5088562119</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>55 Lake Avenue North</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
