<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Representation Theoretical Methods in the Theory of Special Functions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140108</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research is on the Theory of Symmetric Functions and its &lt;br/&gt;applications to Representation Theory and Combinatorics. The &lt;br/&gt;connection between Representation Theory and the Theory of &lt;br/&gt;Symmetric Functions is provided by the Frobenius map which &lt;br/&gt;relates group characters to symmetric functions. Combinatorics &lt;br/&gt;plays a role in that multiplicities of irreducibles are often &lt;br/&gt;obtained by counting tableaux, paths, trees and a growing variety &lt;br/&gt;of newly emerging discrete structures. In the more than ten years &lt;br/&gt;since its discovery, the Macdonald basis has progressively emerged &lt;br/&gt;as a central element in these connections. For more than a decade &lt;br/&gt;of research in the Theory of Macdonald Polynomials, the &lt;br/&gt;investigator and M. Haiman have been led to a variety of &lt;br/&gt;conjectures in Representation Theory, Algebraic Geometry, &lt;br/&gt;Combinatorics and Symmetric Function Theory. Efforts in proving &lt;br/&gt;these conjectures have yielded fundamental facts and methods in &lt;br/&gt;each of these areas. More recently the investigator discovered a &lt;br/&gt;variety of summation formulas (PNAS V. 98 (April 2001) 4313-4316) &lt;br/&gt;which permitted the proof of the first significant positivity &lt;br/&gt;result in the Theory of Macdonald Polynomials. In joint work with &lt;br/&gt;J. Haglund the investigator proved a beautiful combinatorial &lt;br/&gt;formula (conjectured by J. Haglund) for a rational function which &lt;br/&gt;had come to be known as the $q,t$-Catalan. The investigator in &lt;br/&gt;collaboration with students and associates plans to use his &lt;br/&gt;recently discovered symmetric function identities for a direct &lt;br/&gt;attack of some of the conjectures that are still unresolved.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Theory of Symmetric Functions is a powerful symbolic &lt;br/&gt;manipulation tool. The reason for this is that non linear problems &lt;br/&gt;may often be linearized by the introduction of an infinite number &lt;br/&gt;of variables. Now it develops that the change of bases matrices &lt;br/&gt;of Symmetric Function Theory may be used to "mimic" the presence &lt;br/&gt;of infinities within a finite device, thereby permitting the &lt;br/&gt;linearization and solution of many a computational problem. &lt;br/&gt;Discoveries in the theory and applications of symmetric functions, &lt;br/&gt;should also turn out to be of significant impact in the various &lt;br/&gt;areas of mathematics in which symmetric function methods have been &lt;br/&gt;shown to be effective. This given, we can see how important it is &lt;br/&gt;to pursue investigations in the Theory of Symmetric functions &lt;br/&gt;that extend and deepen the computational power of the theory. &lt;br/&gt;This is the foremost goal of the present project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200364</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Adriano</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garsia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>garsia@schur.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
      <CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
