<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Character Theory of Non-Linear Groups</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>216081</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joe W. Jenkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Adams&lt;br/&gt;The representation theory of linear reductive groups, such as GL(n) is a very active subject, in part because of applications to the automorphic forms and the Langlands program. However important interesting examples of automorphic forms come from non-linear groups, i.e. groups pwhich can not be realized as a subgroup of GL(n).&lt;br/&gt;A fundamental result in the theory of real reductive groups is Vogan duality. In joint work with Peter Trapa I plan to extend this to non-linear groups. There are a number of interesting features in this setting which are quite different from the linear case.&lt;br/&gt;In a joint project with Rebecca Herb I propose to study the characters of real reductive non-linear groups, by relating them to linear groups via a "lifting" theory. This lifting is closely related to Vogan duality for these groups.&lt;br/&gt;In a project with Niranjan Ramachandran I am studying the structure of non-linear p-adic reductive groups. This is an important first step in studying character theory for these groups.&lt;br/&gt;Finally Annegret Paul and I are working on a project to parametrize the theta-correspondence over R for one-dimensional representations as completely as possible.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200851</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jda@math.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
