<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Proposal in Support of the Travel of Young U.S. Researchers to Participate at the 17th ISCRE</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Burka</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The field of Chemical Reaction Engineering is key in the development of efficient, environmentally friendly and effective manufacturing. Promoting the exchange of ideas among leading researchers in this field will not only favorably impact the future growth of the Chemical Reaction Engineering discipline but should ultimately result in more efficient and cleaner technologies and an improved way of life for the society as a whole. The international symposium in Chemical Reaction Engineering (ISCRE) is the premier meeting in the field, which takes place every two years and sets the tone for progress in the field. Its impact has been without any doubt tremendous as measured by the number of citations the ISCRE proceedings have received, the increased industry-university interactions that is has fostered, and the improved education and exposure of young researchers in the field. With the Asia Pacific region hosting the upcoming ISCRE 17, it is hoped that this premiere event for Chemical Reaction Engineering (CRE) researchers will provide a step-jump for the participation of researchers in that region, taking a historic step towards the globalization of ISCRE. The meeting of US academic and industrial researchers with an insight into the fast growing CRE community in that region an opportunity that was not available in previous ISCRE's.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF's travel support for ISCRE 17 will make it possible for up to twenty five young researchers from the US to attend the meeting covering registration and defraying some of the travel and lodging expenses. NSF funding will allow these researchers to profit by listening to state-of-the-art review talks and research papers and from the opportunity to interact with their fellow researchers in the area. The public at large will significantly benefit by the advancement of the Chemical Reaction Engineering field as a whole and the use of the new ideas generated for the development of more efficient and environmentally friendlier technologies for the production of fuels, materials and chemicals.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200487</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tsotsis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tsotsis@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wei</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jameswei@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
