<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Intelligent Control of Robotic Contact Operations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>119214</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Werbos</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0200388&lt;br/&gt;Newman&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent developments in the separate domains of robot force control and neurocontrol&lt;br/&gt;have advanced to the point where integration of these technologies may yield a dramatic&lt;br/&gt;leap forward in robot competence. At present, robot contact operations are clumsy and&lt;br/&gt;ineffective, except in instances where the environment is highly predictable and the tasks&lt;br/&gt;can be accomplished using position control alone. However, for futuristic applications of&lt;br/&gt;robots, such as autonomous assembly of a space-based power system, robots for defense&lt;br/&gt;applications, or a potential industry in domestic robotics, competence in contact&lt;br/&gt;operations in unstructured environments is essential for success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The exploratory project will evaluate the use of intelligent control algorithms with appropriate set of assumptions and representations of robot/environment contact dynamics, using "Natural Admittance Control" and "virtual dynamics" as a means to integrate high and low-level controls. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It will consider four tasks in intelligent control research: (1) constructing a reflexive damage-avoidance layer to assure the safety of a robot and its environment and enable the capability for safe, autonomous learning; (2) human strategies for contact operations will be analyzed and "cloned" for robot execution, using identification of atomic behaviors and recognition of events that trigger sequential behaviors; (3) on-line identification of environment dynamics; (4) neural-net based optimizing control algorithms employing "adaptive critics" will be constructed in the context of NAC/virtual dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200388</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Wyatt</FirstName>
      <LastName>Newman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wsn@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510403</Code>
      <Name>Engineering &amp; Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
