<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research in Enumerative Combinatorics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>123000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigator studies problems in enumerative combinatorics &lt;br/&gt;related to permutations, symmetric functions, and lattice paths. &lt;br/&gt;One of the investigator's approaches is to apply Richard &lt;br/&gt;Stanley's theory of P-partitions and its generalizations to the &lt;br/&gt;study of descent algebras of symmetric and related groups. &lt;br/&gt;Several other problems related to the enumeration of permutations &lt;br/&gt;by descents are also studied. The investigator also studies a &lt;br/&gt;generalization of two-stack-sortable permutations leading to a &lt;br/&gt;symmetric-function refinement of the formula of West (proved by &lt;br/&gt;Zeilberger) for counting these permutations, and several problems &lt;br/&gt;involving the enumeration of lattice paths.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Enumerative combinatorics involves counting mathematical objects &lt;br/&gt;with given properties. It has applications to computer science, &lt;br/&gt;physics, and chemistry, as well as to other areas of mathematics, &lt;br/&gt;such as algebra, probability and statistics, topology, analysis, &lt;br/&gt;and number theory. The investigator's long-range goal is to &lt;br/&gt;develop, extend, and systematize the methods of enumerative &lt;br/&gt;combinatorics, and the problems studied will contribute towards &lt;br/&gt;this goal.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200596</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ira</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gessel</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gessel@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Brandeis University</Name>
      <CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7817362121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>415 SOUTH ST MAILSTOP 116</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
