<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2002 Tetrapyrroles Gordon Conference; July 14 -19, 2002, Newport, Rhode Island</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070800</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Neil E. Hoffman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This application requests support for the 19 th Gordon Research Conference on the&lt;br/&gt;Chemistry and Biology of Tetrapyrroles, to be held at Salve Regina University,&lt;br/&gt;Newport, RI, from July 14-19, 2002. The specific aims of this conference are the&lt;br/&gt;following:&lt;br/&gt;1) To provide a forum for discussion of recent unpublished data by scientists with&lt;br/&gt;common interest in the study of the chemistry and biology of tetrapyrrole compounds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2) To promote the exchange of ideas between established and new investigators from a&lt;br/&gt;wide variety of scientific disciplines (e.g., chemists, biochemists, clinicians, plant&lt;br/&gt;biologists, microbiologists, biotechnologists) by providing ample discussion time&lt;br/&gt;following formal presentations, by holding poster sessions which serve as a focus for&lt;br/&gt;the discussion of common interests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This biennial interdisciplinary conference has stimulated collaborations between basic&lt;br/&gt;biologists, chemists and clinicians interested in tetrapyrroles for more than three&lt;br/&gt;decades. In association with proteins, tetrapyrroles serve diverse roles as biological&lt;br/&gt;redox catalysts, in the harvesting of light energy, in the activation and delivery of&lt;br/&gt;oxygen, and as signaling molecules. Free tetrapyrroles are also essential nutrients&lt;br/&gt;(e.g., vitamin B12), serve as regulators of gene expression (e.g., hemes), and are being&lt;br/&gt;utilized as therapeutic agents (e.g., photodynamic cancer therapy, target delivery of&lt;br/&gt;radionuclides). Owing to their photodynamic activity, toxicity and lipophilicity, the&lt;br/&gt;accumulation of tetrapyrroles (e.g., porphyrins, bilirubin) is associated with numerous&lt;br/&gt;pathologies of the skin, liver and brain. For these reasons, this conference represents&lt;br/&gt;an important venue for exchange between basic and applied researchers on&lt;br/&gt;tetrapyrroles and for refinement of new tools and therapies for development by the&lt;br/&gt;biomedical industry. Funds requested in this application are targeted to support 10&lt;br/&gt;young investigators who have not previously had the opportunity to attend this&lt;br/&gt;conference and for travel of two young ioprimarily undergraduate institutionle&lt;br/&gt;researchers. The sessions, which highlight recent technological progress, will include&lt;br/&gt;22 invited speakers, a plenary lecturer and 14 discussion leaders. All of these&lt;br/&gt;individuals have been selected for their scientific excellence, recent innovative work&lt;br/&gt;and contribution to the breadth of the program. The remaining 100 conferees will be&lt;br/&gt;chosen to ensure a broad representation of women, ethnicity and young scientists from&lt;br/&gt;various disciplines in academia, medical research institutions and industry. Strengths&lt;br/&gt;of this ongoing Gordon conference are its high disciplinary diversity, integration of&lt;br/&gt;research from basic chemistry through practical and clinical applications, focus on&lt;br/&gt;new unpublished work, time for discussion, informal atmosphere, and ban on&lt;br/&gt;dissemination of conference proceedings, (which it is essential to assure&lt;br/&gt;confidentiality when discussing unpublished results).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200930</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gloria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ferreira</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gferreir@health.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlyle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Storm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grc@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
