<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sharp Estimates for Eigenvalues, Integrals, and Sobolev Imbeddings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>89997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joe W. Jenkins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The author proposes to work on various extremal problems&lt;br/&gt;for functionals which are defined in terms of integrals&lt;br/&gt;or eigenvalues. These problems include: Lieb-Thirring&lt;br/&gt;inequalities for the number bound states of Schrodinger &lt;br/&gt;operators; sharp Moser-Trudinger and Sobolev inequalities&lt;br/&gt;for the CR sphere, with applications to determinants of CR &lt;br/&gt;invariant operators; sharp inequalities for integrals&lt;br/&gt;involving cross-ratios, with applications to zeta functions&lt;br/&gt;of Laplacians on the sphere; sharp inequalities of log-Sobolev&lt;br/&gt;type on the disk, with applications to zeta functions of&lt;br/&gt;Dirichlet and Neumann Laplacians on the disk; dimension&lt;br/&gt;-free Carleson measure inequalities. The research will&lt;br/&gt;touch on important questions arising in differential&lt;br/&gt;geometry, harmonic analysis, and mathematical physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is difficult to understate the importance of eigenvalue&lt;br/&gt;estimates in both applied and theoretical sciences. It is&lt;br/&gt;very often the case that to given physical structures, such&lt;br/&gt;as systems of particles, vibrating membranes, or strings,&lt;br/&gt;one can attach certain characteristic numerical values,&lt;br/&gt;called "eigenvalues". These numbers are important, as some&lt;br/&gt;relevant properties of a given structure can be often coded&lt;br/&gt;into numerical functions of the eigenvalues, called&lt;br/&gt;"spectral functionals". In an extremal problem one tries&lt;br/&gt;to find out which structures of the same type would&lt;br/&gt;yield the highest (or lowest) possible spectral functionals; &lt;br/&gt;very often, they are the ones with exhibit the most&lt;br/&gt;symmetrical geometry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0200574</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morpurgo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>morpurgo@math.missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
