<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student and Young Scientist Participation in the 8th International Conference on X-Ray Lasers to be held in Aspen, Colorado</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Filbert J. Bartoli</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI's are requesting funding from NSF to support the attendance of US students&lt;br/&gt; and young scientists to the "8th International Conference in X-Ray Lasers", that will be held at&lt;br/&gt; the Aspen Institute, in Aspen Colorado during the last week of May of 2002. This bi-&lt;br/&gt; annual international conference is recognized as the most important in the field of X-Ray lasers,&lt;br/&gt; and constitutes a forum to report the most recent advances in one of the frontiers of laser&lt;br/&gt; research. The conference will cover advances in ultrashort wavelength laser development,&lt;br/&gt; theory, and applications. Advances in the field of soft x-ray lasers have a synergistic effect in&lt;br/&gt; several disciplines. After decades of research these sources have now reached the point at which&lt;br/&gt; they are making important contributions to numerous disciplines, including plasma physics,&lt;br/&gt; material surface characterization, nanoelectronic metrology, and biology. The continuation of&lt;br/&gt; advance of this field is therefore of significant scientific and industrial interest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The conference has historically changed locations, to give at different times the&lt;br/&gt; maximum opportunity for attendance to scientists and students from different countries. In May&lt;br/&gt; 2002 it will be 8 years since the conference was held in the United States, in Williamsburg&lt;br/&gt; (Virginia), in May 1994. The 2002 Aspen conference follows very successful meetings in&lt;br/&gt; Sweden (Lund, 1996), Japan (Kyoto, 1998) and France (Saint Malo, 2000). The Aspen meeting&lt;br/&gt; will offer the United States scientific and broad technical community the opportunity to actively&lt;br/&gt; participate in this international forum. National Science Foundation support will be important in&lt;br/&gt; assisting the participation a maximum number of US students and young scientists, and to make&lt;br/&gt; the presentations at the meeting accessible to the scientific community in general through the&lt;br/&gt; rapid publication of the conference proceedings. More than 250 scientists from all over the world&lt;br/&gt; are expected to attend.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0201947</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dunn6@llnl.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jorge</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rocca</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rocca@engr.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Szymon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Suckewer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>suckewer@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
