<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: The Costs and Benefits of Self-Enhancement: Coping with the Terrorist Attack on the World Trade Center</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>45280</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven Breckler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The September 11, 2001 terrorist attack on the World Trade Center (WTC) in New York City was a traumatic event of unparalleled magnitude. In addition to the thousands who perished in the attack, literally tens of thousands of others were directly and without warning exposed to grave danger as they fled the buildings. Still others not in immediate physical danger nonetheless were forced to watch in horror as people jumped from the towers, or were engulfed by debris. Such images and experiences will undoubtedly leave thousands vulnerable for Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). Yet, based on past research, it can be anticipated that many of the individuals directly exposed to the WTC attack will recover their equilibrium and return to normal functioning within a month or two after the event. The goal of this small grant for exploratory research is to understand this remarkable resilience. In two previous studies, the principal investigator and his colleagues found that individuals disposed toward self-enhancement were better able to cope with extremely adverse conditions. The current study is designed to explore whether self-enhancing individuals who were directly exposed to the WTC attack (i.e., in or near the WTC and either in immediate danger or witnessed horrific sights) might cope better than other individuals. The relationship between self-enhancement and long-term adjustment will be examined using multiple measures, including a biological marker of stress reactions and ratings of participant's adjustment provided by close friends and family members. In addition, this study will further explore the social cost of self-enhancement and how it relates to overall adjustment and well being by including a wider range of measures of social relations than had been used in previous research. Finally, the study will examine how survivors of the WTC attack experience express emotions when they talk about their experiences on September 11. These data will help determine whether self-enhancers process emotions differently than other individuals and, if so, whether these differences hold the key to their unusual ability to cope with extreme adversity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0202772</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bonanno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gab38@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Teachers College, Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276625</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2126783000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>525 West 120th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1332</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
