<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Differential Geometry by way of Partial Differential Equations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>224999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT DMS - 0202508.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first proposed project is to understand the topology of complete manifolds &lt;br/&gt;whose Ricci curvature is bounded from below by a negative multiple of the bottom &lt;br/&gt;of the spectrum of the Laplace operator. In this case, the bottom of the spectrum &lt;br/&gt;is assumed to be positive. The second project of the Principal Investigator is to &lt;br/&gt;investigate the size of the space of harmonic functions with polynomial growth on &lt;br/&gt;complete manifolds with non-negative sectional curvature. In particular, &lt;br/&gt;the primary goal is to prove that the dimension of the space of harmonic functions &lt;br/&gt;of polynomial growth with degree at most d is bounded by the dimension of an &lt;br/&gt;analogous space in Euclidean space of the same dimension. The third project is &lt;br/&gt;to understand the geometry of stable minimal hypersurfaces of Euclidean space. &lt;br/&gt;More generally, he would like to study minimal hypersurfaces with have finite index. &lt;br/&gt;The PI also proposes to support a postdoc, Dr. Xiaofeng Sun, in his research projects. &lt;br/&gt;Dr. Sun proposes to study the regularity theory of harmonic maps into a metric space. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These proposed projects have the unified theme of using analytical techniques in &lt;br/&gt;studying the underlining geometric spaces. In many instances, topological and &lt;br/&gt;geometrical conclusions can be drawn by detail analysis of solutions of some &lt;br/&gt;appropriate partial differential equations defined on the space.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0202508</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pli@math.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
      <CityName>Irvine</CityName>
      <ZipCode>926173067</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9498244768</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5171 California Avenue, Ste 150</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1260</Code>
      <Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1265</Code>
      <Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
