<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Bronx Community College Pharmaceutical Manufacturing Technology Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>694513</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eileen L. Lewis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;The Pharmaceutical Manufacturing Technology (PMT) program is establishing an A.A.S. degree in PMT at Bronx Community College, the first of its kind in the City University of New York. The PMT program is a chemical technology program specifically designed to prepare technicians to meet the growing needs of the New York, New Jersey, and Connecticut tri-state pharmaceutical, cosmetics, and related industries. To accomplish the primary goals of the PMT program, objectives and activities addressing the following categories are being implemented: a) Curriculum and course development; b) Instructional materials adaptation and development; c) College faculty and high school teacher training and professional development; and d) Student enrichment and internship activities. The PMT curriculum is incorporating the Voluntary Industry Standards (VIS) of the American Chemical Society. Long established ties between the Department and local chemical and pharmaceutical industries are an integral component in the design of this program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Pharmaceutical Manufacturing Technology A.A.S. degree curriculum is related to a series of secondary school programs such as the Tech Prep, School-To-Work, STEP and C-STEP programs in the Bronx and supported by the Bronx Educational Alliance and the Greater New Jersey Process Technology Alliance. Articulation agreements leading to the B.S. and B.A. science degree programs in CUNY and other colleges are in place. Thus, the program is providing new career pathways for minority students and other individuals by establishing strong viable links from high school to college level science and technology education to job placement. Graduates of the program will be in a competitive position to fill rewarding entry-level technician positions in the regional industries. Other long-term results, beyond the duration of the project, will be to increase the retention and the enrollment of minority and female Bronx students in science and technology programs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0202386</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Panayiotis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meleties</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmeleties@york.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brennan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>motsset@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Bronx Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Bronx</CityName>
      <ZipCode>104532804</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7182895183</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2155 University Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
