<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Consortium for Education in Renewable Energy Technologies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>420280</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The overall goal of this project is to establish a Consortium for Education in Renewable Energy Technologies (CERET) to facilitate implementation of a broad-based interdisciplinary approach to technical education in renewable energy technologies. This goal supports the vision of the consortium to embrace and mainstream renewable energy technologies through:&lt;br/&gt;(1) development of a technically-competent renewable energy industry workforce.&lt;br/&gt;(2) fostering of the production of more energy from Wisconsin grown agriculture products and by-products.&lt;br/&gt;(3) encouragement of the use of distributed sources of energy generation.&lt;br/&gt;(4) promotion of the understanding and knowledge of renewable energy applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CERET focuses on:&lt;br/&gt;(1) establishing a technology demonstration site where business, industry, farmers, agribusinesses, consumers, legislative and governmental leaders, trades people, students, and educators can learn about renewable energy technologies and distributed sources of energy generation from the around the U.S. and the world.&lt;br/&gt;(2) working with business and industry partners to provide hands-on training and new curriculums for skilled workers in the distributed energy generation, new and emerging energy technologies, and renewable energy field. &lt;br/&gt;(3) encouraging the use of ethanol, bio-diesel, and other Wisconsin-based renewable fuels from agricultural sources.&lt;br/&gt;(4) making the promise of renewable and distributed energy technologies a reality for Wisconsin.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CERET includes as partners and collaborators: Madison Area Technical College, Nicolet Area Technical College, the University of Wisconsin Madison Biological Sciences Engineering, the Wisconsin Technical College System Board and Foundation, Milwaukee School of Engineering, Wisconsin state agencies including the Department of Agriculture, Trade and Consumer Protection, Department of Commerce, and Department of Administration Divisions of Energy and Alternative Fuels, Alliant Energy Corporation, Wisconsin Public Service, and energy consultants, equipment producers and skilled trades associations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CERET offers technical training and education to incumbent workers as well as students seeking careers in renewable energy technologies. To insure that faculty of college students and teachers of high school students are well prepared in these technologies, the project is conducting workshops and courses for teachers. The project also facilitates discussion and implementation of a public voice for renewable energy technologies through a partnership with the Wisconsin Educational Communications Board. CERET provides training for the workforce needed to implement technologies for energy generation and distribution to sustain the economic strength and competitiveness of Wisconsin and the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0202352</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joy</FirstName>
      <LastName>McMillan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmcmillan@matcmadison.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbrown@nicolet.tec.wi.us</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gibson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gibsonj@board.tec.wi.us</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>BillJohnson@allian-energy.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/10/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Madison Area Technical College</Name>
      <CityName>Madison</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537042599</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082466676</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1701 Wright Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
