<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SMAR2T: Science and Mathematics Academy for the Recruitment and Retention of Teachers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>872690</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan T Prival</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In order to address the increasing science and mathematics teacher shortage in rural Missouri, the Science and Mathematics Academy for the Recruitment and Retention of Teachers (SMAR2T) project is developing and testing models of Alternative Pathways to Teaching that will recruit and prepare individuals who possess STEM baccalaureate degrees to teach at the middle and secondary levels. The University of Missouri-Columbia (MU), with five rural school district partners, is designing and implementing two models of post baccalaureate certification: 1) an accelerated post baccalaureate program (APB) which certifies individuals within a 15-month intensive program that takes place both at the university and in residence in a partner school; and 2) a 2-year alternative certification program (ALT) in which individuals with provisional teaching licenses, who are employed full time by a school district, are supported over three summers and two academic years. A defining feature of the program design is the partnership among science and mathematics educators, scientists and mathematicians, and Missouri school districts in the preparation and induction of these teachers into the profession. Another defining feature is the role of technology in delivering innovative Internet-based distance learning opportunities for interns, their mentors, and university faculty through the Shadow netWorkspace software developed at MU. Project evaluation includes formative assessments to inform and continuously improve the project, and summative measures that allow the dissemination of project outcomes to a wider audience across the state and nationwide. The 4-year project is resulting in the certification of 80 new science and mathematics teachers for Missouri schools, as well as effective models of recruitment, preparation, and induction for post-baccalaureate students that can be adopted on a broader scale.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0202847</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Volkmann</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>volkmann@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Meera</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chandrasekhar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>meerac@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abells@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Weaver</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>weaverjc@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lannin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>LanninJ@missouri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fran</FirstName>
      <LastName>Arbaugh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>arbaugh@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>652110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>115 Business Loop 70 W</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
