<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Behavior of the Ricci Flow and Related Curature Flows</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>83552</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alexandre Freire</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT DMS - 0202796. PI: Dan Knopf&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;My research centers on geometric evolution&lt;br/&gt;equations, notably the Ricci flow and related curvature flows. I plan&lt;br/&gt;to study seven areas in which I have obtained prior results, and where&lt;br/&gt;continued work is likely to yield new and useful mathematics. [1] When &lt;br/&gt;a flow converges, it is valuable to study the stability of its limit, in&lt;br/&gt;order to improve our global understanding of the dynamics of flows. [2] If&lt;br/&gt;a flow fails to converge but behaves in a nonsingular way, one can still&lt;br/&gt;study the dynamics of this collapse by classifying the asymptotic behavior&lt;br/&gt;of nearby solutions. [3] In most cases, a flow does become singular; so it&lt;br/&gt;is of paramount importance (particularly in regard to Hamilton's program&lt;br/&gt;to resolve Thurston's Geometrization Conjecture) to develop a better&lt;br/&gt;classification of singularities. [4] The basic method of studying&lt;br/&gt;singularities is the construction of a sequence of parabolic dilations&lt;br/&gt;(blow-ups). To take limits of these solutions, one must obtain (partial)&lt;br/&gt;injectivity radius estimates by various means. [5] The most powerful (but&lt;br/&gt;perhaps most difficult) way to obtain such injectivity radius estimates&lt;br/&gt;would be to study and extend existing Harnack estimates of the type&lt;br/&gt;pioneered by Li and Yau and further developed by Hamilton. [6] It is &lt;br/&gt;also useful to study the asymptotic behavior and stability of parabolic&lt;br/&gt;dilations at certain model singularities (a method which has been very&lt;br/&gt;fruitful in studying the mean curvature flow). [7] Further information&lt;br/&gt;about singularities can be obtained by constructing and studying solitons:&lt;br/&gt;self-similar solutions that often arise as limits of blow-ups. Moreover,&lt;br/&gt;Kaehler Ricci solitons have interesting connections with complex geometry&lt;br/&gt;and algebraic geometry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Geometric evolution studies the way an&lt;br/&gt;object's shape changes. In some cases, such as the mean curvature flow and&lt;br/&gt;porous media flow, the motivation is to model certain physical phenomena&lt;br/&gt;such as the motion of an interface in forming metallic alloys, the shape&lt;br/&gt;of a thin film of highly viscous oil, or the flow of oil in shale. In&lt;br/&gt;other cases, the goal is to improve the shape of an object, either to find&lt;br/&gt;optimal (most efficient) shapes, or else to help mathematicians recognize&lt;br/&gt;and classify geometric objects. My own research is part of a large program&lt;br/&gt;to resolve one of the most compelling open questions in mathematics: the&lt;br/&gt;desire to understand and classify all possible 3-dimensional shapes. But&lt;br/&gt;regardless of whether their motivation comes from material science or pure&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, all geometric evolution problems have much in common; so that&lt;br/&gt;the field benefits from rich cross-fertilization. In particular, ideas and&lt;br/&gt;techniques that are developed for any of these highly nonlinear problems&lt;br/&gt;are usually quickly adaptable to related applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0202796</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Knopf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>danknopf@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1265</Code>
      <Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
