<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Compactness of Critical Metrics and Some Fully Nonlinear Equations in Conformal Geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>115383</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT DMS - 0202477.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Jeff A. Viaclovsky's project has three parts. &lt;br/&gt;The first part is joint work with Gang Tian, &lt;br/&gt;dealing with orbifold compactness of Bach flat &lt;br/&gt;metrics in dimension 4. The second part is joint work &lt;br/&gt;with Matt Gursky, and is about curvature functionals and &lt;br/&gt;conformal deformation of curvatures in dimension 3. &lt;br/&gt;The third part deals with existence of solutions &lt;br/&gt;to some fully nonlinear equations in conformal geometry. &lt;br/&gt;The first project is to understand compactness properties &lt;br/&gt;of the moduli space of critical points of the L2 norm &lt;br/&gt;of the Weyl tensor in 4 dimensions. The Euler-Lagrange &lt;br/&gt;equations are known as the Bach equations, and there are &lt;br/&gt;many known solutions, for example, metrics that are locally &lt;br/&gt;conformally Einsten, and self-dual or anti-self-dual &lt;br/&gt;metrics. Since it is known that these metrics exist in &lt;br/&gt;abundance, it is an interesting problem to understand &lt;br/&gt;the moduli space of solutions. The project of Viaclovsky &lt;br/&gt;and Tian is to show that, with certain geometric &lt;br/&gt;conditions, one may compactify this space by adding &lt;br/&gt;metrics with orbifold singularities. The other parts &lt;br/&gt;of the project deal with fully nonlinear equations in&lt;br/&gt;conformal geometry. The goal is to conformally deform a &lt;br/&gt;metric so that the kth elementary symmetric function of the &lt;br/&gt;eigenvalues of the Schouten tensor is constant. This may &lt;br/&gt;be viewed as a fully nonlinear generalization of the &lt;br/&gt;well-known Yamabe problem. An application of this is to &lt;br/&gt;improve the curvature by conformal deformation. For &lt;br/&gt;example, given an initial metric, conditions are found so &lt;br/&gt;that the metric can be conformally deformed to positive &lt;br/&gt;sectional curvature. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project with Tian generalizes some well-known &lt;br/&gt;results for Einstein metrics. Einstein metrics are &lt;br/&gt;particularly interesting from the connection with Eisteins's &lt;br/&gt;theory of general relativity, and the Bach equations &lt;br/&gt;are a natural higher order generalization &lt;br/&gt;of the Einstein equation. The work in conformal &lt;br/&gt;geometry is naturally conformally invariant &lt;br/&gt;and also has applications in physics through &lt;br/&gt;conformal field theory. Firthermore, new notions of mass &lt;br/&gt;arise for these equations, and this is also &lt;br/&gt;of interest in general relativity. These equations &lt;br/&gt;also have applications to determining the topology &lt;br/&gt;of 3-manifolds, given some geometric constraint &lt;br/&gt;on the curvature.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0202477</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeff</FirstName>
      <LastName>Viaclovsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jeffv@math.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/17/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1265</Code>
      <Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1281</Code>
      <Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
