<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2002 Electronic Processes in Organic Materials Conference; Newport, RI; July 21-26, 2002</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>LaVerne D. Hess</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Gordon Research Conference on Electronic Processes in Organic Materials (EPOM) will be held July 21-26, 2002 at Salve Regina University, Newport, RI. The main goals of the conference are to provide a forum for the presentation of new and exciting experimental and theoretical results on EPOM and to bring together investigators from diverse disciplines so that they can share their experimental and theoretical approaches in solving problems related to electronic and photophysical processes in complex organic materials of many different types. The scientific program is multi-faceted and will also serve to educate young and established scientists in areas they are not so familiar with. Topics include fundamental science and device applications, e.g., organic superconductors, field-effect transistors, lasers, conducting wires, light emitting diodes, semiconductors, electronic structure and dynamics in low-dimensional systems, light harvesting and electron transfer in artificial and photosynthetic systems, organic-inorganic heterostructures, single polymer and biomolecular spectroscopy and, nano-architectronics. The conference will consist of nine formal sessions with a total of 28 oral presentations, and two afternoon poster sessions. Invited speakers and discussion leaders were selected on the basis of their relevant expertise and recent achievements while emphasizing a program with gender balance, minority representation, and participation of young investigators. Along with the opportunity to assess the field and future directions, it is expected that new ties will be established between universities, research institutions, and industry.&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;An evaluation of the progress and status of Electronic Processes in Organic Materials and related device issues along with current assessments of the most important developments will be of significant value to the understanding and enhanced utilization of electronic/photonic materials in computing, data processing, and communications. This conference is co-supported by the Chemistry and Materials Research Divisions within the Mathematical and Physical Sciences Directorate. &lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0203859</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Small</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gsmall@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carlyle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Storm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grc@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
