<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Workshop on Cooperative US-Europe Research in Sensors and Smart Structures Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34195</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Shih-Chi Liu</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;0203143&lt;br/&gt;(B.F. Spencer, Univ. Notre Dame)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project provides support for a joint US-Europe Seminar/Workshop in Sensors and Smart Structures Technology in April 2002 in Somma Lombardo, Italy.. The objective of this project is to establish a common framework for expanded future joint research through mutual learning in the emerging subject areas between US and Europe.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the last few years, significant progress has been made in the area of sensing&lt;br/&gt;technology and structural health monitoring/condition assessment in the US and Europe.&lt;br/&gt;Innovative concepts involving new hardware, algorithms, and software, as well as&lt;br/&gt;vibration control have been proposed. There have also been several full scale trial&lt;br/&gt;implementations of densely sensor instrumented infrastructures and health monitoring&lt;br/&gt;systems, as well as case studies on bridges in Europe and the US. There is much &lt;br/&gt;can be learned from the European experts and vice versa, especially in the area of&lt;br/&gt;experimental verification on small, medium, large and full scale projects. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The program will consist of four seminar sessions on the theme topics of (1) innovative sensing hardware, (2) advances in wireless technology, (3) damage detection/characterization and condition assessment methodology, and (4) case studies and experimental verification on international testbeds. Then four workshop&lt;br/&gt;sessions will follow to summarize the status of the sensors and smart structures technology in these topics, to identify the outstanding research issues, and to formulate an action plan with recommendations for development and implementation through possible collaborative research projects and sharing of scientific data. A final report of the workshop will be prepared and made available to the research and practitioner community through normal distribution means and also through Internet for wider information dissemination.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/06/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/06/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0203143</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Billie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spencer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bfs@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/06/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
      <CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
      <ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
