<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Power Control and Call Admission Policies for Multiclass Traffic in SIR-Based Power-Controlled DS-CDMA Cellular Networks</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>305656</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project aims at studying problems fundamental in cellular networks and specifically related to the call admission control schemes. Efficient call admission control schemes provide the users with access to wireless networks and at the same time are crucial for network operators in guaranteeing services and operating efficiently. In this three-year project, the following research activities will be particularly pursued. First, a novel call admission control algorithms for signal-to-interference ratio (SIR) based power-controlled direct sequence code division multiple access (DS-CDMA) cellular networks that provide multiple classes of services will be developed. When a new call (or a handoff call) arriving at a base station requesting for admission, the new, desired, power level for that new call as well as the power levels for all existing calls will be calculated. These calculations are based on the interference received at the base station and the desired quality of service target (i.e., the desired SIR) for each call. In the case of a higher priority calls, e.g. handoff calls, different thresholds for new calls and handoff calls can be allowed. The research within this project will particularly focus on the admission control decision based on a computationally tractable calculation of the target power level, which would avoid the iterative process of power control for determination of the required power levels for all users. Finally, power control algorithms with vigorous theoretical results regarding stability, convergence, and feasibility of solutions will also be studied for the best applicability in future cellular networks. This project will include graduate and undergraduate students in research and will be conducted as means of creating awareness and interest among students on the issues surrounding wireless networks.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0203063</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Derong</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dliu@ece.uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>Chicago</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>4097</Code>
      <Text>NETWORKING RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
