<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Approximate Reasoning in Stochastic Concurrency: Applications to Secure Substitution and Stochastic Hybrid Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sol J. Greenspan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Stochastic programs involve time, probability and concurrency. The classical research into reasoning about probabilistic models of concurrency provides methods to establish when two processes can be considered the same and be inter-substituted for each other. Such equivalences are too exact since they are usually not robust under even slight perturbation of probabilities. This is particularly unfortunate since practice dictates that probability numbers are to be viewed as numbers with some error estimate. The focus of this proposal is approximations and approximate reasoning for stochastic concurrent systems. The PI proposes to use metric based frameworks to formalize approximation schemes and develop compositional reasoning methods to study robust notions of ''approximately inter-substitutable'' programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first intended application is the exploration of ''secure substitution'' in mobile code applications, where programs (such as tax software) are downloaded as needed, executed on a trusted host (the home computer), require access to sensitive local data (such as financial information) and yet should not be permitted to leak information. Probabilistic modeling is used in such applications to quantify the amount of information flow between systems. A permissible secure substitution of one component for another in a program context has to preserve such information flow properties in addition to the usual observations. The goal of this project is to define a robust notion of secure substitution, and develop compositional proof rules and algorithms to determine if a component can be securely substituted for another.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second intended application is the design and implementation of StochCC, an executable specification language for stochastic hybrid systems. This research will build on the PI's prior work into HybridCC, a declarative language for specifying and simulating hybrid systems. Users of HybridCC(in biological systems modeling) have already found it useful to add limited forms of discrete probabilistic specification to HybridCC. StochCC will perform a full and general integration of probabilities into HybridCC. In order to come to computational grips with such systems, one needs a notion of discrete approximation. Such discrete approximants play a role in both simulation (executing the system within some error bound) and approximate reasoning (calculating the observations of the system within some error bound).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0203716</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Radhakrishnan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jagadeesan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjagadeesan@cs.depaul.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Loyola University of Chicago</Name>
      <CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>606601537</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7735082471</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1032 W. Sheridan Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>2880</Code>
      <Text>SOFTWARE ENGINEERING AND LANGU</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
