<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Floer Theory, Symplectic Geometry and Mirror Symmetry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>129831</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0203593&lt;br/&gt;Yong-Geun Oh &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Floer homology in symplectic geometry&lt;br/&gt;was introduced by Floer in an attempt&lt;br/&gt;to prove the Arnold conjecture. &lt;br/&gt;Various results by Chekanov, Oh, Polterovich&lt;br/&gt;and Seidel have proved that the Floer homology is a general &lt;br/&gt;powerful tool to investigate symplectic topology.&lt;br/&gt;In this project, Oh proposes to &lt;br/&gt;further investigate structure and applications of the Floer &lt;br/&gt;theory for deeper understanding of the Hamiltonian diffeomorphism group &lt;br/&gt;and Lagrangian submanifolds or more generally symplectic topology.&lt;br/&gt;The Floer theory of Lagrangian submanifolds, via &lt;br/&gt;Fukaya's A-infinity category, also provides a geometric framework&lt;br/&gt;for Kontsevich's homological mirror symmetry&lt;br/&gt;proposal on Calabi-Yau manifolds. Oh's recent work with Fukaya, &lt;br/&gt;Ohta and Ono provides several key steps towards a rigorous &lt;br/&gt;construction of Fukaya's category by developing an obstruction &lt;br/&gt;theory for defining the Lagrangian intersection Floer homology.&lt;br/&gt;Complete construction will involve study of singular Lagrangian &lt;br/&gt;submanifolds, Lagrangian surgery and their relations to the Floer homology.&lt;br/&gt;Oh proposes to investigate these new aspects of the Floer theory&lt;br/&gt;in relation the mirror symmetry on the Calabi-Yau manifolds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Hamiltonian formalism plays&lt;br/&gt;important roles not only for solving problems in classical mechanics&lt;br/&gt;but also for quantizing the classical mechanics into&lt;br/&gt;quantum mechanics. The Poisson&lt;br/&gt;bracket is the crucial geometric structure that plays a key role in&lt;br/&gt;the classical mechanics and the quantum mechanics through the&lt;br/&gt;quantization process. When one considers mechanics in &lt;br/&gt;a constrained system, i.e., mechanics on a curved space, &lt;br/&gt;description of the corresponding phase space&lt;br/&gt;and the geometric structure corresponding to the Poisson bracket&lt;br/&gt;requires the notion of the symplectic structure&lt;br/&gt;and symplectic manifolds. Symplectic geometry and topology &lt;br/&gt;is the study of symplectic manifolds. &lt;br/&gt;In symplectic geometry, there are two most important objects of&lt;br/&gt;study. One is the study of Hamiltonian systems, a special type&lt;br/&gt;of differential equation, and their periodic orbits.&lt;br/&gt;This is dynamical in nature. The other is the study of geometry&lt;br/&gt;and topology of Lagrangian submanifolds. This is geometric in nature.&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the intersection theory of Lagrangian submanifolds&lt;br/&gt;is the core of symplectic topology. Floer homology introduced &lt;br/&gt;by Floer in the end of 80's is a general machinery to study&lt;br/&gt;this intersection theory. The Floer theory also provides a &lt;br/&gt;geometric framework for the mirror symmetry phenomenon that &lt;br/&gt;was discovered by physicists in string theory.&lt;br/&gt;Oh's proposed research aims at, on the one hand, deeper understanding of&lt;br/&gt;symplectic topology, and also aims at understanding inter-relations &lt;br/&gt;between the symplectic and the complex geometry &lt;br/&gt;via the study of mirror symmetry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0203593</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yong-Geun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Oh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>oh@math.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
