<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Chern-Simons Theory, and Its Limiting Geometry and Topology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>130866</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0203129&lt;br/&gt;Stavros Garoufalidis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stavros Garoufalidis plans to study applications of quantum field theory&lt;br/&gt;to 3-dimensional topology and geometry. This work is motivated by &lt;br/&gt;the Chern-Simons path integral, its exact computation (in terms of &lt;br/&gt;quantum invariants of knots and 3-manifolds) and its perturbative expansion.&lt;br/&gt;Quantum field theory predicts that invariants of knots and 3-manifolds which&lt;br/&gt;are defined via cut-and-paste topology carry geometric information of the&lt;br/&gt;underlying structures; in particular of the fundamental group of a 3-manifold&lt;br/&gt;and its representations to Lie groups. A key question is to recover the&lt;br/&gt;geometric information (described in terms of surgery theory or Riemannian&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic geometry) by taking an appropriate limit of quantum invariants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The above mentioned relation between physics and mathematics has deep roots&lt;br/&gt;in the past century. Mathematics has strongly influenced Physics, as is &lt;br/&gt;evident from the development of Mechanics, Quantum Mechanics and General&lt;br/&gt;Relativity, which describe our world in three quite different scales.&lt;br/&gt;Knotedness is a fundamental property that binds fundamental particles&lt;br/&gt;together, but also the DNA molecule.&lt;br/&gt;The most recent interaction between 3-dimensional quantum field theory and &lt;br/&gt;topology aims at describing knotedness in terms of geometric and &lt;br/&gt;topological language. Topology could be a unifying language to describe&lt;br/&gt;the building blocks of physics, but also of life itself.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0203129</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stavros</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garoufalidis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stavros@math.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
      <ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
