<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometry and Combinatorics of Hyperbolic 3-manifolds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>273213</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0203976&lt;br/&gt;Yair Minsky&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project Minsky will study connections between the geometric&lt;br/&gt;structure of hyperbolic 3-manifolds, and the combinatorial structure&lt;br/&gt;of surfaces. The main focus of the project is a program to solve&lt;br/&gt;Thurston's Ending Lamination Conjecture, which states that a&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic 3-manifold is uniquely determined by its topological type&lt;br/&gt;and a list of invariants describing the asymptotic geometry of its&lt;br/&gt;ends. This conjecture is central in the field and would settle a&lt;br/&gt;number of outstanding questions about the structure of the deformation&lt;br/&gt;space of all hyperbolic structures on a given manifold. The principal&lt;br/&gt;tool in this approach is the Complex of Curves, a combinatorial object&lt;br/&gt;which describes the set of all essential homotopy classes of simple&lt;br/&gt;loops on a given surface. Such a complex, viewed as a metric space,&lt;br/&gt;is hyperbolic in the sense of Cannon and Gromov, and the invariants&lt;br/&gt;which describe the geometry of a 3-manifold turn out to be "points at&lt;br/&gt;infinity" for the complex. A study of geodesics within the complex of&lt;br/&gt;curves then allows us to construct a model for the geometry of the&lt;br/&gt;3-manifold which depends only on its end invariants. Part of the&lt;br/&gt;program is joint work with Brock and Canary. The complex of curves is&lt;br/&gt;also instrumental in studying the Teichmuller space of hyperbolic&lt;br/&gt;structures on a surface, and its symmetry group, known as the Mapping&lt;br/&gt;Class Group. Hyperbolicity of the complex implies a type of relative&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolicity property for the Teichmuller space and the Mapping Class&lt;br/&gt;Group, and in collaboration with Brock and Masur, Minsky hopes to&lt;br/&gt;apply this to study the geometric properties of Teichmuller space, and&lt;br/&gt;to answer a number of group-theoretic and algorithmic questions about&lt;br/&gt;the mapping class group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Topological spaces appear in mathematics at varying levels of&lt;br/&gt;abstraction. The earth, for example, can be thought of as a sphere,&lt;br/&gt;spinning around its axis. The set of all positions of this sphere,&lt;br/&gt;perhaps as parameterized by the time of day in New York, can itself be&lt;br/&gt;visualized as a circle. The positions of the earth in its orbit&lt;br/&gt;around the sun also make up a circle, and all this information&lt;br/&gt;together can be described by a 2-dimensional surface, called a torus,&lt;br/&gt;so that each point in the torus corresponds to exactly one position of&lt;br/&gt;the earth-sun system, and our motion in space gives rise to a&lt;br/&gt;trajectory winding around the torus. Once a surface is being studied,&lt;br/&gt;we often give it various structures: it can have a metric, which is a&lt;br/&gt;way of measuring distance in it; it can also be filled up in different&lt;br/&gt;ways by loops. The set of all possible metrics can itself be studied&lt;br/&gt;as a "space", where motion in this space corresponds to changing&lt;br/&gt;shapes of the surface. The set of all loops in the surface gives&lt;br/&gt;rise to another space, of a more combinatorial character. A&lt;br/&gt;fascinating phenomenon, not uncommon in mathematics, is the appearance&lt;br/&gt;of analogies between these different levels of abstraction. For&lt;br/&gt;example, a property of a single metric on a surface called "hyperbolicity"&lt;br/&gt;appears again, in another guise, as a property of the space of all&lt;br/&gt;metrics on the surface and the space of all loops. The interaction&lt;br/&gt;between these different levels yields interesting phenomena and tools&lt;br/&gt;which can be applied to solve a number of problems in</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0203976</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yair</FirstName>
      <LastName>Minsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yair.minsky@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
