<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Integrated Strategy for Testing User-Oriented Software Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sol J. Greenspan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research develops an integrated strategy for the effective&lt;br/&gt;testing of ubiquitous software systems accessed by the massive user&lt;br/&gt;population, such as those used to support the Internet and World Wide Web (WWW),&lt;br/&gt;to ensure their satisfactory performance and reliability from the users'&lt;br/&gt;perspective. This strategy includes three important components:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Development of a set of high-level operational profiles (OPs),&lt;br/&gt;which enumerates major functions to be supported by a software and their&lt;br/&gt;usage frequencies by target users, organized in groups of related user&lt;br/&gt;functions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. For each high-level function group above, a Markov chain based&lt;br/&gt;model is constructed to exhaustively test high-level operations and&lt;br/&gt;selectively test important low-level implementations, with the testing results&lt;br/&gt;analyzed to identify system bottlenecks for reliability improvement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3. Reliability of the critical parts identified above can be assured&lt;br/&gt;using traditional testing techniques or other quality assurance techniques. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will involve industrial partners, including IBM, Nortel &lt;br/&gt;Networks, and Lockheed-Martin Aeronautics, for result validation, &lt;br/&gt;software tool support, and future deployment.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204345</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeff</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tian</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tian@engr.smu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Methodist University</Name>
      <CityName>Dallas</CityName>
      <ZipCode>752750302</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2147682030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6425 BOAZ</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
