<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Geometry and Topology of Orbifolds</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>82045</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-4724&lt;br/&gt;Ernesto Lupercio&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal consists of a number of research projects on the topic&lt;br/&gt;of cohomology theories for orbifolds and related subjects. The suggested&lt;br/&gt;methods combine algebraic topology with techniques&lt;br/&gt;coming from stack theory in algebraic geometry and tools arising&lt;br/&gt;in symplectic geometry. It proposes the use of the theory of&lt;br/&gt;groupoids as a unifying tool in the solution these questions; a&lt;br/&gt;methodology that has proved successful before in our study of&lt;br/&gt;orbifolds. The following is a brief summary of some aspects of the &lt;br/&gt;project. The first project is program whose objective is&lt;br/&gt;the study of the cohomological invariants that can be naturally&lt;br/&gt;obtained from several natural spaces associated to an orbifold. A&lt;br/&gt;second project consist of a study the orbifold elliptic genus, &lt;br/&gt;its modularity and rigidity properties from the homotopy &lt;br/&gt;theory point of view. The third project describes a program to &lt;br/&gt;define and study Orbifold Deligne cohomologies and their relation &lt;br/&gt;to gerbes defined over the orbifold. The fourth is a project to study &lt;br/&gt;the relation between the Hodge-Deligne numbers of an orbifold &lt;br/&gt;resolution of singularities of an orbifold and the original orbifold. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Orbifolds are geometric spaces in which it is very important to keep track&lt;br/&gt;of the local symmetries of the particular situation. So in general the&lt;br/&gt;points&lt;br/&gt;of an orbifold are classified by the amount of local symmetry. In ordinary&lt;br/&gt;spaces all points are equal, while in an orbifold points carry different&lt;br/&gt;weights corresponding to the amount of local symmetry. Orbifolds have been&lt;br/&gt;used in the study of structural crystallography allowing for a convenient&lt;br/&gt;book-keeping device by reducing the redundant information in the space &lt;br/&gt;group diagrams of the crystallographic groups. Orbifolds have also become&lt;br/&gt;extremely important in the field of theoretical physics referred to as&lt;br/&gt;Superstring&lt;br/&gt;theory. In String Theory, the multitude of particle types of classical&lt;br/&gt;high &lt;br/&gt;energy physics is replaced by a single fundamental building block, a&lt;br/&gt;`string'.&lt;br/&gt;As the string moves through time it traces out a tube or a sheet,&lt;br/&gt;according &lt;br/&gt;to whether it is closed or open. Moreover, the string can vibrate, and &lt;br/&gt;different vibrational modes of the string represent the different particle &lt;br/&gt;types, since different modes are seen as different masses or spins. In an &lt;br/&gt;attempt to make these theories describe the physical universe, physicists&lt;br/&gt;have&lt;br/&gt;been motivated to let the string move on an orbifold space. In these cases&lt;br/&gt;the&lt;br/&gt;theory acquires properties that are very desirable for it to model&lt;br/&gt;reality. &lt;br/&gt;The work proposed in this project involves the development of rigorous&lt;br/&gt;mathematical methods to study the geometry of these spaces.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204724</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alejandro</FirstName>
      <LastName>Adem</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>adem@math.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ernesto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lupercio</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lupercio@math.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>03/30/2004</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
