<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Sweden Workshop: Partial Differential Equations and Spectral Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>26948</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark A. Suskin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0204308&lt;br/&gt;Hislop&lt;br/&gt;This award supports graduate students from US universities to participate in a special program on partial differential equations and spectral theory at the Mittag-Leffler Institute in Djursholm, Sweden. The workshop will provide a unique opportunity for young mathematicians to develop collaborations with their counterparts from Sweden, as well as with leaders in the field from all of Scandinavia. The theme of the program is the interaction between partial differential equations and spectral theory, and applications to microlocal analysis and Schrodinger operators. The Mittag-Leffler Institute is a world-renowned mathematics research institute located near Stockholm. The Institute has a research building with offices, conference room, and up-to-date library, and apartments for researchers are located on campus. As a result, the Institute is an ideal place for in-depth and collaborative mathematical study and provides an optimal milieu for fostering collaboration. The Fall 2002 Program is the third such program on differential equations and spectral theory held at the Institute, two others having been held in 1982 and 1992.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204308</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hislop</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peter.hislop@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ari</FirstName>
      <LastName>Laptev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>laptev@math.kth.se</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Lexington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
      <StateCode>KY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
