<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Large Scale Geometry, Index Theory and Representations of Groups</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>126660</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0204558&lt;br/&gt;Jonathan L. Block&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In recent years there has been an explosion of interest in the&lt;br/&gt;applications of large scale or "coarse" methods in geometry, &lt;br/&gt;topology, index theory and group theory. For many topological &lt;br/&gt;and geometric problems of interest, this large-scale structure &lt;br/&gt;is relevant in answering them. The Principal Investigator will &lt;br/&gt;study three such instances. First, on a singular space, phenomena &lt;br/&gt;are affected not only by the global fundamental group, but also&lt;br/&gt;by a local picture of the fundamental group. The fundamental &lt;br/&gt;groups of the link of a stratum changes from stratum to stratum &lt;br/&gt;and affects the topological behavior of the space, in particular, &lt;br/&gt;the classification of stratified spaces must take into account &lt;br/&gt;this behavior. The PI proposes to study via operator K-theory&lt;br/&gt;how the index theory of the strata of singular spaces &lt;br/&gt;(as non-compact manifolds) fit together to give an index &lt;br/&gt;theory for the singular space itself. Second, the PI &lt;br/&gt;proposes to study more generally quantitative aspects &lt;br/&gt;of homology theory, taking into account such issues as the &lt;br/&gt;images of the homology of balls of a given size in the homology &lt;br/&gt;of a non-compact manifold. Applications to existence of &lt;br/&gt;infinitely many null-homotopic geodesics are proposed. Third, &lt;br/&gt;the large-scale / small-scale duality between a discrete group&lt;br/&gt;and its unitary representation theory has been studied under &lt;br/&gt;the rubric of the Baum-Connes conjecture. The PI, motivated by &lt;br/&gt;his work in large scale geometry proposes a broader study of &lt;br/&gt;this duality. This requires the development of tools from &lt;br/&gt;algebraic geometry (especially moduli space theory) to &lt;br/&gt;apply to infinite dimensional unitary representations. &lt;br/&gt;These tools place families of representations at the fore, &lt;br/&gt;which as two effects. First, families of representations &lt;br/&gt;seem to be more rigid then single ones. And secondly, one &lt;br/&gt;can concentrate ones attention on specific parts of the &lt;br/&gt;representation theory. Thus, the PI demonstrates, in several&lt;br/&gt;situations, that for lattices in Lie groups, the&lt;br/&gt;representation theory in an infinitesimal neighborhood &lt;br/&gt;of the trivial representation coincide for the lattice and &lt;br/&gt;the ambient group. A second type of question proposed by the &lt;br/&gt;PI are called reconstruction problems. When can one reconstruct representations on the ambient group knowing its values on the&lt;br/&gt;lattice? The PI views this as a version of the Sampling theorem &lt;br/&gt;from signal processing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Large scale geometry is the study of spaces as seen from an increasingly distant perspective. For many problems in geometry &lt;br/&gt;and topology, the phenomena at a small or moderate scale only &lt;br/&gt;obscure the situation and the large scale perspective shines &lt;br/&gt;the essential light on the subject: seeing the forest for the&lt;br/&gt;trees. This proposal focuses the attention of large-scale &lt;br/&gt;geometry on problems in index theory and representation theory &lt;br/&gt;of discrete groups. Students of PI and his collaborators are &lt;br/&gt;involved at various stages of the project. The developments &lt;br/&gt;and anticipated results are intended as a bridge between &lt;br/&gt;algebraic and geometric topology, harmonic analysis and &lt;br/&gt;functional analysis. This should provide a clearer understanding &lt;br/&gt;of all these subjects and enhance the interaction between &lt;br/&gt;the experts in them.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204558</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Block</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>blockj@math.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
