<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Topics in Differential Geometry and Mathematical Physics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT DMS - 0204002.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's first program in this proposal is concerned with the &lt;br/&gt;geometry of Hermitian or hyper-Hermitian connections with totally &lt;br/&gt;skew torsions. The results will be applicable to an investigation &lt;br/&gt;in quantum mechanical black holes. The PI's second program is to &lt;br/&gt;study the complex deformation theory and Hermitian geometry of &lt;br/&gt;nilmanifolds. Parallel to the algebraic analysis on the classical &lt;br/&gt;and extended moduli, he and his collaborators investigatge the &lt;br/&gt;geometry on these spaces from the viewpoint of special holonomy &lt;br/&gt;and symplectic structures. A senior participant proposes to &lt;br/&gt;analyse the structures of compact quaternionic Kaehler manifolds &lt;br/&gt;and the A-hat genus of non-spin manifolds with finite second &lt;br/&gt;homotopy. Both issues are tackled through an analysis of the &lt;br/&gt;rigidity of elliptic genus. Through the theory of elliptic genus, &lt;br/&gt;the two proposers will jointly calculate a Hilbert polynomial &lt;br/&gt;relevant to holomorphic contact structures or rational curves &lt;br/&gt;invariant with respect to a holomorphic automorphisms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed projects here are enabled by theoretical physicists' &lt;br/&gt;and mathematicians' knowledge on field theory, complex deformation &lt;br/&gt;theory and differential topology of fixed point sets. All proposed &lt;br/&gt;projects are intended to address issues relevant to current &lt;br/&gt;physcial or mathematical issues. The PI's projects will address a &lt;br/&gt;type of geometry less known to mathematicians than to physicists. &lt;br/&gt;The results will increase mathematicians' knowledge on Hermitian &lt;br/&gt;geometry and directly addresses issues to theoretical physcists' &lt;br/&gt;concerns. The senior participant's project addresses a long-&lt;br/&gt;standing conjecture in the field of holonomy. The central tool in &lt;br/&gt;this project is a novel differntial topological mechinary for &lt;br/&gt;studying fixed point sets with respect to group actions. The &lt;br/&gt;investigators joint project will combine their expertise to &lt;br/&gt;extract topological information on a class ofspace central in &lt;br/&gt;algebraic geometry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204002</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yat Sun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Poon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ypoon@math.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
