<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Detonation Shock Dynamics and Multi-Step Kinetics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>190822</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS Award Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Award #: 0204023&lt;br/&gt;PI: Short, Mark&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign&lt;br/&gt;Program: Applied Mathematics&lt;br/&gt;Program Manager: Catherine Mavriplis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Detonation Shock Dynamics and Multi-step Kinetics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are three outstanding problems in our pursuit of a fundamental understanding of detonation dynamics, all of which are important in an engineering tool, such as those above, that utilizes detonations. These concern the propagation and stability of curved detonations with realistic reaction kinetics; the problem of how a deflagration (flame) undergoes a transition to detonation (DDT) and the mechanisms which cause a detonation to ignite or fail (criticality). One of primary goals of this project is to obtain intrinsic surface propagation laws for both steady and unsteady curved detonation waves that are governing by several forms of realistic, but fundamental, reaction kinetics. Also, one of the most important concerns in engineering applications has to do both with the successful initiation of detonation and preventing premature failure. Mathematical investigations of these events will be conducted, including research on a new mode of detonation propagation that must be accounted for in failure problems, namely the edge-detonation. Subscale mathematical modeling will be used, applying rational asymptotic perturbation methods to derive, for example, intrinsic surface propagation laws for the motion of the detonation wave in a given system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of this project is to further our understanding of the basic mathematical physics of detonations in explosive systems ranging in size from micro-detonic applications to the collapse of stars (supernova). Traditional applications of detonation theory have focused on important issues such as safety, to defense and mining related uses. In recent years, there has been substantial interest in modern high-tech engineering applications ranging from hardening, forming and welding of metals, to precision cutting devices and thin-film manufacturing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204023</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Short</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shortl@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
