<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Invariants of Hyperbolic 3-Manifolds and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>108182</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0204311&lt;br/&gt;G. Robert Meyerhoff&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The monumental work of W. Thurston has shown the fundamental &lt;br/&gt;importance of hyperbolic 3-manifolds within the study of 3-&lt;br/&gt;manifolds. The proposer plans to work on a hard open problem in &lt;br/&gt;the theory of hyperbolic 3-manifolds, and to attempt to strengthen &lt;br/&gt;connections between number theory and the study of invariants of &lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic 3-manifolds. The hard open question is the problem of &lt;br/&gt;finding the closed hyperbolic 3-manifold of minimum volume. The &lt;br/&gt;proposer, working jointly with D. Gabai and P. Milley, and in &lt;br/&gt;consultation with N. Thurston, has a computer-based scheme to &lt;br/&gt;attack this problem. The computational aspects of the approach are &lt;br/&gt;interesting in their own right. The connection between number &lt;br/&gt;theory/algebraic K-theory and invariants of hyperbolic 3-manifolds &lt;br/&gt;is well-known, but a new approach to understanding it is proposed. &lt;br/&gt;Specifically, a new method for computing the Chern-Simons invariant &lt;br/&gt;of a hyperbolic 3-manifold might lead to interesting properties of the &lt;br/&gt;dilogarithm function.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Almost 200 years ago, J. Bolyai, C. Gauss, and N. Lobachevsky &lt;br/&gt;revolutionized mathematics by claiming that a legitimate geometry &lt;br/&gt;could be constructed by taking the five classical postulates of Euclid &lt;br/&gt;and negating the fifth postulate (the parallel postulate). Further,&lt;br/&gt;they theorized that this new and mysterious non-Euclidean geometry &lt;br/&gt;(now called "hyperbolic geometry") would have important applications. &lt;br/&gt;Their theorizing has been borne out: hyperbolic geometry is vitally&lt;br/&gt;important in the modern study of geometry. For example, hyperbolic&lt;br/&gt;geometry turns out to be much more important than Euclidean geometry&lt;br/&gt;in the study of "3-dimensional manifolds" (our 3-dimensional&lt;br/&gt;Universe is an example of a 3-dimensional manifold). As another&lt;br/&gt;example, it is quite possible that our Universe adheres to the laws&lt;br/&gt;of non-Euclidean geometry rather than the laws of Euclidean geometry.&lt;br/&gt;The proposer, working jointly with D. Gabai and P. Milley, and in &lt;br/&gt;consultation with N. Thurston, plans to work on a computer-based &lt;br/&gt;approach to solving one of the hardest and most fundamental problems &lt;br/&gt;about hyperbolic 3-manifolds: finding the smallest one. In addition, the&lt;br/&gt;proposer will try to strengthen the already existing connection between &lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic 3-manifolds and number theory. The history of mathematics&lt;br/&gt;has borne out the importance of finding strong connections between&lt;br/&gt;(supposedly) disparate areas of mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204311</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>G. Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meyerhoff</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robert.meyerhoff@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Boston College</Name>
      <CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
