<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Quantum Field Theories on Algebraic Curves and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>344997</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0204628 - Leon Takhtajan &lt;br/&gt; Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal is devoted to the study of quantum field theories on &lt;br/&gt;algebraic curves from complex analytic and algebraic points of view. &lt;br/&gt;String theory is the unifying theme of the complex-analytic part of&lt;br/&gt;the project. The main goals of this part are: 1) geometric formulation &lt;br/&gt;of two-dimensional quantum Toda theories associated with simple Lie &lt;br/&gt;algebras; 2) Fermi-Bose correspondence for compact Riemann surfaces and &lt;br/&gt;closed smooth Jordan curves; 3) proof of general Kleinian reciprocity on &lt;br/&gt;deformation spaces; 4) construction of the universal Weil-Petersson &lt;br/&gt;potential for the universal Teichmuller space; 5) curvature properties of &lt;br/&gt;the new Kahler metric on moduli spaces of punctured Riemann surfaces; 6) &lt;br/&gt;explicit form of factorization formula for determinants of Laplace &lt;br/&gt;operators acting on higher order differentials; 7) Faddeev-Popov ghosts &lt;br/&gt;for string field theory of open strings. Symmetries and Ward identities &lt;br/&gt;for correlation functions are guiding principles of the algebraic part &lt;br/&gt;of the project. The immediate and long term goals of this part are: 1) &lt;br/&gt;proof of adelic Fermi-Bose correspondence for vertex operators, complete &lt;br/&gt;construction of quantum field theory of multiplicative bosons and proof &lt;br/&gt;of A. Weil's reciprocity law; 2) construction of quantum field theories &lt;br/&gt;on algebraic curves in non-zero characteristic with Artin-Schreier and &lt;br/&gt;Kummer theories as main examples, proof of Artin's reciprocity law using &lt;br/&gt;quantum field-theoretical methods; 3) adelic formulation of the WZW &lt;br/&gt;theory on algebraic curves in characteristic zero.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In mathematical development a pivotal role is played by ideas from &lt;br/&gt;physics, originated in the study of the surrounding world. The last twenty &lt;br/&gt;five years have been characterized by dramatic success in application &lt;br/&gt;of quantum fields and strings to different areas of mathematics. The idea &lt;br/&gt;is to probe mathematical objects by quantum theories and to measure their &lt;br/&gt;response in order to get new information about the various mathematical &lt;br/&gt;properties of these objects. Usually the output is encoded in terms of &lt;br/&gt;partition function and correlation functions of physical theory, and the &lt;br/&gt;problem is to decode it back in mathematical terms. The goals of this &lt;br/&gt;proposal are the following: 1) to extend further quantum-theoretic method &lt;br/&gt;for the study of complex analytic properties of surfaces in two &lt;br/&gt;dimensions and their families; 2) to develop a new systematic &lt;br/&gt;quantum-theoretic approach for arithmetic surfaces and algebraic number &lt;br/&gt;fields (like the usual field of rational numbers). Fundamental properties &lt;br/&gt;of these objects are discrete and it is only natural to study them at a &lt;br/&gt;microscopic scale using quantum theory. In particular, many classical &lt;br/&gt;mathematical results about fields of algebraic functions and algebraic &lt;br/&gt;numbers, known as reciprocity laws, can be interpreted as conservation &lt;br/&gt;laws (like conservation of energy) in quantum theory. The main goal of &lt;br/&gt;the algebraic part of the project is to develop a new approach based on &lt;br/&gt;quantum theory towards fundamental laws that are satisfied by the very &lt;br/&gt;basic mathematical objects: algebraic numbers - solutions of algebraic &lt;br/&gt;equations with coefficients being rational numbers, and algebraic &lt;br/&gt;functions - solutions of algebraic equations with coefficients being &lt;br/&gt;rational functions. Realization of the goals of the proposal will &lt;br/&gt;contribute to the fundamental interface between mathematics and physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204628</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Takhtajan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>leontak@math.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1264</Code>
      <Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1265</Code>
      <Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1287</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
