<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Study of Ropelength and Knot Energies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>203992</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christopher W. Stark</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0204826&lt;br/&gt;Jason Cantarella and Joseph Fu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will study the geometry of knots which are critical&lt;br/&gt;configurations for "ropelength", which is defined to be the quotient&lt;br/&gt;of their length over the radius of their largest embedded tubular&lt;br/&gt;neighborhood. Since the ropelength functional is not smooth, there is&lt;br/&gt;no classical Euler-Lagrange equation describing the minimizers. The&lt;br/&gt;primary aim of the projec666t is to provide an analogy to the&lt;br/&gt;Euler-Lagrange equation: a "balance criterion", which shows that a&lt;br/&gt;curve is ropelength critical if and only if the first variation of the&lt;br/&gt;length of the core curve can be balanced by a system of self-contact&lt;br/&gt;forces acting on the surrounding tube. The methods used to prove the&lt;br/&gt;balance criterion (a generalization of certain aspects of tensegrity&lt;br/&gt;theory to a class of "continuous tensegrities", using a version of the&lt;br/&gt;Farkas alternative theorem for linear operators on Banach spaces)&lt;br/&gt;promise rich applications in other areas of mathematics, such as the&lt;br/&gt;study of convex curves, and of "knot energies".&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A natural model for a rope with a circular cross-section is a space&lt;br/&gt;curve surrounded by a non-self-intersecting tube of fixed radius. If&lt;br/&gt;such a rope is tied in a knot, and the knot is pulled tight, the&lt;br/&gt;resulting curve is a critical configuration for the "ropelength" of&lt;br/&gt;the curve, which is defined to be the quotient of the length of the&lt;br/&gt;curve over the radius of the tube. The project studies the geometry of&lt;br/&gt;ropelength-critical curves using ideas from the theory of frameworks.&lt;br/&gt;This theory studies simple engineering models of structures, and gives&lt;br/&gt;a precise description of how external loads on a structure are&lt;br/&gt;resolved into tensions and compressions of different structural&lt;br/&gt;elements. The project views the tension in a tight knot as exerting a&lt;br/&gt;force directed towards the inside of each curve of the rope, and aims&lt;br/&gt;to show that such a curve is tight if this force can be resolved into&lt;br/&gt;a system of self-contact forces acting on the surface of the tube.&lt;br/&gt;This "balance criterion" has surprising consequences. Imagine a rope&lt;br/&gt;stretched horizontally, like a clothesline. If another rope is passed&lt;br/&gt;over the line, and pulled down until the pair is tight, the ropes form&lt;br/&gt;four straight segments joined to a central region where the strands&lt;br/&gt;curve around one another. One would expect the ropes to maintain&lt;br/&gt;contact throughout this curved clasp, with the two points on the&lt;br/&gt;inside of each bend touching one another. However, according to the&lt;br/&gt;balance criterion, this cannot happen: there is always a small gap&lt;br/&gt;between the two strands at the center of the turn. This model has&lt;br/&gt;already been used in molecular biology to describe the behavior of DNA&lt;br/&gt;strands; the new geometric information provided by the project will&lt;br/&gt;help to refine and extend many other appications of this model in&lt;br/&gt;physics, biology, and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0204826</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph H.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fu@alpha.math.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cantarella</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cantarel@math.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
