<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Integrated IT Approach for Teaching Undergraduates Spectroscopy and Photochemistry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>304998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Susan H. Hixson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is using the twin themes of spectroscopy and photochemistry as a conceptual basis for developing chemistry lectures and chemistry laboratories in upper level undergraduate courses which are logical extensions of the materials presented in the lower level courses. This intergrated approach aims to provide students with a clearer connection between the concepts presented at different stages in their undergraduate education in chemistry. The project is also producing software modules which are "Spectroscopy Tutors" that aim to facilitate the learning of spectroscopy (IR, UV-VIS, NMR) and assist in the intergration of spectroscopy and photochemistry throughout the undergraduate curriculum including undergraduate research. These visions are being achieved through a collaboration with Professor Leonard Fine and students at Columbia University. In addition, partnerships have been established with faculty at two undergraduate institutions (Professor Tom Poon, Claremont Colleges and Professor Raymond Dominey, University of Richmond) and a community college (Professor Ron Rusay, Diablo State College). The project couples the undergraduate institutions by establishing an undergraduate exchange program in which students from the undergraduate institutions spend a summer at Columbia University under the mentorship of the PI, extending and enriching research projects, which are initiated in the academic year. The PI is also mentoring an undergraduate selected from Columbia Unversity's Minority Affairs summer research program for undergraduates. The PI is mentoring a postdoctoral associate who is involved in all aspects of the project and in particular the intergration of research and education of undergraduates. The postdctoral associate is assisting the PI in the development of course materials, the development of IT tools for courses and laboratories and in the development of course materials, the development of IT tools for course and laboratories, and the development of the photochemical experiments for the undergraduate laboratories and for undergraduate research. The outcomes of the project will be disseminated through presentations at professional meetings, publications in professional journals and an annual workshop led by the partnering faculty. As part of the dissemination effort, the Spectroscopy Tutors produced will be made available to undergraduates across the nation via the world wide web. In addition, the PI is producing a web based video course in which he teaches undergraduates spectroscopy and organic photochemistry. As part of the course, modules are being developed to assist the students in learning the fundamental principles of organic photochemistry. It is anticipated that the course and laboratory materials, as well as IT modules developed in the project, can also be profitably employed in the curriculum for the non-SMET education of undergraduates. In collaboration with the Associate Dean for Assessment at Columbia University, the PI is defining the desired educational objectives for the students' experiences in the courses and laboratories and IT modules. This assessment process aims to measure student performance on course-specific tests and on the effectiveness of the Spectroscopy Tutors in the enhancing of learning by students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0205781</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Turro</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>njt3@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1253</Code>
      <Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1746</Code>
      <Text>DISTINGUISHED TEACHING SCHOLAR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1746</Code>
      <Text>DISTINGUISHED TEACHING SCHOLAR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
