<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR: New directions in clustering and learning</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1530001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Beigel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>New directions in clustering and learning&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Faced with ever-larger amounts of data, researchers, government &lt;br/&gt;institutions, corporations and even the general public seek tools that help them deal &lt;br/&gt;with large bodies of information, identify patterns in it, learn what these&lt;br/&gt;patterns mean, and act upon that information in a timely fashion. &lt;br/&gt;Developing such tools involves a novel and interesting blend of algorithms, &lt;br/&gt;statistics, AI, and machine learning. The project assembles a team of experts (four&lt;br/&gt;from academia and two from industry) in these areas to attack an interesting&lt;br/&gt;and meaningful subset of such problems which have the general flavor of&lt;br/&gt;clustering or learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The defining philosophy of this proposal is that no clear boundary &lt;br/&gt;Separates the twin notions of clustering and learning. Clustering is usually driven&lt;br/&gt;by the end goal of learning, but can also be viewed as a learning task&lt;br/&gt;in itself since it results in a more compact description of the data.&lt;br/&gt;By the same token all learning involves clustering of some sort, and&lt;br/&gt;in fact this viewpoint is implicit in recent papers in the learning &lt;br/&gt;literature. The project takes an integrated view of the entire problem of learning&lt;br/&gt;patterns in data, starting from streaming computations that might produce&lt;br/&gt;representative sketches of the data as it streams by, to problems of &lt;br/&gt;clustering data into meaninful patterns (with attendant problems of outlier removal,&lt;br/&gt;multiobjective optimization etc.), to learning algorithms that fit&lt;br/&gt;sophisticated models (SVMs, bayesian nets, gaussian mixtures etc.) for &lt;br/&gt;inference and reasoning tasks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators believe that all these disparate algorithmic efforts have&lt;br/&gt;unifying ideas. Furthermore, their synergistic approach throws up several&lt;br/&gt;interesting ideas of its own that could lead to significant advances. &lt;br/&gt;Examples: include using coding theoretic ideas in disparate applications such as &lt;br/&gt;Multiclass learning (a broad class of learning problems including text and speech &lt;br/&gt;categorization, part-of-speech tagging, gesture recognition etc.) and shape recognition&lt;br/&gt;in vision; the use of clustering ideas to do dimension reduction (offering&lt;br/&gt;an alternative to popular SVD based approaches), and using ideas from&lt;br/&gt;approximation algorithms and clustering to do near-optimal model fitting&lt;br/&gt;for models such as bayesian nets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project also includes a management and educational plan that involves&lt;br/&gt;dissemination of the ideas of this research through development of new &lt;br/&gt;courses and also pieces of learning software that will be placed in the public domain.&lt;br/&gt;Algorithms developed in as part of this project will be tested on large &lt;br/&gt;datasets, including those obtained from Google Inc. Some algorithmic ideas will &lt;br/&gt;also be implemented in industry (including Google).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0205594</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amit</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sahai</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sahai@cs.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Moses</FirstName>
      <LastName>Charikar</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>charikar@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sanjeev</FirstName>
      <LastName>Arora</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>arora@cs.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
