<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Studies of Supernovae and Supernova Remnants</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>270520</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020415</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael M. Briley</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PI Kirshner&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a program of diligent observation and analysis of supernova explosions. The goals&lt;br/&gt;are to understand the mechanisms by which stars explode, to assess the supernova&lt;br/&gt;contribution to the heavy element enrichment of the Universe, and to use supernova&lt;br/&gt;explosions as tools for measuring the expansion history of the Universe. Many people have&lt;br/&gt;embarked on finding supernovae, but these discoveries only lead to increased understanding when they are followed up. This group has been one of the most effective teams in the world at following supernovae -- in part because of the ideal instrumentation at Mount Hopkins . In the coming years, the 6.5 meter MMT will become available along with the extraordinary opportunities at the two Magellan telescopes in the southern hemisphere. They are also refurbishing the 1.3 meter former 2MASS survey telescope at Mount Hopkins to augment the world's supply of infrared data. The group has made excellent progress in using Type Ia supernovae as accurate tools to measure extragalactic distances. This leads to a measurement of the expansion rate of the Universe, an estimate for the age of the Universe, demonstration of time dilation at high redshift, a way to detect large scale flows, and gives the only direct evidence for an accelerating Universe. Supernova observations have revealed that 2/3 of the Universe is dark energy, of an as-yet undetermined type, a finding with deep resonances with fundamental physics.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0205808</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kirshner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kirshner@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Harvard University</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
