<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Broken-Symmetry States of Confined Interacting Electrons</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daryl W. Hess</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant supports research and education at an undergraduate institution (RUI) and focuses on the novel aspects of the physics of strongly interacting electrons that are confined to bilayers or superlattices. A major emphasis is placed on mentoring undergraduate students by involving them directly in carrying out original research and publishing their work. &lt;br/&gt;The research is organized around three well-defined projects that have been chosen according to two criteria: (1) a project should address problems in the physics of confined electrons that are intrinsically interesting and novel, and (2) a project should make extensive use of undergraduate contributions to the research, primarily in carrying out computer-based physics calculations. Two of the projects involve calculating properties of interacting electrons in double quantum wells. The third project involves calculating the properties of broken-symmetry states in superlattices. The work proposed here includes the study: of partial pseudospin polarization in quantum Hall bilayers and an effective theory of the nT =1/3 bilayer quantum Hall state, of charge-order of broken-symmetry states of superlattices, and of the effects of interlayer correlation in bilayer hole systems. Parts of this research will be carried out in collaboration with experimentalists. &lt;br/&gt;Each project has computational aspects that are suitable for mentored undergraduates working with the PI. Calculations will emphasize experimentally measurable physical properties of these multilayer systems.&lt;br/&gt;This RUI award will have an impact on the education of undergraduates at Boise State; they will be exposed to problems at the frontiers of theoretical condensed matter physics research. Although the nature of the subject is technical, the PI has been successful in carrying out and publishing condensed-matter-physics research with undergraduate students, including students from groups that have been traditionally underrepresented in physics.&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;This grant supports research and education at an undergraduate institution (RUI) and focuses on the novel aspects of the physics of strongly interacting electrons that are confined to two or more closely spaced two-dimensional layers. The PI will study new electronic phases in these high mobility semiconductor structures that are stabilized by a strong magnetic field applied perpendicular to the layers. A major emphasis is placed on mentoring and educating undergraduate students by involving them directly in carrying out original research and publishing their work. This RUI award will expose undergraduates at Boise State to areas of fundamental condensed matter physics that are at the forefront of current theoretical research and may shape future electronic device technologies. Although the nature of the subject is technical, the PI has been successful in carrying out and publishing condensed-matter-physics research with undergraduate students, including students from groups that have been traditionally underrepresented in physics.&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206681</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hanna</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>channa@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Boise State University</Name>
      <CityName>boise</CityName>
      <ZipCode>837251135</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2084261574</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1910 University Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Idaho</StateName>
      <StateCode>ID</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
