<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Year of Algebra at the University of Florida</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>35000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia M. Wiegand</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Year of Algebra 2002- 2003 at the University of Florida &lt;br/&gt;is highlighted by the celebration of the 70th birthday of John&lt;br/&gt;G. Thompson. The general theme of the Year of Algebra is provided &lt;br/&gt;by the wider context of Thompson's monumental contributions: the &lt;br/&gt;beauty and power of group theory, and how it applies to problems of&lt;br/&gt;arithmetic via the basic principle of Galois. The Year of Algebra &lt;br/&gt;features a conference in Galois Theory (Nov. 3--9, 2002), a conference&lt;br/&gt;in Group Theory (March 9--16, 2003) and a workshop on Computational&lt;br/&gt;Aspects of Algebraic Curves, and Cryptography (March 9--15, 2003).&lt;br/&gt;The Galois conference centers around the Inverse Problem of Galois&lt;br/&gt;Theory, one of the major open problems of mathematics. The conference&lt;br/&gt;on Finite Group Theory has speakers involved in the completion/&lt;br/&gt;revision of the Classification, as well as speakers in Representation&lt;br/&gt;Theory, and applications of Finite Groups to Finite Geometries and&lt;br/&gt;other areas. The workshop deals with interactions between modern &lt;br/&gt;computational tools/questions and the theory of algebraic curves,&lt;br/&gt;emphasizing the application to public key cryptography. It has a &lt;br/&gt;strong instructional component (mini-courses).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Group Theory is the abstract study of symmetry patterns (of any&lt;br/&gt;object), and Galois Theory provides tools for applying Group Theory&lt;br/&gt;to algebra and arithmetic. Recent applications to data security&lt;br/&gt;(public key cryptography) are the topic of the workshop. Galois &lt;br/&gt;Theory and Group Theory have further applications to physics, &lt;br/&gt;chemistry and coding theory. The Year of Algebra provides an&lt;br/&gt;opportunity for young mathematicians, women and minorities to &lt;br/&gt;learn the latest advances. It was John G. Thompson who shaped &lt;br/&gt;finite group theory like no-one else, leading the way towards a &lt;br/&gt;major milestone of 20th century mathematics, the classification&lt;br/&gt;of finite simple groups. After the classification, it was again&lt;br/&gt;J. Thompson who led the way in exploring its implications for&lt;br/&gt;Galois Theory. For these contributions, Thompson has recently&lt;br/&gt;been awarded the National Medal of Science. He also won the Fields&lt;br/&gt;Medal, the highest honor in mathematics. For the Year of Algebra,&lt;br/&gt;University of Florida Graduate Research Professor John G. Thompson&lt;br/&gt;acts as an advisor. His powerful ideas continue to inspire the young.&lt;br/&gt;We want to use this opportunity in a special effort to integrate&lt;br/&gt;research and education during the Year of Algebra. While the two&lt;br/&gt;conferences emphasize latest advances in research, the workshop &lt;br/&gt;has a strong instructional component.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206201</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Helmut</FirstName>
      <LastName>Voelklein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>helmut@math.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexandre</FirstName>
      <LastName>Turull</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>turull@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chat-Yin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ho</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cyh@math.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
