<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Student Developer: Using 360-Degree Multisource Assessment for Student Learning and Professional Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>494178</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myles G. Boylan</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A team of multidisciplinary assessment researchers from several universities is adapting and enhancing a proven, validated methodology for assessing and developing student learning outcomes via feedback solicited from multiple sources. The project team is enhancing the Team Developer system to allow students the opportunity to select any number of feedback providers in support of their own learning and development. This newly enhanced system supports the assessment of a broader set of learning outcomes based on the full EC-2000 criteria (A-K). The resultant system, designated as the Student Developer, allows students to build a more comprehensive set of competencies by soliciting feedback from multiple sources including peers, faculty, co-op and intern supervisors, family members, and others. It allows students to receive periodic assessments of their learning and professional development from various perspectives -- providing a 360-degree view of how their learning and development is being perceived by others within the educational environment . In addition, the Student Developer is web-based to facilitate its use. A comprehensive evaluation is a major activity throughout the project's life cycle. A series of project metrics helps monitor performance and overall impact on student learning, faculty, and academic programs. Defined metrics include student usage and satisfaction, student improvement actions taken based on collected data, and input from various feedback sources. Dissemination is an integral activity in this project and these efforts include workshops, presentations, and publications in major engineering education forums. Additionally, John Wiley Publishers is supportive of publishing the Student Developer, using the same model that has been successfully applied to the Team Developer. For the Student Developer, the PIs are writing a similar student workbook to complement the system being developed through this project. The team plans to distribute the Student Developer application to faculty for free and students would have the opportunity to learn more about EC2000 related skills through an associated workbook published by Wiley.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206630</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>McGourty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jm723@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shuman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shuman@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Harvey</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wolfe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hwolfe@engrng.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Besterfield-Sacre</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mbsacre@engr.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J Elaine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seat</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>seat@tennessee.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
