<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Massive Stellar Evolution, Supernovae, and Nucleosynthesis</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>402567</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020415</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Donald M. Terndrup</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>AST-0206111&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI Woosley&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will continue research into nucleosynthesis and the end points of massive stellar evolution. This includes the evolution of stars eight times as massive as the sun and greater through all stages of their lives; modeling their explosions as supernovae, calculating the detailed production of the isotopes of all the elements; and examining the properties of the neutron stars and black holes they leave behind. The output from these calculations will be important input to other studies of the chemical evolution of our Galaxy and other galaxies. As a byproduct, the approximate distribution of neutron star and black hole masses throughout Galactic history will be determined. This project will result in a better understanding of the origin of the elements, the nature of supernovae, and the compositions of stars formed at various epochs in the past. Personnel with valuable computational and scientific skills will be trained. All model results will be made available to the community at the website, www.supersci.org.&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206111</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stanford</FirstName>
      <LastName>Woosley</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>woosley@ucolick.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
