<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sampled Data Stabilization and Tracking for Partial Differential Equations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75176</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0206951&lt;br/&gt;Rebarber&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will focus on developing techniques for sampled-data &lt;br/&gt;feedback for infinite dimensional systems. A discrete time controller can &lt;br/&gt;operator with only limited frequency response, and infinite dimensional &lt;br/&gt;systems often have high frequency effects which cannot be ignored, so &lt;br/&gt;there is not only interest in what can be done with sampled-data control &lt;br/&gt;design, but also in its limitations. The following question is basic: can a &lt;br/&gt;given continuous-time controller be replaced by a related sampled-data &lt;br/&gt;controller, while maintaining the desired response of the closed-loop &lt;br/&gt;system? Both idealized and generalized sample-and-hold will be &lt;br/&gt;considered. Generalized hold can be used as a design parameter, and &lt;br/&gt;generalized sampling can be used when the output is not sufficiently &lt;br/&gt;smooth to accommodate point evaluations in time. The PI will &lt;br/&gt;characterize as completely as possible those continuous-time feedback &lt;br/&gt;systems which do not lose their closed-loop stability when a sampled data &lt;br/&gt;scheme (with sufficiently small sampling time) is applied to the feedback, &lt;br/&gt;and will determine whether the performance of the sampled-data system &lt;br/&gt;can approximate the continuous time performance. The performance &lt;br/&gt;measures considered are closed-loop growth rate and stability radius. &lt;br/&gt;Tracking techniques for infinite dimensional systems will also be studied &lt;br/&gt;and developed. Suppose a system has an external disturbance term which &lt;br/&gt;is to be rejected, or an external reference term to be tracked. One common &lt;br/&gt;approach to doing this is by a low-gain controller suggested by the internal &lt;br/&gt;model principle. The effectiveness of such a controller for a wide class of &lt;br/&gt;systems will be studied, as well as its sensitivity to frequency variations in &lt;br/&gt;the external signal. Sampled-data versions of tracking controllers will also &lt;br/&gt;be considered. These sampled-data and tracking results will be applied to &lt;br/&gt;PDEs in more than one space variable, especially coupled PDE models &lt;br/&gt;with at least one hyperbolic component. Due to the fact that these models &lt;br/&gt;involve two different of PDEs, coupled via highly unbounded operators, &lt;br/&gt;the analysis has features which are distinct from the analysis for &lt;br/&gt;uncoupled systems. For this problem a central concern for output &lt;br/&gt;feedback design is the analysis of the input-output map, i.e. the map from &lt;br/&gt;the control to the observation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advances in digital technology have led to an emphasis on sampled-data &lt;br/&gt;design in control engineering, but the development of sampled data &lt;br/&gt;control for infinite-dimensional systems such as PDEs has been limited. &lt;br/&gt;In many applications output data is available in discrete time rather than &lt;br/&gt;continuous time, and a feedback controller for such a system should be &lt;br/&gt;designed to take discrete data as its input, but act in continuous time. &lt;br/&gt;Since there is already an enormous literature on continuous time &lt;br/&gt;stabilization of PDEs, the project will involve the investigation of how to &lt;br/&gt;modify continuous time controllers to obtain sampled data controllers, &lt;br/&gt;while maintaining system performance. Also of interest are techniques for &lt;br/&gt;designing effective sampled-data controllers without reference to &lt;br/&gt;continuous time design. Another topic to be considered is the design of &lt;br/&gt;active feedback control tracking external signals and rejecting noise. As an &lt;br/&gt;application, these methods will be used to design a controller to reject &lt;br/&gt;noise in a PDE model which describes the interaction between sound &lt;br/&gt;waves in a cavity (for instance, an airplane cockpit) and the motion of a &lt;br/&gt;flexible wall of the cavity. Suppose that there is an external noise source, &lt;br/&gt;such as engine noise, which is to be rejected, and active feedback control &lt;br/&gt;is to be applied to smart material actuators on the cavity walls. Then a &lt;br/&gt;properly designed low-gain controller (either continuous time feedback or &lt;br/&gt;sampled-data) will attenuate the sound pressure at and near finitely many &lt;br/&gt;points of the cavity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206951</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rebarber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rrebarber1@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
      <CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
      <ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 Vine St, 151 Whittier</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
      <StateCode>NE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
