<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Homotopy Theory of Commutative Algebras and its Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>108409</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0206647&lt;br/&gt;James M. Turner&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An active area of research in commutative algebra since the &lt;br/&gt;1950s has involved the use of homological methods to &lt;br/&gt;characterize Noetherian rings and the homomorphisms between &lt;br/&gt;them. In the 1960s, simplicial methods were used to enable &lt;br/&gt;homotopy theory to apply to commutative algebras and develop &lt;br/&gt;richer homological techniques. This project seeks to use &lt;br/&gt;homotopy theory to characterize (simplicial) commutative &lt;br/&gt;algebras with a Noetherian property. Part of this effort &lt;br/&gt;will seek to resolve a conjecture of Quillen on the rigidity &lt;br/&gt;of the homology of commutative algebras and draw deeper &lt;br/&gt;connections between simplicial methods and methods from &lt;br/&gt;differential homological algebra. This project will also &lt;br/&gt;study how the cohomology of algebras can serve as host &lt;br/&gt;for obstructions to realizing a topological space from &lt;br/&gt;given algebraic data that functions as the value of a &lt;br/&gt;suitable homotopy invariant of the putative space. &lt;br/&gt;Attention will be paid to developing methods for computing &lt;br/&gt;such obstructions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Homotopy theory is a method of studying certain mathematical &lt;br/&gt;objects and the relations between them from a global &lt;br/&gt;perspective. In the case of geometric objects, certain &lt;br/&gt;algebraic invariants can be assigned to study and distinguish &lt;br/&gt;between homotopy types. Understanding the properties of these &lt;br/&gt;algebraic structures and how they relate to the geometric &lt;br/&gt;objects they are associated to are therefore important parts &lt;br/&gt;of this theory. This project seeks to further the &lt;br/&gt;understanding of the homotopy theory of geometric objects &lt;br/&gt;from the algebraic perspective. There are two aims to this &lt;br/&gt;project. The first is to develop further the homotopy theory &lt;br/&gt;of algebras that parallels that of geometric objects. The &lt;br/&gt;second aim seeks to make use of the homotopy of algebras &lt;br/&gt;and their various properties to understand the homotopy of &lt;br/&gt;spaces. This would involve studying the extent to which &lt;br/&gt;algebraic structures and properties can be lifted to &lt;br/&gt;corresponding structures and properties for geometric objects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206647</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gerard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Venema</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>venema@calvin.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Turner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jturner@calvin.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Calvin College</Name>
      <CityName>GRAND RAPIDS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>495464301</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6165266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3201 BURTON ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
