<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Maintenance of Genetic Variation in an Island System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6972</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mark Courtney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigators will conduct a survey of genetic variation for a set of fitness related genes (the Major Histocompatability Complex or Mhc) in a locally threatened endemic canid, the Island fox (Urocyon littoralis). The goal is to understand the role that natural selection has played in maintaining variation in small populations. This understanding will also allow for a more effective management of the endangered Island fox and other species that are declining or threatened. An initial survey of polymorphism at the Mhc has revealed an unprecedented level of genetic variation in Island foxes. The investigators will survey molecular variation of four Mhc genes in Island foxes using PCR (polymerase chain reaction) based techniques, and compare this to the null model of neutral genetic variation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mhc genes are integral to vertebrate immune function, and variation in the Mhc affects individual fitness (e.g. resistance or susceptibility to pathogens). This study will attempt to illuminate, though direct observation and computer simulation, the strength of natural selection necessary to maintain genetic variation in a species with limited genetic variation. These results will have direct implications for conservation and management of the Island fox, as well as provide a greater understanding of the extent of natural selection operating upon an immunologically important set of genes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206760</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wayne</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rwayne@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0312000</Code>
      <Name>Population</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
