<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Technoquest</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1821569</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Arlene M. de Strulle</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Oregon Museum of Science and Industry (OMSI) will design, develop, evaluate and install "Technoquest," a permanent 6,000 square foot interactive technology exhibition for families, underrepresented groups, school groups and OMSI's general audience. "Technoquest" will fill OMSI's Technology Hall with a suite of highly interactive, exciting and engaging hands-on educational exhibits, computer simulations, audio and video components, text, graphics and artifacts. The exhibition hall will be divided into five thematic areas: industrial technology (robotics), medical technology, transportation technology, computer technology and communications technology. Other experiences will include a quick-change area for rapidly exhibiting emerging technologies and a Technology Lab where activities conveying a deeper understanding of the general principles of technology will be presented. Ancillary educational materials will be disseminated to the general public and to educators via print, the exhibition website, teacher workshops and professional development workshops for informal science educators. Content of the exhibition and ancillary materials will focus on general educational principles established by the International Technology Education Association (ITEA) that emphasize the processes common to all forms of technology and that align with state and national science standards. Principal concepts include The Nature of Technology, Technology and Society, Design, Abilities in a Technological World, and The Designed World. These principles will be reinforced throughout the exhibition. Each thematic area will highlight all five key principles of technology as defined by the ITEA.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206403</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dabrowski</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jan.Dabrowski@omsi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>05/20/2003</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vandiver</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rvandiver@omsi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/20/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fleskes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Ben.Fleskes@omsi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/20/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oregon Museum of Science and Industry</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972143354</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037974681</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1945 SE WATER AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
