<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Northwest Corps of Re-Discovery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>325455</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia M. James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Students in grades 6-9 will be recruited to participate in the "Corps of Rediscovery," conducted by the Portland State University in partnership with the Oregon Historical Society, the Center for Columbia River History, the Metro Regional Greenspaces &amp; US Forest Service and the Jackson Bottom Wetland Preserve. Students will gain a cultural, historical and ecological understanding of the impact of the settlement of the lower Columbia River, beginning with the time of the Lewis and Clark expedition. Students will study the environment using past and current techniques and technologies. Activities include studies of plant and animal species, navigation and mapping using GPS, in addition to land use practices. It is anticipated that up to 72 students will participate in years 1-2 of the project meeting bi-weekly after school, supplemented by a monthly field day and a summer institute. During the final year of the project, Leadership Teams will be formed with a subset of 24 students who participate in advanced ecological studies and site planning while developing products for use in dissemination. A CD ROM showcasing student products and a website will be produced, as well as student posters and mapping data.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0206412</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Becker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>beckerw@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lauri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shainsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shainsk@aol.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Portland State University</Name>
      <CityName>Portland</CityName>
      <ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
