<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>North American participation in the NSF-DELOS Working Group on Digital Archiving and Preservation.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>31543</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stephen Griffin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposal is to establish a US-EU/DELOS working group on "Digital Archiving and Preservation". The working group will meet over the next year to discuss and evaluate fruitful joint activities and research paths for collaborative activities in this general topical area. The EU component of the effort is funded and managed by the DELOS Forum, a major organizer of digital libraries research and planning activities in Europe. DELOS receives support from the Information Societies Technologies (IST) 5th Framework Programme of the European Commission. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This effort continues the planning and assessment activities begun by an earlier NSF-EU working groups' process. In their final report "An International Research Agenda for Digital Libraries", delivered in Brussels in October 1998, increased levels of collaboration and interaction was seen as critical to building multi-lingual, multi-national digital libraries. The objective of the new working groups, of which this is one, is to define a research agenda on a specific topic and identify areas and activities for cooperation between EU and US researchers. The efforts of this particular group take the next step in the planning process by assessing future directions for research and resource development related to archiving and preservation of digital content.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0207482</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hedstrom</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hedstrom@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
