<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Moment Differential Equations, CTRW and Functional Renormalization to Predict Transport in Highly Heterogeneous Porous Media: Theory and Experiments</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>64000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030109</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>L. Douglas James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0207988&lt;br/&gt;Sornette&lt;br/&gt;Transport in heterogeneous porous media poses formidable challenges to model and predict with good reliability. We propose to develop a microscopic physical basis for effective large scale models such as the continuous-time random walk (CTRW) method, which takes into account extreme fluctuations and anomalous transport paths in the contribution to the large scale transport properties. For this, we will use a combination of renormalization group and functional renormalization techniques to coarse-grain and extrapolate from the microscopic realm to the large-scale description. We also propose to generalize the CTRW model to a multi-scale hierarchical framework with standard local Poissonian-in-time and Gaussian diffusion-in-space describing microscopic processes, to investigate in what sense the coexistence of multiple scales is responsible for the effective anomalous power law properties, such as non-Gaussian distribution of trapping times and of jump sizes captured by the CTRW framework which are usually postulated at a phenomenological level.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0207988</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Didier</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sornette</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sornette@moho.ess.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
