<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Inventory of U.S. - South African Research and Training Collaborations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>34673</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jolene K. Jesse</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funds for the Social Science Research Council to conduct an inventory of existing linkages between U.S. and South African institutions. The goal of the inventory is to identify existing gaps in U.S.-South Africa collaborations in research and training, and to contribute to the development of priorities for future collaborative activities. The inventory will specifically survey collaborations in social science research and capacity building activities devoted to training in all fields. It will thus serve as an important resource for U.S. researchers and universities in identifying new potential partnerships with South African scientists and higher education institutions. In consultation with the National Science Foundation and relevant components of the South African research community, the SSRC will develop the scope and terms of reference for the inventory, identify a small team to carry out the study, and oversee data collection and the production of a report that will be completed in various stages. Preliminary results will be available in January 2002 with a final report completed in the summer of 2002.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/03/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/30/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0207344</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kassimir</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kassimir@ssrc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Social Science Research Council</Name>
      <CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
      <ZipCode>112010000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2123772700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Pierrepont Plaza</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
