<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Investigation of Archean Ophiolites and Oceanic Crust and Mantle Fragments in Melange, North China Craton: Implications for Archean Tectonics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>109907</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030103</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Fountain</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Understanding Archean crustal and mantle evolution hinges upon proper identification and characterization of oceanic lithosphere. The PI has discovered and reported a complete, albeit slightly dismembered and metamorphosed, Archean ophiolite sequence in the North China Craton. The top of the ophiolitic succession is marked by sulfide-rich chert and banded iron fon-nation overlying several tens-to one hundred meters of variably deformed pillow lavas. These grade down through a mixed dike/pillow lava section into a 2 km thick I 00% sheeted dike complex mapped continuously for more than 5 km along strike; reconnaissance mapping suggests that the dike complex may extend for more than 20 km. The dikes consist of diabase, basalt and hb-pyx-gabbro. Most have chilled margins developed on their NE sides, but not their SW sides, indicating one-way chilling. The sheeted dike complex is underlain by several km of mixed isotropic and foliated gabbro, which develop compositional layering approximately 2 km below the sheeted dikes, and then over several hundred meters merge into strongly compositionally layered gabbro and olivine-gabbro. The layered gabbro becomes mixed with layered pyroxenite/gabbro marking a transition zone that grades into cumulate ultramafic rocks including dunite, pyroxenite and wehrlite, and finally into strongly defon-fied and serpentinized olivine and orthopyroxene-bearing ultramafic rocks that may be depleted mantle harzburgite tectonites. The PI has obtained a U/Pb zircon age of 2.505 Ga from gabbro of the Dongwanzi ophiolite, making it the world s oldest recognized, laterally- extensive complete ophiolite sequence. Study of this remarkable ophiolite may offer the best constraints yet on the nature of the Archean oceanic crust and mantle, and offer insights to the style of Archean plate tectonics and global heat loss mechanisms. The Dongwanzi ophiolite is one of the largest well-preserved greenstone belts in the Zunhua structural belt (part of the Central orogenic belt),that divides the North China craton into eastern and western blocks. More than I 000 other fragments of gabbro, pillow lava, sheeted dikes, harzburgite, and podifonn-chromite bearing dunite occur as tectonic blocks in a blotite- gneiss matrix in the Zunhua structural belt. The PI interprets these rocks as an Archean ophiolitic melange and recognize that some of the blocks preserve deeper levels of oceanic mantle than the Dongwanzi ophiolite. The PI and co-workers have designed a comprehensive series of studies to fully document the field, structural, geochronological, mineralogical, and chemical characteristics of this ophiolite and related melange. They will assess what these data mean in ten-ns of Archean crustal and mantle evolution, thermal state of the early Earth, and ideas about Precambrian plate tectonics. They regard this as an unsurpassed opportunity to evaluate fundamental properties of Archean crust and mantle, and to understand processes critical for evaluating Archean oceanic crustal and mantle evolution. Understanding Archean oceanic processes in the North China craton will provide a valuable contrast with similar processes recorded in younger ophiolites, indicating how mid-ocean ridge processes may have evolved from a period of high heat production to one of lower heat production. Detailed mapping will accurately delineate the extent, thickness, and relationships between individual units, which is important for understanding mechanisms of Archean sea floor spreading and heat loss. Structural analysis of mantle tectonites will reveal deformation conditions in the Archean oceanic mantle. U/Pb geochronology will be used to establish the age and duration of magmatism represented in the ophiolite and document the structural chronology by dating igneous dikes and plutons that intruded between different events, as deten-nined by mapping. Geochemical analyses will be aimed at determining relationships between the crustal and depleted mantle components of the ophiolite, and comparing these data with younger ophiolites from different tectonic settings, and also from Archean greenstone belts, some of which may include severely dismembered Archean ophiolite fragments. Analyses will include major, minor, trace, REE, and several isotopic systems (in collaboration with geochemists from several cooperating institutions)and will be used to assess crustal and mantle evolution. Archean oceanic lithospheric structure is likely to have been as complex and variable as that in the present-day plate mosaic. Documentation of the characteristics of the Dongwanzi ophiolite and related rocks may serve as the first reference column for Archean oceanic lithosphere, since it is the most complete Archean ophiolite known on the planet.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0207886</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kusky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kusky@eas.slu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/30/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Saint Louis University</Name>
      <CityName>St Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3149773925</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>221 N. Grand Blvd.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
