<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improved Security and Management of Underground Infrastructure Systems: Lessons Learned from September 11, 2001</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>36336</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Miriam Heller</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The collapse of the WTC Towers and destruction of surrounding buildings were accompanied by damage to underground water distribution, electric power, natural gas, steam, wastewater conveyance, telecommunication, and transportation systems. This research aims to investigate and model complex system response, involving underground facilities that are often taken for granted or overlooked in comprehensive emergency planning. Understanding and documenting how underground infrastructure performs during extreme events is a necessary step for increasing the resilience of urban utility and transportation networks. This research will strive to extend the knowledge gained to understand the interdependencies of underground infrastructure and improve their security in future extreme events. In addition to investigating integrated system response in New York, the research will compare the effects of intense localized damage at WTC with infrastructure system performance affected by distributed damage during major California earthquakes. Response during extreme events will be compared with the effects of previous severe accidents in New York. Three activities are involved: 1) data collection and interviews with system managers; 2) comparative analysis; and 3) methodology for assessing interdependencies. Some of this work has already begun. Deliverables include recommendations for developing a methodology to evaluate the damage, areas of greatest vulnerability, and the possibilities of cascading damage. Eventually, a methodology will be sought that adapts risk management techniques used in industrial process control to decision support systems for civil infrastructure managers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0207266</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arthur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lembo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ajlembo@salisbury.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>O'Rourke</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tdo1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/17/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
