<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Geometric and Algorithmic Techniques for Design and Verification of Hybrid Control Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>213123</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>D. Helen Gill</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Frazzoli - Branicky Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is aimed at the development of new tools and techniques for the design and analysis of high-confidence software for complex, distributed, reconfigurable aerospace embedded systems, and to transfer these methods to undergraduate and graduate students, other researchers, and industry. &lt;br/&gt;Problems of direct interest include those arising in the control and coordination of multiple autonomous air and space vehicles, and in the detection and resolution of conflicts in Air Traffic Control. The techniques developed in this project are also applicable to other systems which require similar levels of reliability and performance, such as highway traffic automation systems, health care systems, power networks, and&lt;br/&gt;financial services.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of this project is a better understanding of the interactions between real-time software and dynamical systems. This will lead to new and powerful tools and techniques for the design and analysis of embedded systems, as well as an improved approach to the requirement specification for real-time systems.&lt;br/&gt;The core of the research is aimed at dramatically reducing the complexity of embedded and hybrid systems design and verification by exploiting the geometric structure of the underlying physical system in the modelling effort, and by preserving this structure in the design of control laws and algorithms. This will make feasible the analysis of the complete system (including its physical and software components) by otherwise poorly scalable techniques such as abstract interpretation and model checking, and will provide&lt;br/&gt;the means for the effective use of techniques based on compositional reasoning. For example, group symmetries in vehicle dynamics give rise to families of equivalent controlled trajectories: such sets are called motion primitives for single vehicles, and motion coordination primitives for groups of vehicles. A maneuver automaton is a collection of a finite number of motion primitives. It provides a discrete model of the vehicle dynamics, which leads to a dramatic reduction of the complexity of describing and controlling the vehicle behavior, by providing a high level of abstraction, and at the same time providing invariants which ensure that the physical state remains within some known bounds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational part of the project is implemented through new course and curriculum development, and student mentoring. The main educational objective is to provide both undergraduate and graduate students with the knowledge and the skills to understand the key issues and to ensure technical leadership in the current and future aerospace information technology arenas. Finally, an interactive web site is being developed, where it is possible to access information and software developed in the research project and for the courses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0208919</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Branicky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>msb@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
