<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Minority Postdoctoral Research Fellowship for FY 2002</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Fellowship</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080305</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carter Kimsey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Minority Postdoctoral Research Fellowship for FY2002. The goal of the fellowship is to prepare minority scientists for positions of scientific leadership in academia and industry. To attain this goal, the fellowship provides opportunities for postdoctoral training of the highest quality to recent doctoral recipients. This program is an effort by the NSF to increase the number of research scientists from underrepresented minority groups, thereby contributing to the future vitality of the Nation's scientific enterprise. It is expected that Fellows trained through these fellowships will play important roles in training of the future workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research and training plan for this fellowship is entitled "Understanding how the TAR binding protein (TDP43) regulates alternative splicing of messenger RNA." Alternative splicing during mRNA processing greatly contributes to generate the protein diversity necessary for development and function of complex organisms. TDP43 regulates exon inclusion of the CFTR gene presumably through inteaction with nuclear proteins and specific sequences of nucleic acid. This research investigates the molecular determinants and importance of TDP43 protein complex formation and nucleic acid binding.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0208077</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Youhna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ayala</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>05/02/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ayala, Youhna M</Name>
      <CityName>Trieste 34100</CityName>
      <ZipCode></ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber></PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress></StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>Italy</CountryName>
      <StateName/>
      <StateCode></StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
