<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research in DAta in Your Space (DAYS)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>126000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research investigates a new architecture designed to provide&lt;br/&gt;data to wireless users using a broadcast technique. The objective of this research is to develop schemes for implementing the concept ``DAta in your space (DAYS)" which combines broadcasting (push) and traditional querying (pull) techniques into one global wireless approach. In this scheme the data broadcasters (special servers) will continuously&lt;br/&gt;broadcast (push) requested data to a set of ``dedicated" wireless&lt;br/&gt;channels, which will be captured by clients (users of the data) at&lt;br/&gt;any time and at any place. The space will thus be used as&lt;br/&gt;persistent storage for all mobile as well as static devices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A universal wireless broadcast approach requires that mobile users be able to find and use the right broadcast information. Some of the questions to mbe addressed include:&lt;br/&gt;1. How can the mobile user know which channel has the correct data?&lt;br/&gt;2. How is data to be assigned to channels?&lt;br/&gt;3. What techniques can be used to effectively determine the best contents of each channel given many mobile users?&lt;br/&gt;4. Without explicit user queries, how can the mobile user be assured that the needed data is being broadcast?&lt;br/&gt;5. How can the mobile user be assured that the needed data moves with&lt;br/&gt; him?&lt;br/&gt;These issues have to be examined on a global scale.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0208741</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mhd@lyle.smu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Southern Methodist University</Name>
      <CityName>Dallas</CityName>
      <ZipCode>752750302</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2147682030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6425 BOAZ</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
