<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Construction of BAC Libraries of Metazoans Occupying Key Phylogenetic Positions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven L. Klein</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Large-insert libraries of genomic DNA are a valuable resource for comparative studies in&lt;br/&gt;development evolution and genetics for addressing such fundamental questions in biology as&lt;br/&gt;how genomes have evolved and how evolution of genomes has resulted in evolution of body&lt;br/&gt;plans. The goal of the proposed research is to construct 11 BAC libraries representative of the&lt;br/&gt;breadth of the Metazoa. The focus is on animals that occupy phylogenetic positions key to an&lt;br/&gt;understanding of animal evolution. Preference is given to organisms with demonstrated potential&lt;br/&gt;as developmental model organisms. Therefore, 2 deuterostomes have been chosen: lamprey,&lt;br/&gt;basal in the craniates and pivotal for understanding the pattern of gene and chromosomal&lt;br/&gt;duplications during vertebrate evolution, and the cephalochordate amphioxus, the closest living&lt;br/&gt;invertebrate relative of the vertebrates. On the basis of molecular phylogenetics, the protostomes&lt;br/&gt;have recently been divided into two groups, the Ecdysozoa and the Lophotrochozoa. However,&lt;br/&gt;branching patterns of the phyla within each of these groups are poorly resolved. Because&lt;br/&gt;representatives of the Ecdysozoa, Drosophila and Caenorhabditis have been well-studied, we&lt;br/&gt;have not chosen any Ecdysozoan. For the Lophotrochozoa, which have, in general, received little&lt;br/&gt;attention in regard to genes, development and evolution, seven organisms have been chosen.&lt;br/&gt;These include 2 annelids, one of which, the polychaete Platynereis dumerilii, is relatively basal&lt;br/&gt;within the annelids and the other of which, the leech Helobdella robusta, is more highly derived.&lt;br/&gt;Platynereis is rapidly becoming a lophotrochozoan model developmental organism, and while&lt;br/&gt;the leech is quite derived, it has been the object of developmental genetic studies for some years.&lt;br/&gt;Two molluscs are included-- one bivalve, (Spisula solidissima) and one gastropod (Ilyanassa&lt;br/&gt;obsoleta). The other Lophotrochozoans include 1 nemertean (Cerebratulus lacteus), 1 sipunculid&lt;br/&gt;(Temiste langiformis), and 1 acoel flatworm (Neochildea fusca). The phylogenetic position of&lt;br/&gt;the acoels is controversial. On the basis of morphology, they were considered basal Bilateria.&lt;br/&gt;However, most, but not all, molecular phylogenetic analyses place acoels within the protostomes.&lt;br/&gt;To address bilaterian origins, we have chosen a ctenophore (Mnemiopsis leidyi). Finally, to&lt;br/&gt;address the origin of the metazoa, a sponge, Callyspongia diffusa, a representative of the most&lt;br/&gt;basal Metazoa, was selected. BAC libraries will be constructed and distributed by P. de Jong&lt;br/&gt;(Children's Hospital Research Institute, Oakland), who has a long track-record in construction of&lt;br/&gt;BAC libraries, including making the BAC library for the human genome project. For organisms&lt;br/&gt;for which interest is high to sequence the entire genome, 15X coverage is proposed. For others,&lt;br/&gt;10X coverage is proposed.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0208138</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Holland</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lzholland@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
      <CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
