<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Radiation of Teleseismic Body Waves from Dynamic Faults</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>57500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kaye Shedlock</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Thomas H. Heaton&lt;br/&gt;EAR-0208494&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is examining the effects of fault opacity (the tendency of reflected phases to be trapped in the hanging wall of the fault) on radiated energy by constructing models of P and SH body waves from shallow thrust fault earthquakes at teleseismic distances. Three-dimensional finite-element models are used to calculate rupture history assuming a variety of friction models. These slip histories are used to calculate the teleseismic body waves that results from the different friction models. Systematic differences are determined between these dynamic models and traditional dislocation models that are commonly used for determining seismic moments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main goal is to quantify how teleseismic P and SH body waves from dipping faults are affected by near-source interactions between the seismic waves and a dynamically slipping fault. It has been common practice to estimate seismic moments by modeling these teleseismic waveforms using double-couple source representations. In these models, the medium is modeled as an elastic continuum with displacement jumps caused by distributions of double-couple body forces. While these models satisfy all boundary conditions within a continuous medium, they are not necessarily compatible with the frictional stress boundary conditions on the slipping fault (a discontinuous medium). In particular, shear waves that reflect off of the Earth's surface are generally allowed to propagate back through the slipping fault without reflection; this is sometimes referred to as a transparent fault. There is a long-standing question about whether or not systematic errors in determining earthquake sizes have been introduced by using transparent fault models. This study should provide quantitative estimates of the importance of this effect.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0208494</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heaton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>heaton@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code/>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
