<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Genesis of the Western Slope of the Altiplano Plateau and Atacama Basin</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030103</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Fountain</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The common association of thrust belts with the slopes of the great mountain belts has resulted in the common assumption that topographic relief and surface shortening are intrinsically linked. For example, many of the world's great mountain belts are doubly vergent, with well-developed thrust belts facing away from the interior of the orogen. However, in some key cases, significant topographic relief has developed in the absence of major faulting. These orogenic scale monoclines and their along-strike discontinuities have the potential to elucidate crustal mechanical and rheological controls on continental orogenesis. An exceptional example of an orogenic-scale monocline occurs along the western border of the Altiplano-Puna plateau of the central Andes. Although climate, and in particular precipitation, has a strong influence on the morphology of a mountain belt, in this region the climatic input is minimized because it is one of the driest places on Earth. The profound lack of precipitation causes the landscape to evolve extremely slowly and extend the preservation potential of landforms and surfaces from the thousands of years typical of mountain belts into millions of years. Therefore, the western edge of the plateau's morphology reflects a nearly pure tectonic signal, making it the most logical starting point for studies aimed at improving our understanding of continental plateau formation and orogenesis. A chronologic framework for the Miocene to present uplift of the Andean monocline will be derived from investigation of: 1) the geometric relationships between strata accumulating in sedimentary basins at the toe of the monocline, and 2) estimations of the degree of rotation of stream paleo-gradients in a set of drainages which are deeply incised into the monocline surface. Paleo-gradients will be determined by correlation and high accuracy surveying of terrace surfaces preserved in stream valleys. Extensive volcanism and large-volume ignimbrite eruptions are well distributed throughout the Neogene rock record, so that existing chronologic constraints can be improved upon by identification and collection of volcanic material for dating. The Atacama and Tamarugal Basins are ideal field areas in which to conduct the stratigraphic research in both outcrop and seismic. Both basins lie at the foot of the monocline and are hydrologically closed. Therefore, they preserve complete Neogene depositional histories. The Atacama Basin contains an especially valuable record because it lies within the largest along-strike anomaly in the monocline. Determining if a genetic link exists between the basin and the deflection of the monocline (temporally and spatially) will be an important research focus, as it may yield insight into processes fundamental to plateau uplift. This study is extremely timely and has the potential to be an excellent contribution to the understanding of surface processes, orogenesis and plateau uplift. The outcomes of this work will advance the present state of knowledge concerning the causes of plateau uplift by testing whether monocline warping is synchronous with deformation on the opposite side of the orogen, as expressed in the Sub-Andean belt and Eastern Cordillera. It will also test the significance of large topographic anomalies in otherwise continuous mountain-fronts. This study will explore the feasibility of plateau-derived groundwater as a substantial factor in landform genesis. The results of this study will contain many parallels to research on the Tibetan Plateau, where performing similar studies would be hampered by exposure problems. This research will have educational and human resource impacts. At Cornell University, results from this study will become components of undergraduate courses in geomorphology, geophysics and basin analysis. All results will be cataloged in GIS software and available to the public via the internet. This research will also serve as thesis components for two Cornell graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0208130</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jordan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tej1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Isacks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bli1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
