<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Trusted Peer-To-Peer Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Karl Levitt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will develop techniques for trusted systems that can provide correct information and take correct actions when needed and where needed. The focus will be on peer-to-peer (P2P) systems, where computers or nodes operate autonomously, without any central control. In a P2P system, each node provides storage and compute resources. It connects to other neighbor nodes, and the community provides services like file sharing, document archiving, or data analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;P2P systems are especially well suited as the "backbone" of a trusted system because nodes operate independently, without reliance on particular network connections or on nodes with a fixed functionality. Thus, a P2P system can adapt to a changing environment, and with the proper mechanisms, can isolate or ignore malicious nodes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As part of the project, several important problems will be addressed such as: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Denial of Service (DoS): How does one protect against malicious sites that generate excess load to prevent others from receiving resources or service?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Searching: How does one efficiently find information without using centralized index facilities, and in a dynamically changing environment?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Information Authenticity: How does one verify the authenticity of documents or information?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Preservation: How does one preserve information past the lifetime of the originating node?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is high risk, but there is also the potential for a large payoff. The research is high risk because the problems faced are difficult: Building a trusted community out of building blocks that may be transient and malicious, is not an easy task. However, the only way to build a trusted system is, as proposed, by making as few assumptions as possible about the trustworthiness of its components. The techniques to be developed, if successful, will provide a solid foundation for building truly reliable, secure, and trusted systems for electronic commerce, military applications, healthcare, and many other applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0208683</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hector</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garcia-Molina</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hector@cs.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
