<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improving Sequence Proximity Search</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>185001</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gia-Loi Le Gruenwald</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Finding sequences similar to a given query sequence in a large data set&lt;br/&gt;is a fundamental problem in many database applications including&lt;br/&gt;computational genomics and proteomics, computational finance, audio, text&lt;br/&gt;and multimedia image processing. This proposal considers proximity search&lt;br/&gt;problems for strings and sequences in such applications where existing&lt;br/&gt;methods typically employ distance functions based on character edits only&lt;br/&gt;(commonly unweighted edit distance) and modify off-the shelf index&lt;br/&gt;structures to improve search efficiency. However, in many applications&lt;br/&gt;block edit operations such as translocations, deletions and copies, as well&lt;br/&gt;as linear transformations on strings are as common and important&lt;br/&gt;as character edits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Unfortunately, computation of distance measures that allow block edits&lt;br/&gt;are generally known to be NP-hard. Thus the investigators propose to work&lt;br/&gt;on practical methods for approximating the block edit distances and performing&lt;br/&gt;approximate searches under such measures. These measures are many times&lt;br/&gt;not symmetric (transforming a long sequence to a short one may be&lt;br/&gt;performed through a single deletion whereas transforming the short&lt;br/&gt;sequence to the long one may require many copy operations) or do not&lt;br/&gt;satisfy the triangular inequality (string space under edit operations is&lt;br/&gt;fundamentally different from Euclidean space) and thus do not provide a metric.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;However many of them can be proven to be almost-metrics, i.e.,&lt;br/&gt;the symmetry and/or the triangular inequalities may be satisfied within&lt;br/&gt;multiplicative constants. This property can be fundamental in sequence&lt;br/&gt;proximity search as it seems possible that known distance based indexing&lt;br/&gt;methods for metric spaces could be extended for use in almost-metric&lt;br/&gt;spaces. Thus a main component of the proposal is the investigation of&lt;br/&gt;the limitations and extendibility of distance based indexes for&lt;br/&gt;almost-metrics and other string/sequence measures which may be&lt;br/&gt;non-symmetric or fail to satisfy the triangular inequality because they&lt;br/&gt;allow block edits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An alternative/complementary approach to distance based indexing is based&lt;br/&gt;on approximate random mappings of the space of items to be searched to&lt;br/&gt;Euclidean spaces. This general strategy has received considerable&lt;br/&gt;attention in the context of vector spaces. The mappings used guarantee&lt;br/&gt;(with high probability) to reduce the number of comparisons during search&lt;br/&gt;from linear to poly-logarithmic, provided some error of approximation can&lt;br/&gt;be tolerated in the answers obtained. This approach was later generalized&lt;br/&gt;to sequence spaces through a mapping of sequences under block edit distance&lt;br/&gt;to binary strings under Hamming distance. The error tolerance is not&lt;br/&gt;very practical. Thus a second component of this proposal is to obtain&lt;br/&gt;novel mappings of sequence spaces to Euclidean spaces within smaller&lt;br/&gt;approximation errors. The goal is to generalize such mappings to both&lt;br/&gt;character and block based edit distances, especially those which assign&lt;br/&gt;weights to edit operations (that reflect the likeliness of that&lt;br/&gt;particular edit).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0209145</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Piotr</FirstName>
      <LastName>Indyk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>indyk@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Z. Meral</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ozsoyoglu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>meral@case.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>S. Cenk</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sahinalp</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cenk@cs.sfu.ca</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>03/05/2004</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
