<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>EXPLORATORY: Microrheology of Particulate Gels</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>155000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert M. Wellek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Understanding how interactions, microstructure and microscopic mechanics determine&lt;br/&gt;the macroscopic properties and responses of complex fluids is a fundamental problem that&lt;br/&gt;impacts materials processing and development, biology and medicine. For particulate gels&lt;br/&gt;that occur in the manufacture of ceramic parts, coatings, mineral recovery and lubricant&lt;br/&gt;degradation, we seek to understand the microscopic origins of viscoelastic, yield, and non-&lt;br/&gt;linear behavior that ultimately affects processing and final properties, such as the thermal&lt;br/&gt;and mass transport characteristics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research is to explore the use of direct microscopic manipulation&lt;br/&gt;and imaging to understand the relationship between microscopic and macroscopic properties&lt;br/&gt;in particulate gels. The PI will develop and employ new experimental tools based on optical&lt;br/&gt;micromanipulation and visualization, including optical trapping in combination with video,&lt;br/&gt;fluorescence, and confocal microscopies. Because the techniques will allow investigation of the&lt;br/&gt;basic, microscopic mechanisms of rheological and mechanical behavior by quantifying struc-&lt;br/&gt;tural rearrangements, stresses and interactions in situ, they are powerful complements to&lt;br/&gt;scattering and rheological methods used by other groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific research aims are:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Directly measure the micromechanical properties of models of the gel back-&lt;br/&gt;bone. To understand fundamental mechanisms of gel elasticity, shear and compressive&lt;br/&gt;yield behavior in particulate gels, the PI will develop optical trapping and microscopy tech-&lt;br/&gt;niques to measure the bending stiffness, frequency response, and relaxation timescales&lt;br/&gt;of model aggregates of the gel backbone. With videomicroscopy, the PI will characterize&lt;br/&gt;particle rearrangement mechanisms that are relevant to creep, yield and non-linear be-&lt;br/&gt;havior. The PI will systematically vary interparticle interactions, particle concentration,&lt;br/&gt;and polydispersity, and characterize surface heterogeneity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Measure the mechanical properties of flocs and floc- floc interfaces. Using&lt;br/&gt;the experimental techniques designed for measuring gel backbone properties, the PI will&lt;br/&gt;measure the frequency response and rupturing mechanics of flocs formed during the&lt;br/&gt;aggregation process. Concurrent videomicroscopy and optical trapping will enable the PI&lt;br/&gt;to characterize and correlate mechanics and structural rearrangements in flocs that give&lt;br/&gt;rise to strain-hardening in fractal colloidal gels. The PI will measure mechanics between&lt;br/&gt;flocs to distinguish the contribution of internal and floc- floc mechanics in the rheology&lt;br/&gt;of gels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3. Develop optical trapping and microscopy for dense, gelling suspensions.&lt;br/&gt;Establishing the relationship between individual aggregate mechanics, microrheology&lt;br/&gt;and rheology of particulate gels will require micromechanical measurements in bulk&lt;br/&gt;suspensions. The PI will develop the appropriate core-shell particles and experimental&lt;br/&gt;techniques to take advantage of simultaneous optical trapping and confocal microscopy&lt;br/&gt;in dense suspensions. This will enable the PI to directly visualize structure while inducing&lt;br/&gt;local deformation and stresses in the concentrated, bulk gel, ultimately providing a&lt;br/&gt;means of characterizing mechanisms of stress relaxation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0209936</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Furst</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>furst@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Delaware</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Delaware</StateName>
      <StateCode>DE</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
