<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Photodissociation Dynamics of Transient Species</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>578600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this project, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Reisler will undertake a detailed study of binary intermolecular interactions that range from weak covalent to van der Waals couplings. Systems to be studied include weakly bound dimers of free radicals, hydrogen-bonded dimers of ammonia with weak pi-acids, and adducts of strong Lewis acids and bases. Several techniques will be used: pair-correlated velocity and angular distributions of dissociation fragments and IR-UV excitation/detection; recently developed resolution and detection sensitivity schemes will be employed for images of the velocity and angular distributions of dissociation fragment; and REMPI and photoelectron spectroscopies will be applied to study the fragment properties. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project deals with the question of how molecules interact with one another. The results of such interactions depend on the strength of forces between the interaction partners. This research uses several experimental techniques to investigate the reaction dynamics for several select systems that exhibit different strengths of interactions. The research is directed to obtain detailed quantitative information of the behavior of interacting molecules and the results will bring about a better understanding of gas phase chemical reactions. The work will be conducted with students and postdoctoral research associates. An effective outreach program is part of this project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0209889</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hanna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reisler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reisler@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
