<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Testing Based on Hybrid System Models</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>D. Helen Gill</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lee, Insup&lt;br/&gt;CCR-0209024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many embedded systems are part of safety-critical applications, e.g.,&lt;br/&gt;avionics systems, manufacturing, automotive controllers, and medical&lt;br/&gt;devices. The safety-critical nature of embedded applications requires a higher&lt;br/&gt;level of robustness and reliability than is called for in conventional&lt;br/&gt;software systems development. In the attempt to insure a higher level of&lt;br/&gt;confidence in the design and implementation, current practice merely&lt;br/&gt;increases the duration, frequency, scope, etc. of traditional&lt;br/&gt;verification practices. The net result is substantially higher&lt;br/&gt;development costs and longer design cycles, leading to a design cycle&lt;br/&gt;where a verification bottleneck is impacting overall operational&lt;br/&gt;effectiveness, efficiency and safety. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to mitigate the verification bottleneck by identifying&lt;br/&gt;appropriate specification formalisms, and using those formalisms as a&lt;br/&gt;basis to develop fully automated techniques for verifying&lt;br/&gt;implementations using testing. An important distinguishing &lt;br/&gt;characteristic of the embedded applications listed earlier is the &lt;br/&gt;hybrid (discrete and continuous)nature of behaviors. The continuous &lt;br/&gt;components of embedded systems, and the large state&lt;br/&gt;spaces of all industrially relevant systems, make verification&lt;br/&gt;techniques based on exhaustive exploration of the state space&lt;br/&gt;intractable. Therefore, it is necessary to approach the verification&lt;br/&gt;problem with techniques based on sampling, i.e., testing. This requires &lt;br/&gt;abstracting the original system state space to&lt;br/&gt;create a condensed state space that can be explored to determine&lt;br/&gt;valuable points to sample. Methods of abstraction, methods for&lt;br/&gt;selecting test points, and methods for evaluating the relative merit&lt;br/&gt;of one set of test points vs. another are all issues addressed by this&lt;br/&gt;work. The research also explores the use of traditional&lt;br/&gt;notions of test coverage applied to formal specifications of hybrid&lt;br/&gt;systems. Test suites are generated using the counterexample or&lt;br/&gt;witness generation techniques of model checkers as well as random path&lt;br/&gt;generations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The practical issues of demonstrating the working techniques, and the&lt;br/&gt;efficacy of these techniques when applied to realistic systems, are&lt;br/&gt;addressed through the implementation of tools that automate all&lt;br/&gt;steps of the process: abstraction, test selection, test derivation,&lt;br/&gt;test application to concrete implementations, and the evaluation of&lt;br/&gt;test results. Tools are developed on top of the existing&lt;br/&gt;CHARON framework for creating hybrid system models.&lt;br/&gt;Case-study work based on real system specifications and&lt;br/&gt;benefit from interaction with practicing engineers working for Honeywell, a&lt;br/&gt;leader in the development of advanced avionics systems. One issue is how&lt;br/&gt;to integrate the techniques into development processes that conform &lt;br/&gt;to the DO-178B avionics certification process.&lt;br/&gt;Among the broader impacts that are anticipated from this work are (1)&lt;br/&gt;an increase in awareness of and actual use of formal methods by&lt;br/&gt;practicing developers, and (2) an acceleration of the safety-critical&lt;br/&gt;embedded system development process that will enable the creation of&lt;br/&gt;safer, more reliable systems with shorter development cycle times.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0209024</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Insup</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lee@cis.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oleg</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sokolsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sokolsky@cis.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
      <CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
      <ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
