<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Test-bed Facility for Research in Video Database Benchmarking</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>134998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frank Olken</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will create a comprehensive test-bed facility to support research in video database management. Real-world video applications demand database technology that is capable of providing real-time content-based query and retrieval for stored digital video. However, video is a complex data type that requires a significant amount of preprocessing for content representation before research issues in database management for real-time video data can be addressed. This project will facilitate video database research by abstracting video as a fundamental and fully functional database data type. Tools for video content analysis, feature extraction and high-dimensional indexing will be integrated into the test-bed facility, which will then be used to address several research challenges in the management of real-time streamed video data, including multi-feature nearest neighbor queries, feature-based query processing, video operators, buffer management for streaming video, and continuous video streaming with real-time constraints. The system will provide standardized methods for integrating components and measuring their performance, and will be furnished with a large collection of indexed videos. The underlying database management system, video-processing tools, and video data will form a complete environment for the video database research community, providing an effective platform for implementation, validation and evaluation of new video database technology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0209120</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arif</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghafoor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ghafoor@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ahmed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elmagarmid</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ake@cs.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Walid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Aref</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aref@cs.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Purdue University</Name>
      <CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
      <ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
