<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>QEIB: Stochastic Nonlinear Population Dynamics: Mathematical Models, Biological Experiments, and Data Analyses</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael H. Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Cushing&lt;br/&gt;0210474&lt;br/&gt; The project entails a theoretical and experimental study&lt;br/&gt;that examines nonlinear population dynamics phenomena in the&lt;br/&gt;context of stochasticity and that addresses fundamental concepts&lt;br/&gt;of how stochastic and nonlinear forces combine to produce&lt;br/&gt;observed population phenomena. The methodology involves an&lt;br/&gt;interdisciplinary effort that features a thorough integration of&lt;br/&gt;biologically based modeling (deterministic and stochastic),&lt;br/&gt;mathematical and numerical analyses of model dynamics, and the&lt;br/&gt;derivation and application of statistical techniques for&lt;br/&gt;connecting models with data (including parameter estimation and&lt;br/&gt;model evaluation). The investigators study the fundamental&lt;br/&gt;question about how (demographic) stochasticity at the individual&lt;br/&gt;level propagates to the population level. A promising class of&lt;br/&gt;models that incorporates both demographic and environmental&lt;br/&gt;stochasticity is pursued. A variety of statistical and&lt;br/&gt;mathematical questions that arise from these studies are&lt;br/&gt;investigated. The validity of this modeling methodology and&lt;br/&gt;accuracy of a priori model predictions is directly testable by&lt;br/&gt;experiments. The project study includes an experimental test of&lt;br/&gt;this modeling approach to demographic and environmental&lt;br/&gt;stochasticity, using a laboratory model that the investigators&lt;br/&gt;have successfully used in a wide variety of population dynamics&lt;br/&gt;and modeling studies during the last decade. The modeling&lt;br/&gt;methodology is also applicable to field populations and the&lt;br/&gt;investigators pursue the development of field studies with&lt;br/&gt;several researchers who have expressed interest in such a&lt;br/&gt;collaboration. These collaborators include colleagues at (1) the&lt;br/&gt;Center for Environmental Analysis at California State University,&lt;br/&gt;Los Angeles in a project modeling the spatially structured&lt;br/&gt;dynamics of seashore species, (2) the University of California,&lt;br/&gt;Davis in a project to model a lupine-caterpillar-nematode system,&lt;br/&gt;(3) Andrews University on mathematical/statistical models of the&lt;br/&gt;distribution of marine birds and mammals on Protection Island&lt;br/&gt;National Wildlife Refuge in the Strait of Juan de Fuca, and (4)&lt;br/&gt;the Virginia Institute of Marine Science on nonlinear models of&lt;br/&gt;the blue crab in the Exuma Cays.&lt;br/&gt; An understanding of the dynamics of biological populations&lt;br/&gt;is fundamental to the understanding of ecological and&lt;br/&gt;environmental problems. Mathematical models can be a valuable&lt;br/&gt;tool that provides this understanding. They can also provide the&lt;br/&gt;means to predict the future of ecosystems and the species that&lt;br/&gt;they include. An accurate descriptive and predictive capability&lt;br/&gt;gained through mathematical models provides not only a basic&lt;br/&gt;understanding of ecological problems, but also the ability to&lt;br/&gt;design programs for the assessment, management, and control of&lt;br/&gt;ecosystems and for the solution of environmental problems. A&lt;br/&gt;fundamental difficulty in the application of mathematical models&lt;br/&gt;to ecological problems has been the lack of a close connection of&lt;br/&gt;models with biological data. A key problem is the ability of&lt;br/&gt;models to incorporate random effects and disturbances. The&lt;br/&gt;investigators extend, analyze, and apply a modeling methodology&lt;br/&gt;they have developed during a decade of experimental studies, in a&lt;br/&gt;controlled laboratory setting, that addresses these difficulties.&lt;br/&gt;The methods are not restricted to laboratory populations,&lt;br/&gt;however, and the project also includes collaborations with new&lt;br/&gt;colleagues for the purpose of applying the methods to field&lt;br/&gt;studies of natural populations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0210474</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Costantino</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rfc@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cushing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cushing@math.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dennis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brian@uidaho.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Desharnais</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rdeshar@calstatela.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shandelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Henson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>henson@andrews.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
