<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR: Synthesis and Characterization of a Light-Driven Molecular Motor</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1170000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Nanoscale Interdisciplinary Research Team (NIRT) award to University of Nevada Reno is supported by Divisions of Chemistry (MPS), Physics (MPS) and Electronic and Communications Systems (ENG), and this proposal was submitted in response to the solicitation "Nanoscale Science and Engineering" (NSF 01-157). With this award, Professor Frederick and his team will synthesize a molecular motor that exhibits unidirectional rotary motion upon light absorption. The motor consists of a rotor chromophore geared into a chiral "ratchet" base. The base and rotor can be functionalized for incorporation into a variety of nanostructures. Motor operation will be modeled by molecular dynamics calculations, and its actuation and positional control will be measured experimentally using polarized light when the motor is immobilized on a surface. The motor also will be incorporated into biopolymers, such as DNA, and measuring light-induced conformational changes will test motor functions. The results of modeling and experimental testing will be used to optimize the molecular design. This motor potentially offers unprecedented positional and temporal control, as well as high rotary speed. Students will learn and do research in molecular design and synthesis, surface immobilization and characterization, polarized laser excitation and fluorescence microscopy, biopolymer techniques, and large molecule dynamics calculations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, a team of research scientists with expertise in organic synthesis, molecular spectroscopy, biophysics, and molecular modeling and dynamics will design, construct, and test a molecule-sized motor, capable of converting light energy into directed mechanical energy. Polarized laser light will be used to drive the motor, potentially offering precise positional control and extremely high rotary speeds. The motor will also be incorporated into large biomolecules, such as DNA, to control their shape and function. Students working on the project will receive advanced training in molecular design and synthesis, laser spectroscopy and microscopy, computer modeling, and molecular biology. Potential applications of these molecular motors include light-controllable drugs, molecule-sized switches and pumps, and friction-free materials, as well as engines and propellers for nano-machines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0210549</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>twb@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cremo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cremo@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Frederick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhf@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cline</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cline@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1248</Code>
      <Text>PHYSICS-OTHER</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1517</Code>
      <Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1674</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1674</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1767</Code>
      <Text>Nanoscale Research-for PHY use only</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7202</Code>
      <Text>NANO - CHEM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9107</Code>
      <Text>BIOELECTRONICS AND BIONETWORKS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
