<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Assessing the Accuracy of Self-reported Pollution Data</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>83032</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Information provision is increasingly used as a regulatory tool. The &lt;br/&gt;Environmental Protection Agency's Toxics Release Inventory (TRI) program &lt;br/&gt;requires manufacturing facilities that handle threshold amounts of specific &lt;br/&gt;chemicals to report yearly their releases and transfers of these toxic &lt;br/&gt;substances. This project investigates how accurate TRI data are and what &lt;br/&gt;factors give rise to errors or evasion in self-reporting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research uses two different methods to assess the accuracy &lt;br/&gt;of TRI data. For 12 of the chemicals covered by TRI reporting, the EPA samples &lt;br/&gt;air concentrations of these chemicals using a network of monitors across the &lt;br/&gt;country. Geographic information systems (GIS) software allow one to determine &lt;br/&gt;which polluting facilities are within range of the EPA's monitors. The &lt;br/&gt;researchers can thus compare how measured trends in pollution from monitoring &lt;br/&gt;data match self-reported trends on air releases by the polluting facilities. To &lt;br/&gt;investigate potential divergences between the monitoring data and TRI figures, &lt;br/&gt;the analysis will also explore how the nature of the surrounding community, &lt;br/&gt;state environmental enforcement, and company and facility-level characteristics &lt;br/&gt;affect the apparent accuracy of the reported TRI air emissions. The comparison &lt;br/&gt;of reported TRI figures with expected distributions of emissions digits offers &lt;br/&gt;a second way to assess the accuracy of pollution data. The key insight is that &lt;br/&gt;if facilities are estimating emissions with a downward bias, the overall &lt;br/&gt;distribution of digits will not follow the same pattern as the actual digits in &lt;br/&gt;the monitor data. This research will demonstrate the degree that selected &lt;br/&gt;physical monitoring and analysis of data patterns for statistical bias can help &lt;br/&gt;determine the accuracy of self-reported data.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0210069</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hamilton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jayth@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>de Marchi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>demarchi@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
