<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NER: Focused Ion Beam (FIB) Micromachining and Advanced Characterization of Carbon Nanotube-Metal Junctions</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>96436</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Lyons</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project was received in response to Nanoscale Science and Engineering initiative, NSF 01-157, category NER. The goal of the research is to develop the methodology of localized atomic-level structural and chemical interfacial characterization of carbon nanotube-metal junctions using high resolution transmission electron microscopy (TEM), electron energy loss spectroscopy and energy filtered TEM. The Focused Ion Beam micromachining will be used to fabricate platinum metal contacts onto carbon nanotubes (CNTs), and also for localized specimen cross-sectioning for further TEM analysis. The objectives of the study are threefold: (1) advancement of nanoscale characterization techniques to achieve an understanding of the effects of FIB-assisted metal deposition on the CNT/Pt interfacial structure and chemistry at atomic level; (2) development of a specimen preparation technique for selective (localized) high-resolution TEM and electron energy loss spectroscopy of CNT-metal junctions; (3) development of reproducible metal contact fabrication technique with atomic-level control of inter-diffusion and morphology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will advance the nanoobject/metal junction studies to the atomic-level of understanding of the interfacial structure and chemistry. Development of optimized methodology of CNT/metal localized cross-sectioning technique for high-resolution chemical and structural analysis of the junction will be useful for studies of the majority of nanoscale objects and future nano-devices. Controlled nano-fabrication of CNT/metal junctions with known properties will facilitate the reliable electrical testing of the nanosized materials and structures for variety of applications ranging from chemical sensors to field effect transistors, thus enabling fabrication of new devices to serve people in their everyday life. Two graduate student will be directly involved in the program gaining knowledge in such advanced characterization techniques as transmission electron microscopy, electron energy loss spectroscopy, and FIB micromashining. The expertise generated by this program will be utilized directly in the educational process to teach the current and future scientists/technologists. The PI will organize and carry out scientific seminars, will incorporate new data into the graduate level courses to facilitate the dissemination of knowledge and the developed methodology.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0210249</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katharine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dovidenko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kdovidenko@uamail.albany.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>11/29/2005</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kdunn@sunypoly.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/30/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
      <CityName>Albany</CityName>
      <ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5184374550</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
