<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Moderate and High Resolution Spectroscopy of Reactive Chemical Intermediates</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>733655</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090004</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In his project, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Miller will conduct spectroscopic detection and characterization experiments on reactive chemical intermediates. The methods used are medium resolution, vibronically resolved and high resolution, rotationally resolved spectroscopy, based on laser-induced fluorescence (LIF) and cavity ringdown spectroscopy (CRDS) techniques. The systems under investigation are alkyl peroxy radicals discovered by the principal investigator during the previous grant cycle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Chemical reactions proceed from initial reactants to the reaction products usually along one of several possible reaction pathways. The reaction intermediates are generally characterized by different short lifetimes. Knowledge of these reaction intermediates, the relative likelihood of their occurrence and their lifetimes plays an important role in predicting the flow of chemical reactions. The systems chosen for investigation are important to the chemistry of the atmosphere, some industrial process, and to our general understanding of reactive molecules. This research is designed to detect and characterize such intermediates. Students and postdoctoral research associates participate in this research. They thereby acquire important knowledge and skills in preparation for entry into the scientific/technological workforce. &lt;br/&gt;In his project, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Miller will conduct spectroscopic detection and characterization experiments on reactive chemical intermediates. The methods used are medium resolution, vibronically resolved and high resolution, rotationally resolved spectroscopy, based on laser-induced fluorescence (LIF) and cavity ringdown spectroscopy (CRDS) techniques. The systems under investigation are alkyl peroxy radicals discovered by the principal investigator during the previous grant cycle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Chemical reactions proceed from initial reactants to the reaction products usually along one of several possible reaction pathways. The reaction intermediates are generally characterized by different short lifetimes. Knowledge of these reaction intermediates, the relative likelihood of their occurrence and their lifetimes plays an important role in predicting the flow of chemical reactions. This research is designed to detect and characterize such intermediates. Students and postdoctoral research associates participate in this research. They thereby acquire important knowledge and skills in preparation for entry into the scientific/technological workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0211281</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tamiller+@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6142923732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
