<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Isomerizations of Isotopically Labeled Hydrocarbons</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090003</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With the support of the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program, Professor John E. Baldwin, of the Department of Chemistry at Syracuse University, is studying isomerization reactions of isotopically labeled hydrocarbons. Professor Baldwin is establishing the relative importance of one-center and two-center epimerizations in spiropentanes and cyclopropanes and obtaining the first experimental measures of secondary deuterium kinetic isotope effects on these stereomutations. In addition, he is exploring a number of other fundamental hydrocarbon isomerizations, including the conversion of cyclopropane to propylene via 1-propylidene, [1,3]-carbon shifts, [1,5]-hydrogen shifts, interconversion of bicyclo[5.1.0]octa-2,4-dienes via intermediate bicyclo[4.1.1]octa-2,4-dienes, and "carbo-Claisen" rearrangements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Thermal reactions of small hydrocarbon molecules play key roles both in fundamental organic reaction chemistry and in large-scale petrochemical processes such as hydrocarbon reforming. Professor John E. Baldwin, of the Department of Chemistry at Syracuse University, is studying the thermal transformations of a variety of small molecules. By incorporating stable isotopes, Professor Baldwin is able to obtain a comprehensive view of these transformations, obtaining insights into the reaction mechanisms which will ultimately lead to a fundamental understanding of how thermal reactions characteristic of simple organic chemicals occur.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0211120</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baldwin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbaldwin@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Syracuse University</Name>
      <CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
