<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Effects of Species Composition and Environmental Context on Redundancy Within a Functional Group: A Test With Freshwater Mussels</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>279785</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Alan James Tessier</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Species that are believed to play the same functional role in ecosystems are often placed in&lt;br/&gt;functional groups, types or guilds, and redundancy of ecological function is predicted to be highest&lt;br/&gt;within such groups. The concept of functional groups composed of interchangeable, redundant&lt;br/&gt;species is appealing because it simplifies the study and management of ecological systems.&lt;br/&gt;However, there are problems limiting the applicability of this concept. The degree of redundancy&lt;br/&gt;among species assigned to many functional groups or guilds is unknown and we do not understand&lt;br/&gt;the degree to which the functional roles of species change with environmental context. The vast&lt;br/&gt;majority of our knowledge of species roles and how they are influenced by the environment comes&lt;br/&gt;from studies of short-lived, terrestrial plants. We now need to broaden our understanding of&lt;br/&gt;species roles in other equally important systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Freshwater systems, and streams in particular, are losing biodiversity at a higher rate than&lt;br/&gt;terrestrial or marine systems, but few studies have examined functional redundancy in these&lt;br/&gt;systems. Freshwater mussels are a functional group of long-lived, benthic, burrowing filter-feeders&lt;br/&gt;that are thought to play an important role in stream ecosystem function. Within this functional&lt;br/&gt;group, the potential for redundancy in ecological roles should be high because species have similar&lt;br/&gt;life histories, typically occur as speciose assemblages, and there is little evidence for differences&lt;br/&gt;in microhabitat or resource preferences between species. However, we have almost no quantitative&lt;br/&gt;information on either the overall importance of mussel assemblages to stream function or the roles&lt;br/&gt;of individual species. In recent years, many mussel populations have undergone a drastic decline.&lt;br/&gt;In order to predict how this loss of both species and overall mussel biomass will impact stream&lt;br/&gt;ecosystems, we must quantify the effects of both overall mussel abundance and individual species&lt;br/&gt;on ecosystem processes, and we must understand how these relationships may change with&lt;br/&gt;environmental conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will address the following questions: (1) What is the overall importance of&lt;br/&gt;the mussel functional group to stream ecosystems? What ecological processes do mussels&lt;br/&gt;perform in streams? How do these processes relate to overall mussel abundance/biomass? (2)&lt;br/&gt;Are species within the mussel functional group ecologically redundant? Do mussel species vary&lt;br/&gt;in their performance of ecological processes? Do ecological effects of mussel species within an&lt;br/&gt;assemblage vary based on species composition and/or abundance? (3) How are the overall&lt;br/&gt;importance of the mussel functional group and effects of species roles within the group influenced&lt;br/&gt;by environmental context? Are the ecological effects of the overall mussel assemblage and of&lt;br/&gt;individual species constant or do they change with environmental conditions? A series of&lt;br/&gt;complementary laboratory stream and field enclosure experiments will measure the ecological&lt;br/&gt;function of single and multi-species assemblages of mussels under varying abundance and&lt;br/&gt;environmental conditions. Laboratory stream experiments will focus on ecological processes&lt;br/&gt;performed by mussels (eg. filtering rates, nutrient excretion) and field enclosure experiments will&lt;br/&gt;examine the effects of mussels on the rest of the benthic community. Small-scale laboratory&lt;br/&gt;experiments and analyses will quantify the potential contributions (eg. nutrient excretion and&lt;br/&gt;biodeposition rates) of different mussel species to streams under differing conditions, and&lt;br/&gt;mechanisms underlying differences in ecological function between species (eg. gill morphology,&lt;br/&gt;behavior). Finally, experimental results will be combined with quantitative information from an NSF-funded mussel biodiversity inventory to make predictions about mussel functional role and&lt;br/&gt;redundancy in different stream systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0211010</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Caryn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vaughn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cvaughn@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/24/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
      <CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510301</Code>
      <Name>Structure &amp; Function</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
