<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>LTREB: Long-term Research in Environmental Biology: Microevolution in the Fast Lane</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>57608</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08010208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Saran Twombly</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0211391&lt;br/&gt;Bell&lt;br/&gt;LTREB&lt;br/&gt;Integrating pattern and process has always been a crucial but frustrating objective for&lt;br/&gt;evolutionary biology. Analysis of rapid evolution in extant populations provides a unique means&lt;br/&gt;to integrate evolutionary pattern and process. To that end, annual samples from the Loberg Lake,&lt;br/&gt;Alaska population of threespine stickleback fish, Gasterosteus aculeatus, will be used to study&lt;br/&gt;rapid evolution. This population was founded by a natural invasion of anadromous (i.e., sea run)&lt;br/&gt;stickleback after the native stickleback population was exterminated in 1982. It has been&lt;br/&gt;sampled annually since 1990, and lateral plate phenotypes have been scored in all samples.&lt;br/&gt;Lateral plates are modified scales that form a single row of armor on each side of the body.&lt;br/&gt;Lateral plate morphs (i.e., complete, partial, low) and low morph-plate number are heritable,&lt;br/&gt;subject to strong natural selection, and exhibit extensive adaptive geographic variation in western&lt;br/&gt;North America. &lt;br/&gt;This study will document maximum evolutionary rates, the trajectory of evolutionary&lt;br/&gt;change, and patterns of transient polymorphism. These patterns can be integrated with known&lt;br/&gt;evolutionary mechanisms. The increasing frequency of low morphs and their declining mean&lt;br/&gt;plate number can be explained by natural selection in many similar populations. Based on the plate phenotypes of the original Loberg Lake stickleback population before it was exterminated and comparison to other lake stickleback populations, lateral plate&lt;br/&gt;divergence should continue in the Loberg Lake population until the low morph is fixed and mean&lt;br/&gt;plate number declines to about five per side. This LTREB award will support continued annual sampling of the Loberg Lake population.&lt;br/&gt;This study will provide an unusually detailed account of rapid phenotypic evolution with implications for divergence during speciation and post-glacial adaptive radiation of threespine stickleback. It will complement ongoing research in paleontology, functional morphology, natural selection, genetics, phylogeogaphy, and developmental evolutionary biology of G. aculeatus. It will prolong a long series of annual samples in which rapid evolution of plates and other traits and trait correlations can be studied.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0211391</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael.bell@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0312000</Code>
      <Name>Population</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1174</Code>
      <Text>POPULATION DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1196</Code>
      <Text>LONG-TERM RSCH IN ENVIR BIO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1306</Code>
      <Text>ECOLOGICAL RATES OF CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1355</Code>
      <Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
