<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Molecular Analysis of Drosophila Neurotransmission in a Reconstituted Fusion System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>501601</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Martha Flanders</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Nerve cells, or neurons, communicate and relay signals by the regulated release of chemicals called neurotransmitters. This extremely complex process is tightly regulated and is required for all movement as well as higher brain functions such as learning and memory. One method to study such a complicated process is to carefully dissect the problem into smaller units and gain a better understanding of the component parts. The final step in the release of neurotransmitter is the merger of the membrane bound sac that contains these chemicals with the cell membrane, the barrier that separates the nerve cell from its environment. The consequence of this membrane fusion event is the release of neurotransmitter to the space between neurons, resulting in communication between these cells. We seek to understand the structural and functional basis of this membrane fusion event. The process of membrane fusion can be further subdivided into discrete steps. Many of the molecular components that drive the fusion process have been identified, but the precise way they interact to perform their role is not well understood. The objectives of this work are to identify the specific interactions that determine the spatial and temporal coordination of neurotransmission in a defined system. We will develop a synthetic fusion system to model neurosecretion using only the minimal components, specifically pure phospholipids and fusion proteins from the fruitfly Drosophila melanogaster. Neuronal fusion proteins, called SNAREs, will be produced in bacteria and incorporated into synthetic phospholipid vesicles. A detailed molecular analysis of the protein-protein interaction affect SNARE function will be studied. In addition, the role of regulatory factors will be analyzed. This assay will provide a unique window into the way in which cells fuse biological membranes. The ability to study these proteins in their native context of a phospholipid bilayer will be a major step toward a better understanding of their critical physiological role.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0212605</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>McNew</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcnew@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
