<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>RUI: Developmental and Cognitive Constraints on Birdsong Learning</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>261251</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John A. Byers</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>RUI: Developmental and Cognitive Constraints on Birdsong Learning&lt;br/&gt;Richard F. Braaten, Colgate University, PI&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Animals are constrained in the kinds of things that they are most likely to learn. For example, humans and other primates easily learn to fear snakes and other predators of their evolutionary ancestors, but do not so easily learn to fear some other objects, even when they are clearly associated with danger. As another example, rodents and other mammals are more likely to learn about the association between the taste of food and subsequent illness than about other characteristics of the feeding experience. Birdsong learning is a particularly interesting example of constrained learning because it is constrained in two ways. First, songbirds are more likely to learn the song of their species than the songs of other species, even under experimental conditions in which the amount of song exposure is equated. Second, like human language learning, in which languages are learned more effectively early in life, birdsong learning is also temporally constrained. Songbirds are much more likely to learn songs presented during a specialized early period of development, the sensitive period. This project attempts to better understand the role that cognitive processes such as attention, perception, and memory may play in constraints on song learning in birds, and also how the role of these cognitive processes may change with development. For example, do birds learn the songs of their own species because those songs are particularly memorable? Are they especially memorable during the sensitive period of song learning? To answer these questions, zebra finches will learn to make responses to particular songs to receive food reward. Birds will later be tested for their memory of both their own and other species' songs. In order to study possible developmental changes in memory, zebra finches will be tested during and after the sensitive period for song learning, at 30 and 90 days. Effects of early experience will also be evaluated by testing 30-day-old birds raised in acoustic isolation from zebra finch song. Similar experiments will be done that will assess developmental changes in attention, perception, and categorization of the songs of zebra finches and other species.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this research are two-fold. An understanding of the cognitive processes involved in constraints on song learning may help to better understand constraints on learning in general. Song learning in birds has many parallels with human speech development, including the existence of sensitive periods, and the presumed involvement of attentional, perceptual, and memory processes in human speech learning. The second broader impact of this work derives from it being carried out in an undergraduate institution. Concepts and experiments from this proposal will be integrated into all levels of the undergraduate curriculum. Undergraduates will be involved in the research both during the academic year, and as part of a special summer research program at Colgate University.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0212393</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Braaten</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rbraaten@mail.colgate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colgate University</Name>
      <CityName>Hamilton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>133461398</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3152287451</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>13 Oak Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
