<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Materials Research Science and Engineering Center: Center for Nanostructured Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>8181825</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070001</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary E. Galvin-Donoghue</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Materials Research Science and Engineering Center (MRSEC) at Columbia University investigates ways of forming films containing complex metal oxide nanoparticles and the properties of these films through an interdisciplinary and collaborative effort. The Center is composed of a single interdisciplinary research group (IRG). The focus of the IRG research is the materials chemistry of oxide nanoparticle systems, and includes nanoparticle synthesis, assembly, and diagnostics. The Columbia MRSEC links thirteen faculty members from five departments on campus with other faculty at City College of New York, and with fourteen collaborators in industry and at national laboratories. The MRSEC maintains shared experimental facilities that meet the needs of the Center research and serve for the training of students. Education outreach efforts of the MRSEC include a summer research experience for undergraduates and for high school teachers, and an extensive visitation program to high and middle schools in New York City that brings materials demonstrations to teachers and students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participants in the Center currently include 13 senior investigators, 3 postdoctoral associates, 8 graduate students, 10 undergraduate students and 1 support personnel. Professor Irving P. Herman directs the MRSEC.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0213574</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Irving</FirstName>
      <LastName>Herman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>iph1@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
