<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Hormonal Control of an Avian Neuromuscular System</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>354635</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Hormonal control of behavior extends to physically complex courtship displays in many bird species, but is not well understood. In a tropical bird of Panama, the golden-collared manakin, the males execute characteristic loud wingsnaps as part of a courtship dance. The males have three wing muscles that differ from those in females in size and/or biochemical composition, and there are motor neurons in the spinal cord that show more molecular receptors for androgenic sex steroid hormones than in females, suggesting that manakins are useful models for evaluating steroid control of complex peripheral neuromuscular systems. This project integrates molecular biology, biochemistry, anatomy and behavioral work to determine how hormones seasonally regulate this behavior in this sexually dimorphic system. Gene expression and metabolic enzyme activity provide data on distributions of steroid hormones and their receptors, and for comparisons between male and female spinal cords. Determining which particular muscles are involved in the wingsnap allows determining how sexual dimorphism of the muscles and the androgen-sensitive motoneurons in the spinal cord are relevant to the behavior. Use of androgen-blocking agents tests whether seasonally fluctuating androgens may cause changes across the breeding and non-breeding seasons in the anatomy and physiology of the spinal cord and muscles. Results from this work will provide important information on how steroid hormones act on this peripheral neuromuscular system to control behavior.&lt;br/&gt; The impact of this work extends beyond neuroendocrinology to reproductive physiology and evolutionary biology, and may have use in bird breeding. This project also involves excellent opportunities for student training and an important international component with Panama.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0213194</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barney</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schlinger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schlinge@lifesci.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
