<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Ultra-Broadband Ferrite Circulators/Isolators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Winslow L. Sargeant</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project addresses the development of Innovative Ultra-Broadband Ferrite Circulators/Isolators providing a transmission bandwidth broader than a 10:1 frequency ratio. A traditional circulator junction utilizing a single ferrite material results in a 3:1 bandwidth. A non-traditional stripline junction circulator for which the transmission band extends from 1.6 to 16 GHz has been designed and fabricated. This circulator design involves 3 different kinds of ferrite materials to be packed as tiles to form a composite junction. Even broader bandwidth has also been theoretically predicted, if more ferrite materials are used to compose the junction, rendering a bandwidth covering from 1 to 20 GHz. Researches on broadband transformer circuits are thus proposed, allowing for 50 S impedance to be realized with the input/output ports accompanying the operation of the broadband circulator/isolator junctions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed innovative circulators/isolators can be used as universal instruments under broadband considerations. For example, it can be used in measurements requiring interband operation, such as encountered in a Network Analyzer performing scattering parameter measurements. In radiometry applications it allows for narrow-width electromagnetic pulses to&lt;br/&gt;be used with monostatic radars. Multiple radars operating at distinctive frequency bands can be combined to share a common antenna aperture so as to reduce overall radar cross section.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0213210</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hoton</FirstName>
      <LastName>How</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hhow@ferrosi.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>HOTECH INC</Name>
      <CityName>BELMONT</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024782648</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6174848444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>262 CLIFTON ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
