<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthesis and Characterization of Open Framework Materials from Semiconducting Nanoclusters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>385050</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph L. Templeton</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Advanced Materials Program in the Chemistry Division makes this award to University of California Riverside to develop novel open framework chalcogenide materials to advance new synthetic and structural concepts, and to better understand self-assembly processes and host-guest interactions. With this award, Professor Feng will study interactions between organic molecules and the semiconductor nanocrystal precursors to generate larger clusters, and to organize these clusters with controlled surface properties into 3-dimensional ordered frameworks. Properties of these clusters and their 3-D assemblies will be controlled by changing the composition and interactions between their inorganic and organic components. The synthesis of larger nanocrystals may lead to better understanding of material transition between molecules and colloidal nanocrystals, which in turn will help to control nucleation and growth processes in the synthesis of semiconductor materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research studies will be carried out in the synthesis and characterization of semiconductor nanoclusters and 3-dimensional ordered frameworks to enhance the understanding of nanocrystal synthesis and assembly of semiconductor materials, which will have potential applications in magnetic and electrooptic devices. Instructional and research training in solid state and materials chemistry will be provided to graduate and undergraduate students with this award.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0213310</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pingyun</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pingyun.feng@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
      <CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>925211000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
