<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Novel Microsphere Biomaterials for Genomics and Industry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Om P. Sahai</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0214808&lt;br/&gt;Pegg&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I Project proposes to develop novel biomaterial-based microparticles called Sphericules. These microparticles are self-contained micrometer-scale reactors capable of performing genetic analysis without expensive instruments. The new composite beads, with temperature stability, solvent resistance, controlled buoyancy and other properties, will find applications in many diverse markets. The Sphericule methodology combines layers of natural and synthetic polymers, metals, ceramics and other chemicals to produce new composite beads, fibers and coatings. In contrast, multifunctional latex beads using a surface coating of antibody on a micron sized fluorescent particle are labor intensive to produce. Particle batch processing results in aggregation, uneven surface treatment, and loss of signal molecules. This Phase I project proposes a novel method for synthesizing uniform particles using micro-scale systems in a continuous process. In this process, the chemistries of bead formation, optical reagent incorporation and surface modifications are expected to be straightforward, stoichiometric and predictable. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial applications of this project are in the areas of biomedicalresearch, diagnostics, electronics, and defense.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0214808</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pegg</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rpegg@fscj.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NUCLEIC ASSAYS CORPORATION</Name>
      <CityName>FERNANDINA BEACH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>320345252</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9042619039</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2432 LYNNDALE RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510402</Code>
      <Name>Biomaterials-Short &amp; Long Terms</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
