<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: Genetic Engineering of Maize for Increased Tolerance to Heat Stress</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99990</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Om P. Sahai</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Research (STTR) Phase 1 Project proposes to develop transgenic maize (Zea mays L.) with increased tolerance to heat stress. It has recently discovered that a gene encoding the maize chloroplast protein synthesis elongation factor, EF-Tu, plays a role in the development of heat tolerance. EF-Tu protects other proteins from heat-induced inactivation and aggregation. The overall goal of this project is to genetically engineer maize that overproduces EF-Tu under high temperature conditions and to exploit the protective role that EF-Tu plays in heat tolerance. The key objectives of the Phase 1 research include (a) the creation of EF-Tu transgenic maize protoplasts, Arabidopsis and maize whole-plants and (b) the assessment of their heat tolerance in the laboratory. The results of the Phase 1 project will lay the groundwork for the follow-on Phase 2 and Phase 3 projects. They will include the testing the performance of EF-Tu transgenic maize in the field (Phase 2) and its commercialization (Phase 3). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial applications of this project will be in the area of agriculture. High-temperature is a major limiting factor to plant productivity, often causing significant economic losses to both domestic and international agricultural markets. The development and commercialization of transgenic maize with greater ability to tolerate heat stress is expected to have enormous economic benefits for the United States and the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0214789</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eugene</FirstName>
      <LastName>Butler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eugene.butler@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Genetic Architecture Education Analysis (GAEA), Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Brookings</CityName>
      <ZipCode>570060506</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6056922751</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2308 6th Street, E.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0201000</Code>
      <Name>Agriculture</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
