<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Very-Large-Area Lithography System for Flexible Displays and Fluidic-Self-Assembly-Based Electronics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Winslow L. Sargeant</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project addresses the manufacturing of very-large-area flexible displays. It is critical to develop a low-cost manufacturing process that enables very-large-area flexible displays to be manufactured for the military as well as the consumer. Recent technical innovations in the area of very-large-area lithography and fluidic self-assembly offer a unique process for low-cost high-volume flexible display manufacturing. Anvik Corporation has developed a breakthrough lithography technology that enables high-throughput, cost-effective production of very large displays (20 to 120 inches diagonal) on flexible substrates, which may be either loaded as discrete sheets or fed continuously in a roll-to-roll configuration. Anvil's very-large-area lithography technology represents a significant breakthrough in display manufacturing. In this proposal, we present a program for developing a production-worthy lithography system for high-throughput, low-cost fabrication of flexible, high-resolution displays of sizes up to 60-inch diagonal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This lithography process are that it is compatible with fluidic self-assembly manufacturing techniques will potentially result in higher performance and lower cost displays.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0214745</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
      <LastName>Klosner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mklosner@anvik.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Anvik Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>HAWTHORNE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>105322165</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9143452442</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6 SKYLINE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
