<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI/RUI: Acquisition of DNA Sequencing and Genotyping Instrumentation for Research and Undergraduate Training at Middlebury College</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>106359</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Helen G. Hansma</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Acquisition of DNA Sequencing and Genotyping Instrumentation for &lt;br/&gt;Research and Undergraduate Training at Middlebury College&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Matthew H. Dick, PI&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; A grant has been awarded to Middlebury College under the direction of Dr. Dick to establish a DNA sequencing and genotyping facility at the college through acquisition of relevant instrumentation. DNA sequencing is used to determine the sequence of 'letters' in DNA, and is best known through its application in the Human Genome Project. DNA genotyping allows unambiguous identification of genetically different individuals, and well-known applications include the DNA fingerprinting used in forensic work, as well as determination of paternity. These tools are now fundamental to all disciplines of biology. DNA sequences are used, for example, in studies ranging from identifying genes implicated in human diseases, to understanding the spread of HIV, to reconstructing the history of life on earth. The DNA sequencing/genotyping facility at Middlebury College will enhance research by the faculty, foster new research directions, and help attract top faculty and students to the college. Furthermore, it will spark undergraduate interest and augment training in molecular biology and its application across biological disciplines.&lt;br/&gt; Dr. Dick and three other faculty in biology, who will be involved in the project as senior personnel, will make use of the sequencing/genotyping instrumentation to address diverse research problems. Dr. Dick will sequence DNA from a widespread group of marine organisms called bryozoans in order to reconstruct their evolutionary relationships, which are poorly understood. Dr. Helen Young will use genotyping to examine the effects of bird versus insect pollinators on the exchange of genetic material among flowering plant populations. Dr. Vickie Backus will use genotyping to understand the diverse life history strategies of ants in New England forests. Dr. Joshua Kavaler will sequence DNA in a study of gene regulation in fruit fly sense organ development. In addition, several faculty will collaborate to design and implement a new undergraduate training course, Molecular Methods in Ecology and Evolution. This course will provide students in ecology and evolution the knowledge they need to utilize molecular techniques in their research. It will also give students in molecular genetics training they do not encounter in traditional courses. The course will thus foster communication among students of diverse biological disciplines.&lt;br/&gt; The research projects to which the instrumentation will initially be applied address basic problems in biology which, however, have broad significance. Bryozoans, for example, are important as indicators of environmental quality, are a source of one class of potent anti-cancer drugs, and are exceptionally useful for evolutionary studies because of their excellent fossil record. Studies of pollination are relevant to conservation, because they address the impact of introduced insect pollinators such as the honeybee on native plant populations. Studies on forest ants address fundamental problems in evolutionary theory. Cell signaling during fruit fly development makes use of molecular pathways identical to those in humans; indeed, much of what we know of human gene function has derived from such studies. Finally, the broadest and most important use of the instrumentation will be to spark interest in biology in the next generation of physicians and researchers, and train them in current techniques.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215782</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dick</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dick@middlebury.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/02/2003</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ward</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jward@middlebury.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/02/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Middlebury College</Name>
      <CityName>MIDDLEBURY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>057536000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8024435000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>14 OLD CHAPEL ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Vermont</StateName>
      <StateCode>VT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
