<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>IMR: Acquisition of Modern Gel Permeation Chromatography Instrumentation for the Butler Polymer Research Laboratory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>140700</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Instrumentation for Materials Research program supports the University of Florida with the acquisition of of a gel permeation chromatography (GPC) instrument equipped with four detectors and high temperature capability to provide molecular weight information on a number of new polymers being developed. The projects span the range of modeling conventional polyolefins, to conjugated and electroactive polymers with especially low oxidation potentials, to examining the structure of highly organized core-shell polymers. The instrument is based on a Waters high temperature GPC, capable of making measurements at temperatures up to 150 degrees C, and possessing an array of detection systems (UV/Vis, refractive index, light scattering, and differential viscometry) assembled from three vendors: Waters Corporation, Wyatt Technology Corporation, and Viscotek Corporation. Several NSF initiated or funded research in polymers science will benefit from using the instrument. In addition 40-50 undergraduate students, graduate students (including two NSF Graduate Research Fellows) and postdocs present at any one time in the Butler Laboratory will attain training on this instrumentation. Researchers from other Departments in the Center for Macromolecular Science and Engineering (especially Materials Science) will use the facility. Further, Professor Duran leads an NSF/REU site with strong ties to France, and each of the faculty members directs REU students through this.&lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;The research team that operates out of the Butler Polymer Research Laboratory at the University of Florida, will acquire instrumentation to measure the size (so called molecular weight) of the large polymeric molecules with which they work. The instrument is a gel permeation chromatography (GPC) instrument and will be fully equipped for modern research capability. The projects span studies of conventional polyolefins (e.g. polyethylene), to conjugated and electrically conducting polymers, to examining the structure of polymers for colloids. The instrument will be based on a Waters high temperature GPC possessing an array of detection systems assembled from three vendors: Waters Corporation, Wyatt Technology Corporation, and Viscotek Corporation. NSF initiated or funded research that will benefit from using the proposed instrument includes projects to make new plastics, polymers for drug release, polymers to make all-organic displays, and polymers for biological and chemical sensors. In addition 40-50 undergraduate students, graduate students (including two NSF Graduate Research Fellows) and postdocs present at any one time in the Butler Laboratory who will recieve training on this instrumentation. Researchers from other Departments in the Center for Macromolecular Science and Engineering (especially Materials Science) will use the facility. Further, Professor Duran leads an NSF/REU site with strong ties to France, and each of the faculty members directs REU students through this.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215994</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>K.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wagener</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wagener@chem.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reynolds</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>reynolds@chemistry.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Randolph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Duran</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rduran@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
