<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: COSEE-WEST</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1243467</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides support to establish a COSEE West in the greater Los Angeles area with a diverse mix of activities aimed at 1) enhancing regional awareness of ocean sciences, 2) using ocean science as a vehicle to increase general science literacy and 3) increasing the number of students who choose science and ocean science careers. These goals will be addressed by through catalytic, multi-faceted collaboration between the University of Southern California and the University of California at Los Angeles with additional links to the Los Angeles County Museum of Natural History and the greater Los Angeles school districts. A distance learning partnership will be established with the College of Exploration in Virginia. Activities will include an extensive professional development and leadership program for science teachers, a community lecture series, an ocean science web site, a college mentorship program and curriculum development activities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;COSEE West has the potential to enhance science education in a densely populated and diverse major urban area. The program conveys a focused vision and a set of interesting plans for incorporating ocean scientists and their research results into classrooms, informal education activities and public outreach. Because of its focus on the LA basin, this COSEE Center has the potential to have a major impact on science education in school districts within the greater Los Angeles area. This proposal is collaborative with proposal #02-15497.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215506</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hamner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>whamner@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
      <CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11000 Kinross Avenue, Suite 211</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
