<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-New Zealand Cooperative Research: Gradient-Related Trends in Mountain Channel Geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11300</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Christine French</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0215134&lt;br/&gt;Wohl&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a collaborative research project between Professor Ellen Wohl of Colorado State University and Professor Timothy Davies of Lincoln University in Canterbury, New Zealand. While mountainous regions provide the major water source for many regions and produce a disproportionately large amount of the global sediment budget, we know relatively little about the basic processes operating along mountain river channels. This project will investigate mountain rivers to understand relationships between potential control variables (valley gradient, discharge, bedrock substrate resistance, and local sediment supply) and response variables (channel geometry and flow hydraulics). The study will be conducted on the northwest side of the South Island of New Zealand where mountainous catchments remain largely unimpacted by human activities. Knowledge gained should help in developing effective management schemes for mountain drainage basins. This project will benefit from the expertise and facilities of both the U.S. and Australian institutions, and will include the active participation of American students in the international collaboration.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215134</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wohl</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ellenw@cnr.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colorado State University</Name>
      <CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
      <ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0208000</Code>
      <Name>Water Resources</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
