<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Innovative Materials for Thermal Management</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98144</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Winslow L. Sargeant</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will enable a 2-fold increase in conductivity for products without sacrificing power or capability. Recently, a new high thermal conductivity material has been produced using CVD fluid bed coating process and low cost consolidation techniques. The realization of improved electronic substrates is dependent on the increases in thermal conductivity over standard materials. Though high conductivity materials have been identified, consolidating these materials in a cost effective and durable manner has remained illusive. The encapsulation of materials prior to consolidation has aided the durability and low cost processing. The innovation in this program is to improve the encapsulated materials being produced, and potentially develop even greater and distinctly different physical properties additional development of the encapsulated powder/consolidation process is necessary. This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will enable a 2-fold increase in conductivity for products without sacrificing power or capability. Recently, a new high thermal conductivity material has been produced using CVD fluid bed coating process and low cost consolidation techniques. &lt;br/&gt; The realization of improved electronic substrates is dependent on the increases in thermal conductivity over standard materials. Though high conductivity materials have been identified, consolidating these materials in a cost effective and durable manner has remained illusive. The encapsulation of materials prior to consolidation has aided the durability and low cost processing. The innovation in this program is to improve the encapsulated materials being produced, and potentially develop even greater and distinctly different physical properties additional development of the encapsulated powder/consolidation process is necessary.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215327</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stbaker2000@cs.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>POWDERMET INC</Name>
      <CityName>EUCLID</CityName>
      <ZipCode>441177125</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2164040053</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>24112 ROCKWELL DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
