<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Feasibility assesment for Stachybotrys Chartarum and Aspergillus Fumigatus ELISA Kits</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>76009</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Om P. Sahai</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR)Phase I project will investigate a biotechnological approach to rapidly detect two notorious toxin-producing fungi. Indoor fungal growth related to water leaks and floods can induce a variety of disease symptoms. The presence of some fungi, like Stachybotrys chartarum , can cause severe morbidity. Unfortunately, the detection of harmful fungi, like Stachybotrys, has been hampered by inadequate methods. The proposed research will determine the feasibility of developing a rapid detection method for toxigenic fungi that could be used at any test site. The primary objective of this research is to isolate a diffusible spore molecule from S. chartarum spores and one from A. fumigatus spores for the development of an antibody-based detection kit. The molecules will be extracted in saline solution to mimic diffusion into lung linings and used for polyclonal antibody development. If successful, the&lt;br/&gt;antigens will be used for monoclonal antibody development in a Phase II project. This will allow for the development of a rapid, on-site testing kit to detect potentially dangerous fungal organisms quickly and inexpensively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial application of this project will be in the area of diagnostics linked to human health and animal health.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215114</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yvette</FirstName>
      <LastName>Piceno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yvette.piceno@microbe.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>MICROBIAL INSIGHTS INC</Name>
      <CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379322567</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8655738188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>10515 Research Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
