<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Computing and Peripheral Hardware to Support Collaborative Research and Research Education in Imaging and Information Visualization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>243130</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>EIA-0215356&lt;br/&gt;Ikhlas Abdel-Qader&lt;br/&gt;Bradley Bazuin&lt;br/&gt;Karlis Kaugars&lt;br/&gt;Abhay Sharma&lt;br/&gt;Li Yang&lt;br/&gt;Western Michigan University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;MRI/RUI Acquisition of Computing and Peripheral Hardware to Support Collaborative Research and Research Education in Imaging and Information Visualization&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal from a RUI institution, developing an Ethernet-Based imaging and visualization infrastructure, supports interdisciplinary research projects that span a variety of application areas such as Information Visualization, Imaging Science, Color Analysis, Time-Varying Images, and Real-Time Image Processing. The laboratory, consisting of one server, multiple workstations, associated cameras, frame grabbers, output devices, and selected network and image processing software, will be bridged to existing departmental, college, and campus networks, and will be used to accomplish the following goals:&lt;br/&gt; Expand research investigations advancing image processing and information visualization,&lt;br/&gt; Encourage interdisciplinary research, research training, and educational activities,&lt;br/&gt; Increase industrial collaboration adding a real world problem environment,&lt;br/&gt; Support graduate and undergraduate instruction in related courses such as Pattern Recognition, Computer Graphics, and Digital Imaging, and&lt;br/&gt; Attract women and minority groups at both graduate and undergraduate levels to pursue research projects.&lt;br/&gt;The infrastructure will service the following projects within three research groups:&lt;br/&gt;1. Information Visualization and Data Mining Group&lt;br/&gt;A. Visual Exploration and Mining of Large Relational Datasets&lt;br/&gt;B. Algorithm Visualization&lt;br/&gt;C. Interactive Document Management&lt;br/&gt;D. Visualization of Association Rules&lt;br/&gt;2. Image Visualization, Color Measurement, and Color Analysis Group&lt;br/&gt;A. Color Reproduction in Digital Imaging&lt;br/&gt;B. Fundamental Analysis of CCD Imaging Systems Using Fourier Theory&lt;br/&gt;3. Real-Time Image Processing and Pattern Recognition Group&lt;br/&gt;A. Utilizing Wavelets for Target Tracking&lt;br/&gt;B. An Integrated Image Analysis Algorithm from Dynamic Scenes&lt;br/&gt;C. Confocal Microscopy and Image Analysis in Gamma-Ray Astronomy&lt;br/&gt;D. Wireless Vision for Intelligent Transportation System&lt;br/&gt;E. Pavement Surface Image Analysis System</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/17/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215356</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ikhlas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Abdel-Qader</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ikhlas.abdelqader@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Karlis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaugars</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>karlis.kaugars@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Li</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>li.yang@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bazuin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brad.bazuin@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Abhay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sharma</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abhay.sharma@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Western Michigan University</Name>
      <CityName>Kalamazoo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2693878298</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1903 West Michigan Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
