<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of an Analytical Ultracentrifuge for Use in Biochemistry, Structural Biology and Polymer Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>223115</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Helen G. Hansma</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A grant has been awarded to the State University of New&lt;br/&gt;York at Stony Brook under the direction of Dr. Raleigh for the acquisition of an analytical ultracentrifuge.&lt;br/&gt;The analytical ultracentrifuge was first developed more than 50 years ago&lt;br/&gt;and its invention lead to a Nobel Prize. Since that time it has evolved&lt;br/&gt;from a custom made piece of specialized apparatus to an essential everyday&lt;br/&gt;tool for the investigation of basic biochemistry and chemistry. Analytical&lt;br/&gt;ultracentrifugation is the method of choice for studying the properties of&lt;br/&gt;large molecules that associate in solution. It is applicable to biological&lt;br/&gt;and non-biological systems and it is now an important research tool in&lt;br/&gt;biochemistry, structural biology and polymer science. The ranges of&lt;br/&gt;applications of this technique are immense and are rapidly increasing.&lt;br/&gt;Acquisition of an analytical ultracentrifuge will complement major ongoing&lt;br/&gt;initiatives in polymer science and in structural biology and biochemistry&lt;br/&gt;at SUNY Stony Brook.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Ten investigators representing five academic departments at SUNY Stony&lt;br/&gt;Brook will conduct basic research projects. Their research interests span&lt;br/&gt;the range from the development of new materials, to biology, polymer&lt;br/&gt;chemistry, enzyme mechanisms, protein dynamics and folding, and viral&lt;br/&gt;assembly. Together they supervise more than 90 researchers. Professor Chu&lt;br/&gt;will use the instrument in his investigations of novel vesicle structures&lt;br/&gt;and surfactants formed by modified fullerenes. These new materials have a&lt;br/&gt;range of potential applications including delivery agents. Professor Kisker&lt;br/&gt;will use the ultracentrifugation in her studies of DNA repair while&lt;br/&gt;Professor de Los Santos will make use of the instrument in his studies of&lt;br/&gt;damaged DNA. DNA repair is essential for maintaining the correct genetic&lt;br/&gt;information. Mutations are the primary cause of hereditary diseases, as&lt;br/&gt;well as cancer, and may also be involved in aging. Professors' London and&lt;br/&gt;Smith will investigate fundamental issues in membrane protein structure and&lt;br/&gt;folding and the ultracentrifuge will play an important role in their work.&lt;br/&gt;It is estimated that 30 % of all proteins are membrane proteins but very&lt;br/&gt;little is known about their structure and folding despite the fact that&lt;br/&gt;they play a central role in many important biological processes. Professor&lt;br/&gt;Raleigh will use the instrument in his studies of the process of protein&lt;br/&gt;folding. The protein-folding problem refers to the mechanism by which an&lt;br/&gt;initially unfolded protein achieves its final functional structure. It has&lt;br/&gt;long been known that the linear sequence of aminoacids dictates the final&lt;br/&gt;folded structure of proteins but the rules that govern this key assembly&lt;br/&gt;process are still not understood. Professor Sampson will use the instrument&lt;br/&gt;in her studies of the important enzyme cholesterol oxidase, which is used&lt;br/&gt;as a cholesterol sensor. Professor Sampson and Professor Tonge will make&lt;br/&gt;use of the instrument in their basic studies of enzyme functions while the&lt;br/&gt;laboratory of Professor Scarlata will apply the instrument to studies of&lt;br/&gt;viral assembly. Professor Schindelin will use the ultracentrifuge in his&lt;br/&gt;studies of the proteins involved in the biosynthesis of critical molybdenum&lt;br/&gt;cofactors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The consortium of investigators who will make use of the analytical&lt;br/&gt;ultracentrifuge study fundamental problems in biology, biochemistry and&lt;br/&gt;polymer chemistry. Many biologically important molecules as well as many&lt;br/&gt;man made macromolecules work in tandem with closely associated partners.&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the detailed nature of these interactions is key to&lt;br/&gt;understanding these complex systems. An analytical ultracentrifuge is&lt;br/&gt;required for these studies. Examples taken from work at SUNY Stony Brook&lt;br/&gt;include studies of critical proteins involved in the repair of damaged&lt;br/&gt;genetic material, the assembly of viruses, the behavior of novel new&lt;br/&gt;materials made from C60 ("buckyball" derivatives), and studies of the&lt;br/&gt;fundamental processes by which proteins acquire their biologically active&lt;br/&gt;state. The instrument will also greatly enhance the infrastructure for&lt;br/&gt;training graduate students at SUNY Stony Brook and will also benefit&lt;br/&gt;researchers at nearby Brookhaven National Laboratory</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215690</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Raleigh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>daniel.raleigh@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/30/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9184</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY - INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
