<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Novel Low Cost Technology for High-Performance Integrated Microcombustor/Evaporator</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>643000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Deepak G. Bhat</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is aimed at the continued development of novel microscale combustors/evaporators, which are intended for evaporation of fuel and water in fuel reformers as well as for personal portable heating and cooling systems. The general objective of the Phase II program is to optimize and scale up a technology for microchannel combustor/evaporators demonstrated in the Phase I and to develop a compact device, which could generate at least 25- 30 watts of thermal energy per square centimeter of heat transfer area and transfer that energy to fluid with efficiency greater than 85 percent. Innovative fabrication technology and a new microreactor concept were combined to create a highly efficient device, which uses hydrogen or hydrocarbon fuel combustion for heating and/or boiling working fluids. Conditions of heat transfer and combustion of hydrogen and methane in microchannel combustor/evaporators will be determined and optimal design of the microscale device will be established. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Potential commercial applications include lightweight, safe and high performance microcombustors for microturbines, man-portable microheaters for cold climates, man portable cooling microsystems for hot climates, on-board fuel processors for hydrogen generation, distributed space conditioning of buildings, etc. Utilization of microchannel combustor/evaporators for these applications will result in increase of energy efficiency, reduction of air pollution and enhancement of life quality.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215792</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lev</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tuchinskiy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ltuch@mercorp.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Materials and Electrochemical Research Corporation (MER)</Name>
      <CityName>Tuscon</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857569237</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5205741980</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>7960 South Kolb Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5373</Code>
      <Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1467</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
