<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Nematode Intestinal Proteins as Anthelmintic Targets</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>93016</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Om P. Sahai</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0215151&lt;br/&gt;Hresko&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project proposes to identify potential targets for the development of therapeutic agents to treat infections by parasitic nematodes. Nematode infections represent a serious heath concern for both humans and domesticated animals and, as such, represent a significant market for anthelmintic drugs. This project proposes to test a new approach to the discovery of anthelmintic agents. Divergence, LLC has identified a class of essential nematode-specific genes in Caenorhabditis elegans, representing a rich pool of potential targets for the control of human, animal and plant parsitic nematodes. Antibodies will be produced against a subset of proteins that are predicted to be gut-localized. The antibodies will be used to confirm localization of the protein and to challenge cultures of nematodes. Based on "hidden antigen" vaccine theory, it is anticipated that the antibodies against one or more of the gene-products proposed in this project may disrupt or impair the life cycle of the nematode. Completion of this Phase I project will allow a swift transition into the investigation of parasite genes. Expression of parasite genes introduced into C. elegans, which can be grown in large scale, will allow production of protein for the in vitro screening of peptide or small molecule libraries and for potential vaccine antigens.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial application of this project is in the area of therapeutics aimed at both human and animal health.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215151</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hresko</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hresko@divergence.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Divergence, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631322900</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3148128024</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1005 North Warson Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510102</Code>
      <Name>Role-Terrestrial Ecosystem</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
