<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Southeastern Center for Ocean Science Education Excellence: A Systemic Approach to Forming Ocean Science Education Partnerships</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>969136</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06040104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a Regional Center for Ocean Sciences Education Excellence with administrative offices located at the South Carolina Sea Grant Consortium Office in Charleston, SC. The center will focus on the North Carolina, South Carolina and Georgia region, and center personnel will work to forge stronger relationships between research organizations, researchers, schools and informal educational sites in the region. The Southeastern Center for Ocean Sciences Education Excellence (SECOSEE) will also reach out to underrepresented groups in the ocean sciences by creating programs based on the unique African American coastal heritage in the area. Activities include an inventory of existing ocean science materials and programs, awareness workshops for educators and researchers, collaborations between researchers and educators, enhanced professional development opportunities, supplemental school and summer science programs, website development, and evaluation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This center will be one of seven COSEE's that represent the initiation of the COSEE network. The initial set of centers covers most of the East Coast, Florida, the Gulf Coast, and California. A central coordinating office for the seven centers will also be funded. Substantial funding for the SECOSEE program will be provided by NOAA's Coastal Ocean Services and Office of Ocean Exploration.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0215402</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Malcolm</FirstName>
      <LastName>DeVoe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Rick.DeVoe@scseagrant.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lois</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spence</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lundie.spence@scseagrant.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>South Carolina Sea Grant Consortium</Name>
      <CityName>Charleston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>294011514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8439532078</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>287 Meeting Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
