<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Providing Access to Scanning Electron Microscopy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>219829</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Helen G. Hansma</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PROVIDING ACCESS TO SCANNING ELECTRON MICROSCOPY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A grant has been awarded to Drs. Angel Valdes, Brian Brown, Kirk Fitzhugh, Gordon Hendler and Joel Martin at the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County (LACM) to acquire a Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM). The SEM is a fundamental research tool in biological and physical sciences, offering a level of resolution (magnifications over 300,000 times) not possible with light microscopy, which is limited to magnifications no greater than 1,000 times. A state-of-the-art SEM with variable pressure capability and an Energy Dispersive Spectrometry unit (EDS) will be purchased. The variable pressure capability is necessary to allow examination of uncoated samples, which is critical when dealing with type material or delicate specimens. The EDS unit will be essential for geological and archeological research. For most biological samples a sputter coater will be required. We selected a high resolution sputter coater that utilizes noble targets such as gold, gold/palladium and platinum.&lt;br/&gt;The SEM will constitute the core of a new research unit shared by seven research departments including Invertebrate Zoology, Vertebrate Zoology, Botany, Earth Sciences, Invertebrate Paleontology, Vertebrate Paleontology and Anthropology. Another important component of the SEM usage at the LACM will be the identification of collection materials. Staff in the Marine Invertebrate Biodiversity Processing Center, Earth Studies, and Vertebrate Paleontology departments will be using the SEM on a regular basis for the identification of minerals, meteorites and biological specimens. The SEM will also be used by the Education Division to enhance public understanding of science and highlight the work of museum scholars. Images produced using the SEM will be a component of future exhibits, curriculum materials, and web sites produced for educational purposes. Education staff will be able to arrange tours to the SEM facility with research staff who will provide access to the machine and explanations of the application of the SEM technology to natural sciences.&lt;br/&gt; The installation of a SEM at LACM will offer a unique opportunity for integration of on-going research programs and education activities as a dynamic, interactive exhibit component. The SEM facility will also provide a tool for affiliated research associates and visitors, enhancing cooperative research activities with regional, national and international colleagues. The SEM will be a critical component of this training process and will provide the LACM students with the necessary tools for their research in situ.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0216506</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmartin@nhm.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/10/2003</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hendler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hendler@nhm.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Kirk</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fitzhugh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fitzhugh@bcff.usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brown</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bbrown@nhm.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Angel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Valdes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aavaldes@cpp.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Los Angeles County Museum of Natural History Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900074057</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137443301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>900 Exposition Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7226</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9184</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY - INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
