<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR/STTR Phase II: Microchip-Laser-Based Optical Alloy Analysis Instrument</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>499957</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Juan E. Figueroa</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project concerns the development of an optical alloy composition sensor based on laser induced plasma spectroscopy. A key element of the sensor is the use of a microchip laser excitation source. The technology has the capability to detect industrially relevant compositions in steel alloys and possibly aluminum alloys. The Phase I results indicated the efficacy of the technique for the analysis of iron alloys. The Phase II project will focus on the development of a small, lightweight and mobile field prototype, which will be able to analyze various alloy samples.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The key commercial application of this technology is aluminum and iron scrap metal analysis, substantial market niches which are not effectively covered by existing analysis&lt;br/&gt;technology. The major market is for steel and aluminum alloys that have significant components of light elements. These precision instrument currents have sales worldwide in excess of $10 million per year.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0216309</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wormhoudt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jody@aerodyne.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Aerodyne Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>BILLERICA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>018213976</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9786639500</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>45 MANNING RD STE 2</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
