<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: New Elastomeric Microelectrodes for Improved Neuroprostheses</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>522740</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George B. Vermont</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project is to develop electrically conductive polymer-silicone composite materials for improving the performance of implantable neural prostheses. Prior Phase I study has demonstrated the feasibility of synthesizing electrically conductive polymer nanocomposites with mechanical properties of silicone elastomers. Polymer-based prototype electrical devices were found to be stable toward simulated physiological conditions and cyclic current pulsing. The Phase II program will extend the benefits of these systems to the fabrication of more complex devices such as multi-poled cuff electrodes for chronic peripheral nerve stimulation and recording. An expanded test plan would include development of advanced device fabrication methods and extensive testing of the prototype neural prostheses for electrical response, tissue compatibility, and durability in chronic implantation applications. The optimized elastomeric electrodes will be characterized for biocompatibility, stability and electrical properties. Methodology will be developed for fabricating prosthetic electrodes for extensive in vitro pulsing studies and acute animal testing. Finally, test protocols for the new electrode products will be established in an effort to obtain FDA approval.&lt;br/&gt; The commercial applications of this project will be in the area of biomedical devices and systems that serve the needs of disabled individuals following stroke or spinal cord injury.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0216035</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
      <LastName>Keohan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fkeohan@capecodresearch.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/17/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cape Cod Research, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>EAST FALMOUTH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>025364440</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5085404400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>19 RESEARCH RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0510402</Code>
      <Name>Biomaterials-Short &amp; Long Terms</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
