<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Linux Cluster Super Computer for Meteorological Modeling and Computer Science Research and Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>205454</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>EIA 02-16661 &lt;br/&gt; Rafkin, Scot &lt;br/&gt; Chun, Robert&lt;br/&gt; San Jose State University &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: MRI/RUI/MII: Acquisition of a Linux Cluster Super Computer for Meteorological Modeling and &lt;br/&gt; Computer Science Research and Education &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Proposed:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal from an RUI/MII institution, establishing a Linux-based parallel computing cluster, aims to simulate meteorological phenomena and study and teach the use of parallel processors. The infrastructure will be used in support of ongoing&lt;br/&gt;Numerical modeling of the atmosphere of Mars using the Mars Regional Atmospheric Modeling System (MRAMS) and&lt;br/&gt;Computer Science Research in the parallel and distributed hardware and software.&lt;br/&gt;The first component will benefit the following current research underway:&lt;br/&gt;Large eddy simulations (LESs) of the Martian atmosphere to provide insight into the structure and dynamics of the highly unstable convective boundary layer (including the dynamics of dusts devils)&lt;br/&gt;Mesoscale simulations of past and proposed Mars landing sites&lt;br/&gt;Simulation of local and regional dust storms, and wind-produced landforms (aids satellite observations)&lt;br/&gt;Simulations of orographic water ice and carbon dioxide clouds.&lt;br/&gt;The second component will investigate and/or explore&lt;br/&gt;Software optimization of the MRAMS code (tune it for maximum performance on hardware platform) and&lt;br/&gt;Alternative hardware architectures for high-performance computing&lt;br/&gt;The cluster will serve as a central research platform to investigate processor-to-processor communication overhead, memory contention of symmetric multiprocessors, cache coherence, and distributed processing. Moreover, performance of novel processor, memory, and network topologies will be evaluated.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0216661</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bornstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pblmodel@hotmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/27/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Robert.Chun@sjsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scot</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rafkin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rafkin@boulder.swri.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/08/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>02/07/2003</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>San Jose</CityName>
      <ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
