<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of a Small Angle X-ray Scattering Facility at the University of Tennessee</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>244700</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award from the Major Research Instrumentation program supports the acquisition of a Small Angle X-ray Scattering (SAXS) Facility at the University of Tennessee. The instrument will be used to characterize the structure of materials on a length scale of 1-100 nm. &lt;br/&gt;Current and future research that will benefit from the SAXS facility ranges from studies of the structure of 'soft materials' such as polymers to the more traditional 'hard materials.' The studies of soft materials include investigation of the morphology of (a) polymer blends and copolymers, (b) polymer crystallization, (c) polymer electrolytes, (d) polymer composites and (e) processed polymers (fibers, films, moldings, etc.). Studies of 'hard materials' include investigations of (a) the nanostructure of new metal oxide based materials, (b) the nanometer-size dispersions of metals and compounds in sapphire, (d) development of nanoparticles through pulsed laser ablation techniques, and (e) void formation in carbon fibers. An interesting overlap involves the use of microphase separated diblock and triblock copolymers as templates to synthesize new nanostructures, well ordered carbon nanotubes, and nanoscale magnetic wires. In addition, studies of X-ray scattering of materials will provide background for neutron scattering studies at Oak Ridge National Laboratory with the HFIR reactor upgrade and, in the longer term, the completion of the Spallation Neutron Source (SNS). &lt;br/&gt;This acquisition will (1) foster the development of new areas of research in nanoscience and new collaborations among UT faculty in science and engineering, especially in the soft materials area, (2) develop new collaborations among UTK faculty and students with scientists and engineers at Oak Ridge National Laboratory, and with and other internationally prominent researchers, (3) provide opportunities for SAXS measurements to investigators from neighboring institutions, especially those that have traditionally served underrepresented minorities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;***&lt;br/&gt;This award from the Major Research Instrumentation program supports the acquisition of a Small Angle X-ray Scattering (SAXS) Facility at the University of Tennessee. The instrument will be used to characterize the structure of materials on a length scale of 1-100 nm.&lt;br/&gt;The SAXS system will serve faculty, postdoctoral research fellows, and students in a wide range of sub-disciplines of Materials Science, including polymer science and engineering, ceramics, metallurgy, and solid state physics. Examples of areas of study include investigation of the structure of (a) polymer blends and copolymers, (b) polymer crystallization, (c) polymer electrolytes, (d) polymer composites (e) processed polymers (fibers, films, moldings, etc.), (f) new metal oxide based materials, (g) the nanometer-size dispersions of metals and compounds in sapphire, (h) development of nanoparticles through pulsed laser ablation techniques, and (i) void formation in carbon fibers. &lt;br/&gt;This acquisition will (1) foster the development of new areas of research in nanoscience and new collaborations among UT faculty in science and engineering, especially in the soft materials area, (2) develop new collaborations among UTK faculty and students with scientists and engineers at Oak Ridge National Laboratory, and with and other internationally prominent researchers, (3) provide opportunities for SAXS measurements to investigators from neighboring institutions, especially those that have traditionally served underrepresented minorities.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0216252</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Phillips</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>paul.phillips@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Spruiell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>spruiell@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda (Lee)</FirstName>
      <LastName>Magid</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lmagid@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>06/03/2004</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jimmy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mays</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jimmymays@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dadmun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Dad@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
      <CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
      <StateCode>TN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
