<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Acquisition of Test Equipment for Non-Contact Measurement of Thermal and Mechanical Properties</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>415109</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ken Chong</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Program of Integrated Science and Technology (ISAT) at James Madison University (JMU) features a multi-disciplinary curriculum that places a strong emphasis on hands-on, project-based learning. The Infrared Development and Testing Laboratory (IDTTL) was established at ISAT in 1997 to provide opportunities for effective hands-on, project-oriented, student-centered learning that reinforces concepts and skills introduced within the ISAT program. The IDTTL provides access to research in advanced topics and emerging measurement technologies, fosters development of teaming and communication skills in an interdisciplinary environment, and avails undergraduates of professional activities including writing papers, presentation at conferences, and participation in summer internships.&lt;br/&gt;A suite of projects ongoing in the IDTTL is presently supported by NASA including (i) non-contact measurement of the thermal-structural response of an aluminized thin-film polymer membrane, with application to sunshields, solar sails, and membrane optics and (ii) development of an imaging gas-filter correlation radiometer (GFCR) for measurement of tropospheric carbon monoxide. The laboratory also develops non-contact techniques for manufacturing process control, boiler analyses, and predictive maintenance. The common thread connecting these projects is the measurement of critical parameters where contact with the target object is either impossible or will alter the desired parameters.&lt;br/&gt;The equipment requested includes an infrared imager with multiple lenses, hemispherical directional reflectometer, laser vibrometer, shaker, and vacuum chamber with cold plate. These instruments will elevate the capability of the laboratory and allow undergraduates and faculty mentors the opportunity to advance existing studies, and to prepare proposals for future studies that are more competitive than would otherwise be possible. The equipment will also be incorporated into new course laboratory activities through which all ISAT majors will benefit, and undergraduates and faculty from other departments at JMU, including physics, chemistry, biology, and geology, will be invited to utilize these instruments. The IDTTL will improve its stature as a model for other colleges and universities that wish to develop an interdisciplinary research laboratory capable of conducting valuable research and development and providing undergraduates an extraordinary learning experience.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0216287</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Blandino</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>blandinojr@vmi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miles</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>milesjj@jmu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>James Madison University</Name>
      <CityName>HARRISONBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>228077000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5405686872</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>MSC 5728</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
