<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI/RUI: Acquisition of Isothermal Titration and Differential Scanning MicroCalorimeters for Chemistry and Biology Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>117220</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan M. Frye</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With support from the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) Program, Stephen Dunham, Paul Greenwood and Dasan Thamattoor of Colby College will acquire an isothermal titration calorimeter (ITC) and differential scanning microcalorimeters (DSC) for chemistry and biology research. Research projects that will exploit this equipment include a) structural studies of modified oligonucleotides; b) metal ion binding affinities and stabilities of modified DNA aptamers; c) binding affinities of DNA aptamers to biological targets; d) ion binding affinities and structural characterization of proteins in nematocysts; e) ion binding selectivity of polyoxa[n]peristylanes; f) computer aided molecular design and guest-host chemistry of H2-antagonists; and g) structural analysis of RNase mutants that allow self-fertilization in plants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Calorimetry is an extremely useful tool in modern analytical chemistry. Calorimetric analysis is used to measure the thermal energy (heat) exchange that occurs during molecular interactions and reactions. Thus it can provide a very reliable and sensitive method for determining the thermodynamic properties of materials such as changes in heat capacity of liquid and solid samples. Colby College is an undergraduate institution, and the availability of these instruments will have a strong impact on undergraduate research. In addition, commercial ITC and DSC microcalorimeters are currently not available in the state of Maine.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0216655</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Greenwood</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pggreenw@colby.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dunham</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sdunham@colby.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dasan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Thamattoor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dmthamat@colby.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Colby College</Name>
      <CityName>Waterville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>049018840</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2078594770</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 Mayflower Hill</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maine</StateName>
      <StateCode>ME</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9184</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY - INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
