<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Study on Minimization of Torque Ripple of Disk Brushless Permanent Magnet Motors Applied as Gearless Drive for Light Electric Vehicles</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>119995</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Tomsovic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The aim of the project is to study how to minimize the torque ripple of disc brushless DC permanent magnet motors, keeping, at the same time, a high level specific torque (torque to motor mass ratio). Some preliminary results indicate that it can be achieved by modifying the shape of permanent magnets and the structure of the stator core, and by modifying the current waveform. The research on this subject will concentrate on analysis of magnetic field in 3-D space for two versions of disc motors: torus-type and disc motor with axial magnetic flux in a stator core, and on evaluation of motor performance using dynamic model of electronic converter - permanent magnet motor set in order to select the optimum solution. To verify the computer simulation a laboratory motor model, together with the appropriate converter will be built and tested.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results and experience obtained from the project will allow the design and manufacture of smoothly running motors that are required not only for light, low speed electric vehicles (in particular - wheelchairs), but also in a vast area of drives, where high torque ripple cannot be tolerated. The high efficiency motors with high specific torque, which will result from the project will contribute to the extension of the driving distance of electric vehicle and to save energy, if the motor is applied as a variable speed drive in industry, as well as to low the cost of the final product. &lt;br/&gt;This project will provide the subject for one M.Sc. and one for Ph.D. theses. The results of this project will be disseminated through reviewed publications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0217308</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leszek</FirstName>
      <LastName>Czarnecki</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>czarneck@ece.lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ernest</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mendrela</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ermen@ece.lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
      <CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>LA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0306000</Code>
      <Name>Energy Research &amp; Resources</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1518</Code>
      <Text>CONTROL, NETWORKS, &amp; COMP INTE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1519</Code>
      <Text>INTEGRATIVE SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
