<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Dirac Centenary Conference (Baylor University)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Earle L. Lomon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Baylor University's Dirac Centenary Conference (http://www.baylor.edu/Dirac) is an interdisciplinary evaluation of the seminal contributions of Paul Dirac (1902-1984) to the methodology, progress, and future of twentieth and twenty first century physics. Drawing together scholars from theoretical physics, mathematics, the history of science and the philosophy of science, it provides a rare chance for students and researchers across different disciplines to benefit from interaction with each other. The discussion into the cutting-edge developments in canonical quantum gravity, supersymmetry, superstrings and geometric functional analysis made possible by Dirac's innovations in mathematics and physical theory will give physics and mathematics students exposure to active research in their fields, and also contribute to an understanding of the development of physical theory in a way that will aid historians and philosophers of science as they examine the methodological, epistemological and metaphysical implications of modern physics. The cross-fertilization of different disciplines will also contribute to advancing knowledge and understanding within and across fields in beneficial ways. The fruits of this scholarly interaction will be published in an edited volume of conference proceedings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference also provides a unique opportunity for undergraduate and graduate students, as well as postdoctoral researchers in physics, mathematics, philosophy and history to present their work in a context where they can get feedback from senior scholars at the forefront of their respective fields. The conference opens with a poster session competition for students in the physical sciences and mathematics, and a short paper presentation competition for students in the history and/or philosophy of science. Conference scholarships are available for student participation and attendance with minority students strongly encouraged to apply. The impact of this effort on science education will be furthered by Baylor's coordination of a consortium of Texas schools co-sponsoring the conference, and by the recruitment of student involvement from many of the smaller colleges in the southwest, particularly those that are historically African-American or Hispanic. Publicity for the conference will draw public attention to issues in science and contribute to promoting science awareness and education in central Texas and beyond.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0217730</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gordon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Bruce_Gordon@baylor.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Truell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hyde</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Truell_Hyde@baylor.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Baylor University</Name>
      <CityName>Waco</CityName>
      <ZipCode>767987360</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2547103817</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Bear Place #97360</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1287</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
