<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Reference Guide on Power and Energy for the IEEE Virtual Community on Power and Energy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29808</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin Tomsovic</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will develop an online reference guide, called "Pathfinder," primarily for non-technical audiences, including undergraduate and graduate students. This guide will enable users to gain an overview of the power and energy field in pursuit of educational opportunities and resources. Developed in conjunction with IEEE's Virtual Community on Power and Energy, this tool will aggregate quality resources and provide an orderly process for discovery. Recourses will include publications from the IEEE and other sources, as well as "knowledge or learning objects" found in online collections, including the NSF-funded DLNET collection. These objects will include publications and other resources that define the field of power and energy, its attendant industries, and specialized technical and applications areas. IEEE staff and volunteers from the IEEE Educational Activities will work with other volunteers from the IEEE Power Engineering Society and the IEEE Industry Application Society. They will also work with staff from IEEE Press and Wiley to identify and possibly make available resources for the user community. The IEEE Virtual Community on Power and Energy will provide the online platform for developing and reviewing this tool.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0217645</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wiesner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>p.wiesner@ieee.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Institute of Electrical &amp; Electronics Engineers, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088544141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7325626520</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>445 HOES LANE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0306000</Code>
      <Name>Energy Research &amp; Resources</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
