<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Aiming for Algebra</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>899908</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jolene K. Jesse</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Aiming for Algebra is a project of Girlstart, a nonprofit organization in Austin, Texas. &lt;br/&gt;Its goal is to prepare middle school girls for and support their completion of Algebra 1 &lt;br/&gt;in the eighth grade as a means of readying them for college preparatory math and science &lt;br/&gt;classes in high school that lead ultimately to completion of the college majors required&lt;br/&gt;for SMET careers. The primary objectives of the initial 36-month demonstration period &lt;br/&gt;include improving girls self confidence and academic self-esteem; increasing girls'&lt;br/&gt;awareness of SMET careers and the high school and college coursework required to enter &lt;br/&gt;such careers; enhancing girls knowledge of and ability to use algebra in their lives; &lt;br/&gt;improving parents awareness of SMET careers for women; and increasing parents'&lt;br/&gt;awareness of ways to encourage their daughters' success in algebra and&lt;br/&gt;subsequent math and science courses in high school and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed intervention methods to achieve these ends include participation in an&lt;br/&gt;integrated continuum of activities as part of a ifgirls-only science math clublc over &lt;br/&gt;a three-year period, as well as involvement in a range of other community- and &lt;br/&gt;Internet-based math and science experiences with parents and other adults. The &lt;br/&gt;intellectual merit of this project derives from its translation of a significant &lt;br/&gt;portion of the body of previous research on the best practices for addressing gender&lt;br/&gt;inequities in SMET careers and the disparity in the mathematics and science &lt;br/&gt;achievement of girls in the United States into a single, cohesive informal program &lt;br/&gt;approach. Moreover, the project will employ a cohort design that will facilitate an&lt;br/&gt;understanding of what parts of the intervention model have the most impact on the&lt;br/&gt;intended outcomes. A rigorous evaluation component and a strong dissemination plan &lt;br/&gt;further strengthen the likelihood that Aiming for Algebra will result in a better &lt;br/&gt;understanding of how specific programmatic activities affect girls mathematical &lt;br/&gt;skills and their attitudes about and aspirations for math and science careers.&lt;br/&gt;The straightforward, unwavering focus on the completion of Algebra 1 in the eighth&lt;br/&gt; grade is another feature&lt;br/&gt;that makes this project meritorious. By tying its success to a single, observable goal&lt;br/&gt;and directing all of its energies to achieve this one purpose, the project sets itself&lt;br/&gt;up for rigorous comparison with other efforts with an identical goal. Aiming for Algebra &lt;br/&gt;intends to make its methodologies so transparent and so well documented that future &lt;br/&gt;research and demonstration projects can be erected squarely on the intellectual&lt;br/&gt;capital it creates and disseminates. Insofar as its broader impacts, the project will&lt;br/&gt;contribute to an improved understanding of the ways girls can be best prepared for &lt;br/&gt;taking and making good grades in Algebra 1 before they reach high school; it will&lt;br/&gt;advance understanding among teachers and teacher preparation programs of how girls' &lt;br/&gt;expectations of their science and math performance in high school and beyond can be &lt;br/&gt;improved; it will provide empirical evidence of ways that female members of groups&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented in SMET careers- including but notlimited to those who are ethnic &lt;br/&gt;and racial minorities, low-income, linguistic minorities, and differently abled- can&lt;br/&gt;be included in informal programming designed to redress the inequity; and, perhaps most&lt;br/&gt;importantly, the project will benefit society by improving the nation's ability to &lt;br/&gt;identify and remedy long-standing social, economic and academic practices that have&lt;br/&gt;disadvantaged its female population and created obstacles to their full and equal &lt;br/&gt;participation in scientific, mathematical, engineering and technological professions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0217038</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muir</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rachel@girlstart.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lozano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sharon@girlstart.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/09/2002</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Girlstart</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787055116</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5129164775</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 West Anderson Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
