<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Girls Creating Games: Increasing Middle School Girls' Interest in Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>892552</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jolene K. Jesse</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The vast success of products like the "GameBoy" sends a clear message that technology is&lt;br/&gt;the domain of boys. The Girls Creating Games Program is a demonstration project designed&lt;br/&gt;to challenge this message by teaching girls to design and program a computer game. This &lt;br/&gt;project is unique in its approach: it puts girls in the role of producers of technology, rather &lt;br/&gt;than simply consumers. One hundred eighty middle school girls will participate in a study &lt;br/&gt;to determine whether producing technology (computer game design) can increase girls'&lt;br/&gt;fluency, interest, active participation and persistence in technology studies. The&lt;br/&gt;specific project goals are to a)increase girls' knowledge, interest, attitudes, and&lt;br/&gt;confidence with computers, b) increase adults capacity to support girls in technology,&lt;br/&gt;and c) add to research on the kinds of programs and technologies that increase the interest &lt;br/&gt;and persistence of middle school girls in technology studies and careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will take place with small groups of girls after school and during&lt;br/&gt;the summer in a small, urban county (70% White, 21% Hispanic) in California. It involves an&lt;br/&gt;unusual partnership between four entities: 1) researchers and program developers from a &lt;br/&gt;non-profit health promotion agency (ETR Associates); 2) school personnel and students&lt;br/&gt;from New Brighton Middle School; 3) staff and youth from a Boys &amp; Girls Club; and 4) &lt;br/&gt;female technology students, teachers, and professionals from local colleges and&lt;br/&gt;companies. This partnership is essential for building knowledge (e.g., identifying&lt;br/&gt;effective program strategies to increase girls interest and persistence in&lt;br/&gt;technology studies), and increasing social capital (e.g., building the capacity of&lt;br/&gt;adult female role models, teachers, and staff to provide a supportive environment).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Teaching computer game design holds great promise as an intervention strategy for&lt;br/&gt;increasing girls' interest in technology. Indeed, interactive games have an early&lt;br/&gt;influence on theskills and attitudes that are the best predictors of future &lt;br/&gt;technology-related behavior (Greenfield &amp; Cocking, 1996; Levine &amp; Donitsa-Schmidt,&lt;br/&gt;1998; Subrahmanyam &amp; Greenfield, 1998). Only two other known programs (with &lt;br/&gt;elementary and high school students) have used game creation as an intervention &lt;br/&gt;strategy or as part of a research-driven agenda (Kafai, 1995; Miller, Chaika, &amp;&lt;br/&gt;Groppe, 1996). Our work extends that research by working with middle school students &lt;br/&gt;in an informal learning (out of school) environment, and using theoretically and&lt;br/&gt;empirically-based program activities that build on girls development research. &lt;br/&gt;Our project is also innovative in that it includes identity formation as part of the&lt;br/&gt;program as a way to transform, not simply respond to existing gender roles&lt;br/&gt;(Cassell &amp; Jenkins, 1999). Our program strategies are designed to appeal to girls.&lt;br/&gt;They include having fun with computers; linking technology with its real-world &lt;br/&gt;application; focusing the game content on social issues; using a collaborative &lt;br/&gt;instructional model; involving technical female role models, school teachers and &lt;br/&gt;program staff; and assessing the impact of game design on participants as well as&lt;br/&gt;the teachers and staff.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed intervention will be evaluated using a quasi-experimental, pre-post test&lt;br/&gt;design. Two hypotheses will be tested. First, compared to the control group, the &lt;br/&gt;participants in the intervention group will report a greater increase in problem-solving&lt;br/&gt;and computer skills, interest in computers, positive attitude toward computers, intention &lt;br/&gt;to pursue computer studies, confidence using computers, knowledge about tech careers,&lt;br/&gt;and support to pursue a career in technology. Second, the instructional model that uses &lt;br/&gt;collaboration with peers and guidance from teachers, staff, and female role models &lt;br/&gt;will increase the adults' capacity and interest to support girls active participation&lt;br/&gt; in technology, and challenge stereotypes about who is good at computers. Data will &lt;br/&gt;be collected using surveys, interviews, and student notebooks. The findings will result &lt;br/&gt;in a replicable version of the program that can be used to increase girls interest in &lt;br/&gt;technology and adults capacity to support them in other school and after school settings.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0217221</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
      <LastName>Denner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jilld@etr.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>ETR Associates</Name>
      <CityName>Scotts Valley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950663248</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314384060</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 Enterprise Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
