<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PLN - Creating the Next Generation of Women Leaders in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29940</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Ruta Sevo</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PLN - Creating the Next Generation of Women Leaders in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Pima County Superintendent of Schools, a local education agency (LEA) will &lt;br/&gt;develop and pilot an after school program for Hispanic 5th and 6th grade girls --&lt;br/&gt;Creating the Next Generation of Women Leaders in Science, Technology, Engineering&lt;br/&gt;and Mathematics (STEM). Creating Leaders combines innovative leadership training &lt;br/&gt;with enhanced STEM programming. The Creating Leaders program is innovative and &lt;br/&gt;builds on research that has identified elements of successful programming for Hispanic &lt;br/&gt;girls. Innovative components of this program include: 1.combining leadership development &lt;br/&gt;training with STEM enrichment; 2. teaching practical applications of mathematics in finance &lt;br/&gt;and investment; 3. linking STEM with politics and public policy; 4. developing partnerships&lt;br/&gt;between women in STEM careers, 5th and 6th grade girls and their parents; and 5. awarding &lt;br/&gt;STEM mini-grants to elementary and middle school girls.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Outcomes of the planning grant will include:&lt;br/&gt;1. A more extensive literature search to inform curriculum design and program planning;&lt;br/&gt;2. The development of curricula for the after school program to be utilized with Hispanic&lt;br/&gt; girls in 5th and 6th grades and their parents;&lt;br/&gt;3. The development of an Advisory Board;&lt;br/&gt;4. The development of partnerships for implementing the program at multiple sites;&lt;br/&gt;5. A pilot test of the after school program in one elementary school;&lt;br/&gt;6. Focus groups with participants in the pilot; and&lt;br/&gt;7. The development of a full proposal for the Creating Leaders program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Creating Leaders after school program will be piloted in the Elvira Elementary&lt;br/&gt;School in Tucson, Arizona. The culturally relevant program components are designed&lt;br/&gt;to work synergistically to make SMET fun and relevant to real life, raise SMET literacy,&lt;br/&gt;reinforce learning through hands-on activities, allow girls to practice their newly &lt;br/&gt;acquired skills and knowledge through community problem solving, and inspire girls to&lt;br/&gt;pursue STEM coursework, careers, and leadership positions in STEM fields. Program &lt;br/&gt;activities include:&lt;br/&gt;1. Playing the Real Game which teaches students about the global economy while &lt;br/&gt;reinforcing the importance of teamwork and cooperation.&lt;br/&gt;2. Raising financial literacy by playing the Cashflow Game which teaches about investing,&lt;br/&gt;rate of return, business ownership, and calculating cash flow;&lt;br/&gt;3. Attending field trips to organizations which employ women in STEM careers and &lt;br/&gt;local colleges and universities.&lt;br/&gt;4. Utilizing women in STEM careers and high school students to serve as role models&lt;br/&gt; and mentors.&lt;br/&gt;5. Leadership development activities.&lt;br/&gt;6. Teaching girls to develop proposals for funding and receive mini-grants to solve a &lt;br/&gt;community problem using STEM.&lt;br/&gt;7. Learning about the relationship between STEM, politics and public policy.&lt;br/&gt;8. Developing STEM educational and career goals through academic and career planning.&lt;br/&gt;9. Involving family members in supporting girls STEM educational and career goals.&lt;br/&gt;10. Developing on-line e-tools for teachers and girls in the program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This multi-disciplinary program will provide significant advances in knowledge in&lt;br/&gt;the fields of education, leadership development, public policy, and the wide range of&lt;br/&gt;Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math fields. The activities proposed will broaden &lt;br/&gt;the discovery and understanding of how to successfully reach underrepresented groups&lt;br/&gt;and will promote teaching, training, and learning among K-12 staff and administrators, &lt;br/&gt;students, families, women in STEM careers, and organizations which employ them.&lt;br/&gt;Creating Leaders will impact knowledge capital through the creation of a curriculum for&lt;br/&gt;use with Hispanic 5th and 6th grade girls and their families, social capital through&lt;br/&gt;the creation of a community-based partnership designed to improve the STEM achievement &lt;br/&gt;and career attainment of Hispanic girls, and human capital in the improvement in STEM &lt;br/&gt;educational and career attainment of Hispanic girls.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0217007</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Debbie</FirstName>
      <LastName>D'Amore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ddamore@schools.co.pima.az.us</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Parker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stephanie@aurora.tuccoxmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/12/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pima County School Superintendent's Office</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857011332</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5207408451</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>130 West Congress 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
