<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR: Systematic experimentation of the role of pedagogical agent features in promoting learning and motivation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>438846</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project systematically investigates the value of pedagogical agent features (*image: character, realism, gender, ethnicity; *animation: task-related, expressive; and *pre-defined agent roles: expert, motivational advisor, co-collaborator) in supporting learning-related outcomes. Using Multiple Intelligent Mentors Instructing Collaboratively (MIMIC) as the research environment, the standard experimental research design includes multiple factors and will be analyzed primarily via MANOVA. Additional micro-genetic data from logged agent-learner interactions and supplemental case studies triangulate the findings. All participants are individually randomly assigned to treatment conditions with large sample sizes (125-200 students), including educational technology undergraduate students from both a state university and a historically black university. The instructional content focuses upon the ill-structured domain of instructional planning with diverse learning outcomes, including metacognition, cognitive strategies, attitude/motivation, as well as traditional performance. Through extensive dissemination of results to the relevant multi-disciplinary communities, this project proposes to: a) illuminate principles of learning with pedagogical agents, b) facilitate computer scientists in prioritizing areas of future development for pedagogical agents; c) inform teachers of the most desirable characteristics of agent-based applications for their&lt;br/&gt;students; d) refine key features for pedagogical agents within distance learning course nvironments; and, e) advise instructional systems designers in developing training systems for industry and government.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0218692</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baylor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baylor@coe.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida State University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1686</Code>
      <Text>ITR SMALL GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1687</Code>
      <Text>ITR MEDIUM (GROUP) GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7314</Code>
      <Text>ITR FOR NATIONAL PRIORITIES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1657</Code>
      <Text>SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC IMPLICATIONS OF IT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
