<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Modification of Carbon Nanotubes with Boron Carbide Nanolumps for Nanocomposite</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>286212</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Clark V. Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0219836 Wen &lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A new approach to enhance load transfer from polymer matrix to carbon nanotubes by modifying multiwalled carbon nanotubes will be developed under an SGER award. The approach is based on the modification of multiwalled carbon nanotubes (MWNT) by growing boron carbide nanolumps on nanotubes. Boron carbide is a covalent bonding compound, so the bonding between boron carbide and carbon nanotube is expected to be covalent too. In addition to this strong bonding, boron carbide nanolumps can be also bonded to inner layers of MWNTs through covalent bonding. Thus, the load transfer from a matrix to carbon nanotubes can be dramatically increased since usually only the outermost layer of MWNTs contributes to carrying load. This is because the interaction between cylindrical graphene sheets is through relatively weak van der Waals bonding. Therefore, MWNTs with boron carbide nanolumps are expected to be the ideal reinforcing fillers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will start from the synthesis of MWNTs with boron carbide nanolumps on a large scale. Secondly, the mechanical properties of the dispersed and aligned nanotube/polymer composite will be measured in order to understand the influence of boron carbide nanolumps. Finally, a direct observation of load transfer using transmission electron microscopy by applying in-situ tensile stress on a microtomed slice of the nanotube/polymer composite will be carried out. This test will utilize a specially fabricated in-situ tensile loading holder. This project will present a unique opportunity for carbon nanotube applications in light-weight super-strength materials.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0219836</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zhifeng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ren</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>renzh@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>J. G.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jgwen@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/16/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0109000</Code>
      <Name>Structural Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1633</Code>
      <Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
