<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Modeling Inelastic Response of Reinforced Concrete Columns and Steel (RCS) Connections For Use in Performance-Based Evaluation of RCS Frame Structures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199808</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas A. Foutch</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>RCS structures consisting of reinforced concrete columns and steel beams are a cost-effective type of construction in seismic zones. Models for RCS joints have been restricted to either strength models or monotonic force-deformation models based on experimental results. The behavior of joints typically encountered in frame structures, such as connections with strong outer panels and T-configurations, is not well known. Inelastic behavior of connections with strong outer panels could significantly differ from that of joints with strong inner panel. Bearing failures might represent a threat in T-joints because of the lack of a column section above the connection. Macro models that simulate the behavior of RCS connections in shear and bearing for performance-based design will be developed based on new and existing experimental and analytical results. These models will include the effect of confinement, concrete softening, and relative strength contribution from shear resistance mechanisms on hysteretic response of RCS joints.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0219503</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wight</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwight@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gustavo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Parra-Montesinos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gparra@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
