<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR: Network-Oriented Memory Hierarchies for Internet Servers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy M. Pinkston</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Main memory has long been the weak link in high-performance Internet-connected computer systems, sandwiched between continuing rapid increases in both network bandwidths and CPU performance. As&lt;br/&gt;networks reach 10 Gb/s and CPU clock rates shoot past 2 GHz, the memory system is under more pressure than ever to keep up. Meanwhile, increased transistor counts are enabling integration of multi-megabyte&lt;br/&gt;caches and DRAM controllers directly on the processor device, with switched interconnects built from high-speed point-to-point channels carrying I/O and memory coherence traffic between chips.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This inflection point in the configuration, level of integration, and capacity of the memory hierarchy represents an opportunity to optimize the memory system for high-bandwidth Internet networking support.&lt;br/&gt;This research will (1) establish a baseline analysis to characterize the key bottlenecks of future memory hierarchies on Internet server workloads, and (2) evaluate specific system enhancements to address&lt;br/&gt;these bottlenecks, leading to more efficient, higher performance Internet server systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0219640</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Reinhardt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stever@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
