<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Joint NU-UIUC Project for the Development of New Integrated Tools for Predicting, Monitoring and Controlling Ground Movements due to Excavations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2153505</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard J. Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CMS-0219123&lt;br/&gt;PI: Richard J. Finno&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Northwestern University&lt;br/&gt;Title: "Collaborative: A joint NU-UIUC Project for Development of New Integrated Tools for Predicting, Monitoring and Controlling Ground Movements due to Excavations"&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The increased urbanization, population density and traffic congestion in major urban centers in the US has lead to a greater demand for underground space. Current homeland security concerns have prompted consideration of use of underground space for placement and protection of critical and sensitive infrastructure along urban corridors. With new development, and increasingly more redevelopment within the urban areas, there is a clear need to efficiently and safely develop underground space. A major concern when placing deep excavations in urban environments is the impact of construction-related ground movements on adjacent buildings and utilities. The ground movements cause structures supported by the affected ground to deform and possibly sustain damage. It is critically important to predict and control the magnitude and distribution of the ground movements that result from creating the underground space.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaborative research project aims to develop new, integrated tools for predicting, monitoring, and controlling ground movements associated with excavations in urban areas. The project is a joint venture between Northwestern University and the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will explore and develop new technologies that offer substantial promise for greatly enhancing the construction control process and attendant mitigation of ground deformations including: (1) field instrumentation and sensors with wireless communication capabilities, (2) data storage and display, including the display of construction progress and ground and building movements in a virtual reality environment, and, (3) intelligent, self-updating numerical models to simulate the excavation and support process and to compute anticipated ground and structure movements. These new technologies and improvements will be field tested in real time during excavation projects. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has strong educational and industry outreach components in addition to its research components. A group of contractors and engineering firms that have national practices will provide access to ongoing excavation projects and participate in the project advisory board. Faculty and their students from primarily undergraduate institutions will participate in the project.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0219123</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Finno</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>r-finno@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jamshid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ghaboussi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jghabous@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Youssef</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hashash</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hashash@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
