<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR: Collaborative Research: Accurate Representations of Signals in a Coarse-Grained Environment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>214970</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The aim is to provide a better mathematical framework and&lt;br/&gt;alternative design methodologies for coarse quantization of signals in&lt;br/&gt;a highly oversampled setting. The central themes is "sigma-delta&lt;br/&gt;quantization" in analog-to-digital conversion of audio signals and its&lt;br/&gt;counterpart "error-diffusion" in digital halftoning of images. In both&lt;br/&gt;cases, a given target analog signal is represented by a judiciously&lt;br/&gt;chosen one-bit (or few-bit) sequence which approximates the signal in a&lt;br/&gt;suitable low-pass subspace. A wide range of different schemes exist for&lt;br/&gt;this purpose, each corresponding to a different implementation and&lt;br/&gt;approximation order. As our primary mathematical objective, we expect&lt;br/&gt;to better understand the law of error decay of the existing schemes as&lt;br/&gt;well as to improve on these by new designs. On the algorithmic side, we&lt;br/&gt;aim to extend this analysis to settings with computational and other&lt;br/&gt;implementational constraints.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fact that digital signals and data sets can be processed, stored&lt;br/&gt;and retrieved with great precision and speed places high demands of&lt;br/&gt;accuracy on the conversion process from and to the analog world.&lt;br/&gt;However, the devices used in the translation process (such as in the&lt;br/&gt;case of analog-to-digital and digital-to-analog conversion circuits in&lt;br/&gt;audio applications, and printers in image reproduction) are of&lt;br/&gt;necessity analog devices, which have physical limitations that, at&lt;br/&gt;first sight, conflict with those accuracy demands. To cope with this&lt;br/&gt;problem, engineers have empirically developed special signal processing&lt;br/&gt;techniques leading to alternative signal and number representations&lt;br/&gt;that are quite different from standard decimal or binary&lt;br/&gt;representations. Typical techniques take advantage of the highly&lt;br/&gt;accurate performance of the analog devices in sampling very densely in&lt;br/&gt;time or space to compensate for the lack of amplitude precision of&lt;br/&gt;those devices. Interestingly, while these empirical schemes have proved&lt;br/&gt;efficient and have been used in consumer products for a long time, the&lt;br/&gt;corresponding framework of signal processing has little mathematical&lt;br/&gt;support. We aim to study these schemes in more detail, with the&lt;br/&gt;goals of improving the mathematical theory as well as proposing&lt;br/&gt;variants that outperform those used presently, and to identify a wider&lt;br/&gt;range of applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0219233</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ingrid</FirstName>
      <LastName>Daubechies</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ingrid@math.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Princeton University</Name>
      <CityName>Princeton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
