<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR: Invariant Detection and Interpretation of Specific Objects in Image Data</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>grace yang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Donald J Geman&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: ITR SMALL: Invariant Detection and Interpretation of Specific Objects in Image Data&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The area of investigation is automated scene analysis. The main objective is to detect the appearance in image data of objects from a small repertoire. Two key liabilities in current methods are insufficient invariance, both photometric and geometric, and inefficient computation. To confront these difficulties, a unified statistical and computational framework is proposed which is based on a coarse-to-fine sequence of approximations to a full Bayesian model. Research topics include both algorithmic and mathematical issues arising in coarse-to-fine search, model selection and deformable shape analysis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The interpretation of natural scenes is effortless for human beings but is the main challenge of artificial vision. This "semantic gap" has largely resisted any satisfying solution and impedes scientific and technological advances in many areas, including automated medical diagnosis, industrial automation, and effective security and surveillance. The general objective of this project is to design computer algorithms for detecting and interpreting certain objects appearing in still pictures in order to relieve humans of wearisome visual search tasks in medical imaging, law enforcement, industrial inspection and everyday life</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0219016</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yali</FirstName>
      <LastName>Amit</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>amit@galton.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Geman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>geman@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mim@cis.jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105168668</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
