<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Computer and Mathematics Scholar Support Alliance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>406265</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pratibha Varma-Nelson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;St. Joseph's College provides a strong academic education rooted in a liberal arts tradition. The CSEMS program will supplement existing scholarships to encourage and support thirty eligible students, with demonstrated financial need, enabling them to complete degrees and enter the high technology workforce as qualified professionals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Consistent with the CSEMS goals, we are:&lt;br/&gt;1. Increasing the number of well-educated and skilled employees in technical areas of national need by:&lt;br/&gt;Actively recruiting students, especially women and other under-represented groups for programs in Mathematics and Computer Sciences;&lt;br/&gt;Providing breadth and depth in a quality degree program;&lt;br/&gt;Maintaining and upgrading computer facilities and library resources;&lt;br/&gt;Creating a database of alumni, for a Speakers Bureau at recruitment events;&lt;br/&gt;Attracting younger competent students through high school Programming Competitions and class visitations.&lt;br/&gt;2. Improving educational opportunities for students in these disciplines by:&lt;br/&gt;Promoting opportunities for students to engage in activities and research which enhance their understanding;&lt;br/&gt;Expanding courses with an "Honors" component;&lt;br/&gt;Involving our majors as volunteer tutors and mentors in the Math Clinic to assist disadvantaged high school students.&lt;br/&gt;3. Increasing retention of students to degree achievement by:&lt;br/&gt;Providing additional scholarships of one-third tuition for qualified students, particularly underrepresented minorities and women;&lt;br/&gt;Formalizing our assessment and mentoring programs.&lt;br/&gt;4. Improving student support at institutions of higher learning by:&lt;br/&gt;Providing role models and individual mentors for students, particularly underrepresented minorities and women;&lt;br/&gt;Assessing the needs of the supported student, the effectiveness of the curriculum, and the requirements of the high tech workplace;&lt;br/&gt;Expanding peer tutoring in our Math Lab;&lt;br/&gt;Extending career and placement services to provide a database of industrial contacts;&lt;br/&gt;Increasing assistance to students applying to graduate programs;&lt;br/&gt;Strengthening "networking" opportunities to enhance interaction between current students and successful graduates.&lt;br/&gt;5. Strengthening partnerships between institutions of higher learning and the local high technology industry by:&lt;br/&gt;Extending internship programs and seeking additional partnerships with local business and industries;&lt;br/&gt;Promoting our BA/BS + MS program with Polytechnic University;&lt;br/&gt;Involving more faculty in education-industry collaboration programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recruitment from incoming and existing student populations are through personal invitations and current strategies (publications, TV, school visitations). Transfer students are recruited through cooperation with the local community college, business and industries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CSEMS Selection and CSEMS Retention Committees select students, encourage them to achieve and assure that they are qualified to enter the workforce. Both committees are by the PI and include the Co-PI's and appropriate representatives. One Co-PI is responsible for assessment and outcomes evaluation of CSEMS students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CSEMS scholars receive approximately one-third of their tuition at St. Joseph's College, where they receive personal attention in small classes, in a supportive learning environment. Internships and opportunities to contribute to their community reinforce classroom theory with practical experience, and to motivate them to complete their degrees.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0219800</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>S. Jane</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fritz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jfritz@sjcny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>McAllister</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wmcal@sjcny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seppala-Holtzman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dholtzman@sjcny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>St Joseph's College Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
      <ZipCode>112053688</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316875149</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>245 Clinton Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>CSEMS--CS, ENG &amp; MATH SCHOLAR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
