<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ITR: Sublinear Algorithms for Massive Data Sets</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>590000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard Beigel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Manipulating large scale data sources leads to question what are efficient algorithms. Even linear time algorithms may be much too slow on truly massive data. Similarly, even using linear space&lt;br/&gt;to store the data may be unreasonable when input data that is generated is far too voluminous. Applications abound where these constraints are natural. For example, data stores that archive web pages on the Internet, all telephone call records or molecular sequences are massive, and even linear time algorithms to process them prove slow. Data sources such as network traffic measurements are voluminous and rarely get archived; instead, it is desirable to process them as they are generated to obtain suitable sublinear space representations. Two approaches to building sublinear algorithms are sampling and streaming. In sampling, algorithms examine a (small) subset of input and solve problems of interest in sublinear time, typically to some provable approximation. While sampling has been studied in Probability and Statistics for decades, truly sublinear algorithms for sophisticated tasks such as clustering and building fourier representations have only recently been obtained. The algorithms should have solid theoretical foundations, and should be amenable to analysis using rigorous theoretical tools. However, some of the algorithms will be also implemented and subjected to experimental evaluation. It is expected that the algorithms developed in the context of this project&lt;br/&gt;will have significant practical impact.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0220280</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Piotr</FirstName>
      <LastName>Indyk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>indyk@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Shanmugavelayu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muthukrishnan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>muthu@cs.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/20/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1686</Code>
      <Text>ITR SMALL GRANTS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>T473</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code/>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9216</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
