<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Graduate/Undergraduate Engineering Initiative for Development and Enhancement (GUIDE)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Duncan E. McBride</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Michigan Technological University's College of Engineering strives to attract and retain more students from underrepresented groups, specifically women and minorities. This project supports undergraduate students during their first two years of college. The goal is for these high-risk students to perform well early in their college career with the expectation that their strong performance will help them to obtain alternate funding sources (e.g.: co-op and internship positions) during the latter two years of study. In addition, the project provides graduate scholarships for engineering students who are in unfunded programs so that they can cost effectively complete an advanced degree. The project builds upon and utilizes pre-existing campus programs, campus Learning Centers, and peer tutoring programs. To facilitate undergraduate success, students attend and participate in the engineering seminar series and the Career Center Workshops associated with this program. They regularly meet with their mentor and the program advisor. To retain their scholarships, undergraduate students need to show satisfactory progress towards their degree, become active in an on-campus professional organization, and work toward obtaining a co-op/internship position. The graduate scholars serve as academic mentors to the undergraduate scholars and offer insights regarding student life and the local community. Two groups of graduate students are targeted for the scholarships: Peace Corps International Masters students and the Master of Engineering students. (These graduate students are not typically eligible for traditional funding sources.) Graduate students in both programs are ideally suited to be mentors to undergraduate students: they have received a technical undergraduate degree and are interested in working with and supporting others. The graduate students receive training in mentoring and advising students. All target group engineering graduate and undergraduate students entering Michigan Tech are sent information and a scholarship application in the spring of each year of the program. Faculty/ staff evaluate the applicants based on need and individual merit. Each undergraduate scholarship recipient receives $2,500 per year to assist with college expenses. Each graduate scholarship recipient receives $3,125 per year to assist with college expenses. The graduate students receive funding for one year (the amount of time they are on campus for their degree program), while the undergraduate students are funded for two years. The interaction of undergraduates and graduate students is one of the most important components of this program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0220500</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mihelcic</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jm41@eng.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gretchen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>glhein@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Monte</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aemonte@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
      <CityName>Houghton</CityName>
      <ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
