<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Electromagnetic Modeling of Cylindrical Waveguide-Based Deielctric Resonator Amplifier Arrays for Spatial Power Combiners</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>232000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eric G Johnson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal addresses two areas of critical emerging technology in the microwave and millimeter wave regions. The first area is the fundamental characteristics of dielectric resonator antennas and finite antenna arrays operating in a cylindrical waveguide environment. The study and analysis of single dielectric resonator antenna element show the advantages of this new antenna type at millimeter wave frequencies in comparison with traditionally used microstrip and patch printed antennas. This new radiator is expected to be an excellent element in antenna arrays used in many critical applications. This part of the project focuses on the development of new analytical and numerical tools for full-wave analysis of antenna radiation characteristics and on the investigation of performance of dielectric radiators as elements in waveguide-based antenna arrays. Based on the understanding of dielectric resonator antenna performance in cylindrical waveguides, the second part of the project addresses the issue of modeling a fully integrated cylindrical waveguide-based spatial power combining amplifier array. A cylindrical spatial power combining architecture, which utilizes an array of dielectric resonators, is proposed. In this system, dielectric resonator antennas play a critical role, which is justified by their radiation characteristics and high power handling capabilities. Our goal here is to develop an integrated modeling scheme for the full-wave analysis of a complete waveguide-based spatial power combining system, including the interaction of passive (dielectric resonator and hard-horn antennas) elements and active (amplifier) circuits. The newly proposed system will allow to operate in dual and circular polarization regimes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; A high level educational component is considered here by training two graduate students during the course of this project that merge the basic research with high level practical applications. In order to broaden the scope of benefits, a new course will be developed to involve and expose more graduate students to this area. The course will be developed based on the study of dielectric resonator antennas in an array environment and the use of hard surfaces as an artificial magnetic surface.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0220218</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ahmed</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kishk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ahmed@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yakovlev</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yakovlev@olemiss.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Mississippi</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>386771848</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6629157482</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 BARR HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
