<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-India Cooperative Research: Digital Library Network</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>4440</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marjorie Lueck</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0220523&lt;br/&gt;Rahman &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Description: This award supports US-India cooperative research on the Digital Library Network. US PI Saifur Rahman of Virginia Polytechnic Institution (VPI) &amp; State University will collaborate with Sivaji Chakravorti and other faculty at Jadavpur University, Kolkata on developing lifelong learning materials for the Digital Library Network for Engineering and Technology (DLNET). The investigators will create protocols and content materials for a new portal through which contents can be both posted and accessed. The portal will provide a gateway for educational and research materials that are newly created by universities and professional associations in various engineering disciplines. It will also enhance the dissemination of new knowledge across disciplinary boundaries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Scope: This activity adds an international component to NSF supported research on the National Science, Mathematics, Engineering and Technology Education Digital Library. &lt;br/&gt;It will facilitate lifelong learning among engineering faculty, practicing engineers and technical professionals, a practice that is gradually becoming a major thrust in developed and developing countries alike. Digital libraries and their content development is a major area of investigation, in which experts from all over the world and in various fields can contribute to its successful culmination. The faculty at Jadavpur University is experienced in the design of web-based materials; the students are well-versed in modern software techniques. The award will support an exchange of visits between Rahman and Chakravorti. Jadavpur University will host the US PI's visit to Kolkata.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0220523</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Saifur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rahman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Srahman@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/02/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
