<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Probabilistic Model for Microstructure Evolution with Application to Smart Concrete Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>271717</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Perumalsamy N. Balaguru</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project proposes to formulate methods for representing and analyzing random&lt;br/&gt;heterogeneous materials in three directions. First, general probabilistic models are developed&lt;br/&gt;for the microstructure of cement based composites with carbon fibers. The models&lt;br/&gt;are random fields characterizing the geometrical, mechanical, and electrical properties of the&lt;br/&gt;material constituents. These cement based composites have an interesting microstructure,&lt;br/&gt;and are used in both mechanics and electronics as sensors of mechanical properties. Second,&lt;br/&gt;a computational environment is developed for calculating the evolution in time of the&lt;br/&gt;properties of microstructures subjected to deterministic loads. Finite element procedures&lt;br/&gt;are used to calculate changes in, for example, the stress, strain, damage and electric fields&lt;br/&gt;in cement based composite specimens generated from their probabilistic models. Development&lt;br/&gt;of the finite element code entails advances in numerical solver techniques as well as&lt;br/&gt;formulation of new mathematically sound traction-displacment relationships to model cohesive&lt;br/&gt;fracture. Third, the results of the finite element analyses are used to (i) update&lt;br/&gt;the probabilistic models of the material microstructure so they reflect the current damage&lt;br/&gt;state and (ii) develop macroscopic damage models for cement based composites by using&lt;br/&gt;homogenization procedures.&lt;br/&gt;The evolution of the material state is monitored by a mathematical object, referred&lt;br/&gt;to as digital material (DM), that defines uniquely the state of the microstructure at any&lt;br/&gt;time during loading and can be stored in the computer. The results of the analytical and&lt;br/&gt;numerical developments are validated against experimental tests providing information of&lt;br/&gt;the properties of the fiber matrix interaction and on the dependence of electric conductivity&lt;br/&gt;of macroscopic specimens on their damage state.&lt;br/&gt;The main outcome of the project is a novel methodology for predicting structural behavior&lt;br/&gt;of composite materials and for designing materials with better structural properties&lt;br/&gt;and better capabilities for sensing damage and strain. Other outcomes include new finite&lt;br/&gt;element codes, new mathematical models, and a strong educational outreach program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0220327</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Katerina</FirstName>
      <LastName>Papoulia</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>papoulia@civmail.uwaterloo.ca</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mircea</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grigoriu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mdg12@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
