<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Computer Science, Engineering, and Mathematics Scholarships Program (CSEMS)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lee L. Zia</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is creating a comprehensive scholars program for students whose goals are to pursue degrees and careers in high technology fields. The program provides $3,000 scholarships annually to 30 students who have academic ability and documented financial need, and who enroll full-time in our computer science, engineering, network technology or computer information systems (CSEM) associate degree programs. The program particularly targets women and first generation college students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two activities in particular contribute to the overall success of the scholarship recipients, as well as other students enrolled in these high technology curricula. The activities are:&lt;br/&gt;(a) intensive instructional support for historically difficult classes. A supplemental instruction program assists students in the targeted curricula who are enrolled in classes that have high attrition rates. Each of the five courses identified as historically difficult is a requirement for at least one of the CSEMS degree programs.&lt;br/&gt;(b) creation of a community of scholars to engage students receiving the CSEMS scholarships, faculty, alumni, local high school faculty, and local industry representatives in developing relationships and fostering an environment that supports and inspires students to achieve. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project builds on existing relationships between high school faculty and guidance counselors to recruit and enroll academically gifted students. Student development events include annual scholars' reception, open house and a high technologies career forum. Opportunities for student enrichment activities, including internships with local industry, faculty mentoring, and field trips are being developed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the program are to increase the number of :&lt;br/&gt;(1) educated workers prepared for placement in the high technology careers, especially in the region.&lt;br/&gt;(2) students recruited, enrolled, retained, graduated and transferring in the CSEMS disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;(3) underrepresented populations (women and first generation college students) enrolled and graduated in CSEMS majors.&lt;br/&gt;(4) quality of support services and educational opportunities available to students enrolled in the targeted curricula.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These goals are being assessed and evaluated by measuring annual rates of retention, graduation and transfer; subsequent success of transfer students at baccalaureate institutions; and employer satisfaction with our graduates.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0220655</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Penrose</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jpenrose@sunyjefferson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Genny</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pond</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>GPond@sunyjefferson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Oliver</FirstName>
      <LastName>Youst</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>oyoust@sunyjefferson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
      <LastName>Donato</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jdonato@sunyjefferson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dittrich</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ldittrich@sunyjefferson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Jefferson Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Watertown</CityName>
      <ZipCode>136011822</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3157862200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1220 Coffeen Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
