<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Clearing a Path for Talented and Needy Students to Pursue Careers in Computer Science and Information Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>393200</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Pratibha Varma-Nelson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project allows talented and needy students the opportunity to pursue their educational dreams in the field of computer science or information technology at Armstrong Atlantic State University. More specially, 28 two-year scholarships to undergraduates in computer science, 12 two-year scholarships to graduate students in computer science, and ten four-year scholarships to undergraduates in information technology would be awarded.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Having a typical class size of less than twenty and an in-state cost of $3,969 for tuition, room and board, and fees for undergraduates, Armstrong Atlantic offers one of the best educational values in computer science or information technology in the country. Armstrong Atlantic's student body is 70% female and 30% of the students are minorities. Many of these students are unable to remain in school due to job pressures, broken homes, and/or lack of financial resources. This project would change the lives of 50 individuals by providing scholarships so that they can pursue their studies full-time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A comprehensive plan is in place for recruitment, selection, support, and job placement issues. The recruitment plan includes developing brochures, pamphlets, and Web materials; advertising on bulletin boards and newspapers; attending college fairs and University open houses; and visiting high schools among other things. The selection process involves a well-defined set of criteria, a numerical evaluation form, student interviews, and selection committee discussion. Support for scholars includes community building, student activities, advising, mentoring, and tutoring. Job placement involves advising, internships, resume preparation, ACM and IEEE discussions, meetings with industry representatives, Savannah's Business and Educational Technical Alliance, and discussions with Armstrong Atlantic's Director of Career Services among other events.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0220199</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
      <LastName>Greenlaw</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>raymond.greenlaw@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Burge</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mburge@acm.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>05/04/2005</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
      <LastName>McCarthy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chris.mccarthy@armstrong.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/03/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Armstrong Atlantic State University</Name>
      <CityName>Savannah</CityName>
      <ZipCode>314191997</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9123442875</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11935 ABERCORN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
