<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Synthetic Routes to Main-Group Inorganic Solids</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>410709</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>David Nelson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project focuses on the synthesis of novel solid-state inorganic materials, including epitaxial growth of device-quality thin-film heterostructures and nanostructures. These materials will have applications in microelectronics, optoelectronics, and refractory ceramics. A unique aspect of this effort in materials design and synthesis is the ability to build in precise atomic arrangements primarily via molecular chemistry so as to overcome thermodynamic impediments arising from differences in atomic sizes, electronic level filling and electronegativities of constituent atoms and thereby form new and metastable materials that cannot be obtained by conventional routes. The range of target materials includes: (a) New semiconductors in the C-Si-Ge-Sn system, which are intended for integration of Si-based microelectronics with optical components; (b) Quaternary wide bandgap optical materials based on covalent carbides and nitrides of the main group; (c) Si based superhard dielectric materials and diamond-like compounds comprising light elements. The electronic structure, band structure, optical, dielectric, mechanical and structural properties of these materials are thoroughly investigated by experimental as well as theoretical methods. The work is well suited to provide broad preparation and state-of-the-art skills to undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral student researchers in synthetic solid-state chemistry and materials science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research has significant potential for high impact in important areas of national interest including areas such as new optical, semiconducting, and superhard/ultrastrong materials, which are of interest to microelectronics and defense industries. The research provides fundamental knowledge in novel device chemistry and physics, and thus makes important contributions to emerging and future technologies such as, high-speed computers, full color displays and communication and detection systems. In addition to significant research and technological accomplishments which include US and international patents, the work provides graduate and postdoctoral training to new generations of scientists and engineers in the preparation and processing of new materials and in the art of chemical vapor deposition, which is a vital field in the microelectronics industry. Collaborations are ongoing with local industries to develop materials for use in silicon-based high-speed electronic devices as well as new generations of solid-state lighting systems that are energy efficient and environmentally safe. The group maintains international collaborations and outreach with researchers in Germany, Norway, Mexico, and the Czech Republic.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0221993</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kouvetakis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jkouvetakis@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
