<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Japan Cooperative Science: Terahertz and Infrared Studies of 6.1-Angstrom Semiconductor Structures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myra McAuliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0221704&lt;br/&gt;Kono&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a two-year collaborative research project between Professor Junichiro Kono at Rice University in Houston, Texas and Professor Noboru Miura at the University of Tokyo in Japan. The researchers will undertake studies on structures fabricated from the 6 Angstrom III-V semiconductors. Their goal is to increase the fundamental understanding of these quantum structures. They will be undertaking magneto-optic studies in very high (up to 600 T) magnetic fields at Rice University and carrying out additional experiments utilizing the Free Electron Lasers at the University of California at Santa Barbara and at Stanford. They will also be performing ultrahigh field magneto-optics experiments at the Megagauss Laboratory (MGL) in Tokyo. This is a unique high field facility where different types of high-field magnets are available. Finally, theoretical efforts at understanding and interpreting the spectroscopy experiments will be provided by some of the researchers that have expertise in optical, transport, and electronic properties of bulk and quantum confined semiconductors and devices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project brings together the efforts of two laboratories that have complementary expertise and research capabilities. The U.S. researchers have expertise in optical spectroscopy of semiconductors, THz dynamics of semiconductors using free electron lasers and theoretical input. The Japanese researchers have expertise in the growth of magnetic structures, knowledge of electronic and optoelectronic devices, growth of mesoscopic structures, high-speed electron transport and optical properties and devices. &lt;br/&gt;It is likely that some of the interesting properties/phenomena learned in these systems will be used in future semi-conducting devices. The research will offer a good opportunity to join efforts between the two countries. Through the exchange of ideas and technology, this project will broaden our base of basic knowledge and promote international understanding and cooperation. A number of postdocs, graduate students and undergraduate students from the participating institutions will also be participating in the research. The researchers plan to distribute the results of their findings through the Web, publications and presentations at conferences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0221704</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Junichiro</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kono</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>kono@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
