<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Evolution of Biogenic Exopolymer Concentrations and Interaction with Physical Structure in Arctic Sea Ice</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>562444</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William J. Wiseman, Jr.</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Krembs&lt;br/&gt;0221055&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Exopolymeric substances (EPS) comprise a suite of microbially produced, structurally diverse polysaccharides that play important roles in organismal physiology, aquatic ecology, and the oceanic "biological carbon pump". High concentrations of EPS are known to significantly alter the physical properties of water containing habitats as diverse as rocks, aquifers and sediments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;EPS have long been observed in high concentrations in polar seas. They have recently been observed in high concentrations in arctic sea ice with an unknown variable, poorly understood balance of microbial production in the ice and loss via biochemical conversion and export at the ice-water interface. The PIs have also observed a relationship between EPS concentration and sea ice salinity, which indicates a fundamentally new and prospectively consequential interaction between biological processes and the physical structure of Arctic sea ice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The difficulty of separating temporal from spatial variability in ice core observations impedes understanding of environmental forcing of the balance of EPS production and losses. Neither can ice core methods illuminate the key process of biomass incorporation at the ice-water interface, nor the mechanism (and thus environmental sensitivity) underlying the covariation of EPS concentration and salinity. Thus effects of changing arctic climate on marine ecology, carbon cycling, and sea ice properties via EPS production cannot be assessed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant sets out to investigate the environmental factors leading to high EPS production and interaction with arctic sea ice physical properties using a combination of field observations and theory for sea ice growth. The group will collect and analyze fast ice core samples over the course of three ice seasons to track the evolution of the autotrophic community and the organic material pool. They will apply theory for the growth of sea ice to investigate the mechanism(s) of salt retention and biological influence on ice physical properties, and develop and apply nondestructive, in situ fluorometric measurements of Chlorophyll a in the water column and in the ice to observe the key process of biomass incorporation at the ice-water interface. This work will build a basis for automated in situ acquisition of time series of the dynamic of sea ice biota across the ice-water interface, which will be essential for future investigations of large scale polar marine ecological changes in response to varying climate.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0221055</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wettlaufer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>john.wettlaufer@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dale</FirstName>
      <LastName>Winebrenner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dpw@apl.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krembs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ckrembs@apl.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/11/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0311000</Code>
      <Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5205</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESRCH SUPPRT &amp; LOGISTI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5280</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC NATURAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
