<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research in DRMS: Global Climate Change: Risk Perceptions and Behavior</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11414</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the roles of affective imagery and cultural&lt;br/&gt;worldviews in risk perception, decision-making and behavior, using global&lt;br/&gt;climate change as a case study. Past research has focused on the role of&lt;br/&gt;cognitive factors like knowledge, mental models and general environmental&lt;br/&gt;beliefs in risk perceptions of climate change. Recent research, however, has&lt;br/&gt;also begun to focus on the role of affective factors. This project will&lt;br/&gt;develop and test affective image analysis as an innovative method to study&lt;br/&gt;public risk perceptions along both cognitive and affective dimensions.&lt;br/&gt;Additionally, cultural theorists argue that cultural worldviews are also&lt;br/&gt;important factors and need to be included as explanatory variables. This&lt;br/&gt;project will operationalize and test the predictions of cultural theory.&lt;br/&gt;Finally, many researchers assume that risk perceptions and behaviors&lt;br/&gt;correlate, yet little focused research has been done. This research will&lt;br/&gt;test this assumption, using climate change as a case study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project also addresses several applied questions: Does the American&lt;br/&gt;public perceive global climate change as a serious risk? What specifically&lt;br/&gt;do they fear about it? Do these risk perceptions translate into personal&lt;br/&gt;actions and/or support for mitigation policies? This research will&lt;br/&gt;contribute to the continuing discussion on global climate change, as&lt;br/&gt;scientists and policymakers attempt to find scientifically appropriate and&lt;br/&gt;publicly acceptable solutions to this global problem.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0221896</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Slovic</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pslovic@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
      <CityName>Eugene</CityName>
      <ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1321</Code>
      <Text>DECISION RISK &amp; MANAGEMENT SCI</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
