<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Florida A&amp;M University Computer Science, Engineering, Engineering Technology and Mathematics Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>V. Celeste Carter</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The faculty at Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University proposes to continue their NSF Computer Science, Engineering, Engineering Technology and Mathematics Scholarship (CSEMS) Program to provide an additional thirty talented students, who are majoring in these disciplines, with individual scholarships of up to $3,125 per year. Award amounts will be based upon academic achievement and will provide supplementary income to students with financial need. Their participating major departments are electrical, mechanical, civil, chemical, industrial engineering, electrical engineering technology, construction engineering technology, computer and information sciences, biological and agricultural engineering systems and mathematics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Their CSEMS program will also provide scholars with the necessary support and experiences to be successful and competitive in graduate schools or in careers of the CSEM disciplines. The program will continue to assist the CSEM scholars for two years following the receipt of the academic degree to assure a successful transition to graduate programs or career paths. CSEM Scholars will be selected in Spring 2002 and will commence activities in Fall 2002. Their program includes faculty advising mentoring as well as technical professional development seminar series. In addition they provide summer internships in industrial or governmental setting and graduate school/career counseling and placement. These program enhancement activities and scholarship funds are expected to enable their CSEMS Scholars to complete the degree requirements within the appropriate time frame as determined by the academic level, up to four years.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0221402</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>edjones_phd@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roselyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Williams</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Roselyn.Williams@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deidre</FirstName>
      <LastName>Evans</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>deidre.evans@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/13/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University</Name>
      <CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>323073200</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8505993531</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lee Hall Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code/>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>CSEMS--CS, ENG &amp; MATH SCHOLAR</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
