<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Plan for Comprehensive STEM Program Assessment</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49621</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11060000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwa Community College (LCOOCC) will enhance the ability of rural and minority populations on and near the Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwa reservation in northwestern Wisconsin and at two outreach sites that serve the Bad River and Red Cliff bands of Ojibwa to succeed in careers in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM). The College will undertake a comprehensive assessment of community needs as well as institutional strengths and weaknesses in STEM fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Assessment outcomes will drive systemic reform strategies, lead to more effective use of limited resources and further the development of the nation's technologically based workforce. Primary goals of the project are threefold: (1) assessment of community and employer needs and opportunities for STEM-related education and professionals; (2) identification of strategies for increasing student enrollment, retention and graduation in STEM foundation courses and program areas; and, (3) evaluation of STEM student performance to eliminate bottlenecks and strengthen STEM competencies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0222896</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scott</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scott@lco-college.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lac Courte Oreilles Ojibwa Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Hayward</CityName>
      <ZipCode>548439419</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7156344790</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>13466 W Trepania Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
