<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Challenges and Future of Ubiquitous Computing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>29781</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This workshop will investigate the research issues and future associated with the new field of ubiquitous computing, which is centered on a vision of a world populated by networks of cheap and easily accessible computing devices. Such a vision has generated a great deal of excitement as there is a potential for improving the quality of our everyday lives. However, the realization of such a vision requires the resolution of a number of difficult technological and social problems. One major challenge is the interdisciplinary nature of such an endeavor, which requires coordinated advances in many fields of computer science including network design, security, user interfaces, coordination and collaboration theories, privacy, agent technologies, and mobile computing hardware. This workshop will focus on 1) supporting technology areas, 2) promising application areas, 3) research issues, and 4) evaluation methods. The steering committee spans both relevant technology and application areas. Position papers will be invited before the workshop. Formal papers will be gathered into a book-length manuscript after the workshop.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0222781</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ortiz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ortiz@ai.sri.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SRI International</Name>
      <CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
      <ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6508592651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
