<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CMG: Microstructural Controls on Transport Processes in Geophysical Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>350098</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020106</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Peter J. Milne</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A combination of mathematical and numerical modeling, laboratory experiments, field experiments, and three-dimensional data visualization techniques will be applied to the problem of determining the influence of the microscale pore structure of sea-ice on the macroscopic thermodynamic and fluid transport properties of such ice. The work represents a collaboration between a mathematician, a glaciologist and a computer scientist. A variety of mathematical approaches, including both lattice and continuum percolation representations, to modeling the bulk properties of irregular three-dimensional media will be applied to ice with varying degrees of connectivity between microscale brine inclusions. Field and lab experiments, including MRI and X-ray imaging of ice samples, will be combined with modern three-dimensional rendering of the resulting data to provide quantitative and qualitative information about the variability of such connectivity, particularly as a function of ice temperature. Model predictions of macroscopic permeability and thermal conductivity will be compared to experimentally measured transport properties. Through a collaboration with Dr. J. Fry at Victoria University, New Zealand, and student research projects, the models developed for transport in sea-ice will be extended to fluid migration through rock and the diffusion of gas through glacial firn. The latter is an important factor in the interpretation of paleo-atmospheric composition from bubbles trapped in ice-cores. The project also includes a substantial amount of training and outreach, with field work for graduate and undergraduate students, and classroom demonstrations and experiments in elementary and secondary schools.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0222312</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hajo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Eicken</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hajo.eicken@gi.alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1574</Code>
      <Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7215</Code>
      <Text>OPPORTUNITIES FOR RESEARCH CMG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7232</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL GEOSCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
