<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MUSES: Disposable and Reusable Textile Materials in Healthcare Facilities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>110000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Delcie R. Durham</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Biocomplexity in the Environment (BE) for Materials Use: Science, Engineering, and Society (MUSES) incubation activity will investigate the physical, sociological, and economic impacts of disposable and reusable textiles used in healthcare facilities. Exploratory research conducted by an interdisciplinary team consisting of a polymer chemist, a marketing expert and a social psychologist, intends to address questions raised about textile materials currently being used in healthcare facilities and to reassess economic and environmental consequences of using the materials. The analysis of the acceptance and potential impacts of new materials and technologies that are environmentally benign in the healthcare arena is the longer-term objective. Protective clothing and textiles in the medical sphere include surgical gowns, gloves, drapes, wraps, sheets, covers, and facemasks; these are composed of two different textile materials--disposable and reusable fabrics-that serve primarily to impede the transmission of pathogens in healthcare facilities. Disposables, also called non-woven fabrics, are mostly produced from polyethylene, polypropylene, and their blends. After usage, they should be immediately disposed of as bio-hazardous materials. In contrast, reusable textiles, such as those comprised of pure cotton fibers and certain polyesters, can be repeatedly used in healthcare facilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific research tasks include: (1) to determine the most effective, multi-functional (biocidal and water-repellent) materials for medical applications; (2) to assess the economic and environmental impact of using reusable biocidal textiles in the healthcare industry; (3) to determine the social and psychological factors affecting the acceptance of the new technology by healthcare workers. Educational activities include a) involving undergraduate and graduate student in the research and to incorporate the research results into a senior undergraduate course; b) providing educational materials to workers in healthcare community and other hazardous Cupertino as was as to manufacturers of textile materials; c) educating the public about the environmental and economic impacts as well as protective properties of the different textile materials in healthcare facilities. The results of this research will be used to make recommendations regarding materials that are environmentally benign, protect against pathogens and are acceptable to healthcare workers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0223987</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kaiser</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbkaiser@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sun</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gysun@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rucker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mhrucker@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
      <CityName>Davis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
