<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Microbial Community Ecology of Tick-Borne Human Pathogens</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Samuel M. Scheiner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this research is to characterize the microbial communities of several common tick species using DNA sequence-based techniques, analyze patterns of co-occurrence among microbial taxa, and mathematically model the consequences of those patterns on epidemiological dynamics of tick-borne pathogens. In particular, tick-borne microbial communities will be analyzed for evidence of competitive exclusion or mutual facilitation among species. Ecological interactions among species are one of the most important factors shaping community structure. Much research has demonstrated that ticks may simultaneously harbor multiple bacterial species, including symbionts transmitted through eggs and pathogens transmitted through bites. Habitat alteration, expanding ranges of tick vectors, and increased populations of shared animal hosts make the movement of pathogenic microorganisms among tick species more likely. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On a worldwide basis, ticks serve as vectors for more human pathogens than any other arthropod. In the United States, the large majority of cases of vector-borne disease arise from tick bites (e.g. Lyme Disease), and new tick-borne pathogens are regularly being discovered. This research will contribute to our basic understanding of microbial communities of arthropods and the epidemiology of pathogen transmission. Further, this research will have a practical impact on management of tick-borne diseases and our understanding of the relationship between invasion of tick vectors and the emergence of novel, or more highly virulent, human pathogens.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0223813</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clay</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>CLAY@Indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Indiana University</Name>
      <CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8128550516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0312000</Code>
      <Name>Population</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1182</Code>
      <Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9169</Code>
      <Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
