<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Temperature Dependence of Neutral and Ionic Metal Combustion Kinetics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>329972</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Phillip R. Westmoreland</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Reactions of metal monohalides and monoxides of environmental concern are studied over wide temperature and pressure ranges. Similar measurements are &lt;br/&gt;made on combustion reactions of metal cations. Individual reactions will be&lt;br/&gt;studied in isolation using the Rensselaer HTFFR (high-temperature fast-flow reactor) and HTP (high-temperature photochemistry) reactors, suitable for the 300 to 1800 K temperature domain. Together these can be used to cover pressure from 10 to 1000 mbar. The measurements with these facilities are free from interference by other reactions; temperature, pressure, and concentrations can be varied independently.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Very little is known of the temperature dependence of the kinetics of ion-molecule reactions. Such reactions are usually observed below combustion temperatures, frequently in non-thermalized environments. The use of the HTP reactors allows study of bulk, temperature-equilibrated reactions by laser-induced fluorescence, LIF. The use of LIF provides a novel method for the study of ion-molecule reactions, which are commonly studied by mass spectrometry. Exothermic and endothermic as well as addition reactions of alkaline-earth cations of combustion interest are addressed. The results of this work are needed by combustion engineers, particularly modelers concerned with pollution abatement, and are also useful for workers in high-temperature materials, propulsion, chemical vapor deposition, and atmospheric chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0224778</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Arthur</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fontijn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fontia@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/29/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Troy</CityName>
      <ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
