<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Third International Conference on Numerical Solution of Volterra and Delay Equations; Tempe, Arizona, 2003</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS Award Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Award #: 0224848&lt;br/&gt;PI: Jackiewicz, Zdzislaw&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Arizona State University &lt;br/&gt;Program: Applied Mathematics&lt;br/&gt;Program Manager: Catherine Mavriplis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: The Numerical Solution of Volterra and Delay Equations&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this project is to organize the Third International Conference on the Numerical Solution of Volterra and Delay Equations. It will bring together leading world class experts in the newest numerical methods for delay equations, in the most recent aspects of high performance supercomputers, and in the most important applications (especially biological) that lead to Volterra problems. It will, for the first time, emphasize research and applications in the newly developing vast area of delay and Volterra partial differential and integral equations. The subject of Volterra equations includes functional differential equations (delay, advanced, and neutral) as well as delay and Volterra partial differential equations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Volterra equations have have important and crucial applications as models in diverse areas of science and engineering; e.g. biomathematics and medical science, population dynamics, control theory, electrodynamics, neutron transport theory, oscillation theory, and viscoelasticity. These applications arise in a variety of critical areas such as modeling of the spread of infectious diseases and biological agents like anthrax and smallpox, the design of nuclear reactors and weapons, aerospace technology, the guidance of drone weapons and intelligence vehicles, and even the design of super computers themselves. Since the solution of Volterra and delay equations can almost never be obtained in closed form, computational techniques must be used. By their nature, Volterra problems create enormous demands on computing resources (both on computer speed and memory) and therefore require the use of extremely high performance super computers. This conference will bring together the experts in these areas and will help to stimulate various research efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Date: June 25, 2002</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0224848</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feldstein</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>theorems@webtv.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Zdzislaw</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jackiewicz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jackiewicz@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
