<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Japan Joint Seminar: MLabNet 2000-Advanced Multimedia Systems and Applications</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5290</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myra McAuliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0089732&lt;br/&gt;Grosky&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the participation of American scientists in a U.S.-Japan seminar on MLabNet 2000-advanced multimedia systems and applications, to be held in Karuizawa, Japan from October 10-12, 2001. The co-organizers are professors William Grosky of Wayne State University and Professor Frederic Andres of the National Institute of Informatics (NII) in Tokyo, Japan. MlabNet is a virtual multimedia research framework between various institutions in the United States, Japan, France, Italy and Thailand and has existed since April 1999. Two important projects being investigated under this framework are the Very Large-Scale Hypermedia Delivery System (VLSHDS) and MediaSys, which provides an extensible interface for multimedia management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed seminar will include research presentations, posters, and demonstrations. It will assess the research cooperation inside MLabNet in the context of these projects, as well as address issues in information access and sharing multimedia content between the involved countries. They will also address issues in cultural heritage, in the context of future research issues related to the National Science Foundation framework, the Japanese Ministry of Education framework, and the Fifth Framework set by the European Union. Seminar organizers have made a special effort to involve younger researchers, postdocs and graduate students as both participants and observers. The exchange of ideas and data with Japanese experts in this field will enable U.S. participants to advance their own work, and will set the stage for future collaborative projects. Dissemination of information on the seminar will be available on the World Wide Web.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/29/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/29/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0224089</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grosky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wgrosky@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/29/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
