<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Renovation and Expansion of the Seawater System at the University of Texas - Pan American Coastal Studies Laboratory in Support of Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>44804</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080103</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Gerald Selzer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides partial support for renovation of the seawater system at the University of Texas - Pan American Coastal Studies Laboratory (CSL) on South Padre Island, Texas. The CSL supports research and educational activities of the University, and provides a variety of public education activities focused on marine life and related topics. The CSL is currently hampered in fulfilling this mission by the limited capabilities of its seawater system. These limits are imposed by the original design of the system, deterioration of the intake and discharge lines, and the aging of other equipment. The renovated system will have dual intake lines and pumps, sand-filtration, new plumbing for filtered water, and twin discharge lines. The system will support research on marine algae, seagrasses, and small marine animals. In addition to research, the seawater system will support general lab use, university and public outreach courses, and an aquarium intended for public displays.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/01/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0224832</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Don</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hockaday</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hockaday@utpa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hudson</FirstName>
      <LastName>DeYoe</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>HDEYOE@panam.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whelan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>twhelan3@panam.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/01/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley</Name>
      <CityName>Edinburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>785392909</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9566652889</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1201 West University Dr</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
