<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Third International Association for Mathematics and Computers in Simulation (IMACS) Conference on Nonlinear Evolution Equations and Wave Phenomena: Computation and Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award supports participants in The Third IMACS International Conference on Nonlinear Evolution Equations and Wave Phenomena: Computation and Theory, held at the University of Georgia on 7-10 April 2003. The interdisciplinary meeting, sponsored by the International Association for Mathematics and Computers in Simulation, focuses on computational and theoretical aspects of nonlinear waves and optical solitons, and brings together researchers in applied mathematics, computational mathematics, and applied physics. Topics of interest include theoretical aspects of solitons and integrability, nonlinear waves in fluids, symbolic and numeric computations for integrable evolution equations, numerical methods for nonlinear waves (symplectic, IST and Fast Fourier methods, adaptive methods of lines, parallel algorithms), nonlinear waves in optics, dispersion managed solitons in optical fibers, and advances in modeling optical fiber transmission systems. The interdisciplinary meeting will provide excellent opportunities for communication and collaboration between senior and junior researchers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0225143</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thiab</FirstName>
      <LastName>Taha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thiab@cs.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jerry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bona</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bona@math.uic.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/30/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
      <CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
