<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>NSF/CBMS Regional Conference in the Mathematical Sciences: Fully Nonlinear Equations in Geometry</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>31417</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lloyd E. Douglas</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The study of nonlinear partial differential equations is necessitated by countless problems&lt;br/&gt;from diverse disciplines: physics, economics, biology, etc. Fully nonlinear equations is a more recent subject within this field, but its importance is increasing due to the growing number of connections to other &lt;br/&gt;fields. In particular, the study of special Lagrangian submanifolds of Calabi-Yau manifolds is of particular interest in string theory, and consequently an active area of research among physicists and mathematicians alike.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Because of the rapid growth and broad interest of the field, it is a natural topic for a CBMS Regional Conference. Researchers and graduate students who are new to the field can see how geometric problems of current interest can be reformulated as problems in nonlinear PDE, and at the same time witness the often surprising ways in which the geometric aspects of the problem inform the analytic aspects (and vice versa).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Adding to the appeal of the meeting is the principal lecturer, Prof. Neil Trudinger. His reputation as an eminent researcher and gifted expositor make him an ideal choice to deliver the lectures. Moreover, the monograph resulting from the meeting will be of interest to scientists in a wide range of fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/21/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/03/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0225735</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gursky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mgursky@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Qing</FirstName>
      <LastName>Han</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Qing.Han.7@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/21/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
      <CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
      <ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Indiana</StateName>
      <StateCode>IN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
