<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>PREMISE: Environmental/Energy Comparative Analysis of Polymer Powder Coating Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99998</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jian Cao</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The technical approach in this Product Realization and Environmental Manufacturing Innovative Systems (PREMISE) project involves the selection of conventional batch polymerization processes in solvent media and comparison with alternative solventless continuous processes. Application of the produced solid powders will be compared by considering: a) conventional high temperature curing and b) lower temperature curing by UV radiation. The research plan includes detailed engineering calculations; cost comparison and application of life cycle analysis (LCA) principles and Design for Environment (DFE) methodologies to identify the potential advantages of the alternative systems as well as initiation of experimental work towards developing UV curable powder formulations in continuous solventless reactors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Polymeric powder coatings provide environmental and corrosion protection to a variety of substrates for civilian and military applications. By comparison to solvent based coatings whose application is often associated with significant VOC emissions, the production of powder-coated items is sometimes considered as a "green" process. However, there are still many elements in the lifecycle of conventional powder coated products, from manufacturing of the powder by polymerization to its subsequent application and curing, which are excessive in energy and solvent usage. Systems based on continuous bulk polymerization processes in the absence of solvents, followed by UV initiated curing at low temperatures appear to be excellent candidates for reduced energy usage and lower environmental impact versus conventional systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is highly relevant to the R&amp;D priorities of the coating industry, i.e. lower overall cost and lower curing temperatures along with low VOCs and hazardous air pollutants (HAPs). It is also relevant to the growing need in polymer engineering academic curricula to incorporate case studies related to industrial ecology and environmental issues in process/product design.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0225852</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marino</FirstName>
      <LastName>Xanthos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xanthos@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>323 DOCTOR MARTIN LUTHER</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
