<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: Sixth International Symposium On Cytochome P450 Biodiversity, to be held in Los Angeles, California, August 20-25, 2002</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Parag R. Chitnis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The cytochrome P450 monooxygenase superfamily of heme-containing enzymes contains a wide&lt;br/&gt;range of monooxygenase activities that make them critically important to virtually all&lt;br/&gt;life forms. In recent years, they have been shown to be important in human growth and&lt;br/&gt;development because they are involved in steroid biosynthesis and also in many&lt;br/&gt;pharmacological areas because they are critical for the activation and/or detoxification&lt;br/&gt;of drugs in human and vertebrate models. In a rapidly and ever-expanding area, they have&lt;br/&gt;been shown to be important in insect and plant growth and development because of their&lt;br/&gt;involvement in biosynthetic pathways for insect and plant hormones and in agricultural&lt;br/&gt;areas because they mediate the metabolism of herbicides, insecticides, fungicides and&lt;br/&gt;environmental pollutants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Realizing the growing importance of this area of plant and insect P450 research, the&lt;br/&gt;organizing committee for the International Symposium Series on P450 Biodiversity branched&lt;br/&gt;from the more classical area of vertebrate P450 research represented in the Symposium&lt;br/&gt;Series on Microsomes and Drug Oxidations to create an independent and focused series&lt;br/&gt;devoted to microorganisms, plants and insects. For the Sixth International Symposium on&lt;br/&gt;P450 Biodiversity: Functional Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology of P450 Cytochromes in&lt;br/&gt;Microorganisms, Plants and Insects, the organizers have endeavored to continue the&lt;br/&gt;examples set in the five previous meetings in this series by providing platforms for the&lt;br/&gt;presentation of approaches for expression analysis of model P450s as well as functional&lt;br/&gt;analysis of the numerous P450s existing in these non-vertebrate systems. The goal is to&lt;br/&gt;provide a forum for discussing leading research in the field through a single lecture&lt;br/&gt;series of 48 presentations interspersed with scheduled poster presentations and ample time&lt;br/&gt;for informal discussions. With this goal in mind, funds are requested to help support&lt;br/&gt;travel expenses for competitively identified advanced predoctoral and postdoctoral&lt;br/&gt;students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The International Advisory Board and Scientific Organizing Committee for this Series&lt;br/&gt;contains representatives from seven different countries including eleven from the United&lt;br/&gt;States. The meeting will be held August 20-25, 2002 at the Conference Center on the UCLA&lt;br/&gt;campus and hosted by Armand J. Fulco, Professor of Biochemistry at the University of&lt;br/&gt;California, Los Angeles (UCLA). Dr. Fulco's research has focused on characterization of&lt;br/&gt;bacterial cytochrome P450s through a variety of world-wide collaborations. It is expected&lt;br/&gt;that attendance at this meeting will be approximately 200 with participation from the&lt;br/&gt;United States, Europe and the Pacific Rim in approximately equal proportions.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0226565</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schuler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>maryschu@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1168</Code>
      <Text/>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9183</Code>
      <Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
