<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Purchase of X-Ray Diffractometer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>160000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Kuczkowski</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation and Facilities (CRIF) Program, the Department of Chemistry at the University of Nevada in Reno will upgrade an X-ray diffractometer with an area detector for small molecule crystallography. This equipment will enhance research in a number of areas including the following: a) investigations of metal-metal interactions in large cage complexes known as metallocryptands, probing metallophilic interactions between simple trigonally coordinated platinum and palladium phosphine complexes and heavy metal ions; b) development of ligands for aqueous or biphasic organometallic catalysis; c) synthesis and characterization of benzoid nanostructures focused on ribbon and helical structures; d) directed synthesis of short nanotubes and perfluorinated carbon based materials including fullerenes; e) investigations of hydrogen bonding in oligopyrrole species; f) studies in metal promoted syntheses; g) development of catalysts for the addition of nucleophiles to terminal alkynes; h) construction of metal templates for the asymmetric synthesis of chiral phosphiranes and phosphirenes; and i) the investigation of structure-order-property relationships in lyotropic chromonic mesogens. &lt;br/&gt;The x -ray diffractometer allows accurate and precise measurements of the full three dimensional structure of a molecule, including bond distances and angles, and the spatial arrangement of the molecule relative to the neighboring molecules. These studies will have an impact in a number of areas, including materials chemistry and the preparation of more efficient catalysts. In addition, graduate and undergraduate students at the University of Nevada in Reno will have a unique and important opportunity to participate in a chemical research technique that many will depend upon in their future jobs.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0226402</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suk-Wah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tam-Chang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tchang@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vincent</FirstName>
      <LastName>Catalano</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vjc@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sheridan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rss@chem.unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lightner</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lightner@chem.unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jhnelson@equinox.unr.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/03/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
      <CityName>Reno</CityName>
      <ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Nevada</StateName>
      <StateCode>NV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1938</Code>
      <Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9162</Code>
      <Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>AMPP</Code>
      <Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
