<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CADRE: NETwork-Computer for Computer Architecture Research and Education (NETCARE)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>875808</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Stephen Mahaney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>EIA-9975275&lt;br/&gt;Fortes, Jose A.&lt;br/&gt;Eigenmann, Rudolf &lt;br/&gt;Purdue Research Foundation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CADRE: NETwork-computer for Computer Architecture Research and Education (NETCARE)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides support for NETCARE (NETwork-computer for Computer Architecture Research and Education), an infrastructure supporting a repository of computer architecture tools, to be managed by a consortium of three universities: Purdue University, University of Wisconsin and Northwestern University. NETCARE will use the PUNCH network computing software developed at Purdue University, to provide the user interface, manage the repository of architecture tools, and perform high-level scheduling and dedicated resource access control. Condor, a resource management system that uses idle CPU cycles of networked workstations, developed at the University of Wisconsin, will be used to perform low-level scheduling and management of resources. NETCARE will be universally accessible through conventional World Wide Web browsers and will provide software tools and computing resources for the computer architecture research and education community.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0226851</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fortes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fortes@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
