<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRPG: A New Class of Bioinorganic Molecules: Transition Metal Oxo and Nitrido Complexes with Tripodal Sulfur Ligands</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Katharine J. Covert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Sean Seymore, Department of Chemistry, Rowan University, is supported by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry Program. Seymore's research includes the synthesis and characterization of new metal-oxo and -nitrido complexes supported by sulfur-rich tripodal ligands. Ligands such as phenyltris((methylthio)methyl)borate (PhTt) and hydridotris(methimazolyl)borate (Tm) provide a "softer" ligand environment than the more common nitrogen or oxygen donor ligands. The change in ligand may result in enhanced reactivity or unusual electronic properties in the metal-oxo and -nitrido complexes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Metal-oxo and -nitrido complexes are of interest as possible models of important reactive intermediates in catalysis, nitrogen fixation, and many other biological processes. Minority Research Planning Grants are intended to strengthen the proposal writing and planning capabilities of new investigators and to facilitate preliminary studies and other planning activities related to the research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0226114</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
      <LastName>Seymore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>seymore@rowan.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rowan University</Name>
      <CityName>Glassboro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>080281701</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8562564057</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
