<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nanostructures of Surfactants at Solid-Liquid and Gas-Liquid Interfaces and their Influence on Interfacial Properties</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>40692</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Myra McAuliffe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0227583&lt;br/&gt;Miller&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award enables Professor Jan Miller and several graduate students of the Department of Metallurgical Engineering of the University of Utah to collaborate actively with Dr. Anh Nguyen and his group at the University of Newcastle, New South Wales, Australia. The focus of their joint research is the self-assembly of surfactants at solid-liquid and gas-liquid interfaces and how these self-assembled nanostructures change interfacial properties. They are developing quantitative models for the self-assembly of surfactants which they will test experimentally. They will also determine the associated interfacial properties that would influence some industrial processes such as wafer cleaning and minerals processing. The collaborative research exploits the complementary research expertise of the principle investigators in interfacial properties and particle interactions (Newcastle) and in-situ nanostructure imaging and surface force measurements by Atomic Force Microscopy, among other techniques (Utah). Their planned research is likely to contribute to the fields of particle science and surface chemistry by providing the basis for greater control over interfacial properties and thereby a means for improving surface chemistry-based industrial processes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/27/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/09/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0227583</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Miller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Jan.Miller@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Utah</Name>
      <CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
      <ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Utah</StateName>
      <StateCode>UT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
