<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Student/Faculty Mentor Teams for SIAM Symposium on Computational Models and Simulation; October 4-5, 2002; Washington, DC</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>14936</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rita V. Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>EIA - 0228137 &lt;br/&gt;Alo, Richard A.&lt;br/&gt;University of Houston - Downtown &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Student/Faculty Mentor Teams for SIAM Symposium on Computational Models and Simulation &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports teams of mentors and students to participate in the SIAM Symposium on Computational Models and Simulation for Intra-Cellular Processes to be held in Washington, DC, October 4-5, 2002. The project provides access to a high quality technical symposium encouraging a new generation of students to come together with key researchers in the filed, hear research presentation and discuss both technical and community building topics. Developments in High Performance Computing and communications technologies have advanced quickly allowing its tools of visualization and simulation to become new research tools in advancing knowledge in areas where researchers were not traditionally major users of high performance computing such as the soft science of biology. HPC is now becoming a modality for major advances in both systems and intracellular biological processes. Advances are needed in mathematical and statistical methods to impact the prediction of spatio-temporal cellular behavior. The areas require further development in high speed data mining and data analysis techniques, knowledge acquisition tools, new information architectures, scalable computing, collaborative technologies, simulations methods and geometric software promoting and enhancing visualization as a research tool. The project contributes to stimulate students in these areas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0228137</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>RAlo@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/07/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston - Downtown</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>770021001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7132218005</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>One Main Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1714</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9218</Code>
      <Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
