<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>HPNC: Connecting the Visual History Foundation 180 Tera-Byte Archive to Internet 2</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>269500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas Gatchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Survivors of the Shoah Visual History Foundation was established by Steven Spielberg in1994 to collect the testimonies of a large number of Holocaust survivors, witnesses, liberators, and rescuers. Since then, the Shoah Foundation has videotaped over 51,700 testimonies in 57 countries and 32 languages. The testimonies comprise approximately 120,000 hours of video. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently, the Shoah Foundation is supported by a National Science Foundation grant under the ITR program to enable Johns Hopkins University, the University of Maryland, and IBM to perform research experiments in voice and speech recognition in Holocaust testimonies. The Shoah Foundation requests funding to establish a high performance network connection (155 Mb/s) between the Foundation digital library and researchers on Internet2. Initially, this network connection will facilitate the voice and speech recognition efforts by increasing the amount of data and the speed of access to data these researchers currently have. Once this connection is established, other academic research efforts can be enabled in the future. Currently the Shoah Foundation is a sponsored affiliate of Internet2 by the University of Illinois at Chicago. This sponsorship, and hundreds of requests from university researchers, show the desire of the academic community to gain access to the archive. It will also help bring testimony material directly into classrooms, meeting the Shoah Foundation new mission to overcome prejudice, intolerance, and bigotryand the suffering they causethrough the educational use of the Foundation visual history testimonies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0228938</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gustman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sam@vhf.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Survivors of the Shoah Visual History Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Universal City</CityName>
      <ZipCode>916081002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8187774907</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>100 Universal City Plaza</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
