<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>HPNC: Internet 2 Connectivity for UTHSCSA and UTSA</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kevin L. Thompson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project partners the University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio (UTHSCSA) and the University of Texas at San Antonio (UTSA), in the south Texas region, for connectivity to an advanced network. Southwest Research Institute (SwRI) will serve as the sponsor for UTHSCSA and UTSA and will provide experienced technical and engineering staff to assist in connecting to the Abilene network through the Austin POP via a DS-3 line. UTHSCSA and UTSA have a combined annual research budget of over 113 million dollars, enroll over 21,000 students and both are Hispanic-serving institutions with 56% female enrollment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed high-speed network will enhance collaborations with scientists at 21 other Abilene-connected institutions and will immediately support eleven research projects via Abilene: &lt;br/&gt;University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio &lt;br/&gt; Global Analysis of Hydrodynamic and Thermodynamic Properties of Macromolecules &lt;br/&gt; Development of a Remote NMR Data Acquisition Infrastructure &lt;br/&gt; Single Molecule Video Microscopy &lt;br/&gt; High-Speed Data Sharing of Brainmap Images &lt;br/&gt;University of Texas at San Antonio &lt;br/&gt; GEneral NEural SImulation System (GENESIS) Software System &lt;br/&gt; Analysis of the information content of cortical waves in the turtle visual system &lt;br/&gt; IP-friendly Quality-of-Service Mechanisms &lt;br/&gt; Adaptive Transport Protocols for High-Speed Networks &lt;br/&gt; A Tool for Distance Learning &lt;br/&gt; Learning Community Across Campuses and Institutions &lt;br/&gt; Grid Computation Analysis of Uncertainty Management in the Design and &lt;br/&gt; Construction of Blast Resistance Structures for Anti-Terrorist Applications &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These research projects range from strictly biological (e.g., biochemistry at the level of single molecules) to strictly computer science (e.g. network transport protocols that adapt rapidly to the available network capacity). Between the extremes are interdisciplinary research projects at the interface of biological science and mathematics (e.g., general neural simulation system, probabilistic reference system for the human brain, and numerical modeling of a turtle's visual system) plus education of future teachers (e.g., development of teaching strategies and the application of technology).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0228927</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Serwer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Serwer@uthscsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Turgay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Korkmaz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>korkmaz@cs.utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fox</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fox@uthscsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Rajendra</FirstName>
      <LastName>Boppana</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>boppana@cs.utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Borries</FirstName>
      <LastName>Demeler</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>demeler@biochem.uthscsa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/06/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas Health Science Center San Antonio</Name>
      <CityName>SAN ANTONIO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>782293901</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2105672340</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>7703 FLOYD CURL DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>4088</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERF NETWK CONNECT-SCIENG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9217</Code>
      <Text>NATNL RESERCH &amp; EDUCAT NETWORK</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>HPCC</Code>
      <Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
