<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>BioLINK Workshop: Biological Language, Information and Knowledge</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>94317</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sylvia J. Spengler</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>EIA- 0228162&lt;br/&gt;Lynette Hirschman&lt;br/&gt;Mitre Corporation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: BioLINK Biological Language, Information and Knowledge&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BioLINK workshop will focus on the interconnections in biology among literature, information (in databases), and knowledge (in ontologies). The challenge for BioLINK is to improve information access and management through a better understanding of how to combine and synchronize the complementary resources and techniques provided by these different approaches to information management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To address these challenges, the workshop will bring together senior researchers to exchange perspective and develop a multidisciplinary perspective on information management in the rapidly expanding area of biology. The specific goal will be to create a research roadmap that identifies the following:&lt;br/&gt; The use cases for biology: how do researchers uses databases, ontologies, literature, and what would they like to see?&lt;br/&gt; Various ways in which these various areas interact&lt;br/&gt; The missing science for how to connect these resources&lt;br/&gt; A graded set of challenge problems that the BioLINK community can address, to make progress on the underlying issues of connectivity, access, and discovery.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0228162</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lynette</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hirschman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lynette@mitre.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mitre Corporation Virginia</Name>
      <CityName>McLean</CityName>
      <ZipCode>221027508</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7039834017</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>7515 Colshire Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
