<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Scaling Up Standards-Based Accountability</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5534731</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cherniavsky</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Arguably the largest scale-up of an educational program occurring in the United States at the &lt;br/&gt;present time is the implementation of standards-based accountability (SBA) in all 50 states as a &lt;br/&gt;result of the No Child Left Behind Act of 2001 (NCLB). SBA involves several elements &lt;br/&gt;including content and performance standards, aligned assessments, and a set of consequences &lt;br/&gt;tied to assessment results. The utility of standards-based accountability was demonstrated in a &lt;br/&gt;few pioneering states in the 1990s, and a number of studies suggest that SBA systems may &lt;br/&gt;influence both student learning and instructional practices. The government cited the success of &lt;br/&gt;these accountability systems as justification for requiring SBA in all states. This investigation is &lt;br/&gt;designed to identify factors that enhance the implementation of SBA systems, foster changes in &lt;br/&gt;school and classroom practice, and promote improved student achievement. It addresses four &lt;br/&gt;broad questions: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; What strategies are used in implementing SBA at the state, district, and school levels? &lt;br/&gt;Which state, district, and school implementation strategies are associated with &lt;br/&gt;changes in classroom practice? &lt;br/&gt; How valid are the standards-based test scores as indicators of changes in student &lt;br/&gt;achievement? &lt;br/&gt; Which features of SBA implementation are associated with student attainment of &lt;br/&gt;academic standards? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study involves three states that vary in their approaches to SBA. Data will be collected from &lt;br/&gt;state and district officials, principals, and teachers using a combination of questionnaires, &lt;br/&gt;interviews, and artifact examination. The data collection approach is longitudinal, and is &lt;br/&gt;designed to provide information on SBA implementation at all levels, as well as on factors that &lt;br/&gt;influence implementation, such as the clarity of the standards and the methods for promulgating &lt;br/&gt;them, teachers. and principals. understanding of the SBA policies, and the professional climate &lt;br/&gt;of the school. Student achievement data will also be collected to address the third and fourth &lt;br/&gt;research questions. The evaluation of the validity of standards-based test scores involves &lt;br/&gt;examination of the content and format of test items as well as a comparison of score trends on &lt;br/&gt;the standards-based test and on other tests such as the National Assessment of Educational &lt;br/&gt;Progress (NAEP). Relationships among implementation, practices, and student achievement will &lt;br/&gt;be explored using longitudinal multilevel modeling techniques. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Answers to the four research questions will help policymakers, educators, and researchers &lt;br/&gt;understand the ways SBA policies are implemented at all levels of the system; explain &lt;br/&gt;relationships among implementation, instructional practices and student achievement; and &lt;br/&gt;identify successful practices that can be promulgated to make SBA function more effectively. &lt;br/&gt;Over the next three to five years, SBA will affect every public school student in the country, so &lt;br/&gt;insights gained from this research will have wide applicability.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/27/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0228295</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stecher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Brian_Stecher@rand.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hamilton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Laura_Hamilton@rand.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rand Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Monica</CityName>
      <ZipCode>904013297</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3103930411</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1776 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
