<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Peer Instruction for Student Engagement</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jill K. Singer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Peer Instruction for Student Engagement project is placing peer instructors in selected&lt;br/&gt;introductory courses in STEM disciplines and measure the impact that their use has on student&lt;br/&gt;engagement with those courses. Departments have chosen courses (i) which students have&lt;br/&gt;historically found difficult and (ii) which are either required of majors or from which majors &lt;br/&gt;are normally recruited. To keep costs down, departments were asked to determine how peer&lt;br/&gt;instructors could be effectively used no more than three hours per week per class. The six&lt;br/&gt;different disciplines use four different models for peer instruction. Geology and Chemistry &lt;br/&gt;are following the Supplemental Instruction model, using peer instructors to provide voluntary&lt;br/&gt;problem-solving sessions. Computer Science and Biology are following a model already used &lt;br/&gt;by the Computer Science Department in one course, using peer instructors to assist with &lt;br/&gt;small-group learning in laboratories and to hold office hours. Physics is adapting a model, &lt;br/&gt;best known from the University of Washington's Physics Education Group, in which peer &lt;br/&gt;tutors help small groups of students to work, in mandatory laboratory sessions, through &lt;br/&gt;tutorials devised by faculty members. Mathematics is employing a modification of the &lt;br/&gt;Peer-Led Team Learning strategy, combining a web-based homework delivery system with &lt;br/&gt;mandatory problem-solving workshops based around problem sets written by the faculty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project's two objectives are (1) to increase retention in STEM majors at Radford &lt;br/&gt;University by 15%, and (2) to measure the effect of peer instruction on student engagement&lt;br/&gt;in STEM disciplines. Five different assessment measures are used: retention rates, grades, &lt;br/&gt;competency exam scores, surveys and interviews of participants, and the National Survey &lt;br/&gt;of Student Engagement. Each department involved has a department coordinator for the &lt;br/&gt;project who manages recruitment and departmental training of peer instructors, and who &lt;br/&gt;meets with peer instructors as a group during the semester. Global training is provided by an&lt;br/&gt;experienced consultant. The project's co-Principal Investigators are visiting workshops and &lt;br/&gt;tutorial sessions, talking with faculty and students involved, and conducting extensive &lt;br/&gt;assessment of all aspects of the project. The project addresses the NSF merit review criteria.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary intellectual merit of this project is the measurement of the impact of peer &lt;br/&gt;instruction on student engagement with introductory courses in STEM disciplines. Peer &lt;br/&gt;instruction, especially when combined with small-group work, is considered a prime &lt;br/&gt;strategy for increasing engagement; this project will determine, through a number of &lt;br/&gt;assessments, the extent to which this is true at Radford University. It will also look &lt;br/&gt;for differences in results among competing models for peer instruction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project improves education using proven techniques while investigating the important&lt;br/&gt;question of why those techniques work. Its results, both the expected increase in retention &lt;br/&gt;rates and the measurements of student engagement associated with peer instruction, should &lt;br/&gt;be of interest to all who wish to increase student learning in STEM disciplines. Peer &lt;br/&gt;instructors can add diversity to instruction in fields dominated by white males, and all &lt;br/&gt;departments participating have indicated that they could hire significant numbers of &lt;br/&gt;female or minority students to serve in that capacity. The principal investigators will &lt;br/&gt;disseminate the project's results both through the web and through the usual outlets &lt;br/&gt;for publication and presentation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0229652</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chase</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jchase@radford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Corwin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scorwin@radford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/14/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Radford University</Name>
      <CityName>Radford</CityName>
      <ZipCode>241426926</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5408315035</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Box 6926</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
