<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Biosensing in the Gas Phase: A New Approach Based on Imprinted Nanoparticles of a Linear Polymer</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>93079</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patrick L. Brezonik</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0229026&lt;br/&gt;Tepper&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this project is to develop a new kind of gas-phase biosensor to simultaneously detect chemical and biological warfare agents entirely in the gas phase and in real time. Recent studies have demonstrated that biological pathogens emit volatile chemical metabolites that potentially can be utilized as a unique gas-phase signature. Therefore, the volatile chemical agents will be detected directly while the biological species, such as bacteria, will be detected through their volatile metabolites. The PIs will develop nanoparticles possessing synthetic receptor sites targeted to the volatile chemical metabolites of particular biological pathogens. The imprinted particles will be interfaced with a microfabricated transducer and the resulting biochip will be tested under exposure to a variety of vapors including the metabolites. This technology has the potential to reduce or eliminate the costly, labor intensive and time consuming practice of current air sampling and analysis techniques. If successful, a portable, hand-held, gas phase biosensor could be deployed at various high-risk locations to provide real-time monitoring for biological and chemical agents.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0229026</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Tepper</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gctepper@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/31/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
      <CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
      <ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0118000</Code>
      <Name>Pollution Control</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
