<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Promotion, Recruitment and Retention: STEM Initiatives for a Public Liberal Arts College</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>95965</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Terry S. Woodin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is a multi-part planning and pilot testing effort design to increase enrollment in the ten science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) programs at the college. Specifically the four pilot projects and two planning studies cooperatively attack the challenge of low enrollment and low degree production in STEM programs at SUNY Potsdam. Through a variety of activities the project is developing planning strategies to address program promotion, recruitment, and retention. The goal is to study how best to plan for and attract students into science courses and programs. These plans and pilot studies involve exploring ways to help students to enter the program through bridge programs that support their learning, by encouraging experiential learning and undergraduate research, and by providing a bridge to post-graduate life. The college is also studying the development of new interdisciplinary minor and major programs in Informatics. The curriculum planning in Informatics models another way to introduce interdisciplinary science-based programs for students in the future. The impact of the pilot projects is being disseminated through campus and regional newsletters, a website, and at the national level through annual meeting at the Association for Institutional Research Forum, National Education Association, and the Consortium for Computing in Small Colleges.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0230030</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fossum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fossumtv@potsdam.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nostrand</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nostrab@potsdam.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/22/2005</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brehm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brehmlp@potsdam.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/19/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brehm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>brehmlp@potsdam.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/04/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/22/2005</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY College at Potsdam</Name>
      <CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
      <ZipCode>136762294</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3152672537</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Pierrepont Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
