<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of a Textbook and Companion Websites for Chemistry-Specific Writing Instruction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>498420</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bert Holmes</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In response to the national challenge to improve literacy skills, the overarching goals of this project are to enhance the chemistry-specific writing skills of upper-division chemistry majors, promote writing-to-learn-chemistry, and assist students in becoming better readers of the chemical literature. In this project, instructional materials are being developed in the form of a textbook and companion websites that comprise writing modules associated with genres typical of chemistry. Materials target students of different backgrounds, including language minority students, and chemistry instructors with minimal training in teaching writing. Special features of the materials include (a) "canned" research, making it possible for students without research experience to complete scientific papers; (b) the use of corpus linguistics to develop instructional materials based on actual patterns of the language of chemistry; (c) accessibility to nonnative speakers; and (d) reflection and collaborative-learning activities. Materials developed from a previous project are being fine-tuned and tested at our home institution with different instructors and students; two years of the four-year project are dedicated to piloting materials in 15-20 institutions, with a cross-section of student populations. Assessment, linked to student learning and instructor/user objectives, is an integral part of the project. Formative and summative assessment will be conducted, in part, with instruments and procedures adapted from Classroom Assessment Techniques (CATs) developed for SMET instructors, with the assistance of an assessment coordinator and ten external evaluators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0230913</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Robinson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Marin.Robinson@NAU.EDU</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fredricka</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stoller</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Fredricka.Stoller@nau.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northern Arizona University</Name>
      <CityName>Flagstaff</CityName>
      <ZipCode>860110001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9285230886</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ARD Building #56, Suite 240</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
