<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Bridging Engineering and Education in Central Florida (BEEF)</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>130000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sue Kemnitzer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL NO.: 0230630&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR: Morse, Lucy&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION NAME: University of Central Florida&lt;br/&gt;TITLE: Bridging Engineering and Education in Central Florida (BEEF)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this proposed project is to establish and institutionalize a Bridging &lt;br/&gt;Engineering and Education in Central Florida (BEEF) Committee to develop a comprehensive strategic plan. The strategic plan will be designed to increase the numbers and diversity of students entering as STEM majors and enhance the learning and the academic success of these students. Collaborators in the development of this strategic plan will include: the UCF Colleges of Engineering and Education, the 11 area schools districts, the Florida Virtual School, and the six area community colleges. Central Florida has over 485,000 K-12 students, over 73,000 community college students and over 35,000 state university students (approximately 8,600 UCF students are engineering and education majors). This project will have a powerful impact on bridging engineering and education to many of the diverse students in the Central Florida area. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Goal: Enhance and institutionalize collaboration among the College of Education, College of Engineering, the six area community colleges, the Florida Virtual School, and 11 area school districts by establishing a joint BEEF Committee co-chaired by the Deans of each College. &lt;br/&gt;Objective 1: Discussion and evaluation of university curriculum issues including course &lt;br/&gt;revisions in the introductory engineering courses and teacher preparation education &lt;br/&gt;courses, program changes, and accreditation issues. &lt;br/&gt;Objective 2: Renew and expand existing outreach programs with pubic schools and &lt;br/&gt;educational agencies by creating joint partnerships involving both Colleges. &lt;br/&gt;Objective 3: Articulation with community colleges concerning the two introductory &lt;br/&gt;engineering courses, EGN 1006 and EGN 1007. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although this project is specifically designed to serve the Florida population, the courses, and strategies may be used anywhere.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0230630</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hynes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hynes@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lucy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morse</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>morse@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/18/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
      <CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
      <ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4078821120</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1340</Code>
      <Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7218</Code>
      <Text>RET SUPPLEMENTS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
