<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ASU Engineering and Education: DET Expansion for K-12 Teachers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>98375</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sue Kemnitzer</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL NO.: 0230726&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR: Crouch, Peter&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION NAME: Arizona State University&lt;br/&gt;TITLE: ASU Engineering and Education: DET Expansion for K-12 Teachers&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this study is to position the College Engineering and Applied&lt;br/&gt;Sciences and the College of Education at Arizona State University for successful infusion&lt;br/&gt;of Design/Engineering/Technology (DET) concepts throughout the complete range of&lt;br/&gt;teacher education experiences, including pre-service and post-baccalaureate programs.&lt;br/&gt;The project is led by the College of Engineering but includes the full participation of the&lt;br/&gt;College of Education. A team of faculty and administrators from both colleges will&lt;br/&gt;explore ways in which DET can be infused into all aspects of teacher education and&lt;br/&gt;ultimately used to anchor instruction in science and math education. Part of the team will&lt;br/&gt;design and teach a pilot course that will be used as a tool to conduct research and collect&lt;br/&gt;the data needed to inform both engineering and education faculty on best ways of&lt;br/&gt;incorporating DET concepts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the project include 1) identifying curricular and pedagogical needs of&lt;br/&gt;teachers and university faculty for implementing DET, 2) developing a DET-based pilot&lt;br/&gt;course as a research tool for exploring DET in the curriculum, 3) crafting a set of&lt;br/&gt;recommendations for a comprehensive implementation of DET in teacher education, 4)&lt;br/&gt;developing models for the appropriate points in the professional development sequence&lt;br/&gt;for DET, 5) determining the effectiveness of the pilot on instructional practices,&lt;br/&gt;curricular choices and student understanding of DET and engineering careers, and 5)&lt;br/&gt;developing models that extend DET to pre-service education through methods classes&lt;br/&gt;and general education courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merits of this planning grant include a re-conceptualizing part of&lt;br/&gt;the science and mathematics component of teacher education and bringing technological&lt;br/&gt;design, as addressed in the standards, to the forefront of k-12 science and mathematics&lt;br/&gt;instruction.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0230726</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Krause</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>skrause@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Anderson-Rowland</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mary.anderson@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Crouch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>peter.crouch@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hudelson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress/>
      <StartDate>08/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>James</FirstName>
      <LastName>Middleton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jimbo@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arizona State University</Name>
      <CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
