<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of Interactive Problem Solving Tutorials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>74340</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Duncan E. McBride</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to demonstrate the feasibility of using computers to help students learn effective problem solving skills for solving physics problems. This is accomplished by constructing a set of computer tutorials to help students improve their problem solving performance. The tutorial design draws on prior research on teaching students effective problem solving skills and using computers to provide students with individualized guidance and feedback. These tutorials:&lt;br/&gt;(1) are highly interactive,&lt;br/&gt;(2) make explicit the thought processes necessary for effective problem solving,&lt;br/&gt;(3) use a modified reciprocal-teaching strategy to give students practice in the basic cognitive functions necessary for effective problem solving (i.e., deciding on an action, implementing that action, and assessing the result),&lt;br/&gt;(4) provide students with individualized guidance and feedback based on careful instructional design&lt;br/&gt;(5) be flexible enough to accommodate the multiple solutions paths different students might choose for solving a problem.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project demonstrates how technology can be used to improve education by providing students with (1) more interactive and individualized instruction, (2) opportunities to receive effective instruction outside the classroom, and (3) access to alternative forms of instruction. This can be especially important to students for whom standard instruction is insufficient.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0230830</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Leonardo</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hsu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lhsu@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/16/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
