<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>From Computer Data to Human Knowledge: A Cognitive Approach to Knowledge Discovery</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>39731</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research is being done in conjunction with IIS-9731990, which is being&lt;br/&gt;performed by Michael Pazzani in the Information and Computer Science&lt;br/&gt;Department at the University of California, Irvine. The research is&lt;br/&gt;concerned with intelligent decision aids that can be developed by data&lt;br/&gt;mining techniques. Experience has determined that such systems can learn&lt;br/&gt;accurate models, but that experts in areas where those models are used in&lt;br/&gt;decision aids are often reluctant to trust them because they do not, for&lt;br/&gt;instance, use the same tests intermediate conclusions or abstractions that&lt;br/&gt;the experts have grown to trust. Or they do not use certain factors at all&lt;br/&gt;that experts feel to be relevant. Experts also want models that are stable&lt;br/&gt;under small changes in the data being analyzed. Psychologists have&lt;br/&gt;discovered factors that simplify the learning, understanding, and&lt;br/&gt;communication of category and process information by humans. This research&lt;br/&gt;seeks to explore these psychological principles in light of the output of&lt;br/&gt;existing KDD algorithms and then go on to develop and evaluate new KDD&lt;br/&gt;algorithms that will provide output that is easy for people to learn , use,&lt;br/&gt;and communicate to others. With the results of this research, it should be&lt;br/&gt;possible to make such decision aids more "human centered", so that they&lt;br/&gt;will be used more often and more effectively in practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.gatech.edu/psychology/faculty.htm</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0231639</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dorrit</FirstName>
      <LastName>Billman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>billman@psych.stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Institute for the Study of Learning and Expertise</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943061438</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6504943884</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2164 Staunton Court</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
