<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Semidefinite Programming and Approximation Algorithms</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>147639</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Suvrajeet Sen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides funding for the development, analysis, and implementation of semidefinite programming approximation algorithms for solving large-scale combinatorial, discrete, and global optimization problems that arise in production management, manufacture engineering, and network planning. In solving many optimization problems, it is impossible or too costly to obtain a 100 percent optimal solution. However, approximation algorithms can, cost-effectively, deliver a sub-optimal solution with a quality guarantee, say at least 87 percent optimal, which is satisfactory in practice. The semidefinite programming algorithm is a newly developed algorithm for approximating some difficult problems with the best quality guarantees to date. This project is to develop semidefinite programming algorithms for solving a wider class of hard problems with an even better guarantee, and to implement the algorithms in a robust computer code. We then validate the code by solving the network and circuit bisection problem frequently used in the chip design industry, and will test the code on a set of bench-mark problems collected from the industry.&lt;br/&gt; If successful, the project would result in one of the most complete and powerful solvers for approximating hard optimization problems with wide real-world applications. It will strengthen and improve theoretical&lt;br/&gt;results and practical performance of existing approximation algorithms, and will lead to the development of new efficient methods for a variety of discrete optimization problems. Progress in the area of developing efficient algorithms for solving large-scale combinatorial problems is of great importance in improving the efficiency of manufacturing systems, communication networks, aircraft routing, multiple-flow operations,&lt;br/&gt;and resources planning. The underlying theory of the project would also be valuable to education and basic scientific research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0231600</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Yinyu</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ye</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yinyu-ye@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/05/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Stanford University</Name>
      <CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
      <ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
