<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Grain Boundary Doped Thin Film Mixed Conductor for Oxygen Separation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99994</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will focus on the production of grain boundary doped thin film mixed ionic - electronic conductors for optimized oxygen separation membranes. Ion transport properties of mixed conducting ceramics will be studied as a function of controlled grain boundary doping. Ceramics known to perform well for O2 separation will be doped with magnesium for increased performance. Doped thin films will be prepared, tested, and compared to un-doped films and films doped in the bulk rather than the grain boundary. Cost effective grain boundary doping will be accomplished through a tape casting procedure used to produce thin films which can be laminated onto porous supports for increased strength. O2 separation will be maximized while minimizing the amount of dopant used. Test structures will be mechanically characterized for strength and durability. &lt;br/&gt; A cost efficient method of separating O2 from air would be beneficial in a number of industries. Chemical industries would benefit from a cheap source of oxygen for the synthesis of value added chemicals; manufacturing industries such as steel, glass and paper, for example, would be able to heat furnaces more efficiently with an oxidant undiluted by nitrogen; and the energy industry would see improved performance in processes such as coal gasification and conversion of natural gas to syngas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/19/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0231850</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Carl</FirstName>
      <LastName>Evenson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eltron@eltronresearch.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Eltron Research, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803013241</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3035300263</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4600 NAUTILUS COURT SOUTH</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
