<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: A Hydrothermally Stable H2 Selective SiC Membrane for Membrane Reactor Appliction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This NSF Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) program involves the use a hydrothermally stable SiC membrane as a membrane reactor for steam reforming. We have developed an innovative hydrogen selective SiC membrane. This membrane has demonstrated an excellent material stability required for performing methane steam reforming and dehydrogenation via a catalytic membrane reactor. Thus, we believe that the time is ripe to harvest the catalytic membrane reactor technology. We will be able to perform experimental and reaction engineering study to demonstrate a commercially viable catalytic membrane reactor process using an appropriate membrane under an ideal operating condition. We will conduct a bench-top experimental study using this selected membrane to demonstrate the benefits of reactive separations for an industrial significant reaction, hydrogen production via methane steam reforming. In addition, the hydrothermal and chemical stability of the SiC membrane under the proposed reaction condition will be experimentally verified. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The use of hydrothermally stable SiC membranes froe reactive separations can overcome the key technical barriers preventing the implementation of membrane reactor technology in the steam reforming of methane, as well as in dehydrogenation applications. Both are industrially important reaction processes.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232698</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Liu</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pliu@mediaandprocess.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/03/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Media and Process Technology Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152381368</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4128263721</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1155 WILLIAM PITT WAY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
