<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Study of Particulate Composites of Aluminum with Intermetallic Reinforcements</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99990</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph E. Hennessey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will develop composites of aluminum with intermetallic reinforcements. These are important for products that demand higher strength and more ease in processing than is currently available in metal/ceramic discontinuously reinforced aluminum (DRA) matrix composites. The project will explore the mechanical properties of particulate composites of aluminum with intermetallic reinforcements from a fundamental viewpoint. Silicon carbide has been a common choice of the particulate phase in DRA composites. Because the fracture toughness and strength properties of DRA are influenced by the interfacial bond strength between the matrix and the reinforcing phase, there are advantages to a metal/intermetallic particulate composite approach rather than silicon carbide. This will be demonstrated in the project.&lt;br/&gt; From a commercial point of view, discontinuously reinforced aluminum matrix composites are attractive for various applications because of low cost, greater flexibility in processing and isotropy of properties. The resulting material may be used with greater strength for vehicle drive shafts, brake drums, engine pistons, jet engine fan exit guide vanes, satellites, aircraft ventral fins and fuel access covers, bicycle components, golf clubs and a wide variety of other commercial applications.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/09/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232565</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gollapudi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Murty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gsm@trl.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>TOUCHSTONE RESEARCH LABORATORY LTD</Name>
      <CityName>TRIADELPHIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>260599707</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3045475800</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>RR 1 BOX 100B</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
