<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Robotic Surface Finishing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cheryl F. Albus</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will develop a new robot architecture targeting fine-fidelity, force dependent tasks. The project will use an innovative 2 degree-of-freedom manipulator with lightweight construction and smooth, low friction joints. The control system follows the biological model of sensing the environment by touch and performing work by applying force. The project will test the validity of a manipulator concept by constructing a simple unit and attempting a task commonly required of cast metal parts, such as grinding excess material left by the casting process to produce a smooth surface. Successful results can be applied to more sophisticated manipulators for automating the finishing of cast, forged, and molded parts. The concept can also be extended to other labor intensive industrial processes that are difficult and hazardous for people to perform. Further, its more natural mode of operation could permit it to safely work in close concert with people, including the physically impaired.&lt;br/&gt; The potential commercial applications include automated finishing of fabricated parts, including grinding, deburring, polishing, and blending. Automated assembly of closely fitting parts. Robots that can work in close proximity, and provide assistance to, human laborers as well as the physically impaired.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/28/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/28/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232362</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Somes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ssomes@adelphia.net</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/28/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Western Robotics Co</Name>
      <CityName>Willoughby</CityName>
      <ZipCode>440949325</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4402562004</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8840 Eagle Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
