<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Development of Porous Lubricated Nozzles for Suppression of Nozzle Wear in Abrasive Water Jet Systems</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99614</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cheryl F. Albus</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will develop technology to prevent nozzle wear in abrasive water jets used for machining (e.g. automotive/aerospace components). Nozzle wear limits the life and accuracy of jet cutting and currently requires entrainment of abrasives downstream of the nozzle in a larger mixing tube. The new method consists of nozzles made of a porous material surrounded by reservoirs containing high viscosity lubricant, and exposed to the pressure that drives the slurry in the nozzle. This method extends the nozzle life and allows premixing of the particles prior to injection (abrasive suspension jets), enabling operation at lower pressures, cutting of harder materials and smaller jets (micro machining). &lt;br/&gt; The commercial potential of using this diverse technology by both small machine shops to automotive and aircraft industries is very appealing. Wear of the nozzle or mixing tube in present systems is a major problem affecting all the applications of jet cutting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/29/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232626</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Umang</FirstName>
      <LastName>Anand</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>umang@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/29/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lubrijet, Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
      <ZipCode>212285400</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4105165427</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>130 Starhill Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
