<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Artificial Intelligence Software for Student Assessment in Chemistry Education</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project focuses on the development of meaningful interactive tutoring and assessment capabilities for chemistry tutorial software. Although there has been a clearly articulated user demand for advancement in this area, it has been repeatedly identified as one for which existing offerings are weak. Quantum Simulations a new and different approach, adapting and incorporating new concepts from artificial intelligence (AI). More than just assigning a grade, meaningful opportunities will be created for students to learn directly from the assessment itself. The proposed technology will benefit all students. The technology, however, is specifically targeted to help those who have the greatest need--such as students of average or marginal performance and students from historically underrepresented groups--by lowering barriers to accessing high-quality science instructional software. The firm has established a partnership with an NSF-funded systemic reform initiative to further these goals.&lt;br/&gt; The customers for the proffered technology include textbook publishers, software providers, hardware vendors and distance learning companies. Quantum has entered into a long-term contract with a prominent textbook publishe, Holt, Rinehart and Winston, to commercialize this technology. This arrangement will result in rapid dissemination to an established end user base.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232223</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Benny</FirstName>
      <LastName>Johnson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>johnson@quantumsimulations.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Quantum Simulations Incorporated</Name>
      <CityName>MURRYSVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>156689536</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7247338603</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>5275 SARDIS RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0108000</Code>
      <Name>Software Development</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
