<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Nanoporous Silica Slurry Technology for Enhanced Chemical Mechanical Planarization (CMP) of Low "K" Dielectrics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99938</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>TIMOTHY J. RUDD</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will synthesize novel &lt;br/&gt;slurries for chemical mechanical planarization (CMP) of low dielectric constant (K) &lt;br/&gt;materials. Standard abrasives such as silica and alumina lead to significant scratching, &lt;br/&gt;indenting and delamination of the soft low K surface. In this project it is proposed to use &lt;br/&gt;nanoporous silica based slurries in which the hardness of the particle can be controlled. &lt;br/&gt;In the project, synthesis of nanoporous silica particles will first be carried out followed by charcterization; next will be development of the slurry formulation followed by charcterization and finally testing against the specific needs of the CMP application.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Commercially, these slurries are expected to reduce surface defects and enhance slurry stability. It is expected that major electronic manufacturing companies will use this new type of slurry. Wafer level experiments are already planned on patterned wafers in &lt;br/&gt;collaboration with key industrial partners.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/22/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232709</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Deepika</FirstName>
      <LastName>Singh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>singh@sinmat.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/22/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SINMAT, INC.</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326531649</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523347237</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1912 NW 67th Place</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
