<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Optical Diagnostics for Whole-Field Measurement of Dense Fuel Sprays</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99849</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims at developing diagnostics for liquid fuel combustion systems. The proposed instrumentation will provide a noninvasive measurement of liquid volume, surface area and velocity within a cross-sectional plane of the dense spray. The technique is applicable to burning and non-burning sprays and is equally effective for spherical and non-spherical drops and particles. The proposed device is a novel combination of ensemble laser diffraction and image correlation velocimetry, both of which are well-developed technologies and many practical issues concerning their implementation have been already resolved. The goal of the project is to build a bench-top system and prove the underlying concepts. A number of issues concerning the effectiveness of the proposed diagnostics in the combustion environment will also be addressed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broad impact of this work will be commercialization of a new diagnostics tool that may enable cleaner and more efficient liquid fuel combustion systems.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/29/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/29/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232185</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Amir</FirstName>
      <LastName>Naqwi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>anaqwi@mspcorp.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/29/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>POWERSCOPE INCORPORATED</Name>
      <CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554144504</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6123314247</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1313 5TH ST SE, STE 209</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
