<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Development of a New Chemical Ionization Mass Spectrometer (CIMS) for Uptake Studies of Peroxyl Radicals (RO2) by Atmospherically Relevant Surfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>358360</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06020104</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project will develop a new Chemical Ionization Mass Spectrometer (CIMS) instrument adapted to study peroxy radical reactions. Peroxy radicals are important oxidants in the ambient atmosphere and difficult species to measure. Initially, some experiments will be conducted with an existing CIMS instrument at the National Center for Atmospheric Research to determine potential improvements. Then a new instrument will be constructed at University of Miami and laboratory studies of the uptake of peroxy radicals on surfaces representative of ambient atmospheric aerosols conducted using the new spectrometer. Results from this study should improve knowledge on the kinetics of gas-surface heterogeneous interactions of oxidatively important peroxy radicals on aerosol. Broader impacts of the research include: a substantive addition to current understanding of reactions of peroxy radicals in the atmosphere; establishing a state of the art permanent instrument capacity enhancement at University of Miami under the direction of a new female faculty member; and through the mentoring of postdoctoral scholars and students involved on this project promoting scholarship, technology transfer, and research experience to a new generation of young scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0232057</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Noziere</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bnoziere@rsmas.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/10/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Miami Rosenstiel School of Marine&amp;Atmospheric Sci</Name>
      <CityName>KEY BISCAYNE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>331491031</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3054214089</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4600 RICKENBACKER CSWY</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
