<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-France Cooperative Research: Tribological Thin Films on Rough Surfaces: Design, Analysis, Characterization, Fatigue and Wear</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>19800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0233313&lt;br/&gt;Soom&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year award for US-France collaboration in mechanical engineering involves researchers and students at the State University of New York at Buffalo and the University for Science and Technology in Lille, France. Andres Soom and Gary F. Dargush in the US and Jacky Lesage and Gerard Mesmacque in France will lead this collaborative program to model the tribological performance and failure of thin coatings and films. In particular, they will conduct a series of experiments, resulting in patterns of wear or film failure. In parallel, computational mechanical modeling of 3D contact stresses and strains will be developed. The US investigators are expert in computational, contact mechanics and tribological testing. This is complemented by French capabilities in characterization, preparation and failure of thin films, and nano-indentation measurements. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Thin films and coatings are frequently used to enhance performance and durability of mechanical components and production tooling where some sliding occurs at contact with the surface. Recently advanced designs of surfaces have challenged current ability to design films, and predict behavior, based on mechanical properties. This joint effort will advance understanding of life-cycle performance and predictive modeling. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award represents the US side of joint proposals to the NSF and the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS). NSF will cover travel funds and living expenses for the US investigators and graduate student. CNRS will support the visits of the French researchers and graduate students to the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0233313</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andres</FirstName>
      <LastName>Soom</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>soom@acsu.buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dargush</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gdargush@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
      <CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142607016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>402 Crofts Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
