<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: SGER: Exploring the Integration of Electronic Commerce in Industry Value Chains: A Focus on the Home Mortgage Service Sector</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>89563</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>C. Suzanne Iacono</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This SGER grew out of an EU-US workshop held in Venice in October, 2002. The intent of that workshop was to bring together researchers from the US with those from the EU who were working on similar projects related to e-work and e-business and who would like to begin to collaborate together. This SGER will allow for US cooperation with the EU's STAR project, which involves the conduct of dozens of case studies mapping change in a variety of industries across member states of the EU. This project will focus on the home mortgage service sector, in particular specialized lenders, and will bring the US and one its industries into the collection. Case study protocols will be developed that will allow for cross-comparison with the EU case studies that have already been completed. In addition, travel to the EU will allow for a team meeting and coordination of project goals, methods, and analysis.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0233634</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>M. Lynne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Markus</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mlmarkus@bentley.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Bentley College</Name>
      <CityName>Waltham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>024524705</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7818912660</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>c/o Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0104000</Code>
      <Name>Information Systems</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
