<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-France Cooperative Research: Coherent Radiative Transport in Atomic Vapors</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18260</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0233292&lt;br/&gt;Havey&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year award for U.S.-France collaboration in atomic physics involves Mark D. Havey and students at Old Dominion University and Robin Kaiser at the Nonlinear Research Institute of Nice. The investigators propose to examine coherent radiative transport, with specific attention to dynamical effects of atomic motion. A wide range of phenomena associated with coherent radiative transport has already been observed in solids and liquids. But studies in atomic gases have been limited. In this project the investigators will study the influence of coherent transport in thermal atomic gas samples and the coherent backscattering effect in a sample of ultracold atoms. These experiments together will explore these regimes for practical applications and for fundamental experiments directed toward strong localization of light in atomic vapors. The project takes advantage of French expertise in ultracold atoms. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award represents the U.S. side of a joint proposal to the NSF and the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS). NSF will cover travel funds and living expenses for the U.S. investigator and graduate student. The CNRS will support the visits of the French researchers to the United States. U.S. students will benefit from the exchange of scientific techniques and experience with an international research team.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0233292</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
      <LastName>Havey</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mhavey@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/21/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
      <ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
