<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Molecular Design and 3-D Assembly for Coupled Electro-Optical Functionalities</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>900000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda S. Sapochak</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project targets nanoscale control of molecular assembly to create integrated, functional systems such that "every atom counts", i.e. the active volume and function is maximized relative to the atomic density. The approach makes use of organized interfaces with high surface areas and amplification of response. The research is synthesis and processing focused to determine the molecular synthesis and 3 dimensional organization needed to structurally integrate hierarchical assembly with interacting electro-optic functionalities. Because of the ease of simultaneous synthesis and processing and the huge chemical diversity that is accessible through composition, inorganic modification, organic incorporation, and multidomain assembly, the potential significant technological applications are great. In order to realize these possibilities, it is essential to be able to predictively design and control the multivariable kinetic and thermodynamic parameters that lead to the desired multiscale structure and functional properties. The educational emphasis for undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral researchers working on this project will include 1) the promotion of professional careers for female students and postdoctoral associates, 2) providing cutting edge collaborative interdisciplinary interactions and resources within the University of California scientific community, 3) personal exposure to leading research and educational programs in world-wide institutions, and 4) provision of summer "hands-on" training opportunities for K-12 and community college students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to enable, by controlled molecular assembly, the creation of multi-functional devices made up of thin films, coatings or fibers that have thickness' which are the diameter of a human hair or smaller. The thin films, coatings and fibers will contain self-assembled, 3-d patterned and interfaced functional components that are dimensioned on the molecular and nanoscale. Synthesis and processing are carried out simultaneously to greatly reduce the expense and time normally associated with multi-step assembly. Commercial interest includes low-dielectric coatings, optical limiters, photovoltaics, photocatalysts, chemical and bio sensors, displays, microcavity lasers and laser arrays, battery electrolytes, and optical data storage. The educational emphasis for undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral researchers working on this project includes the promotion of professional careers for female students and postdoctoral associates, providing cutting edge collaborative interdisciplinary interactions and resources within the University of California scientific community, personal exposure to leading research and educational programs in world-wide institutions, and provision of summer "hands-on" training opportunities for K-12 and community college students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0233728</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chmelka</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bradc@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Galen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stucky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stucky@chem.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
      <CityName>SANTA BARBARA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
