<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-France Cooperative Research: Genetics and Chemical Ecology of Reticulitermes Termites</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>22500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jennifer Slimowitz Pearl</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0233238&lt;br/&gt;Vargo&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year award for U.S.-France cooperation in population ecology involves the research groups of Edward Vargo at North Carolina State University and Anne-Genevieve Bagneres at the University of Tours' Institute for Insect Biology. They will investigate the genetics and chemical ecology of social insects, in particular, Reticulitermes termites. This species plays an important role in decomposition of cellulose in natural ecosystems. They are serious structural pests throughout the temperate regions of the Northern Hemisphere, including France and the United States. The investigators address two important aspects: colony social organization and taxonomy. They will use molecular genetic markers and analytical chemical techniques to investigate colonies and population of R. santonensis, a subterranean termite found in France. Comparisons to R. flavipes and general utility of chemical characters will also be studied. The US investigator brings to this collaboration the technique of molecular marker genotyping using microsatellite loci. This is complemented by the French investigator's research on chemical analysis of cuticular hydrocarbons and soldier defensive secretions in social insects. The collaboration will advance understanding of how colonies and populations of these social insects are organized and the extent to which differences in biochemical signatures among colonies reflect genetic variation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award represents the US side of a joint proposal to the NSF and the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS). NSF will cover travel funds and living expenses of the US investigator, postdoctoral researcher and graduate student. The CNRS will support visits to US of the French participants.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0233238</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vargo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ed_vargo@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/27/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
      <CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
      <ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5980</Code>
      <Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>5918</Code>
      <Text>FRANCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
