<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Improvement of the Fish, Amphibian, and Reptile Collections at the Bell Museum of Natural History</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>214000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080208</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard M. McCourt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;A grant has been awarded to Bell Museum of Natural History at the University of Minnesota under the direction of Dr. Andrew Simons to recurate the holdings of the Fish, Amphibian, and Reptile collections. These collections contain valuable specimens documenting the historical diversity of fishes, amphibians, and reptiles of the upper Midwest. The collections date from the 1890's and thus represent an irreplaceable historical archive. The collection is actively used and a valuable resource to researchers as well as state and federal agencies. The improvements will safeguard the collection from deterioration and loss of specimens, and enhance access of researchers to data and collection records. Currently the specimens are preserved in 40% isopropyl alcohol, considered inappropriate for long term preservation. Several containers are inadequate and some are deteriorating. Old specimen labels are deteriorating and need immediate replacement. The electronic database is incomplete and contains several errors that will be corrected. &lt;br/&gt;The proposed improvements to the collection include transfer from 40% isopropyl alcohol to 70% ethanol; transfer of specimens from old deteriorating containers to new jars and stainless steel tanks; relabeling of the entire collection using archival quality materials; and standardization and update of the database. The updated database will be available and searchable on the Web. &lt;br/&gt;The activities described in the proposal will train graduate and undergraduate students in collection management procedures. The fish, amphibian, and reptile collections, although primarily research collections, are used regularly in public programs at the Bell Museum. These uses include tours of the collection, loan of specimens for exhibits, and inclusion of high school teachers and students into activities in the collections. The funded activities will also make valuable information regarding specimens in the Bell collections available to the public, researchers, and state and federal agencies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0234432</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Simons</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>asimons@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
      <CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
      <ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
