<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2003 Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Conference on Learning &amp; Memory, April 9 - 13, 2003</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>11206</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Diane M. Witt</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0235420 Grodzicker, Terri I&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference on learning and memory (April 9-13, 2003) will bring together researchers interested in understanding how the brain and nervous system form and retain memories. Different model organisms will be discussed to decipher the biochemical, molecular, electrophysiological and behavioral underpinnings of learning and memory. Young scientists, woman, and minorities will be recruited to participate. The meeting will include platform and poster presentations, and discussions of current research and concepts. Sessions will include invertebrates and vertebrates, in vivo and in vitro approaches, raging from cellular molecular to systems approaches.&lt;br/&gt; The impact of this conference will extend to numerous fields of study that are interested in computational models and cellular and molecular mechanisms underlying plasticity and learning. Prior meetings of a similar nature have been held at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory almost every other year since 1992. However, the present conference will be unique in that it will integrate across levels, paradigms and preparations to characterize the cognitive aspects of learning and memory. The meeting will include approximately 200 scientists from the US and around the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0235420</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Terri</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grodzicker</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grodzick@cshl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>David</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stewart</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>stewart@cshl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</Name>
      <CityName>COLD SPRING HARBOR</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117244220</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5163678307</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 BUNGTOWN ROAD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
