<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Documentation of the Nadou Language of Hainan and the Reconstruction of Proto-Hlai</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6685</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Guy Van Orden</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Under the direction of Dr. Diana Archangeli, and with NSF support, Mr. Peter Norquest will collect and analyze data for his doctoral dissertation. His research concerns one endangered language, the Hlai language Nadou, spoken on Hainan Island, China. The non-Chinese languages of Hainan are in danger of succumbing to modern Chinese influence, a trend that is true of minority languages throughout China. The project will document the Nadou language as it is currently spoken and use it to produce a comprehensive reconstruction of the words that occurred in ProtoHlai, providing an up-to-date analysis of its sound system. Files containing the recordings will be posted on a website for public use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The reconstruction of Proto-Hlai will add to current knowledge of the Kra-Dai family to which Hlai belongs. Kra-Dai is one of the five major language families of Southeast Asia. This linguistic research will complement research in other fields of human prehistory such as archaeology and population genetics. The combined use of historical linguistics, archaeology, and population genetics allows the reconstruction of history when written records are not available. The findings will increase our knowledge of Southeast Asian prehistory and provide a deeper understanding of Southeast Asia from a linguistic point of view. The reconstruction of Proto-Hlai will also provide valuable data upon which to test current theories of contemporary languages, and will be a useful reference for Kra-Dai scholars, field workers in a broader Southeast Asian context, theoretical phonologists, and typologists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0236674</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Archangeli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dba@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/19/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Arizona</Name>
      <CityName>Tucson</CityName>
      <ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arizona</StateName>
      <StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1311</Code>
      <Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
