<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Microbial Genome Sequencing: Sequencing of the Genome of Myxococcus Xanthus</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1150000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Patrick P. Dennis</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Myxococcus xanthus, the most intensively studied myxobacterial species, is the preeminent bacterial model of multicellular development, cell differentiation, and gliding motility, and serves as a model for single-species biofilms. Myxobacteria possess a rich secondary metabolism that includes synthesis of over 150 extracellular molecules with antimicrobial and anti-cancer activities. Myxobacteria play an important role in maintaining the fertility of soil and constitute a taxonomically and physiologically unique group of organisms within the delta subdivision of the proteobacteria, none of which have been sequenced. Over 30 academic research groups focus on many aspects of the biology of this unusual organism. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A low coverage sequence of M. xanthus has previously been accomplished by Cereon Genomics and is available to registered academic researchers and collaborators. This resource, while useful for some purposes, is inadequate for comprehensive analysis of the function of the genome. The lack of a completed genome minimizes the usefulness of comparisons of M. xanthus to other completed genomes. The annotated sequence to be completed and made publicly available through this project will provide the critical resource for going forward in the functional analysis of the M. xanthus genome.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The data from this project will have broad scientific impact, contributing to knowledge in such areas as genome evolution, genome enhancement for multicellular life, and bacterial chromosome size vs. stability. Educational initiatives will bring Myxococcal genomics to high school teachers via an educational activity presented at a national teachers conference and a TIGR Genomics Course for Educators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a Microbial Genome Sequencing Award funded through a collaborative program between the National Science Foundation and the Department of Agriculture.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0236595</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nierman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wnierman@jcvi.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tamara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Feldblyum</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tamaraf@tigr.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/26/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Institute for Genomic Research</Name>
      <CityName>Rockville</CityName>
      <ZipCode>208500334</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3017957591</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9712 Medical Center Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
