<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>High Performance Fiber Reinforced Cement Composites - International Workshop</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>20500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Steven L. Mccabe</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Summary: Fiber reinforced cement composites (FRCs or FRCCs) have made striking advances in recent years, due, on one hand, to several technological developments (involving the matrix, the fiber, the interface, and the composite production process) and, on the other hand, to a better understanding of the fundamental mechanisms controlling their particular behavior. The definition of "high performance" fiber reinforced cement composites (HPFRCC) is now well understood by researchers and implies a stress-strain response in tension that exhibits strain hardening accompanied by multiple cracking. High performance behavior at low fiber content, that is, lower cost is one of the objective of many research studies; it opens the way to large scale structural applications not only in evident areas such as seismic and impact resistant structures, but also in helping conceive innovative structural systems with strain hardening cement-based composites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The main objective of the proposed workshop is to lay out the latest developments in the field, provide a forum for discussion and exchange of information among top specialists, record up-to-date advances in the state of knowledge, set a reference benchmark to surpass in the future, and inspire directions to follow in near-future research. Special topics selected for this workshop include: 1) characterization and modeling; 2) interface properties; 3) impact resistance; 4) fire resistance; 5) scale effects; 6) self-compacting properties; 7) properties and modeling under reverse cyclic loading; and 8) hybrid composites. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed workshop will: 1) provide ideas and solutions at the forefront of research in the field; 2) foster a better understanding of the behavior, mechanics and applications of cement-based composites; 3) help strengthen the technical background of participants allowing them to address more challenging technical issues in the future; 4) engage and train younger researchers; 5) help in knowledge transfer to the classroom; 6) set a reference benchmark to surpass; 7) inspire directions to follow in near-future research; and 8) nurture international cooperation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The applications of HPFRCC in thin sheet products such as cladding, pipes, poles, and housing, as well as in seismic and blast resistant structures, will have an immense impact on the serviceability and durability of the infrastructure leading to broad benefits to society.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0236859</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Antoine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Naaman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>naaman@engin.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/03/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
