<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>International Workshop on Advanced Anode Materials for High Temperature Fuel Cells, Strasbourg, France</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>6000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070009</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In the search for new, improved energy systems for the 21st century, the emphasis is on environmentally friendly, efficient means of energy conversion and storage. High temperature fuel cells offer energy conversion efficiencies as high as 70% and low pollutant emissions, but significant technical and cost problems remain to be overcome for power plants utilizing natural gas. There is also considerable excitement about other applications of high temperature fuel cells including transportation and portable generation. High temperature fuel cells offer considerable promise for working with the hydrocarbon fuels required for these applications. Closely allied to these applications in fuel cell technology is the use of electrochemical reactors for the industrially important electrocatalytic oxidation of hydrocarbons. In the long term solid oxide fuel cell (SOFC) technology is foreseen as a candidate for a much more efficient electrolysis of steam and carbon dioxide. In summary, the high temperature electrochemical oxidation of hydrocarbons is an area of considerable strategic, environmental and economical importance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of the proposed NSF/DOE/ESF workshop, planned for Strasbourg, France on December 9-11, 2002, is to promote U.S./European collaborative investigations on the solid-state electrochemical oxidation of hydrocarbons. The proposed workshop, which will cover both fundamental and applied aspects, will be unique in its focus on scientific issues related to hydrocarbon anode materials. The Program will facilitate the exchange of ideas, educate the participant's groups regarding state-of-the-art worldwide activities, promote educational and research opportunities abroad for young scientists, and develop common programs of activity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0236872</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barnett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>s-barnett@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Northwestern University</Name>
      <CityName>Evanston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
