<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Efficient Resource Allocation and Control in Mobile Wireless Networks with Multimedia Services</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>428424</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Darleen L. Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The explosive growth of the Internet and the continued dramatic increase for all wireless services are fueling the demand for increased capacity, data rates, supported multimedia services, and support for different Quality of Service (QoS) requirements for different classes of services. Wideband CDMA (WCDMA) has been proposed as a key air interface technique for third generation (3G) wireless systems, and will continue to be adopted as a strong candidate for 4G systems that will provide differentiated services to multimedia traffic. With the capability of dynamically varying user channel rates, WCDMA systems can provide more flexibility in bandwidth allocation. Although the out-coming new radio technology will bring more bandwidth at air interface, if not managed properly, the bandwidth resources will not meet the requirements of future users.&lt;br/&gt;In order to address the overall problem of offering efficient and effective wireless multimedia services that meet the users' QoS (Quality of Service) requirements in mobile wireless networks we plan to provide an integrated solution by investigating the various involved problems from two different levels and angles which are aligned with the two main elements associated with the networks under consideration: wireless nature and mobility. &lt;br/&gt;Specifically, given the strict multimedia user requirements, in order to satisfy the main objective of this proposal of designing efficient wireless resource allocation methods we first remove the traditional assumptions of infinite number of users and fixed packet lengths, and analyze the wireless system performance under a more general and realistic case with finite population of voice and data users, finite buffers and variable packet length for data users. Given the wireless nature of the environment under consideration and the variations in the channel capacity, an efficient data rate scheduling scheme that adapts to the changing channel condition is investigated in order to maximize the weighted system throughput. An adaptive compensation technique is also employed in order to guarantee the fair allocation of resources among the competing users despite of the variation of channel capacity. Furthermore in order to deal with the issue of mobility and congestion in mobile wireless networks and their impact on the users' QoS, we study the enhancement of admission control and handoff process by introducing and investigating the following additional dimensions: flexible advanced bandwidth reservation and reconfiguration to optimize the bandwidth utilization especially when services with flexible QoS are supported; integration of pricing and admission control to maximize the users' total utility and alleviate or minimize the network congestion; design of a mobile agent based system to provide a flexible and comprehensive framework to implement these management processes and schemes.&lt;br/&gt;The proposed educational plan includes: undergraduate and graduate teaching; introduction of new courses; graduate student advising and mentoring; undergraduate project supervision; participation in an outreach program; lectures at local technical high schools; and finally, enhancement of existing laboratory infrastructure and facilities. Among the objectives of the education plan is to create an attractive research and educational environment in which both graduate and undergraduate students alike can collaborate and work together in order to learn and discover. Furthermore NJIT has a significant presence of minority and women students (~40% and ~18% respectively) and it is expected that some of these students will have the opportunity to contribute to this project. Finally I expect that the proposed plan will allow me to continue to expand on the already established international dimension of my career-development.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0237331</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Symeon</FirstName>
      <LastName>Papavassiliou</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Papavassiliou@adm.njit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Newark</CityName>
      <ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>323 DOCTOR MARTIN LUTHER</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0206000</Code>
      <Name>Telecommunications</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
