<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Electrochemical Measurements at Liposomes and Lipid Nanotubes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>662000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Professor Andrew Ewing of Pennsylvania State University is supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program to fabricate unilamellar liposomes to use as models for biological cells. The idea is to study fusion of the liposomes using advanced electrochemical methods in order to learn about fusion itself, and as a model for cell exocytosis. Microelectrode work as well as scanning electrochemical microscopy (SECM) using nanotube tips will be performed. Parameters to be examined include vesicle size, mode of fusion, membrane composition, pH and ionic strength and development of an artificial dense core with hydrogels. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Exocytosis is a fundamental process underlying communication between cells, for example between neurons. A better understanding of exocytosis could lead to improved models of brain function and treatment. Fusion of vesicles is an important process in drug delivery. There are applications of this work in microfluidics and possibly for biosensors as well.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/30/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0237180</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ewing</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>age@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/30/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
      <CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
