<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Educational Program in Neuromuscular Biomechanics and Uncovering the Neuromuscular Biomechanics of Dexterous Manipulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>409000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Semahat S. Demir</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0237258&lt;br/&gt;Valero-Cuevas&lt;br/&gt;This five-year CAREER Development project establishes the foundation for interdisciplinary education and research in neuromuscular biomechanics at Cornell University. The project develops two objectives: (a) uncover the neuromuscular biomechanics of dexterous manipulation; and (b) integrate engineering and neuroscience into an interdisciplinary educational network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dexterity is defined in the engineering sense of being able to perform stable dynamic manipulation. Research objectives focus on using engineering science to rigorously characterize dexterous manipulation, and to distinguish between the relative contributions of passive and active biological elements of the hand to stabilize manipulation. To achieve these goals, an integrative and interdisciplinary approach will combine nonlinear dynamics, robotics, biomechanics, and neurophysiology in a unique manner. Three specific investigations are proposed: (1) Analyze human dexterous manipulation experimentally using bifurcation theory. (2) Characterize brain and muscle activity during dexterous manipulation using functional MRI and electromyography. And, (3) use a computer biomechanical model of a multi-digit hand to predict the limits of dexterity with and without neural activity, and test these limits using a robotic manipulator. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the neuromuscular biomechanics of dexterous manipulation in humans will revolutionize understanding of biological motor function, aid in the diagnosis and treatment of hand impairment, and greatly expand the capabilities of robotic hands. The PI's previous work established a theoretical, computer modeling, and experimental foundation for the neuromuscular biomechanics of static force production of individual digits. This foundation will be expanded: (1) by using nonlinear dynamical analysis (to enable the use of reduced order models) to study the transitions from dynamical stability to instability in this complex system and (2) by integrating cerebral, muscular and biomechanical measurements in the context of a comprehensive computer model of multi-digit manipulation. The understanding gained from studying the human hand will be instrumental to improving dexterous manipulation in humans (clinical applications) and machines (robotic manipulators). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational objective is to develop an interdisciplinary educational network that integrates engineering and neuroscience, which will have a broad impact on bioengineering education. The educational methodology will promote discovery in neuromuscular biomechanics among a diverse population spanning from high school students to practicing researchers and clinicians. Education and research will be integrated by: 1) Creating an undergraduate and graduate educational program in neuromuscular biomechanics to improve and broaden the engineering curriculum, 2) Actively promoting opportunities for high school and undergraduate students from underrepresented groups to become involved in neuromuscular biomechanics research and 3) advocating the importance of engineering concepts and methods to researchers and clinicians in neuroscience, motor control, hand therapy, and hand surgery.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0237258</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Francisco</FirstName>
      <LastName>Valero-Cuevas</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>valero@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/12/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Cornell University</Name>
      <CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
      <ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0203000</Code>
      <Name>Health</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1675</Code>
      <Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5345</Code>
      <Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9231</Code>
      <Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9251</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
