<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Signal Processing for Practical Data Communication over the Doubly-Selective Wireless Channel</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>399770</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John Cozzens</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;0237037&lt;br/&gt;Philip Schmiter&lt;br/&gt;Ohio State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The rapidly evolving global information infrastructure includes broadband wireless communication as a key component. Communication technology of the future will need to operate at the data rates, at high carrier frequencies, in high mobility situations, and under high levels of co-channel interference, all while maintaining reliable data transmission using small and inexpensive components. The fundamental challenge for future wireless technology stems from the harsh characteristics of the wireless propagation channel.&lt;br/&gt;In specific, reflections from objects in the physical environment induce rapidly changing echo patterns which make it difficult for the receiver to recover the transmitted information without error. Especially challenging are doubly-selective channels, i.e., channels which echo or blur the transmitted information significantly in both the time and frequency domains. Since, these characteristics arise when high-rate information streams are propagated at high frequencies in highly mobile environments, the success of future wireless applications hinges on our ability to communicate information reliably over the doubly-selective channel.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research investigates practical signaling, detection, and estimation strategies for spectrally-efficient broadband data communication over doubly-selective wireless channels. Orthogonal frequency division multiplexing, known for its advantages in time-non-selective fading, is used as a starting point in the &lt;br/&gt;study of practical data detection and channel estimation methods. Extending these ideas, the investigators focus on non-orthogonal multicarrier signaling schemes which are specifically designed to optimize detection performance under receiver complexity constraints.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0237037</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Schniter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>schniter@ece.osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/08/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6142923732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
