<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: A Composition System for Computer Graphics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>521780</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Chitaranjan Das</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>CAREER: A Composition System for Computer Graphics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Engineers and artists approach problems in a very different manner. The terms engineer and artist are used in a very broad way; engineers are people who primarily build things and tend to approach problems by asking how something can be done. Artists, on the other hand, create content and focus on what information they are trying to convey. Both of these approaches are important, and it is often the intersection of the two that produces the most compelling results. Computer graphics has been fortunate in that a large artistic community is actively involved its development. Unfortunately, software design is still largely in the hands of the engineers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this proposal is to bring the artistic approach into existing software and to bridge the communication gap between artists and engineers. As a maturing field, computer graphics is ready to address the problem of purposeful display - not just how to render an image from a model, but how should it be rendered so as to convey specific information about that model.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0238062</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Cindy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Grimm</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>grimmc@onid.orst.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/19/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
