<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Transition Pathways in Complex Systems. Theory and Numerical Methods.</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>540000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract of NSF Proposal 0239625&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Eric Vanden-Eijnden, Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Transition pathways in complex systems&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The description of complex system driven by rare events, or&lt;br/&gt;conformations, is a major challenge in applied mathematics and&lt;br/&gt;computational sciences. Well-known examples of conformations include&lt;br/&gt;nucleation events during phase transition, conformational changes in&lt;br/&gt;molecules, thermal activated switching of magnetic materials, and&lt;br/&gt;chemical reactions. The disparity between the execution time of the&lt;br/&gt;conformation event and the waiting time between these events is&lt;br/&gt;typically so large that it impossible to simulate the dynamics of&lt;br/&gt;these processes by solving directly the underlying dynamic equations.&lt;br/&gt;This project is a combined theorical and numerical effort to describe&lt;br/&gt;and simulate these rare conformation changes. The theoretical&lt;br/&gt;description of transition pathways in complex systems leads to&lt;br/&gt;challenging problem in probability and stochastic processes theory&lt;br/&gt;which require to go beyond the standard tools of large deviation&lt;br/&gt;theory and extensions thereof. These new theoretical tools will be&lt;br/&gt;developed so as to naturally lead to efficient algorithms, well-suited&lt;br/&gt;for the numerical investigation of the transition pathways required in&lt;br/&gt;realistic complex systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Applied mathematics has much to contribute, and much to gain in&lt;br/&gt;understanding via a coordinate program of analysis, simulation, and&lt;br/&gt;education the mechanisms by which rare conformation changes arise in&lt;br/&gt;complex systems. Topics to be addressed include: (a) the development&lt;br/&gt;of appropriate theoretical tools for the description of the transition&lt;br/&gt;pathways in complex systems; (b) the development of efficient&lt;br/&gt;numerical algorithms for the identification of these pathways; and,&lt;br/&gt;(c) the development of courses at undergraduate and graduate levels in&lt;br/&gt;applied stochastic methods which will provide the students with the&lt;br/&gt;necessary background to do research on these topics at the interface&lt;br/&gt;between mathematics, computer science, and the natural sciences.&lt;br/&gt;Successful pursuit of these issues requires a multidisciplinary&lt;br/&gt;effort, drawing expertise from computational sciences, applied&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, in the multiple fields in the natural sciences which&lt;br/&gt;involve complex dynamical systems. The students and postdoctoral&lt;br/&gt;scientists participating this effort will gain flexibility and&lt;br/&gt;perspective through exposure to these many disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239625</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vanden-Eijnden</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>eve2@cims.nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/07/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1266</Code>
      <Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
