<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Surface Modification of Textiles for Protective Clothing</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>487598</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joseph E. Hennessey</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project involves the modification of the surface of textiles through graft polymerization of an oxidizing polymer resulting in a fabric which has the ability to eradicate/neutralize pathogenic microorganisms, pesticides, and chemical/biological weapons. The fabric could be used to produce medical textiles in order to reduce the transmission of infectious pathogens in hospitals, protect agricultural workers from contact with pesticides, and protect military personnel and first responders from contact with chemical/biological weapons in the event of terrorism or war. The Phase I research showed that the grafted fabric was highly effective against both microbial and chemical agents. The modified fabric was also found to be non-irritating to both intact and abraded (compromised) skin. In this Phase II project the research will consist of optimizing the graft polymerization process, extensive testing of the optimized fabric against microbial and chemical challenges, durability testing through repeated laundering, mechanical property evaluation, extensive cytotoxicity and irritation testing, capacity and regenerability assessment, stability assessment in storage, pilot plant production runs, and custom production/testing of fabric for a strategic partner.&lt;br/&gt; The fabric technology to be developed in this project has a vast amount of potential in a variety of niche applications in the medical, agricultural, and military arenas. In addition to the huge markets that exist for these products, there are obvious societal benefits that are inherent with the technology. Infection control is a huge problem in medical facilities resulting in prolonged hospital stays and leads to higher medical costs. The modified fabric could be constructed into medical textiles for use as surgical drapes, scrubs, lab coats, bed sheets, privacy drapes, gowns, etc. Farm workers could protect themselves from exposure to the pesticides they use in the field. The fabric could be employed in the production of protective clothing for first responders and military personnel who find themselves in an environment where there is a potential risk&lt;br/&gt;of exposure to chemical/biological weapons.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239038</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Waheguru</FirstName>
      <LastName>Singh</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>proposals@lynntech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/22/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Don</FirstName>
      <LastName>Elrod</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>don.elrod@lynntech.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/23/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/22/2004</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Lynntech, Inc</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
      <ZipCode>778456023</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9797642200</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2501 Earl Rudder Freeway South</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
