<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Detailed Chemical Abundances in Galactic Star Clusters-- Fundamental Astronomy and Education Inside and Outside Closed Boxes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>486051</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020419</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Scott Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal ID: AST-0239518&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Clemson University &lt;br/&gt;PI: King, Jeremy&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Jeremy King will use his CAREER award at Clemson University to determine high precision chemical abundances for the stars in a sample of open clusters. He will consistently determine the abundances of Li, C, O, Na, Mg, Al, Si, K, Ca, Ti, Cr, Fe, and Ni; these elements have varied nucleosynthetic origins, circumstellar condensation temperatures, and contributions to interior/atmospheric stellar opacities. Dr. King will use the magnitude and variations of these derived abundances to address several fundamental astrophysical issues, including the efficacy of standard stellar models, the relationship between age and metallicity in the galactic disk, the relationship between age and chromospheric emission in stars, and the absolute ages of star clusters. He will also study the chemical homogeneity in several kinematically-defined "stellar moving groups" as a test of their existence. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to his research, Dr. King will enable the growth of observational astronomy at Clemson University through education and outreach. He will involve undergraduate students in his research, and develop astronomy-related Java applets containing self-assessment and conceptual extension exercises. The development of a dedicated astronomy server, Tiger Premier Astronomy Web Server (TigerPAWS), will not only meet the increased needs of the undergraduate students but also provide educational materials for K-12 classrooms. He will also deliver astronomy outreach programs to several different groups in South Carolina: TigerTailgate Astronomy at football games, Tigers Towards Astronomy In the Life of Seniors (TigerTAILS) for senior citizens, Tiger Rural Observational Astronomy Resource (TigerROAR) for rural K-12 students populating special education classrooms, and Tiger STudents Routinely In Precarious Educational Settings (TigerSTRIPES), aimed at youth under the care of the juvenile detention system.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239518</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
      <LastName>King</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jking2@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/12/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clemson University</Name>
      <CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1219</Code>
      <Text>SPECIAL PROGRAMS IN ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1207</Code>
      <Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1215</Code>
      <Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
