<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Hybrid Lattice Boltzmann Technique for Heat Transfer Prediction</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will produce a unique computational tool for heat transport prediction in industrial devices by hybridizing our Digital Physics technology based on Lattice Boltzmann Methods (LBM) for hydrodynamics with efficient partial differential equation (PDE) solution for heat transfer. The project will start with the development and implementation of a wide range of physical features including variable thermodynamic and kinetic molecular properties as well as flow dependent turbulent/transitional Prandtl number, followed by introducing algorithms that ensure stable, accurate, and noiseless performance of the full-physics LBM/PDE algorithm. Upon algorithm optimization and benchmarking, we will focus on full thermal studies of industrial devices provided by our commercial customers. These beta tests will be followed by Phase III commercialization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The hybrid thermal transport prediction tool for development in this Phase II SBIR project will open major new commercial markets for our current PowerFLOW product, especially at the engineering design level, as well as open important new markets for novel technologies in various industrial problems ranging from classical macroscopic flows to microscopic flows like those in MEMS devices. This new technology should also establish new markets for computer aided engineering (CAE), especially in manufacturing industries.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/13/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239176</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ilya</FirstName>
      <LastName>Staroselsky</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ilya@exa.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/13/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Exa Corporation</Name>
      <CityName>Burlington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>018030000</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7815640287</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>55 Network Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
