<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Creating Nanostructured Gratings on Microstructures for Residual Strain/Stress Measurement in NEMS/MEMS and Traction Force Measurement in Cells</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>454000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>George A. Hazelrigg</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) Program project is intended to create nanostructured gratings (e.g., 1D nanograting lines and 2D nanograting dots) on micromachined devices for residual strain/stress measurements in MEMS (Microelectromechanical Systems) and NEMS (Nanoelectromechanical Systems); and, bio traction force measurements in real time and in live cells. This research project is a unique combination of MEMS, NEMS, nano-optics, biomechanics, and nanomanufacturing. This project involves several broad but highly interconnected areas of micro/nanomanufacturing research, all related to translating morphological recognition into micro/nanomechanics directly in thin films, in real time, and/or in live cells. This project aims at developing several novel nanostructured gratings and the corresponding measurement techniques based on the current emerging nanofabrication/nanomanufacturing technologies. Preliminary results show that the sensitivity of the methodology is at least three orders of magnitude higher than other techniques commonly used in residual strain/traction force measurements. The impact of the theoretical and experimental efforts would be significant. Through a careful leverage from current core competencies in MEMS/NEMS fabrication and biomedical processes, completion of this project will ensure that residual strain/stress in MEMS/NEMS structures and materials be directly imaged, and its magnitude quickly estimated, and more importantly, both direction and magnitude of small traction forces generated by different regions of a live cell be measured accurately and the maximum traction force generated under each of different regions of the cell be quantified in real time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator has chosen to focus the work on the domain of micro/nanomanufacturing science and technology for four reasons: (1) wide scope of the MEMS/NEMS and nanomanufacturing enterprise naturally fosters interdisciplinary research; (2) the investigator has a long track record of expertise and direct involvement with such systems and technologies, giving the project the benefit of a thorough understanding of the real issues, as well as invaluable insights; (3) unquestionable economic and technological importance of MEMS/NEMS and micro/nanomanufacturing is compelling, (4) the investigator's connections with MEMS/NEMS and micro/nanomanufacturing organizations will afford opportunities to transform the research findings to concrete tools. The research project's educational program will encompass both curriculum development and development of innovation teaching techniques. The investigator is involved in a Distance Learning Program that plays an important role promoting the manufacturing engineering department in the classroom and online, providing important industrial connections, international recognition, and important technological initiatives. Students can benefit greatly from opportunities to design, implement and operate complete micro/nanosystems. The investigator has recently created one and will further develop one more micro/nanomanufacturing new courses that give students these opportunities. Collaborative work is planned and broader two-way interaction between the university and industry is highly anticipate</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239163</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
      <LastName>Zhang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>xinz@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/25/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
      <CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
