<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Spectroscopic Studies of Interface Structure and Strain in Low-dimensional Semiconductor Heterostructures by Laser-enhanced Nuclear Magnetic Resonance</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>526715</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Charles D. Pibel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this NSF-CAREER project, supported by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Hayes will examine the interfaces and defects in semiconductor heterostructures, such as AlGaAs/GaAs quantum wells or thin films of InGaP grown on InP, to obtain atomic-level information about the structure, geometry and the chemical nature of nanostructures present. Combined optically-polarized NMR and optically-detected NMR methods will be used to study the interfacial and defect structures, generally termed "laser-enhanced NMR." Because the information provided by each technique is complementary, the combination of the two types of spectroscopy in a single experiment can provide insights into structure and electronic properties of the material simultaneously.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This multidisciplinary research program, through participation in the University's Materials Science initiative, will enhance the infrastructure for research and education. The research component of this project will be integrated with the graduate and undergraduate teaching efforts. Graduate and undergraduate students, as well as postdoctoral research associates will participate in the research and will thereby acquire skills and training for advanced studies or employment in industry, academia, or government laboratories.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239560</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sophia</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hayes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hayes@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/24/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Washington University</Name>
      <CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
      <ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
