<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: An Interdisciplinary Approach Toward Understanding Dynamic Glycosylation in the Brain</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>540000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research program focuses on development of an understanding of the role of O-GlcNAc glycosylation in regulating neuronal function and communication, including the regulation of transcription and the control of genes important for learning and memory. The role of O-GlcNAc glycosylation in cyclic AMP response element binding protein-mediated transcription will be explored. Faciliated by development of a synthetic chemical probe enabling the accelerated identification of O-GlcNAc glycosylated proteins on a proteome-wide scale, such modified proteins will be identified in the brain. The educational experience of graduate, undergraduate, and high school students will be enahnced through tailored course discussion and research involvement, and efforts will be made to increase the representation of women in the chemical workforce through provision of support mechanisms and mentorship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the support of this CAREER Award from the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program and the Molecular and Cellular Biochemistry Program, Professor Linda Hsieh-Wilson, of the Department of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering at the California Institute of Technology, is exploring chemical changes important for brain function and dysfunction. Professor Hsieh-Wilson's studies additionally address the means by which the chemistry of the brain is spatiotemporally regulated to give rise to the intricate biology of the nervous system. These studies are leading to an understanding of the structural, functional, and physiological roles of specific chemical changes in the brain. Professor Hsieh-Wilson is involved in a number of programs designed to enhance the educational experience of graduate, undergraduate, and high school students through tailored course discussion and research involvement and to increase the representation of women in the chemical workforce.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239861</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hsieh-Wilson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lhw@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
      <CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
