<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Stream-of-Variation Modeling and Analysis for Multi-Station Manufacturing Processes Modeling Infrastructure for Virtual Assembly</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Donald Hearn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) Program grant supports an integrated research and education project on modeling; analysis and control of dimensional variation in complex multistage assembly processes (MAP) with compliant parts such as in automotive, aerospace, appliance and electronics industries. The goal is to develop a generic MAP model with capabilities to represent key product and process control characteristics/features (KPC/KCC) with varying resolution/"information granularity" that can be utilized during design, launch and full production phases of a new manufacturing system. The model will be based on a generic Computer-Aided Design and Manufacturing (CAD/CAM) system integrated with statistical analysis to predict manufacturing process performance in early design phase. A challenge facing the proposed plan is the diversity of required information and lack of physical and geometrical relations between KCC and KPC. The research will focus on developing: (1) variation propagation models integrating statistical and CAD/CAM information; (2) multi-resolution/granularity of KPC/KCC as they change during product development; (3) computational efficiency for simulation of multistage assembly processes; and (4) generic issues pertaining to new process-oriented modeling, design and control. The education efforts are to: (1) integrate statistical analysis into CAD/CAM courses; (2) explore challenges in the development and realization of new MAP systems; and (3) provide opportunities in developing and analyzing MAP systems using 3D simulation tools. It also includes creating grade-specific (graduate, undergraduate and K-12) projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: If successful, this project will lead to a new methodology that can: (1) Fundamentally integrate CAD/CAM models with statistical analysis to predict manufacturing process dimensional variability during design as it relates to compliant parts, thus continuously improving product quality while reducing overall new MAP development time through rapid fault root cause detection. (2) Facilitate math-based design and manufacturing of the MAP systems: The integration of product and process variables expands the classical "part interchangeability" concept into "process interchangeability" considered during early design phase of a new MAP development. This is critical in relation to suppliers selection, benchmarking or outsourcing. (3) Train Industrial Engineers in statistical methods and their application in CAD/CAM systems thus preparing them towards developing a new generation of CAD/CAM system for virtual realization of MAP.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239244</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Dariusz</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ceglarek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>darek@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/08/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1786</Code>
      <Text>MANFG ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1187</Code>
      <Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9146</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9147</Code>
      <Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>MANU</Code>
      <Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
