<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>CAREER: Polyolefin-Inorganic Hybrid Materials</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>405000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070012</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The main objective of this award will be the synthesis of novel polyolefin inorganic hybrid copolymers. Investigation of the physical and mechanical properties of these new materials will also be undertaken, and the findings from these studies will then serve to further direct synthetic efforts. By copolymerizing molecularly precise nanometer-scale inorganic particles with simple vinyl monomers development of the fundamental understanding necessary to exploit the resulting structure-property correlation will emerge. Thus, it should be possible to enhance the physical properties of the resulting copolymer hybrids through the anticipated sizable intermolecular interactions that occur between the nanometer-scale particles and through their attachment to polymer chains. These hybrid materials are of great interest in that it may be possible to expand the general utility of commodity polyolefins beyond their current day use. For example, improvement of the strength, toughness, or upper temperature stability of isotactic polypropylene into the realm of engineering resins would allow for use of these hybrid materials in applications that are today dominated by more expensive materials. Pursuit of a chemistry based "bottom-up" approach to the formation of polyolefin nanocomposites will permit harnessing the beneficial thermodynamics associated with self-assembly processes. This will reverse the unfavorable thermodynamics typically encountered in the melt extrusion "top-down" approach to the generation of polymer nanocomposites. Self-assembly processes will thus be used to advantage for generating desired configurations of inorganic particles dispersed in a polyolefin matrix.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research is the vehicle through which some of the most important learning takes place. Research projects offer students the opportunity to not only learn technical skills, experimental techniques, and the process of scientific discovery, but also about how they approach and solve problems and face challenges. This coupled with classroom and other educational opportunities will greatly aid students entering the modern workforce. A new graduate level course will be developed entitled "Industrial Polymers." This course will take a beginning-to-end approach of the chemistry and engineering that are necessary to successfully produce polymeric materials. This is intended to give the students a good technical grasp of the production of a selected set of industrial polymers. This research and development process is what many students will be participating in following completion of their graduate studies. Further leveraging of teaching and outreach activities will also occur through combining efforts with the NSF-sponsored Research Site for Educators in Chemistry (RSEC) on Polymer Chemistry in Western Massachusetts that is in the Polymer Science and Engineering Department at the University of Massachusetts. The goals of this program are (i) to modernize curricula by introducing interdisciplinarity to undergraduate research and education and (ii) to involve faculty and students from local institutions in frontier research in polymer science. The immediate and long-term impacts of this program will be profound. Approximately 60 Bachelors degrees in Chemistry are awarded each year from the participating institutions (nearly 90% women and underrepresented minorities). Teaching modules on polymer chemistry that are appropriate for inclusion in the curricula of the participating institutions will be developed and tested in the classroom. The approach does not advocate a complete change in the curriculum of Chemistry Departments but rather an injection of modern materials chemistry. Successful teaching modules will be disseminated nationally to chemical educators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/27/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>10/31/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0239475</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Coughlin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>coughlin@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/27/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
