<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US-PRC Workshop on Protection of Urban Infrastructure and Public Facilities Against Natural and Manmade Disasters</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25548</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Douglas A. Foutch</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal is to conduct a US-PRC joint workshop on development of new research opportunities for critical infrastructure protection. The focus will be on needed enabling technologies, and the identification of possible candidates for the purpose of demonstration and evaluation of these technologies, particularly those that can be applied to protect infrastructures against earthquake and other natural and manmade disasters in populated urban centers. Special consideration will be given to two types of urban structural systems :a building complex and a transportation network, against earthquake ground motions and accidental and intentional blast loads. This workshop is jointly supported the Ministry of Construction (MOC), National Natural Science Foundation (NNSF), Beijing Science and Technology Committee (BSTC), and Beijing Municipal Education Commission (BMEC) under the US-PRC Earthquake Protocol Annex III program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0240691</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>George</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lee</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gclee@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
      <CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
      <ZipCode>142607016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>402 Crofts Hall</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
