<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Two-Value Model of Intergroup Attitudes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>302863</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amber L. Story</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to better understand the nature and etiology of stereotypes, prejudice and discrimination. The model assumes that intergroup attitudes form an integral part of the individual's important psychological meaning system, and relates them to the fundamental human values of egalitarianism and conservatism. These two values are expected to relate to attitudes toward ingroups and outgroups, respectively. The proposed research is designed to help understand when and how individuals develop prejudices, and what may lead them to engage in discriminatory behaviors. The model also helps account for why intergroup attitudes change across age (because the importance of expressing one's fundamental values changes with age) and why intergroup attitudes are so difficult to change overall (because values are integral aspects of the self concept). Five study sets will test the model. The research involves summarizing and consolidating existing personality measures into the 2-value model, and testing the ability of the values to predict a variety of intergroup behaviors. These relationships are assessed at both the implicit as well as explicit levels. Many of the experiments are designed to assess how individuals resolve conflict between the two competing values. Another major goal of the work is to investigate how individuals develop their prejudices through the cultural transmission of values - parents and peers are expected to be important in this regard. The knowledge gained from the research may be useful in helping to design programs to alleviate or redirect negative intergroup beliefs, and preventing hostile behaviors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0240877</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stangor</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>cstangor@charlesstangor.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/03/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
