<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Coasts Under Stress II Conference, New Orleans, Louisiana, March 2003</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Thomas J. Baerwald</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Geographers have a long and distinguished history in the study of coastal systems. Much of the research has addressed coastal development and resources, coastal hazards, coastal geomorphology and nearshore processes, and coastal environmental systems. Few venues have brought together these disciplinary scholars working in the full range of coastal inquiry, however. Twenty-five years ago, H. Jesse Walker organized a joint meeting of the (then) Commission on Marine Geography of the Association of American Geographers and the (then) Commission on the Coastal Environment of the International Geographical Union. The effort was a symposium entitled Coasts Under Stress, which included paper and poster sessions and a field excursion, Papers based on many of this symposium's presentations were assembled in a special issue of the Zeitschrift fur Geomorphologie. This award will support a comparable international conference on critical issues in coastal geography. Sponsored jointly by the Coastal and Marine Specialty Group of the Association of American Geographers and the Coastal Commission of the International Geographical Union, this meeting will bring senior and junior members of the profession to New Orleans, the site of the 2003 AAG annual meeting. Paper and poster presentation over a two-day period plus a four-day field excursion to study sites in the issue-rich Gulf Coast will convey the results of recent research, spur intellectual exchange, foster networking, and broaden the backgrounds and perspectives of participants. Papers based on many of the 2003 conference presentations will be disseminated through a special issue of the international Journal of Coastal Research. NSF support will facilitate the participation of a number of grad students and international scholars as well as help cover publication costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference should facilitate scholarly attention and scientific inquiry into issues associated with the management of finite resources in areas of high natural and cultural stress. Broader impacts of the research will include fostering of international collaborations and the provision of education and training opportunities for a number of graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0241298</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Norbert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Psuty</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>psuty@marine.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/23/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1045</Code>
      <Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9189</Code>
      <Text>WATER RESOURCES/COASTAL &amp; MARINE ENVIRON</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>EGCH</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
