<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Litigation and the Electoral Connection-An Analysis of State Attorneys General and Modern Business Regulation</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>5837</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frank P. Scioli Jr.</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Research on policy entrepreneurs has grown into a thriving field, but its practical applications have been limited. In this Doctoral Dissertation Research Project the student analyzes a much-overlooked policy maker-the state attorney general-as an entrepreneur. Because they are motivated by reelection and the pursuit of higher office, attorneys general are alert to opportunities to spot market failures, punish businesses and score electoral points with consumer/voters. The student posits that every state attorney general has the potential to be an entrepreneur, but various factors either hinder or help them in realizing this potential. In the first study, the student analyzes the conditions under which state attorneys general join multi-state consumer protection lawsuits, arguing that increased activity results in entrepreneurial behavior. He hypothesizes that a variety of ideological, institutional and environmental variables facilitate entrepreneurial behavior. Preliminary findings show &lt;br/&gt;that a liberal electorate and increased legal personnel within the attorney general office result in attorneys general acting as entrepreneurs. In the second study, the student aim to upholds the assumptions of the first study, by showing that attorneys general with strong records of consumer regulation enforcement are more likely to run for and win governorships or Senate seats.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0241904</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Teske</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pteske@datalab2.sbs.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/22/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1371</Code>
      <Text>POLITICAL SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
