<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Special Session on International Research Collaboration, MRS Meeting, Boston, Massachusetts</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070009</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This project is an information exchange between research managers and policy-makers from several countries in the form of a workshop, held at the Fall Meeting of the Materials Research Society (MRS), in 2002. Mechanisms of governmental research funding will be highlighted, along with a description of the technical areas (related to materials) that are of interest, for each of the participating countries. This information will form the basis of discussions of the mechanisms by which joint research programs can be created, in which funding is provided for the researchers principally by their own respective governments. The workshop sessions will be open to the attendees of the MRS Fall Meeting, who will be active participants in the discussion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: It is anticipated that this project will result in improved articulation of research funding programs in different nations, significantly facilitating the creation of joint research programs in Materials Science &amp; Engineering, between US-based researchers and those in other countries. It will encourage the creation of jointly-formulated proposals which allow the leveraging of research assets and expertise found diversely around the globe. The resulting experience with international collaborative research will form a strong basis for the extension of the models used here to all research subject areas supported by the various research agencies involved.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0242287</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
      <LastName>King</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>alexking@ameslab.gov</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Pachavis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pachavis@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/19/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
      <CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
      <ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0106000</Code>
      <Name>Materials Research</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
