<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Solid Models for Teaching and Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/31/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>84334</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080207</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Manfred D. Zorn</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Although molecular models have played a crucial role in research and teaching for over 100 years, today these models primarily are generated by computer graphics displays that are powerful in some respects but lacking in others. In order to bring balance to this situation, a computer program (SCULPT) has been written to create solid models of selected regions of macromolecules by using atomic coordinates from the Protein Data Bank. These model are constructed in wax, wood, or other materials to a scale corresponding to commercially available atomic models. This utilizes a dedicated computer numeric controlled (CNC) milling machine capable of machining wood (10,000rmp spindle speed) and large enough to build a model of most typical macromolecular binding or receptor sites. An educational consultant assists with the preparation of study guides and classroom materials for teaching high school advanced placement biology and chemistry students. The P.I. is actively involved in undergraduate and graduate teaching of biochemistry students. Research applications are derived from his laboratory and from collaborations with other groups.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0242318</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edgar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Meyer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>model_em@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
