<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Conference: Number Theory and Combinatorics in Physics; March 21-23, 2003; Gainesville, FL</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The investigators together with the University of Florida are hosting a Conference, ``Number Theory and Combinatorics in Physics.'' The main topics of the conference are q-hypergeometric functions, Rogers-Ramanujan identities, exactly integrable models and quantum field theory; alternating sign matrices and determinants; quantum computing; and the Riemann zeta-function, random matrices and quantum correlators. Each of these topics has been enriched by interactions between mathematics and physics. For example, deeper understanding of the alternating sign matrix conjecture of combinatorics was recently found when it was connected with the XXZ spin 1/2 model (on an odd number of sites) from statistical mechanics. In another recent example, Di Francesco and collaborators were able to exactly compute meander configuration exponents using methods of conformal field theory. The main goal of the conference is to bring mathematicians and physicists together to discuss and learn recent developments in these current topics. This interaction should help foster new developments in both mathematics and physics. There are eleven plenary speakers: George E. Andrews, Robert Calderbank, Philippe Di Francesco, Daniel Gottesman, Michio Jimbo, Barry McCoy, Tetsuji Miwa, James Propp, Michael Rubinstein, Xavier G. Viennot, and F.Y. Wu. There are thirteen 20 minute speakers. A number of graduate students and recent Ph.D.'s are participating. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Number Theory is concerned with properties of integers and is one of the oldest branches of mathematics. In the last 20 years Number Theory has had important applications to cryptography. The security of some modern cryptographic methods depends on the complexity of factoring integers. In 1994, Peter Shor showed theoretically how this complexity could be drastically reduced using a quantum computer. A quantum computer is based on the principles of quantum mechanics and is at present only a theoretical device. The concept of a quantum computer was first introduced by the Nobel prize-winning physicist Richard Feynman in his famous course on computation given at Caltech, 1983-1986. It is believed that in the next 20 years the new generation of computers will be quantum computers. This will necessitate synthesis of mathematics, quantum field theory and technology. This conference, Number Theory and Combinatorics in Physics, hosted at the University of Florida, is a forum where progress on such a synthesis can be made.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0242148</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Khandker</FirstName>
      <LastName>Muttalib</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>muttalib@phys.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>F.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Garvan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fgarvan@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Florida</Name>
      <CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Florida</StateName>
      <StateCode>FL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
