<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Natural History of a West Indian Herpetofauna</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>308561</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080303</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Avila University summer research program provides nine participating students with an opportunity to engage actively in science by conceiving, designing, and implementing a research project focusing on the natural history of amphibians and reptiles on West Indian islands. An intense two-week orientation will precede three weeks in the field during which data are collected for subsequent analysis and preparation of manuscripts suitable for submission to peer-reviewed journals. Every participant in six previous programs has published at least one research article or note. Selection of participants will be based on GPA and potential for pursuing graduate studies and careers in science. Other factors being equal, preference is given to students attending non-research institutions and universities providing limited opportunities for undergraduate research. During the ten-week program, students will become familiar with a variety of ecological research techniques. Complementing the research experience are a number of ancillary activities including seminars, workshops, and social functions. For an application and more information, interested students should check the Avila REU webpage: http://www.avila.edu/departments/biology/bobweb/7powreu.htm.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0242589</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Powell</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robert.powell@avila.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/11/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Avila University</Name>
      <CityName>Kansas City</CityName>
      <ZipCode>641451698</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8165013727</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>11901 Wornall Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
