<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>U.S.-Italy Cooperative Research Program: Probing Interdot Coupling within Semiconductor Quantum Dot Molecules</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>27900</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>01090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Graham M. Harrison</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0242579&lt;br/&gt;Phaneuf&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year award provides support for Raymond Phaneuf of the University of Maryland to work with Roberto Cingolani of the University of Lecce, Italy. The primary goal of their research is to investigate the coupling of self-assembled quantum dots in the InxGa1-xAs/GaAs system. They plan to accomplish self-assembly and to control coupling of small numbers of dots, and to selectively probe individual coupled-quantum dot molecules.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The two laboratories have complementary capabilities. The US laboratory will compare results for thin stressor layers grown on patterned substrates with those for lithographically produced arrays of alloy mesas to pattern the surface before regrowth. Parallel investigations using patterning and MOCVD growth will be carried out at Lecce. The Italian laboratory has developed the technique of using scanning tunneling luminescence to selectively probe individual coupled-quantum dot molecules. Existing applications of self-assembled quantum dots include optoelectronic devices such as quantum dot lasers. A potentially important application is the use of coupled quantum dots and qubits for quantum information processing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>11/14/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0242579</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Raymond</FirstName>
      <LastName>Phaneuf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>phaneuf@lps.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/17/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
