<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Foundational Tools for Data Literacy</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2525317</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Michael Haney</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This two project would revise and expand an existing software package, TableTop, as well as field test and disseminate tools that support students in K-12 in data representation and analysis. It specifically deals with data literacy and provides tools that are age appropriate. Both a general-purpose data tool that would be usable across a range of student activities and the supporting instructional and assessment materials will be developed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project builds on the earlier TableTop that is used in an estimated 85,000 classrooms. The original package is user-friendly and depends on visual representations, icons, and batched operations. The proposed project will produce an expanded set of version for various platforms and at level appropriate for different grade levels. It will include a revised and expanded interface that incorporates many of the features requested by teachers. It will support sharing across the web, easy access to many formats of data, an interface with Google, and the capability to work with various data collection devices such as PDA's.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has the potential to reach large numbers of students through a dissemination plan that supports curriculum developers incorporating these materials in their courses. The letters of support and the list of curriculum collaborators indicate that the project could be wide reaching, including both mathematics and science, K-12.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0242626</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hancock</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ch@tertl.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/09/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>TERC Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021401339</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6178739600</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2067 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
