<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>An Immuno-Mimetic Sensor-Actuator using Novel Polymeric Vesicles as Artificial Lymphocytes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>292633</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert M. Wellek</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>An Immuno-Mimetic Sensor-Actuator using Novel Polymeric Vesicles as Artificial Lymphocytes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this program the principal investigator will develop a breakthrough sensor-actuator, mimicking the immune system to identify, amplify signal from, and respond to low levels of multiple target compounds in&lt;br/&gt;a wet environment. This compact (and potentially chip-based), smart system will continuously&lt;br/&gt;monitor a test space and provide independent real time chemical feedback to multiple stimuli.&lt;br/&gt;Microelectronics could be integrated into this stand-alone device for added functions.&lt;br/&gt;The proposed technology exploits novel polymeric vesicles that will act as artificial&lt;br/&gt;lymphocytes, a type of white blood cell. The polymeric vesicles are a new invention, made of&lt;br/&gt;tough membranes that will encapsulate amplification or response molecules. Different surface&lt;br/&gt;receptors on different vesicles will code for target compounds that, when present in the testing&lt;br/&gt;environment, will activate particular vesicles. The test solution flows through an amplification&lt;br/&gt;cascade (a rough mimic of bone marrow) to replicate only the activated vesicles. Replicated&lt;br/&gt;vesicles (a crude mimic of plasma cells) will return to the test space to release response compounds&lt;br/&gt;such as drugs or inhibitors to counteract the target compound(s) detected.&lt;br/&gt;The replicator cascade is like a photomultiplier tube (PMT), with amplification occurring on&lt;br/&gt;each of several stages. The proposed device is, however, more advanced because, of the many&lt;br/&gt;target compounds cataloged, only those in the test space will be amplified. In the device, specific&lt;br/&gt;adhesive interactions facilitate separation of activated vesicles from those not yet activated. While&lt;br/&gt;the latter are recycled, activated vesicles are lyzed to release each test compound (or analog&lt;br/&gt;thereof), at a concentration higher than that at the stage inlet. This solution passes to the next stage&lt;br/&gt;where the process repeats, giving a powerlaw dependence of amplification on the stage number.&lt;br/&gt;This program will conduct the science and device development necessary to form the basis&lt;br/&gt;of a single stage that later could be combined with others to produce the cascade. At the stage&lt;br/&gt;level, the goal is to maximize amplification, maintaining selectivity for activated vesicles (not&lt;br/&gt;triggering the non-activated ones.) To accomplish this, the scientific investigation will address&lt;br/&gt;how adhesive interactions between receptors on vesicle and separator surfaces could be tuned&lt;br/&gt;through receptor placement and macroscopic parameters. Fundamental adhesive behavior will be&lt;br/&gt;assessed using micropipette aspiration methods (paralleling studies of cell adhesion) and compared&lt;br/&gt;with adhesive performance in device prototypes. Results will be interpreted using formalisms&lt;br/&gt;established for cell adhesion, appropriate for specific adhesive groups on a membrane capsule in a&lt;br/&gt;flowing solution.&lt;br/&gt;The specialized vesicles and their replication cascade form a sensor-actuator system whose&lt;br/&gt;end applications bridge a number of industries, from biomedical uses to chemical process control&lt;br/&gt;and environmental monitoring (closed bodies of water) and response. The proposed scientific&lt;br/&gt;investigation targets designs that meet the constraints for a robust technology that will be&lt;br/&gt;implantable or submersible. The scientific team bridges academic disciplines and specialty areas to&lt;br/&gt;combine expertise in polymer interfaces, biomimetics, adhesion, and MEMS. Graduate and&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate students from different engineering and scientific backgrounds will benefit from this&lt;br/&gt;synergistic approach to research, which preserves fundamental rigor and emphasizes engineering&lt;br/&gt;creativity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0242647</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
      <LastName>Santore</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>santore@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/25/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
      <CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
      <ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
