<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site Program at Kitt Peak National Observatory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>308118</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03020419</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robert Scott Fisher</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Proposal ID: AST-0243875&lt;br/&gt;Institution: AURA/NOAO/KPNO&lt;br/&gt;PI: Mould, Jeremy&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The National Optical Astronomy Observatory (NOAO) will continue its existing Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site at the offices of Kitt Peak National Observatory (KPNO) in Tucson, Arizona. Each year six students will be hired as full-time research assistants to work with KPNO astronomers on selected research projects for a period of twelve weeks over the summer. As part of their research activities, REU students will gain first-hand experience with KPNO's state-of-the art telescopes and instrumentation, and develop expertise in the tools of data analysis specific to astronomical research. In addition to the research project, the REU program at KPNO features weekly scientific lectures and colloquia by NOAO and visiting astronomers, informal lunches and group discussions, field trips to other telescope facilities in the Southwest, and a variety of recreational and social activities. All REU students will be encouraged to attend the American Astronomical Society winter meeting following their program to present a paper. Students will be recruited nationally, with special emphasis placed on recruiting qualified applicants from minorities underrepresented in science and engineering, including women, as well as students from institutions lacking access to research facilities or opportunities for paid research employment for undergraduates.&lt;br/&gt;***</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243875</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Mould</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmould@noao.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate>09/14/2007</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>Washington</CityName>
      <ZipCode>200053929</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2024832101</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1212 New York Avenue, N.W.,</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
      <StateCode>DC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
