<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Undergraduate Research in Biology: Interdependence Across Subdisciplines</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>79800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080303</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The aim of our summer undergraduate research program is to facilitate the maturation of undergraduate students as young scientists in biology by immersing them in an interactive, 11-week session of original research activities. The primary goals are to teach students the essentials of the scientific method, which are common to a spectrum of biological subdisciplines, and to expose students to the benefits of interaction, collaboration and interdependence across subdisciplines. The ultimate hope is to inspire students to pursue a life of service in the biological sciences, whether it is in research, applied science or education. The theme for our research activities is cellular stress physiology. Fundamental to all biological systems is the requirement for cellular adaptation to stress, thus enabling organismal propagation in diverse environments. Students will have opportunity to pursue projects among a wide range of cellular and organismal systems from yeast, mammalian cells in tissue culture, amphibian epidermal tissue, to xylem vessel elements in higher plants. The potential types of cellular stress responses examined will include salinity-induced osmotic stress, drought stress, freezing stress, UV-B radiation stress, biomechanical stress, and biochemical stress signaling. Students will play a pivotal role in the conception and design of their personal research projects and will participate in a 2-day retreat to formally present, evaluate and refine their research proposals. All projects will be student-initiated and student-generated within the framework of active, cutting-edge science. Students will be supervised by faculty-mentors in plant physiological ecology, mammalian cell biology, molecular biology, or developmental biology. Each summer the program will begin with a 14-day research orientation workshop during which students will be introduced to specific research techniques and immersed in the research process (literature review, hypothesis formulation, and hypothesis testing). Over the course of the summer, visiting scientists will hold special research seminars and spend time critiquing student projects. Students will receive professional training at special seminars or panel sessions and will participate in community outreach by hosting an "open house" for local school children and their parents. The program will conclude with a student research symposium, student poster session and banquet, bringing cohesion, celebration and closure to the summer experience. Students will receive a stipend of $3600, housing, meal allowance and travel assistance. For more information, contact Stephen Davis at davis@pepperdine.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243788</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Davis</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>davis@pepperdine.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brewster</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jay.brewster@pepperdine.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Donna</FirstName>
      <LastName>Nofziger Plank</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>donna.nofziger.plank@pepperdine.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swartzendruber</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>douglas.swartzendruber@pepperdine.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Vandergon</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thomas.vandergon@pepperdine.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate>07/23/2004</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Pepperdine University</Name>
      <CityName>Malibu</CityName>
      <ZipCode>902634819</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3105064819</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>24255 Pacific Coast Hwy</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>7226</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1359</Code>
      <Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9184</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY - INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
