<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Green Chemistry on the Palouse: A Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site at the Univerisity of Idaho and Washington State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>192000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Randall Christnert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Institution: University of Idaho PI: McHale &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) involving the chemistry departments at the University of Idaho and Washington State University will involve 10 students (8 NSF supported) during the summers of 2003-2005. This 10-week program will emphasize research topics in Green Chemistry which is defined as "design of chemical products and processes that reduce or eliminate the use and generation of hazardous substances". Jeanne L. McHale (Idaho) is the site director and Sue B.Clark (WSU) is the co-PI. Fourteen faculty from these institutions are available to supervise research projects encompassing subjects such as hazardous waste remediation, catalysis, solar energy conversion, and environmentally friendly synthesis. The collaborating departments will maximize their available resources for research and promote more diverse approaches to chemical research. Students will be recruited from regional colleges in the Pacific Northwest, which includes Washington, Idaho, Montana, Oregon, Alaska, and Wyoming. There will be an emphasis on attracting students from under-represented groups. Weekly seminars on research and career issues will alternate between the schools. A field trip will be taken to the Pacific Northwest National Laboratory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/01/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243760</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>I</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cheng</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ifcheng@uidaho.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/12/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jeanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>McHale</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jmchale@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate>10/12/2004</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Sue</FirstName>
      <LastName>Clark</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>s_clark@mail.wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Idaho</Name>
      <CityName>MOSCOW</CityName>
      <ZipCode>838443020</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2088856651</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Idaho</StateName>
      <StateCode>ID</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
