<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Cultural Anthropology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>216794</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda G. Lopez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This ten-week REU Site will provide a research opportunity for 9 students in cultural anthropology. The first five weeks of the program will be spent on instruction in fundamental cultural anthropology research techniques, and the second five weeks will be spent conducting individual research projects. Students will be trained in four major areas of cultural anthropology research: historical and testimonial case studies, participant observation, qualitative data analysis on text-interview material, and quantitative analysis of census and survey data. Students will also be taught the techniques and critical thinking skills necessary for conducting resource material location, library research, and the use of the Internet for research purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Throughout the ten weeks, students are exposed to such topics as: writing research results, stages of research, critical thinking, note-taking during research, getting published, and presenting at conferences. Students also participate in an ethics seminar and the UNT McNair Scholars' Friday Seminars.&lt;br/&gt;This award contributes to the Foundation's continuing efforts to attract talented students into careers in science through active undergraduate research experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243714</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Doug</FirstName>
      <LastName>Henry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>dhenry@pacs.unt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tyson</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gibbs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tgibbs@pacs.unt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Texas</Name>
      <CityName>DENTON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1155 Union Circle #305250</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
