<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Transport Theory with Bose-Einstein Statistics for RHIC and Investigations of Novel Properties of Dense Neutron-Rich Matter</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bradley D. Keister</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>In this RUI (Research in Undergraduate Institutions) renewal proposal, the PI&lt;br/&gt;proposes to undertake two new projects, i.e., (1) development and application of a&lt;br/&gt;transport theory with Bose-Einstein statistics for ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions&lt;br/&gt;at Brookhaven's Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collider (RHIC) and (2) investigations of nov-&lt;br/&gt;el properties of dense neutron-rich matter with energetic radioactive beams. The large&lt;br/&gt;number of pions produced and thus the high value of pion phase-space density reached&lt;br/&gt;in heavy-ion collisions at RHIC requires a proper inclusion of the Bose-Einstein s-&lt;br/&gt;tatistics (multi-boson symmetrization) in the reaction dynamics. The Bose-Einstein&lt;br/&gt;statistics is currently neglected in essentially all dynamical models for RHIC. The&lt;br/&gt;focus of the PI's work on the first project is to include the Bose-Einstein statistics&lt;br/&gt;in both the hadronization and the subsequent dynamical evolution of hadrons, most&lt;br/&gt;importantly pions, within a multi-phase transport model. The transport theory with&lt;br/&gt;Bose-Einstein statistics will be a useful tool for predicting reliably and interpreting&lt;br/&gt;critically nuclear collision data at RHIC, especially the single-particle spectra, multi-&lt;br/&gt;particle correlation functions and the collective ow of pions. It might also beuseful&lt;br/&gt;for solving the Hanbury Brown/Twiss (HBT) puzzle found in experiments at RHIC.&lt;br/&gt;The ultimate goals of the second project are to determine accurately the isospin&lt;br/&gt;dependence of the nuclear equation of state (EOS) and to investigate novel properties&lt;br/&gt;of dense neutron-rich matter that was not in reach in terrestrial laboratories before.&lt;br/&gt;These are important issues identified in the most recent U.S. long-range plan (LRP)&lt;br/&gt;for nuclear physics and foundamental properties that govern many aspects of neutron&lt;br/&gt;stars. To extract crucial information about the isospin-dependence of the nuclear&lt;br/&gt;EOS, the PI proposes to investigate several experimental observables in nuclear reac-&lt;br/&gt;tions induced by energetic neutron-rich nuclei at existing radioactive beam facilities&lt;br/&gt;and the future Rare Isotope Accelerator, identified as the top priority for new con-&lt;br/&gt;struction in the U.S. LRP for nuclear physics. Moreover, several novel properties&lt;br/&gt;of dense neutron-rich matter will be explored. These include the isospin separation&lt;br/&gt;instability, the unique &lt;br/&gt;0</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243571</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bao-An</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Bao-An.Li@Tamuc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Arkansas State University Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Jonesboro</CityName>
      <ZipCode>724672760</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8709722694</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>504 University Loop East</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
      <StateCode>AR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
