<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Force-induced Conformational Transitions in Single Polysaccharide Molecules by AFM</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2002</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>469511</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Force-induced conformational transitions in single polysaccharide molecules by AFM&lt;br/&gt;Pyranose ring-based molecules are of extraordinary importance to biological systems (e.g.&lt;br/&gt;glucose). Many biologically important polysaccharides are composed of pyranose rings and they&lt;br/&gt;are placed under tensile stress in a wide variety of cellular structures such as the cell wall of&lt;br/&gt;plants or the extracellular matrix (ECM) in animal tissues. Mechanical stress is thought to&lt;br/&gt;regulate assembly and physiological properties of these complex elastic systems. The&lt;br/&gt;polysaccharides respond to that stress by mechanical rearrangements of their components but&lt;br/&gt;the underlying mechanism is not well understood. The simplest view assumes that&lt;br/&gt;polysaccharides are entropic springs and the pyranose ring structure is typically portrayed as&lt;br/&gt;inelastic and locked into a stable conformation. The development of single molecule AFM&lt;br/&gt;techniques allowed for critically examining these views. AFM instruments can stretch&lt;br/&gt;mechanically single molecules and have superb length and force resolution. Stretching of&lt;br/&gt;polysaccharides by AFM revealed that they do not behave as simple entropic springs but that&lt;br/&gt;they display yielding phenomena. The origin of these elastic deviations was pinpointed to the&lt;br/&gt;pyranose ring that was found to undergo, upon stretching, conformational transitions such as&lt;br/&gt;chair-boat or chair inversion. These forced transitions change, in a step-wise fashion, the&lt;br/&gt;separation of the glycosidic oxygen atoms, and therefore affect the contour length of the&lt;br/&gt;polysaccharide chain and its elasticity. Axial glycosidic bonds were found to drive those&lt;br/&gt;transitions by acting as atomic levers. The long-term objective of this proposal is to understand,&lt;br/&gt;at the atomic level, the mechanism of these force-induced conformational transitions in&lt;br/&gt;polysaccharides. During the second grant period single molecule AFM techniques will be&lt;br/&gt;combined with the tools of computational chemistry to examine in detail force-induced&lt;br/&gt;conformational transitions in the pyranose ring. The mechanical properties of the ring and its&lt;br/&gt;mechanical conformational transitions will be probed by pulling on the ring from various&lt;br/&gt;directions and by different attachment points. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These studies will determine the contribution of each type of the monomer to the&lt;br/&gt;complex elasticity of a mixed chain and will be valuable in interpreting the molecular elasticity of&lt;br/&gt;many native polysaccharides. The experimental and theoretical findings of this proposal will be&lt;br/&gt;integrated to develop an AFM-based methodology for identifying individual polysaccharide&lt;br/&gt;molecules in solution from their unique force-extension spectra. Such a methodology will be an&lt;br/&gt;important addition to the arsenal of analytical tools for carbohydrate research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2002</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243360</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Piotr</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marszalek</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pemar@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/23/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
