<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU: Interdisciplinary Undergraduate Research in Environmental Science</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>192000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Randall Christnert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal: CHE-0243659 Date: 1-15-2003&lt;br/&gt;PI: Broadbelt Institution: U of Texas Austin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU site at the University of Texas, Austin will expose students to environmental science. Twelve faculty from four departments (chemistry, geological sciences, integrative biology, pharmacy) will be the research mentors. All faculty are members of the Environmental Science Institute. The research projects will develop expertise in a traditional area of science while uniting with other disciplines to attack complex problems. Eight to nine students will be involved in 10 weeks of research and associated activities. The recruiting emphasis will focus on students from undergraduate institutions mainly from Texas that have a high proportion of students from historically underrepresented backgrounds,. A secondary theme of the site is "science communication". Students will interact with a technical writer. They will prepare articles for a "discovery" type magazine and a poster for a poster session at the end of the summer. The students will also engage in three "field study" scientific excursions to introduce them to non-laboratory based scientific endeavors.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243659</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brodbelt</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbrodbelt@cm.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/17/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
      <CityName>Austin</CityName>
      <ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
