<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Land Conservancy and Resource Management at Nature Preserves in the Mid-Atlantic States</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>172028</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080303</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Sally E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The focal points of this interdisciplinary summer research experience are land conservancy and resource management. Students will develop projects specifically addressing the needs of two local nature preserves, located within 15 miles of Gettysburg College, Gettysburg, PA. Under the supervision of a research mentor, participants will work in collaborative teams of two students. During the first two weeks of the10-week program, students will learn the basic information and skills (e.g., introduction to the preserves, ecological and social sciences methods, how to create a GIS database) necessary to develop their research projects. During the following seven weeks students will collect and analyze data as well as attend two series of seminars (one on current research in environmental studies, one on ethical issues). The last week of the program will be devoted to writing up and presenting the results of projects. Additional collegial interactions will take place during weekly dinners and field trips. Finally, students will have the opportunity to present their research to the local community and have their work included in the environmental education programs of the preserves. Participants will be exposed to the broader context of this research and to the social issues involved in the management of nature preserves. Moreover, this work will provide useful information for the local preserves and show the general public the value of basic and applied research. Interested students should contact: Dr. Veronique A. Delesalle, Department of Biology, Gettysburg College, Gettysburg, PA 17325; Tel. 717-337-6153; email: delesall@gettysburg.edu.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/18/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243739</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Veronique</FirstName>
      <LastName>Delesalle</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>delesall@gettysburg.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gettysburg College</Name>
      <CityName>Gettysburg</CityName>
      <ZipCode>173251483</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7173376505</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>North Washington Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
