<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site in Political Science--Ralph Bunche Summer Institute</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>395536</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Linda G. Lopez</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This award provides funds for the renewal of a Research Experiences for Undergraduates Site in Political Science at Duke University. The program, called the Ralph Bunche Summer Institute, was initiated by the American Political Science Association in 1986. NSF joined in funding the program in 1997. The program is designed to expand opportunities for students of color by preparing them to enroll in doctoral degree programs. Twenty black, Latino, and American Indian undergraduates will be immersed in a five-week intensive program that includes graduate level course work, and the design, analysis, write-up, and presentation of original research papers. The program simulates the graduate school experience and focuses on scientific analysis by introducing the students to research methods and statistics, and the research enterprise that is the lifeline of professional political scientists. Additional program seminars cover professional development topics such as GRE preparation and a graduate school recruitment fair. This program also includes an ethics component.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award contributes to the Foundation's continuing efforts to attract talented students into careers in science through active undergraduate research experiences.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0243565</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paula</FirstName>
      <LastName>McClain</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmcclain@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/11/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duke University</Name>
      <CityName>Durham</CityName>
      <ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
