<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Properties of the Einstein Equations and Gravitational Lensing in Relativity</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010700</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Beverly K. Berger</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>There are two main subprojects in this theoretical &lt;br/&gt;gravitational physics project. On the one hand, the &lt;br/&gt;suitability of a new way of specifying information &lt;br/&gt;necessary for numerical simulations of gravity using &lt;br/&gt;the Einstein equations will be studied. This refers to &lt;br/&gt;gravitational information flowing across the boundary &lt;br/&gt;into the region where gravity is being simulated. On &lt;br/&gt;the other hand, a formula for path corrections to light &lt;br/&gt;rays in response to the thickness of a nearby massive &lt;br/&gt;object will be sought within the framework of the &lt;br/&gt;theory of general relativity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first subproject is, potentially, of deep relevance &lt;br/&gt;to the successful simulation of gravitational wave &lt;br/&gt;signals expected at powerful new detectors such as the &lt;br/&gt;Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory &lt;br/&gt;(LIGO). The detectors are expected to open a new &lt;br/&gt;window of research into cosmology and astrophysics &lt;br/&gt;by listening to gravitational waves, rather than &lt;br/&gt;electromagnetic waves such as visible light or x-rays. &lt;br/&gt;The second subproject &lt;br/&gt;has potential relevance to the current astrophysical &lt;br/&gt;practices of extracting information about the mass of &lt;br/&gt;the universe from deep-space pictures by advanced &lt;br/&gt;instruments such as the Hubble Space Telescope. &lt;br/&gt;Undergraduates will participate in this research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244752</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Simonetta</FirstName>
      <LastName>Frittelli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>simo@mayu.physics.duq.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/30/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Duquesne University</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152820001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4123961537</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Room 310 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1244</Code>
      <Text>GRAVITATIONAL THEORY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
