<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Weak Decays of Oxygen-14 and Boron-8</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>373000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bradley D. Keister</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>We plan to design and construct an electron spectrometer&lt;br/&gt;(a device for measuring electron energies) and to use the&lt;br/&gt;spectrometer to carry out two new experiments.&lt;br/&gt;The spectrometer will use superconducting magnet&lt;br/&gt;technology to generate precisely controlled magnetic&lt;br/&gt;fields which deflect and focus electrons emitted from a small&lt;br/&gt;radioactive source. This will permit us to measure the&lt;br/&gt;energy distribution of the electrons produced in the &lt;br/&gt;radioactive decay. The specific experiments to be&lt;br/&gt;performed involve studying the decays of the radioactive&lt;br/&gt;isotopes oxygen-14 and boron-8. The oxygen-14&lt;br/&gt;experiment is designed to test what is referred to&lt;br/&gt;as the Conserved Vector Current (CVC) hypothesis, which&lt;br/&gt;is a fundamental component of the Standard Model of &lt;br/&gt;Weak Interactions. The Standard Model is the basis for&lt;br/&gt;understanding a wide variety of processes, including the&lt;br/&gt;beta-decay of nuclei, the process which produces the electrons&lt;br/&gt;in our experiments. The CVC hypothesis allows us to&lt;br/&gt;predict the electron energy distribution, and the experiment&lt;br/&gt;will test whether that prediction is correct.&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of the boron-8 experiment is to provide new&lt;br/&gt;information that will help physicists understand the&lt;br/&gt;spectrum of neutrinos from the sun. Boron-8 plays a critical&lt;br/&gt;role in solar neutrino studies. The neutrinos from decay&lt;br/&gt;of boron-8 in the sun are relatively high in energy, and most &lt;br/&gt;of the world's operating solar neutrino detectors primarily see&lt;br/&gt;the boron-8 neutrinos. Since the electron and the neutrino&lt;br/&gt;share the decay energy, we can obtain information about&lt;br/&gt;the expected neutrino spectrum from a measurement of the&lt;br/&gt;electron energies.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244893</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lynn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Knutson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>knutson@physics.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/18/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
