<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU: Research Experiences for Undergraduates at Montana State University</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>190875</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090007</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Randall Christnert</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal: CHE-0244206 Date: 1-07-2003&lt;br/&gt;PI: Cloninger Institution: Montana State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Chemistry Division award supports a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site at Montana State University for the summers of 2003-2005. Mary J. Cloninger is the site's program director. Twelve different research groups will offer research projects and mentoring for10 students for ten weeks in the areas of chemistry and biochemistry. Students will be recruited primarily from the northwest region of the US with particular emphasis on Montana colleges and Native Americans in this region. Research projects will involve a broad range of topics including isolation and characterization of natural products and biologically active compounds, bio-nanomaterials, structural biology, x-ray crystallography, bioorganic and biophysical chemistry. The program will have weekly workshops, seminars, and research group meetings. The participants will write a final paper and present a poster on their research at the conclusion of the program.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244206</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
      <LastName>Cloninger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mcloninger@chemistry.montana.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Montana State University</Name>
      <CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>309 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Montana</StateName>
      <StateCode>MT</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
