<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Statistical Mechanics and Field Theory</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>113595</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Earle L. Lomon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>1. The purpose of this project is to enhance our understanding of fundamental problems in&lt;br/&gt;statistical mechanics and probability theory through the use of mathematical methods&lt;br/&gt;involving supersymmetry and the renormalization group. Of particular interest are&lt;br/&gt;statistical models with a geometrical flavor, such as branched polymers and self-avoiding&lt;br/&gt;walks. Basic questions for these models involve, for example, determining the rate at&lt;br/&gt;which the size of a sample grows with the number of monomers or steps. Such divergences&lt;br/&gt;are governed by critical exponents. The values of the exponents may be determined in one&lt;br/&gt;of two ways, either through dimensional reduction (which relates exponents to known&lt;br/&gt;exponents in related systems in fewer dimensions), or through the renormalization group&lt;br/&gt;(which calculates the flow of couplings with the length scale as the microscopic&lt;br/&gt;structures of the problem are averaged out). Supersymmetry plays an important role in&lt;br/&gt;both methods.&lt;br/&gt;Specific goals are: (a) to continue to develop a mathematical theory of dimensional&lt;br/&gt;reduction and apply it to new models, such as directed branched polymers; and (b) to&lt;br/&gt;construct an exact renormalization group flows for such systems.&lt;br/&gt;2. Research activities in this proposal will involve collaborations and exchanges of&lt;br/&gt;ideas with mathematicians and physicists in a wide range of fields, including probability,&lt;br/&gt;analysis, statistical mechanics, and quantum field theory. Graduate student support, and&lt;br/&gt;graduate student participation in scientific meetings, will integrate research and&lt;br/&gt;education and help train a new generation of mathematicians in the methods of field&lt;br/&gt;theory, supersymmetry, and the renormalization group. These activities will in the long&lt;br/&gt;run lead to enhanced interaction between mathematics and physics and to new ideas in both&lt;br/&gt;fields.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244884</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>John</FirstName>
      <LastName>Imbrie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ji2k@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/20/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O. BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1263</Code>
      <Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1287</Code>
      <Text>MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
