<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Nonlinear Control Problems for Rest-to-Rest Maneuvers of Multi-Body Vehicles using Prismatic Actuators</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Radhakisan S. Baheti</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>PROJECT SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;Page A&lt;br/&gt;This proposal describes a novel research program on nonlinear control of multi-body&lt;br/&gt;vehicles operating under the action of gravitational forces and control forces generated&lt;br/&gt;by prismatic actuators. Multi-body vehicles are mechanical systems consisting of a rigid&lt;br/&gt;base body that can translate and rotate in three dimensions and auxiliary bodies that are&lt;br/&gt;constrained to move relative to the base body and to one another. The multi-body vehicles&lt;br/&gt;are controlled using prismatic actuator devices, mounted on the base body. These are&lt;br/&gt;linear electromechanical actuators that move a proof mass along a track fixed to the base&lt;br/&gt;body. This is a novel actuation technology that has great potential for providing new&lt;br/&gt;maneuvering capabilities, namely precision translation and global attitude maneuvers, for&lt;br/&gt;multi-body vehicles. On the other hand, the design and operation of such multi-body&lt;br/&gt;vehicles present many challenges since they are not fully actuated in the sense that there&lt;br/&gt;are fewer control inputs than there are degrees of freedom to be controlled. Key aspects&lt;br/&gt;of the proposed research, from which arise the major research challenges, are: (1) the&lt;br/&gt;presence of controlled mechanical symmetries and their associated integrals of motion and&lt;br/&gt;(2) the objective of achieving arbitrary rest to rest maneuvers for the multi-body&lt;br/&gt;vehicles.&lt;br/&gt;Although some nonlinear control problems for multi-body mechanical systems are relatively&lt;br/&gt;simple, the problems posed in this research can not be adequately handled based on the&lt;br/&gt;current state of knowledge. The proposed research is the culmination of the NSF supported&lt;br/&gt;research of the principal investigator over the last fourteen years. It represents an&lt;br/&gt;extension of his previous research on nonlinear control of constrained and underactuated&lt;br/&gt;mechanical systems to new problems that have not previously been amenable to study using&lt;br/&gt;traditional nonlinear control methods. The expected contributions of the proposed&lt;br/&gt;research are: (1) the development of nonlinear control theory for the class of multi-body&lt;br/&gt;vehicles studied, (2) the development of innovative new system design and control&lt;br/&gt;strategies for multi-body vehicles, and (3) educational impacts through student&lt;br/&gt;participation in the research. The research concepts are to be applied to maneuvering&lt;br/&gt;vehicles operating in space or under water, and they are ideally suited for small-scale&lt;br/&gt;intelligent autonomous sensor systems operating in space or under water. The proposed&lt;br/&gt;research has the potential to provide new and enhanced maneuvering capabilities for&lt;br/&gt;multi-body vehicles, thereby contributing to the overall engineering infrastructure in&lt;br/&gt;transportation, exploration, remote sensing, and surveillance.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244977</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
      <LastName>McClamroch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nhm@engin.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/09/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
      <CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
      <ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0112000</Code>
      <Name>System Theory</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
