<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Probing Electroweak Symmetry Breaking at High Energy Colliders</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>112865</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Frederick Cooper</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal centers on determining precision tests of the Standard Model of particle physics and new physics beyond the Standard Model at present and future collider facilities. The focus will be on probes for understanding for electro weak symmetry breaking which generates the mass for the W and Z bosons as well as for the quarks. The PI proposes to understand the effects of final state interactions on the measurement of the coupling between the top quark-bottom quark and the W boson. He intends to carry out higher order calculations in QCD in order to predict the transverse momentum distribution for the Higgs particle. Predictions will be made for the pair production of W and Z Bosons at LHC in the standard model that can be compared with exotic production mechanisms due to extra dimensions. The PI also intends to investigate the effect of neutrino masses on the phenomenology of Supersymmetric extensions of the Standard Model.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244919</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Chien-Peng</FirstName>
      <LastName>Yuan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>yuan@pa.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/11/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Michigan State University</Name>
      <CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Michigan</StateName>
      <StateCode>MI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
