<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SDSM&amp;T-MUS&amp;T REU Site Collaboration</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>353717</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Esther Bolding</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0244189 Winter&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides support to the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology for a three-year national and international Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site in collaboration with the Mongolian University of Science and Technology (MUS&amp;T) for research in advanced materials and biochemical engineering. The goals of the REU site are to (1) provide ten undergraduates of chemical engineering or allied fields with a unique research opportunity; (2) provide American Indians, women, and other under-represented groups a working knowledge of research in chemical engineering as a career path; (3) provide an opportunity to gain research experience in an international setting; (4) enhance students' critical thinking and communication skills (including written, oral, listening, and audio/visual presentation skills); (5) increase the students' interest in graduate studies with a target of 30% of participants pursuing graduate degrees; (6) introduce students to the 'beyond the classroom' experience in a research setting; and (7) enhance the students' ability to think independently. At least 30% of the students will be recruited from Tribal, four-year, and community colleges and universities from the four surrounding states of Montana, Nebraska, North Dakota, and Wyoming, where research opportunities historically have been lacking.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244189</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robb</FirstName>
      <LastName>Winter</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>robb.winter@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/26/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>South Dakota School of Mines and Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
      <ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6053941218</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>501 East Saint Joseph Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
      <StateCode>SD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
