<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Research in Theoretical Nuclear Physics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>571000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bradley D. Keister</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The proposed program of research is in the area of theoretical physics with an emphasis on&lt;br/&gt;many-body problem in nuclear structure physics, fusion reactions below the Coulomb barrier,&lt;br/&gt;reactions involving heavy-ions, multifragmentation and phase transitions in nuclei, solar and&lt;br/&gt;supernova neutrinos, nucleosynthesis and other neutrino astrophysics. Theoretical research in&lt;br/&gt;these areas is chosen to have a close coupling with the ongoing experimental programs in the&lt;br/&gt;United States and abroad.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit of the Proposed Work: Successful completion of the proposed projects&lt;br/&gt;will lead to i) A better understanding of nuclear equation of state for applications in nuclear&lt;br/&gt;reactions and nuclear astrophysics; ii) Understanding dependence of nuclear reactions on the&lt;br/&gt;isospin of the reacting partners through the recently developed techniques of isoscaling; iii) A&lt;br/&gt;better understanding of the neutrino masses and mixings; iv) Understanding neutrino propagation&lt;br/&gt;through dense media and in strong gravitational fields; v) A better understanding of various&lt;br/&gt;aspects of core-collapse supernovae; vi) A better understanding of the origin of elements, especially&lt;br/&gt;those produced in rapid neutron capture; vii) A better understanding of fusion in astrophysical&lt;br/&gt;environments, and viii) A better understanding of pairing and elaboration of its role in nuclear&lt;br/&gt;many-body problem.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts Resulting from the Proposed Activity: Proposed research contributes to the&lt;br/&gt;support of national priorities in nuclear science such as the proposed National Underground Science&lt;br/&gt;Laboratory and Rare Ion Accelerator. The proposed research involves collaboration between&lt;br/&gt;University of Wisconsin-Madison and Michigan State University, University of California at San&lt;br/&gt;Diego, and University of Washington as well as international collaborations between University of&lt;br/&gt;Wisconsin-Madison researchers and those from Brazil, China, France, Italy, Japan, and Turkey.&lt;br/&gt;The principal investigators participate in multidisciplinary research activities that connect particle,&lt;br/&gt;nuclear, condensed-matter physics and astrophysics. Both principal investigators are involved&lt;br/&gt;in exposing physics to broader audiences. Balantekin plans to continue playing a major role in&lt;br/&gt;developing National Underground Science Laboratory. In addition to enhancing research and education&lt;br/&gt;infrastructure of the Nation in underground science, this proposed laboratory will provide&lt;br/&gt;outreach to the visitors in general and regional Native American colleges in particular.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244384</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>William</FirstName>
      <LastName>Friedman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>friedman@nucth.physics.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Akif Baha</FirstName>
      <LastName>Balantekin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>baha@physics.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/13/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
