<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Heavy-Quark Reaction Cross Sections at RHIC: Studies of Quark-Gluon Plasma Signatures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010500</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bradley D. Keister</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>We propose a program of calculations of heavy-quark hadron cross sections which are&lt;br/&gt;of great importance in the identifcation of a quark gluon plasma (QGP) in heavy-ion colli-&lt;br/&gt;sions. This program will involve the calculation of reaction cross sections of various hadrons&lt;br/&gt;which have been proposed as QGP diagnostic probes, such as heavy quarkonia, hyper-&lt;br/&gt;ons, and antihyperons. Most of these cross sections are not accessible experimentally at&lt;br/&gt;present, and as such can only be estimated using theoretical models. The central compo-&lt;br/&gt;nent of this proposal consists of calculations of these cross sections using the well-established&lt;br/&gt;constituent-interchange model, assuming standard quark model forces and a scattering for-&lt;br/&gt;malism developed previously by two of us (Barnes and Swanson). This approach is known to&lt;br/&gt;give reasonable agreement with existing experimental low-energy scattering data for a wide&lt;br/&gt;range of analogous hadron-hadron scattering processes. Additional research topics which&lt;br/&gt;will be addressed are the generalization of the approach to multichannel and relativistic&lt;br/&gt;regimes, the incorporation of qq pair production amplitudes, a comparison of microscopic&lt;br/&gt;and effective Lagrangian descriptions, and the development of a T-matrix formalism that will&lt;br/&gt;allow direct application to bound state problems. The cross sections obtained here should&lt;br/&gt;be useful as estimates of the various hadronic contributions to the proposed experimental&lt;br/&gt;signals for the quark-gluon plasma. These hadronic contributions must be understood and&lt;br/&gt;incorporated in simulations of heavy-ion collisions before QGP formation can be established&lt;br/&gt;through various signatures; for this reason a third component of our program is a close&lt;br/&gt;collaboration with researchers involved in Monte-Carlo simulations of RHIC experiments,&lt;br/&gt;so that the experimental implications of these hadronic contributions for RHIC can be as-&lt;br/&gt;sesssed. This will be facilitated by the presence of a large RHIC experimental group from&lt;br/&gt;PHENIX at ORNL and University of Tennessee.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0244668</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
      <LastName>Swanson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>swansone@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/27/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
      <CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
      <ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
      <StateCode>PA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
