<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Relativistic Heavy-Ion Physics at the University of Rochester</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>141341</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03010600</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Bradley D. Keister</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant provides operating funds for the relativistic heavy-ion &lt;br/&gt;group at the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of &lt;br/&gt;Rochester. During the year covered by this grant we will complete the &lt;br/&gt;analysis of the data collected in 2001 and 2003 with the PHOBOS detector &lt;br/&gt;at the Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collider (RHIC) at Brookhaven National &lt;br/&gt;Laboratory (BNL) and consider possible upgrade options for the PHOBOS &lt;br/&gt;detector.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; PHOBOS is one of the four experiments looking at the extreme energy &lt;br/&gt;densities that are created when nuclei collide at RHIC. It is believed &lt;br/&gt;that a new state of matter, the so-called quark-gluon plasma (QGP), will &lt;br/&gt;be formed in these collisions. PHOBOS is looking for this new state of &lt;br/&gt;matter, and its properties will provide important and new information &lt;br/&gt;about the state of the very early universe (a few microseconds after the &lt;br/&gt;Big Bang). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; PHOBOS was designed to study as many collisions as possible, in an &lt;br/&gt;unbiased way, and to search for significant differences between p+p, p+A, &lt;br/&gt;and A+A collisions. The data collected sofar inlcudes studies of Au+Au &lt;br/&gt;collisions in 2001, d+Au in 2003, and p+p in 2001 and 2003. It is &lt;br/&gt;expected that the QGP will only be formed in the Au+Au collisions, and the &lt;br/&gt;studies of d+Au and p+p are used to subtract the contribution of "normal" &lt;br/&gt;nucleon-nucleon physics from the data collected in Au+Au collisions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The time-of-flight array, designed and constructed by the Rochester &lt;br/&gt;group, significantly enhances the physics capabilities of PHOBOS, by &lt;br/&gt;roughly doubling its particle identification capabilities. For the &lt;br/&gt;2003 run we have increased the flight path of our arrays, allowing use &lt;br/&gt;to identify particles up to momenta of around 4 - 5 GeV/c. The analysis &lt;br/&gt;of the 2001 data is almost completed, and the analysis of the 2003 data is &lt;br/&gt;just getting started.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0245011</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Frank L.</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wolfs</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wolfs@pas.rochester.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/24/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Rochester</Name>
      <CityName>Rochester</CityName>
      <ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>518 HYLAN, RC BOX 270140</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1233</Code>
      <Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
