<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>3-manifolds and Floer homologies</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>64755</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The problems addressed in this project are in the area of Topology.&lt;br/&gt;The main theme is to study the fundamental and important properties of the gauge-theoretic/symplectic Floer homology, using invariants and methods from &lt;br/&gt;3-manifold topology and symplectic topology. The investigator studied the &lt;br/&gt;semi-infinity of the instanton (gauge theoretic) Floer homology and the intrinsic &lt;br/&gt;dependence of the monopole(Seiberg-Witten-Floer) homology of (homology)&lt;br/&gt;three-spheres. The major part of the project is to study the interactive relation &lt;br/&gt;between the symplectic Floer homology and the classical 3-manifolds, and the&lt;br/&gt;relation between the Floer cohomology and the semi-infinite cohomology, and the Seiberg-Witten-Floer theory intertwining the instanton and monopole results. The &lt;br/&gt;other part of this project is to study intrinsic properties for the invariants of larger&lt;br/&gt;classes of three-spheres.It is a fundamental aim to investigate the change of the new&lt;br/&gt;invariants under certain topological operations. The project will integrate the &lt;br/&gt;interactions among the instanton theory, the monopole theory, the symplectic Floer&lt;br/&gt;theory and the semi-infinite cohomology of infinite-dimensional Lie algebras.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A three-dimensional manifold is a space where a nearsighted person sees a standard three-dimensional space everywhere.(Homology) three-spheres are those three-manifolds &lt;br/&gt;that one cannot tell from the standard three-sphere by using the usual topological tools. A symplectic manifold is an even-dimensional space with a special(symplectic) structure. For &lt;br/&gt;instance, the phase space of a mechanical system is a symplectic space. Such a symplectic &lt;br/&gt;structure is rich in mathematics and physics, and is canonical from any nearby region. This &lt;br/&gt;shows the subtlety and the complexity of the world we live in. Any local information is no &lt;br/&gt;longer useful, the global behavior and the global (topological) invariants are the pivot. The &lt;br/&gt;refined invariants studied in this project are intended to distinguish manifolds from the &lt;br/&gt;aspects of mathematical physics, and to intertwine various quantum field theories from the &lt;br/&gt;aspect of mathematics. Thus it is extremely valuable to investigate the relation between the symplectic Floer cohomology and the semi-infinite cohomology, as well as the interactive link between the instanton homology and the monopole homology. This project addresses some &lt;br/&gt;of the most fundamental problems in this subject.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0245323</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Weiping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Li</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>wli@math.okstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/15/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Oklahoma State University</Name>
      <CityName>Stillwater</CityName>
      <ZipCode>740781011</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>101 WHITEHURST HALL</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
      <StateCode>OK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
