<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Promoting Student Participation In the 35th North American Power Symposium; October 19-21, 2003; University of Missouri-Rolla, Missouri</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9800</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>James Momoh</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This proposal requests travel support for an electrical engineering students (with a major in power engineering) across the United States to attend the 35th annual North American Power Symposium (NAPS) to be held on October 19-21, 2003 at the University of Missouri-Rolla, MO. Travel expenses could be a deterrent for undergraduate or graduate students planning to attend this symposium. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NAPS is an annual symposium, sponsored by the Institute of Electrical &amp; Electronics Engineers (IEEE) and a university on the North American Continent. At this symposium, university professors and students are encouraged to present the results of their research among colleagues at an early stage in their work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NAPS participants are from the electrical/computer engineering departments of major universities in the country with research interests in different areas of power engineering, some from universities abroad, and some from industry. NAPS authors are required to attend the symposium and present their papers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal discusses the justification for travel support, requested from the National Science Foundation, for student authors attending the symposium. It also discusses activities planned for the symposium, and the impact of the proposed travel grant.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0245351</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Badrul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chowdhury</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>b.chowdhury@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/01/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
      <CityName>Rolla</CityName>
      <ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>300 W 12th Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Missouri</StateName>
      <StateCode>MO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0306000</Code>
      <Name>Energy Research &amp; Resources</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
